<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Agon</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-03-18-agon/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 12:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-03-18-agon/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-03-18-agon/ -&lt;p&gt;In this installment, I will continue my reviews of &amp;ldquo;Indie RPGs&amp;rdquo; that have recently made an impression on me. Today I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agon-rpg.com&#34;&gt;Agon&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, a game of mythical Greek heroes. First off, &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; is awesome. I absolutely love it, and if I had like minded players around me, I would run a game tomorrow. It is simple but rich, and it captures the feel of Greek mythology and the whole Greek ethos masterfully. And I&amp;rsquo;m not just talking out of my ass when I say that, as I have a degree in Classics, so consider it my semi-expert opinion that this game is very &amp;ldquo;Greek&amp;rdquo; in feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it achieves this feel is right there in the title: &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; is the Greek world for struggle or competition, but the meaning was much wider than either of those English words. In the ancient Greek mindset, everything was a competition, and it was the struggle for glory between men that the gods found most pleasing. Inherent to the Greek worldview was that everything could be done with more or less arete, or excellence, whether that was mending a shoe or killing a rival warrior, and that the only way to judge a person&amp;rsquo;s arete was through direct competition to see who came out on top. Who made the most beautiful tapestry? Who sang the best song? Who fought with the greatest valor? These questions, and the implicit question behind them, namely &amp;ldquo;Who is the better man (or woman)?&amp;quot;, could only be answered by directly striving against one another. Whoever achieved more rightfully gained more glory and was accorded better status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sets the stage for the key philosophical difference between &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; and other roleplaying games. In most RPGs, the player characters cooperate against foes and threats presented by the game master and succeed or fail as a group, pooling resources and winnings and gaining experience as a whole, divvied up evenly. In &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo;, you still have a game master (the &amp;ldquo;antagonist&amp;rdquo;) and a group of PCs who help each other achieve quests, but the PCs are really vying against one another to be the best and most glorious. They don&amp;rsquo;t fight one another, but each player wants to make sure his character kills the Gorgon, steals the treasure, or wins the maiden, so that he gets the most glory. And the game tracks glory and unabashedly uses it as a scoreboard for which hero is winning. The analogy presented by the author, John Harper, is that it&amp;rsquo;s like a black jack game. The antagonist is the dealer, and the PCs are the players at the table. Everybody is competing against the dealer, but the real competition is against the other players. But like a card game among friends, since everyone comes to the table knowing they&amp;rsquo;re trying to beat the pants off of each other, there&amp;rsquo;s no hard feelings. I think this spirit of friendly competition is helped by the fact that the player heroes never directly fight each other, instead they do help each other fight, but they&amp;rsquo;re still trying to each achieve the most individually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting into the game, the antagonist doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about ambiguity of what the players need to accomplish, as the default way of setting up adventure is for a god to literally descend from the heavens and impart a quest upon the heroes. Sure, it lacks subtlety, but it lets the players get right into what they&amp;rsquo;re there for: heroic exploits! Also, it&amp;rsquo;s entirely in keeping with the Greek mythological flavor, and the game makes no bones about not being about subtle character development or complex storylines. That being said, some adventures available for free from Ben Robbins, the author of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arsludi.lamemage.com&#34;&gt;Ars Ludi&lt;/a&gt; game design blog I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, do a good job of showing that stories can be straight forward and still have plenty of flavor and interest.   The quest system also comes with defined objectives that the antagonist determines for the quest (usually 3-5 per quest). These aren&amp;rsquo;t necessarily laid out at the beginning of the quest, allowing for some roleplaying and investigation opportunities, but there&amp;rsquo;s some solid GM advice given here that is repeated in &amp;ldquo;Spirt of the Century&amp;rdquo;, to be reviewed later: the GM&amp;rsquo;s job is not to hide information from players or keep secrets, it is to provide exciting situations for them to interact with. In other words, you should give more than enough clues for players who are trying at all to find out what they should be doing and where. There&amp;rsquo;s another reason for the codified quest and objective system that allows the fiercely competitive nature of Agon to be fair: strife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strife is a pretty cool innovation. In most games, the GM has total fiat over everything that isn&amp;rsquo;t directly under a player character&amp;rsquo;s control. His only restraint is the real-world social restriction of ending up with no players if he abuses his in-game authority. In Agon, however, the GM has a budget called &amp;ldquo;Strife&amp;rdquo;. If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with wargaming, strife works a lot like points systems in many games. The GMing rules provide costs for using strife to create obstacles, NPCs, and villains. During game play, he can also use left-over strife on the fly to make given conflicts more difficult. Having a budget like this gives the GM license to be as tough as possible on the players, because the game is designed so that he only gets as much strife as the players can theoretically handle (though it will be challenging). The flip side of the coin is that the harder the GM makes any villain or situation, the more glory the players win for beating it. This whole notion of restraints on the GM fits into the similar ethos present in &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; where traditional player/GM roles are questioned and modified, usually giving more in-game power and responsibility to the players. I&amp;rsquo;m all for such changes, as even if you decide you still like a more traditional roleplaying format, having played games like this will make you better at being either a player or a GM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if it hasn&amp;rsquo;t become apparent by now, Agon is a heavily rules-dependent game. Almost everything that happens in the game from an argument to GM NPC creation, is governed by defined rules rather than loose guidelines.This would have the potential to be stifling, except that the rules are admirably straight forward and the competitive philosophy of the game is straightforwardly and unashamedly presented everywhere to remind you &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the rules are so stressed. This brings up one of the guidelines of the game, notable in the use of strife: nobody gets anything for free. Any time there&amp;rsquo;s a conflict of interest, the dice come out. Nothing happens because &amp;ldquo;it should&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;d be good for the story&amp;rdquo;. No rewards are free, but then neither are any challenges free for the GM. This guideline also seems to me to be a helpful rule of thumb to keep in mind for less competitive or rules-focused games on when to break out the dice and when not to: dice are for conflicts of interest. Any time there&amp;rsquo;s not a conflict of interest, don&amp;rsquo;t bother with dice. But when there are, it&amp;rsquo;s probably more satisfying to the group to have the dice decide it, unless you&amp;rsquo;re purposely playing a game with a more communal storytelling feel to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so, having said that the rules are very important, let&amp;rsquo;s shakedown the core mechanic. Stats are listed as dice, from d4 up to d12, with d4 being &amp;lsquo;not very good at&amp;rsquo; and d12 being &amp;lsquo;legendary/divine&amp;rsquo;, and d6 being average. For a conflict you roll all relevant dice (usually 2 or 3) and whoever has the highest single number showing wins. Ties go to the aggressor. And that&amp;rsquo;s it! See what I mean about simplicity? Now, of course there are wrinkles to make the game interesting, such as being able to spend divine favor points for extra dice or rerolls, but as with &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; the scale of dice means that bigger dice are more likely to win, but not guaranteed. Unlike &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; you don&amp;rsquo;t have as much leeway with rolling more of a lower die rather than fewer dice with more sides.  I like the fact that ties go to the aggressor, as this is a subtle but useful incentive to players to do things decisively, as befits Greek heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way that larger sided dice come in, besides giving you a better probability of winning is that for every 4 points you beat your opponent by, you gain a &amp;ldquo;victory&amp;rdquo;, and additional victories are useful in various ways. In combat, they provide more injuries, and in other situations they determine with how much flair you&amp;rsquo;ve overcome your opponent or an obstacle. In situations where all heroes are rolling against the same challenge (like fording a raging river) the one with the most victories does it best/fastest and gets a bonus glory point!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cool factor is that your &amp;ldquo;base die&amp;rdquo; that is used in all rolls is your &amp;ldquo;name die&amp;rdquo;. Mortals start with a d6, half divine characters start with a d8. In addition to your name, you choose an epithet (fleet-footed, clever-eyed, et cetera) that grants you bonuses to certain kinds of rolls as appropriate. This is a subtle but awesome way to hammer home the Greek/Heroic flavor, making your name have in-game effect.  All of your stats are divided into 4 categories of 4 stats each. Arete includes Insight, Grace, Might, and Spirit. Craft includes Lore, Music, Orate, and Heal. Sport has Athletics, Cunning, Hunt, and Wrestle. Battle includes Aim, Shield, Spear, and Sword. And that&amp;rsquo;s it on stats. You don&amp;rsquo;t have any skills in addition to stats, rather different situations are modeled by combining different stats, and more complicated weapons rules are avoided by combining two facts: one, the weapons listed (bows, javelins, spears, swords, shields) were pretty much the only weapons used by heroic Bronze Age Greeks, and two, you can pretty much &amp;lsquo;map&amp;rsquo; other weapons onto the existing weapons without too much trouble because the combat is tactical but somewhat abstract. So it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter if you roll exactly the same thing for a javelin as for a &amp;lsquo;furious charge&amp;rsquo;, since the only parts that matter in game are range and damage. This makes creating monsters really easy as whatever nutty natural attacks they have, they just count as bows, javelins, spears, swords, or shields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four categories of stats are important because you can trade around &amp;lsquo;points&amp;rsquo; in each category to get different dice. For example, within &amp;ldquo;Arete&amp;rdquo;, if you want to up Insight from a D6 to a D8, you can lower Grace from a D6 to a D4. But you couldn&amp;rsquo;t trade a die from the &amp;ldquo;Craft&amp;rdquo; category to up Insight in the  &amp;ldquo;Arete&amp;rdquo; category. Also, in some types of non-combat conflict, the categories are important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aspect of character creation that I really like is the &amp;ldquo;achievements/oaths&amp;rdquo; method. In this, at character creation, every character engages in a simple contest with each other character. When it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to go around to each character, you get to pick what the contest is, but then that person will get a chance to choose a contest with you. These can either be direct like &amp;ldquo;we wrestle each other&amp;rdquo; or less direct like &amp;ldquo;we both engage in stealth to see who is more successful at sneaking into the enemy camp back in the war&amp;rdquo;. Whoever wins the contest gets an &amp;ldquo;oath&amp;rdquo; from the other player. Oaths are an actual mechanic whereby a player owes another player direct in-game help of a mechanical nature. The player holding the oath can choose any time to call in the favor. This system is neat for two reasons. For one thing, the little vignettes of each contest give the heroes a built-in history, explaining why they&amp;rsquo;re traveling together killing monsters and liberating maidens and such. Secondly, it creates a mechanically-reinforced mutual dependence between players. Oaths can force cooperation that might be held back, but you have to deal with the shame of needing help on something (and you have to share the glory when you call in oaths). Also, as the game goes on, oaths are the primary currency in inter-player bargaining (or even bargaining with NPCs). You can say &amp;ldquo;okay, I&amp;rsquo;ll rid your village of these pesky harpies, but you owe me three oaths for it&amp;rdquo; or you can be like &amp;ldquo;hey, heal me in this break, and I&amp;rsquo;ll give you an oath&amp;rdquo;. This encourages at the same time friendly competition as well as cooperation (even if grudging cooperation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, going back to the core notion that any time someone has a conflict of interest or seeks an advantage a contest happens, it is important for players to clearly state their goals whenever they take an action. This allows the antagonist to determine if it would gain the hero an advantage or come into conflict with some other entity. If not, the action happens, no problem. If it does, then a contest happens. There are two types of contests, simple, and battle. Battle is not necessarily physical combat, as you can have a rhetoric battle or a lute playing battle, or an involved wrestling match, or whatever. But obviously the most common more in-depth contest is actual fighting. Simple contests are where all involved parties roll the relevant dice, compare results, and you&amp;rsquo;re done. Any heroes participating who succeed gain glory, but the winner gets an extra glory. Battles are more involved affairs with a series of exchanges between opponents and usually have more at stake than simple contests. A neat feature of the rules, though, is that player characters reserve the right to &amp;ldquo;Invoke Hubris&amp;rdquo; after any simple contest. This escalates a simple contest into a battle, and the loser of the simple contest goes into the battle with a number of wounds equal to the victories rolled by the winner of the simple contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t do a play by play of the battle system here, but essentially it&amp;rsquo;s a series of simple contests with the addition of an initiative system and an abstracted range rule (you have a vertical strip divided into zones. On your turn you can move either yourself or an opponent a certain number of zones closer or farther. Different weapons work optimally at different ranges) that allows a surprising amount of tactical interest while remaining quite simple.   With any contest, simple or battle, things are at stake. Something tangible, besides glory points, always comes out of a contest, whether that&amp;rsquo;s an advantage against a foe in an upcoming battle, or an impairment for the loser or vital information (don&amp;rsquo;t look at the medusa or you&amp;rsquo;ll be turned to stone, or you have to burn the heads off the hydra, or whatever). Impairment is where one of your abilities goes down by a die level, and the first level of impairment is always against the stat used in the contest. In a contest, either the antagonist will dictate which ability is used, or the players will be able to phrase what they&amp;rsquo;re doing in a manner to make it clear what ability applies. A neat exception, though, is that you can opt to use a &amp;ldquo;creative ability&amp;rdquo; to add an extra die to your roll. All you have to do is describe adequately how the ability is being used in the contest. If you use an extra ability, though, it gets impaired afterwards win or lose (all that extra effort!). So, for example, say a foot race calls for a name + athletics roll. But you explain that your character is going to use his cunning to find a short cut, while I explain that my character will use hunting to find a deer trail through the dense woods. So you&amp;rsquo;d roll name + athletics + cunning, while I&amp;rsquo;d roll name + athletics + hunting, but afterwards no matter how we did on the contest, your cunning would be impaired as would my hunting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the one semi-exception to the &amp;lsquo;nothing happens just because it should&amp;rsquo; rule is with &amp;lsquo;obstacle contests&amp;rsquo;. In these contests, the outcome will happen one way or another, but winning allows the heroes to do it easily and with style, while losing makes them tired and struggle harder. Examples include things like crossing a river or purchasing from a hard-driving merchant. It would be boring for the hero to be stuck on one side of the river or not to acquire the necessary item, but if he wins he swims across easily and without danger or strikes a good deal with the guy, but if he loses he wears himself out crossing or gets cheated. Either way he&amp;rsquo;s across the river or in possession of the object, but the in-game effect doesn&amp;rsquo;t come for free. Contests can also be &amp;lsquo;dangerous&amp;rsquo; where losing causes wounds in addition to impairment, but heroes gain extra glory for beating them, and antagonists must spend strife to make them dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to go into the battle system, but I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize by saying that it&amp;rsquo;s relatively simple but detailed enough to be interesting. Also, since glory is awarded based on individual action, there is an inherent tension in needing to cooperate to defeat foes, but wanting to prevent the other heroes from doing better than you. In addition to being the game&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;scoreboard&amp;rdquo;, glory works as the experience of the game. 10 glory = 1 advance, and advances buy you bigger dice at a rate equal to half the sides of the current die. So, to go from a d6 to a d8, you&amp;rsquo;d pay 3 advances. From a d8 to a d10 would be 4 advances, and so on. You must advance to each die in turn, you can&amp;rsquo;t skip any. Each advance also ups your &amp;lsquo;legend&amp;rsquo; which is the scoreboard of the game. The hero with the highest legend gets to add +2 to any orate rolls to determine who makes decisions for the hero band (yup, you even roll who&amp;rsquo;s the leader!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to glory, you have another tracker called &amp;ldquo;Fate&amp;rdquo;. Mortals start with 0, but half-divine heroes start at 8. Fate only goes up, never down. Your fate goes up when your hero is defeated in a battle, when you complete a quest successfully, or when you challenge a god to a contest in order to resist their demand that you go on a quest. In addition to these, you can chose to up your fate for in game benefits like not taking damage from an attack. or to get rid of impairment. Also, as your fate goes up, your name die increases to a d8, d10, and d12. Here&amp;rsquo;s the catch, though. Fate is quite literally a ticking clock on your heroic career. When your fate is filled up (16 boxes, so half-divine characters start out more powerful but have half the time to be glorious) your hero is done. You can look at a handy little chart to see how your final legend score means you meet your end (glorious battle, horrible shame, or old and fat and happy). Once your hero retires or is dead, you get to create a new hero who&amp;rsquo;s a little more powerful (based on how many quests your prior hero completed, so no running up the fate on purpose to get to a better hero!) than your old hero was to start. I rather like the tension between cost and benefit and various trade-offs here, and I think it&amp;rsquo;s a nifty game mechanic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole game, really, is all about cost/benefit trade-offs. GMs have to spend strife to make challenges. Players end up giving the GM more strife whenever they rest to heal and recover. Players may expect oaths if they help you out. And so forth. It makes for interesting decision making and gives yet another thing to be competitive over.   Like with the town creation in &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; has a really nifty island creation system. It can be used randomly or you can choose elements from the various tables (terrain types, residents, monsters, et cetera) to your taste. But it provides ready made sources of quests and conflict to get involved in. I fully plan on taking the idea of rich, interesting random setting generation and adding it into my toolbox for pick-up games that have to be created on the fly. Other elements of the GMing chapter I really appreciated were really good minion rules for mowing through hordes of lesser enemies, and the advice on NPC creation. It says that you should remember that the PCs are the stars of the show, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean NPCs should be flat or boring. Rather, you should ensure that your NPCs have motivations that will create interest &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; the characters. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s someone who thinks the heroes will solve all his problems or someone who thinks killing them will solve all his problems, his focus of action should lead to the PCs so that he remains relevant and interesting to the group and keeps the focus on the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, at the back of the book, the author provides a list of suggested variants and what rules changes would be necessary. He points out that a Norse variant would require almost no mechanical changes and only really flavor ones. This idea struck me as so cool that I&amp;rsquo;m working on a Norse variant. I emailed Mr. Harper about permission to do this and any restraints he wanted on distribution, and he gave me the go ahead on making it and distributing it however I like, so expect to see it here when I finish! I&amp;rsquo;m equally excited about either running a straight-up Greek Agon game or the Norse variant once I get it hammered out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don&amp;rsquo;t think Agon would be the best starter game for new RPG players. I don&amp;rsquo;t want my players&amp;rsquo; first experience with RPGs to be in competition with each other, since most games do not operate that way, and it can in fact be quite rude to be actively competitive with your fellow party members in some games. I feel like a better method of development would be to get used to cooperating and then learn to compete in a friendly fashion rather than the other way around. Also, Agon is less narratively/story focused than I&amp;rsquo;d like to start players out on for reasons discussed in some of my other posts. Still, with the right group of players (maybe ones more used to strategy board games than RPGs) this might be just the ticket, as you&amp;rsquo;re still competing against your friends, but you&amp;rsquo;re controlling a single hero rather than armies or gathering resources or what have you. As always, questions, comments, and even attacks are all welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-03-18-agon/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Dogs in the Vineyard</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-03-18-dogs-in-vineyard/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 12:16:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-03-18-dogs-in-vineyard/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-03-18-dogs-in-vineyard/ -&lt;p&gt;Okay, long time, no post. I apologize, and will try to make with the regular updates!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the moment, I&amp;rsquo;m going to set aside my more general and theoretical speculation about RPGs and discuss some concrete examples. Of course, I plan to sneak general applicability into my discussion, but I&amp;rsquo;ve recently become acquainted with some games that get me very excited, and I want to talk about why. This is still going to be a part of my &amp;lsquo;starter RPG&amp;rsquo; series, because I approached these rules not only as potentially fun games in and of themselves, but with a critical eye towards innovations and techniques worth steeling, with ease of use by new players as the lens through which I viewed these innovations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first game to discuss is going to be &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com/dogsources.html&#34;&gt;Dogs in the Vineyard&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. I mentioned this game in my last post as an example of a just barely alternate history western. No steam powered airships or undead gunmen, just lots of pseudo-Mormons. That being said, the game purposely leaves the setting vague and invites you to experiment and switch things around to your and your players&amp;rsquo; tastes. This game also has the distinction of being one of two on my list by the same creator, D. Vincent Baker. His games were highly recommended throughout the online RPG community as great examples of what &amp;ldquo;Indie Games&amp;rdquo; can and should be, and I&amp;rsquo;ve taken to them like a weasel to a bag full of suet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a general introduction to the game, players take on the role of &amp;lsquo;Dogs&amp;rsquo;, the colloquial name for protectors of the faithful. &amp;ldquo;The Faith&amp;rdquo; is purposely left vague, but as presented in the game is basically early Mormonism. The Dogs journey from town to town and see to the spiritual ills of the communities. But they&amp;rsquo;re not priests in the normal sense, as their job is to see only to those spiritual troubles that have spilled into concrete actions, like spite, jealousy, and murder. With that established, you basically have a reason for a group of people to go from town to town and get into conflicts in good wild west fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first interesting feature of the DITV rules is that dice are used as stats, from D4s up through D10s. Stats can also be a mix, e.g. 2D6 1D4, which would mean that stat has all three of those dice to put towards a conflict. More on how the dice are used in conflict resolution in a moment. What&amp;rsquo;s cool here is that higher numbers beat out lower numbers, so while a D6 gives you a better probability of beating a D4, a 3 beats a 1 whatever die it&amp;rsquo;s rolled on.  You&amp;rsquo;ll also see that the number of dice versus the value of the dice (i.e. having 2D6 rather than 1D8) has more effect than just smoothing out your probability. I like this feature because D&amp;amp;D tricks a lot of us into the default position of &amp;ldquo;die roll plus number vs difficulty&amp;rdquo;, or if you&amp;rsquo;re more old school &amp;ldquo;die roll versus number, roll lower&amp;rdquo; to succeed. Not that there&amp;rsquo;s anything wrong with a roll + stat (+ skill) type approach, but it&amp;rsquo;s refreshing to be reminded that this isn&amp;rsquo;t the only way to do it. Of course, another popular system, Storyteller is similar, where your stats and skills are basically the number of D10s you roll vs a target number, and then you see how many successes you have, but the introduction of multiple dice types adds some subtlety. Plus all those crazy dice are cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s really cool, though, is not that you use dice for stats, but how those dice factor into conflict resolution. First off, you determine what&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;at stake&amp;rdquo; in a conflict. At the end of the conflict, whoever is left will get to decide what happens to what&amp;rsquo;s at stake. Then you figure out the specifics of where it&amp;rsquo;s taking place (anything that might be important like who&amp;rsquo;s watching, chairs that could be smashed, exits that could be escaped through, et cetera). Then you figure out who&amp;rsquo;s participating. At this point, everybody participating takes up the relevant dice and throws them all at once. The dice you roll depend on what category the conflict starts out in: Just talking, physical, physical fighting, and gunplay. If a character has a relationship at stake, or has relationship dice representing his opponent in the conflict, he rolls the relevant relationship dice (relationship dice can cover the obvious like brother, uncle, or what have you, as well as less obvious like &amp;lsquo;the town drunk I helped home one time&amp;rsquo;). That&amp;rsquo;s it for the initial dice. Dice for traits and things come up when and if they&amp;rsquo;re used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, everybody involved has their dice rolled and out on the table. Whoever&amp;rsquo;s opening the conflict starts out by picking two dice to use as his first &amp;ldquo;raise&amp;rdquo;. You can choose any two of your dice, and as you put them forward, you must describe what action those dice represent. The action is something your opponent can&amp;rsquo;t ignore, and must fit the scope of the conflict you&amp;rsquo;re currently at (so if you&amp;rsquo;re just talking, you can&amp;rsquo;t describe your action as punching a guy in the face, you have to escalate to physical conflict for that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your opponent will then attempt to &amp;lsquo;see&amp;rsquo; your raise. He can put forward, one, two, or more dice to see. If he can match your raise with only one die, he has &amp;ldquo;reversed the blow&amp;rdquo; and takes no negative effect, and in fact reverses it against you. He gets to keep that die to use when it&amp;rsquo;s his turn to raise. If he uses two dice to see, he has somehow negated the effect of your action with no negative effect to either of you. If it takes 3 or more dice to see, your opponent &amp;ldquo;takes the blow&amp;rdquo;, which means he&amp;rsquo;s still in the conflict, but he takes a negative effect for your action. After the conflict is resolved, he&amp;rsquo;ll take a number of fallout dice equal to how many dice he had to see with. The size of the fallout dice increases depending on the type of conflict (each fallout die from just talking is a d4, while fallout dice from shooting are d10s). Finally, if an opponent can&amp;rsquo;t or won&amp;rsquo;t see a raise, he can &amp;lsquo;give&amp;rsquo;, which means he&amp;rsquo;s out of the conflict, but he doesn&amp;rsquo;t take any further fallout dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players then take turns raising and seeing. If there are more than two opponents, one player will raise, each other affected by your action will see, then the next player will raise and each other will see, and so on. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s say you run out of dice to see or raise, but you&amp;rsquo;re not happy with where the conflict is ending, what do you do? You escalate! This is where you go from, say, just talking to making a break for it, or throwing a punch, or drawing a gun. When you escalate, you look at what stats are appropriate to the new type of conflict and roll those dice. You can only ever roll a stat, trait, or thing once in a conflict, so if you&amp;rsquo;ve already used one stat for a lesser type of conflict, you don&amp;rsquo;t reroll it when you escalate. Likewise, once you&amp;rsquo;ve introduced a trait or item, you don&amp;rsquo;t get to roll it again no matter how many times you use that trait or thing. Eventually, somebody gives by choice or by being out of things they can roll, and whoever is left in the conflict decides what happens with what&amp;rsquo;s at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the conflict, those fallout dice mentioned get rolled, and depending on what&amp;rsquo;s rolled, you get experience, short term effects, long term effects, minor injuries, serious injuries, or you&amp;rsquo;re dying. Note that due to the size of dice associated with different types of conflict, you can&amp;rsquo;t get injured from a conflict that never escalates past &amp;lsquo;just talking&amp;rsquo; and you can&amp;rsquo;t end up &amp;lsquo;dying&amp;rsquo; unless guns come into the picture (a bit of dramatic license here, since obviously stabbing or severe beating could kill someone, but the game is set up so that such unglamorous things won&amp;rsquo;t off your character unless you want them to for dramatic reasons).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a really rough outline of the conflict resolution, and examples make it much clearer, but I don&amp;rsquo;t want to reproduce too much of the rules here. The point is that the rules are heavily narratively focused, and they give a lot of narrative power to the players, since if they win the conflict, they dictate how it ends and what effects it has. A lot of the &amp;lsquo;fallout&amp;rsquo; also isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily bad, as even ostensibly negative effects can help you have more say in narrative events (for example, you might do something like gain relationship dice of &amp;lsquo;hated foe&amp;rsquo; with the guy who kicked your ass, which could be used any time you&amp;rsquo;re in conflict with him from then on). I also like the back and forth nature of conflict resolution. One of the subtler points of the system is that it quietly encourages both the players and the GMs to escalate conflicts while still allowing meaningful resolution without escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system for traits and things is extremely open ended. You&amp;rsquo;re given a certain number of dice to assign, and you can make up whatever traits or things you want with those dice. While some obviously useful things can be chosen like &amp;ldquo;Good Shot&amp;rdquo;, you can also go for potentially more interesting approaches, like having a trait &amp;ldquo;I love my gun&amp;rdquo;. Sure, the first one would come up whenever you need to shoot well, but the second one might have more scope, but still might help out when making a shot with your particular gun. Even seemingly non-useful things like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m a drunk&amp;rdquo; can give you more say in certain conflicts, but in others your opponent gets to use them. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend this system to extremely munchkiny players, as the only limit on &amp;lsquo;min/maxing&amp;rsquo; is the combined opinion of GM and players. With a group sufficiently dedicated to narrative play, however, it is an extremely flexible and empowering tool for coming up with and resolving in-game conflicts.   Which leads me to perhaps the most abstract benefit of these rules I gleaned, namely the focus on conflict. You&amp;rsquo;ll see the same thing when I review &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; by the same designer. In both games he elucidates that the key source of interest in an RPG is conflict in which the players participate. This is usually most obviously represented by the strong focus on combat in most RPGs, but it supports a conclusion I discovered on my own years ago with one of my first forays into game design. Around about 6th and 7th grade, a few friends of mine and I tooled around with on-the fly games in order to play in settings for which we had no game system at the time (which was pretty much everything except D&amp;amp;D - we played a Final Fantasy III RPG, a Middle Earth RPG, and numerous others). After a while, I got bored with doing nothing but proceeding from fight to fight and sought the opposite extreme of a game with no fighting. I created a game based on running your own business and only ever ran a session or two with a friend of mine as the only player. Pretty quickly the reason for fights in games became evident: it was awfully boring. Strangely enough, my friend who I was running for enjoyed it and requested to play it for some time after, but I&amp;rsquo;d always put him off because I got bored running it with no fights to design and run. What I had failed to grasp was that conflict is what provides excitement and drama, and at the time I was too inexperienced and unknowledgeable to create conflict that wasn&amp;rsquo;t fighting. Both &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; do an excellent job of pointing out that conflict comes in many forms and providing rules for handling all those forms consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, one of the most useful parts of the rules is its system for town generation. Not simply a system for coming up with what buildings and businesses exist in a town, it starts with the assumption that the players wouldn&amp;rsquo;t go there, or at least play time wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be used, if there were no conflicts there. So, the system also creates ready made conflicts for the players to walk into the middle of. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the best ways I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen to quickly and easily create a dynamic and engaging environment for gameplay, and it provides for rich roleplaying and decision making without any sort of overarching storyline or plot. In fact, in this game as well as in &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;, D. Vincent Baker discourages the GM from having set storylines in mind, saying that this takes away agency from the players and results in something less like a game and more like a &amp;lsquo;choose your own adventure&amp;rsquo; book with the GM as the author. This is a valuable point to keep in mind, because most GMs, myself included, love creating intricate worlds and epic storylines (it&amp;rsquo;s a large part of why we want to GM instead of play). The trouble is that your job as GM is not to provide novel-worthy plots or history book worthy detailed settings, it is to facilitate your players having a good time, and if your players don&amp;rsquo;t want to explore the plot or world details that you&amp;rsquo;ve painstakingly created, it&amp;rsquo;s not fun to railroad them into it anyway. Fortunately, both of his RPGs I&amp;rsquo;ve read do an amazingly job of providing resources to come up with interesting, rich roleplaying situations on the fly that allow tons of room for player ownership and involvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I&amp;rsquo;ll close with an analysis of what I do and don&amp;rsquo;t want to take away from these rules for a starter RPG and why I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ll use it &amp;ldquo;as is&amp;rdquo; and instead will continue with designing my own. To address the last point first, I have to admit that part of the reason for designing my own game is because I like designing games. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to not let that be the leading reason, as having a fully home grown game that is less readily available than some other already created game inherently limits its usefulness and options, as any players that get used to it will only be able to play it with me running it or with our circle of gamers. So I&amp;rsquo;m trying to keep an open mind about finding more widely popular games that adequately address all of the issues I want to see covered in a starter RPG. That being said, while I think &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; is an excellent game that I would love to run or play, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s the best choice for a brand new group. First off, it demands a lot of its players as well as its GM. I feel like the level of player control of narrative and responsibility in choosing traits and things for character development reasons rather than concrete benefit might be a little much for people first introduced to gaming. On the other hand, maybe setting the bar high on such levels of player responsibility and involvement would be inculcating good habits. I also feel that the core mechanic, while elegant and flavorful, is a bit much to explain to complete neophytes, though the popularity of poker makes the rounds of &amp;lsquo;raises&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;sees&amp;rsquo; perhaps more accessible. Also, the game lends itself to weighty moral questions and dramatic situations rather than the easier pleasures of high adventure and heroics. Plus, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure I&amp;rsquo;d like there to be some elements of the fantastical in my starter game so that there&amp;rsquo;s something to grab the imagination. As always, I look forward to your thoughts on all of my conclusions. Next up I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss a game that has grabbed me so strong I&amp;rsquo;m working on an expansion for it!&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-03-18-dogs-in-vineyard/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Matter of Taste</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:58:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/ -&lt;p&gt;So, before we go into how to encourage a particular genre with the rules, there is the question of what genre to shoot for. If my whole contention is that the real draw of RPGs is the non-mechanical aspects, then a good starter RPG needs to have a genre with wide appeal and plenty of material to fire the imagination. I&amp;rsquo;ll run through a brief list of some popular settings/genres and my thoughts on them, but this is an area where personal taste could cloud my judgement extraordinarily easily, so I would very much appreciate comments on what flavors are good choices for players new to roleplaying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heroic Fantasy&lt;/strong&gt;: By &amp;lsquo;Heroic Fantasy&amp;rsquo;, I basically mean Dungeons and Dragons. I&amp;rsquo;ll include the grittier Sword and Sorcery flavor under this umbrella to keep things brief. In a heroic fantasy game, the players take on the roles of gifted individuals in a fantastic world (usually pseudo-medieval) and fight monsters and villains with magic, blades, and bows (again, usually. Star Wars has a lot of &amp;lsquo;heroic fantasy&amp;rsquo; elements, despite being in space). Settings frequently come from mythology, popular fantasy books (like Lord of the Rings), or historical/pseudo-historical sources (like &amp;lsquo;7th Sea&amp;rsquo;, which is roughly based on Age of Exploration Europe, but is a made up world with its own history). Benefits include that it is a familiar genre/setting to just about everyone, wide flexibility in the sorts of characters that are helpful, and just plain imagination firing fantastic elements. Negatives are that many folks have negative stereotypes associated with the genre (it&amp;rsquo;s nerdy, it&amp;rsquo;s for kids, it&amp;rsquo;s the work of Satan, et cetera), and that many of the things you can do (magic, sword fights, lots of monsters running around) lend themselves to more complex rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Space Opera&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes, the Star Wars genre. As mentioned above, it has a lot in common with heroic fantasy, and considering both have ancestors in the late 19th and early 20th century pulp writers, this is unsurprising. Space Operas are characterized by, well, space, as well as a usually &amp;lsquo;fuzzy&amp;rsquo; approach to science and technology, a wealth of alien species and cultures, and a generally swashbuckling approach to problems. Benefits include wide knowledge and acceptance of (at least for Star Wars) which gives you players who already have a &amp;lsquo;buy in&amp;rsquo; to the setting, the excuse to come up with just about any situation you want for adventures (on this newly discovered planet. . .), and the fact that you get to use laser guns. Downsides could include many of those listed for heroic fantasy, as well as the potential to need to handle multiple scales of conflict - human scale as well as space ship scale, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hard Science Fiction&lt;/strong&gt;: Hard science fiction is a setting where the technology all either exists or else is based on extrapolations from current knowledge that are all consistent with modern knowledge of physics and science. A frequent &amp;lsquo;freebie&amp;rsquo; is to assume some newly discovered aspect of the physical world that allows faster than light travel, and then treat everything else more rigorously. The emphasis on gritty realism of technology usually spills over into other venues, with realistic politics and gritty challenges based on the hard realities of space being popular sources of drama. Babylon 5, Jovian Chronicles, and Starship Troopers (the book, not the movie) are all &amp;lsquo;hard&amp;rsquo; sci-fi to some degree or another. While the grittier drama and more serious tone of the game might appeal to some players, in reality this is even more of a niche genre than Space Opera or Heroic Fantasy. I love it so, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s a good choice as a default for a starter game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pulp!&lt;/strong&gt;: As alluded to earlier, pulp writing covers a fairly large range of genres, from HP Lovecraft to H Rider Haggard to Edgar Rice Burroughs and beyond. Spirit of the Century does an excellent job of marking out a &amp;lsquo;default&amp;rsquo; pulp setting that focuses on early 20th century adventure with hints of the weird creeping in (rather like Indiana Jones) and an emphasis on the saving power of Science! I like to think of pulp as a genre &amp;lsquo;overlay&amp;rsquo;. Since a huge variety of pulp magazines published a multitude of genres from historical fiction to weird horror, you can easily pick some other more general genre, and &amp;lsquo;pulp it&amp;rsquo;. In pulping a genre, expect to up the action, up the melodrama, make the main characters a little larger than life, make the extras a little more two dimensional, and to keep the pace frenetic. Benefits of the default roaring 20s pulp setting or the wider pulp genre umbrella include emphasis on action, a purposefully simple approach to the world, and a flexibility in what sort of elements to incorporate. Downsides are that a lot of the original pulp sources are, well, written for adolescent boys in the 20s and 30s (or even before), and so tend to be sexist and occasionally racist. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean your game needs to bring those elements in, but your players may have existing baggage about the setting. That being said, I&amp;rsquo;m leaning pretty strongly towards a pulp &amp;lsquo;flavor&amp;rsquo; to whatever genre I pick, and Spirit of the Century is already an excellent quick to pick up game with a delightful roaring 20s pulp setting in the vein of Doc Savage or Johnny Quest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Horror/Supernatural&lt;/strong&gt;: For ease, I&amp;rsquo;m rolling together all the different flavors of horror and games about things that bump in the night. Vampire, Call of Cthulhu (pulp horror!), or whatever else, all of these games have a strong focus on either being scary, or at least on dark subject matter. As with the hard sci-fi, this darker subject matter may appeal to certain folks, especially those wishing their games to have a consciously more &amp;lsquo;mature&amp;rsquo; theme. While I love this genre, I have a few issues with it as a starter game. For one, it&amp;rsquo;s really hard to establish genuine horror in an RPG, and I imagine struggling to remember new rules and how this whole roleplaying thing works can&amp;rsquo;t contribute to a feeling of dread. Likewise, by its nature, horror tends to touch on disturbing and unpleasant subject matter, and one of the ways RPGs make those themes especially immediate is to thrust the players into dealing with them directly via their characters. I think a starter game should be way more concerned with making players comfortable than with pushing their boundaries. So, with a heavy sigh, I&amp;rsquo;m going to put aside the sanity points and save them for when my novice roleplayers are hungry for more depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(a potential exception: a game on or around Halloween, when everybody&amp;rsquo;s in a spooky-stuff mood anyway)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Westerns&lt;/strong&gt;: Here&amp;rsquo;s a genre with even wider appeal than the Space Opera or Heroic Fantasy settings. Not everybody loves westerns, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty rare to find someone who is entirely opposed to the idea. You have plenty of opportunity for action, violence, heists, and otherwise living outside the comfortable reach of the law or social norms. Unfortunately, being based on a fairly recent and well-known historical period gives you less room to play with things. Alternate history is a good way to get around this, and &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com/dogsources.html&#34;&gt;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; does an amazing job of keeping a rock-solid western feel while allowing plenty of flexibility in making the game world suit your group. Some problems that could come out of a totally historical western are things like gender roles, race relations, and the interference of actual historical personages. I would give Samurai settings their own entry, but if Kurosawa and his influence on latter-day westerns didn&amp;rsquo;t convince you, most of the issues and benefits apply equally to Samurai settings as they do to westerns, except that in America, it&amp;rsquo;s a narrower interest than westerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Action (the Ah-nahld genre)&lt;/strong&gt;: By &amp;lsquo;Action&amp;rsquo;, I here mean the genre of popcorn munching action movies. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name of it, but I played a pick up game based on action movies where the more ridiculous and cinematic your described action, the &lt;em&gt;easier&lt;/em&gt; it was to succeed. Suffice to say, it was entertaining and people went over the top. This is a fun and easy to get into genre with loads of cultural context to fit it into. On the other hand, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t by nature focus very much on the roleplaying aspect of things, being defined instead by the aspects of the game most usually revolving around dice and mechanics. My personal take is that Action is a genre better mined for content to throw into other genres/settings than one to host a game all by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other genres I have less experience with (Gaming-wise) and thus less to say, but thought I should throw out there are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Super Heroes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cops&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pirates&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kung Fu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Super Spies&lt;/em&gt; (maybe a subgenre of Action!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Humorous&lt;/em&gt; (see my entry &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.wordpress.com/2010/02/05/dungeons-and-t%E2%80%A6om-outer-space/&#34;&gt;Dungeons and Teenagers from
Outerspace&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said at the get go, I&amp;rsquo;d love the hear your thoughts on various roleplaying genres and their utility for introducing new players.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Setting vs Genre</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:52:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/ -&lt;p&gt;Right now I want to talk about a distinction I recently came up with between setting and genre. Both get used pretty interchangeably with respect to RPGs, with setting usually having a slightly narrower focus. And either one is usually considered fairly separate from rules issues. But in a discussion of whether it was better to have specific rules for every game setting, or to have a great set of generic rules to use in whatever setting, I realized something about the interaction of the game rules and the game world that I think warrants a distinction in terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that game rules have more to do with what the people in the world can do, and what sorts of things are likely to happen. More focused on the action and tone than on the physical places, objects and people. Pretty arbitrarily, I decided &amp;lsquo;genre&amp;rsquo; fits this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separate from genre, then, is setting. By setting here, I mean the actual physical characteristics. The scenery, the playable races, the technology level, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, these two categories interact and overlap to a fair degree, but some examples might help to clarify what I mean, and then I&amp;rsquo;ll go into why I think rules affect genre more than setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have two games with similar settings. Both take place over many planets, have people and aliens with spaceships and guns, and include faster than light travel, lasers, and psychic powers. But in one of these settings, psychic powers come from tapping into a dangerous and largely hostile alternate dimension, humanity is xenophobic and backwards, technology is little understood and maintained by a semi-mystical priesthood, and there is only war. In the other, psychic powers represent the next step in evolution, humans interact with aliens in a number of ways, including trade, diplomacy, and war, technology is basically an extrapolation of what is currently understood, and one piece of it is the last, best hope for peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the physical elements of both settings have little to distinguish them, but what those worlds &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; with these things makes all the difference in the world. While both have &amp;lsquo;space&amp;rsquo; as a setting, one has a genre of &amp;lsquo;gothic science fantasy&amp;rsquo; while the other might be called &amp;lsquo;hard science political drama&amp;rsquo; (or, you might call one &amp;lsquo;Warhammer 40,000&amp;rsquo; and the other &amp;lsquo;Babylon 5&amp;rsquo;, but you get the idea).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my suspicion that game rules have more influence on genre than they do on setting. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure that if you made a space game with minimally modified D&amp;amp;D rules, it would still &amp;lsquo;feel&amp;rsquo; like heroic fantasy, even though your barbarian has chain axes and your space elf has a laser bow, or whatever. Or else you get Spelljammer. That would also explain why you have had for a long time a number of campaign settings for D&amp;amp;D with minimal rules tweaks, but those that change the genre significantly from heroic fantasy have had the most significant rules changes (like horror in Ravenloft or post-apocalyptic survival in Dark Sun).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good rule of thumb for finding the difference between setting and genre is to take a game world (or movie world or whatever) and see if you can describe it as some cliche or familiar genre in X (where X describes a difference in physical location). Some example might include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a western in Space&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like cyberpunk in the wild west, but with steam power&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like a medieval x-files&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, where all this gets me is that the goal of rules design is to come up with rules that reinforce the genre of a game rather than trying to capture aspects of the setting. If your setting has elves, that&amp;rsquo;s cool and all, but if they&amp;rsquo;re just tall, pretty people they don&amp;rsquo;t really need different rules. But if elven culture causes them to act in very different ways, or if subtle differences in their physiology makes them move differently, then rules can reinforce that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agon does an amazing job of defining its genre through rules, and even suggests multiple settings in addition to the default of ancient Greek mythology that would use the same genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is this a useful distinction? Or is it splitting hairs?&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Rules and Roleplaying</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:51:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/ -&lt;p&gt;Well, last time I talked about how I want to focus more on roleplay than on game mechanics in my starter RPG. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: I&amp;rsquo;m a huge game mechanics nut. Sometimes I enjoy designing game rules more than I do actually playing them. As a kid, I once stayed up all night designing a wargame for little green army men that we never got to play because we were so excited about coming up with rules for each weapon, each vehicle, and every situation we could imagine. I mean, that is why I&amp;rsquo;m writing a game design blog right now, after all. So, for a starter RPG, whatever rules I do come up with, I want to be quality rules, but I want them to push the focus towards roleplaying rather than on to the interaction of different parts of the rules (such as which combination of options makes the best combat monster, or whatever). Later on, I&amp;rsquo;ll have a whole series of posts on what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from reading the works of smarter and more experienced game designers than myself, but for now I&amp;rsquo;ll layout some general thoughts on the interaction of rules and roleplaying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my post on Setting vs Genre, I talked about how rules interact more with the &amp;lsquo;genre&amp;rsquo; of a game than with the setting. Basically I defined genre as having more to do with how things in your game world act and what people do with them, whereas setting is the stuff that&amp;rsquo;s there. With this distinction, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty obvious that rules would have more to do with genre since rules cover actions. You don&amp;rsquo;t have rules for whether a tree is there or not (well, you might if you have an anally retentive terrain generation system for a focus on tactics, but even there your interest is in how it will interact with the people around it). But you do have rules for the more common actions, like fast-talking and shooting and investigating and such like. And I&amp;rsquo;m willing to bet that your game has much more detailed investigation rules if it&amp;rsquo;s about discovering hidden truths and following mysteries than a game about fighting monsters and taking their treasure would have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this gets us into an important interaction between rules and roleplaying: rules are for when the characters do stuff. And, more specifically, they&amp;rsquo;re for when they do stuff that someone else might take issue with. You usually don&amp;rsquo;t roll because a character walks across the street. But when he rushes across the street attempting to dodge machine gun fire, you probably would roll something! There&amp;rsquo;s a conflict of interest here. This is what makes the situation interesting enough to focus in on with rules. That conflict also makes it important to determine which party gets to have its say, and things are more fair when there are rules involved. Otherwise it might be roleplaying, but it&amp;rsquo;s not a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us back to genre. Genre helps you to determine what conflicts of interest are worth paying attention to, and how much attention to pay to them. Pretty much any game is going to pay at least some attention to people trying to do violence to one another (or to owlbears or mynocks, or whatever), but it says a lot about the genre desired if the game has detailed rules on quick-draw duels or back and forth sword fights or large scale battles. A particular game system might have some kind of rules for all of those violent conflicts of interest, but it&amp;rsquo;s a good bet that it focuses in on some more than others, and it&amp;rsquo;s a better bet that that focus is on those ares most relevant to the genre of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since actual play time is the only currency that really matters in a game (hat tip to &lt;a href=&#34;http://arsludi.lamemage.com&#34;&gt;Ars Ludi&lt;/a&gt;), genre influencing rules will actually bend the roleplaying towards the genre the game is designed for. If you cover a pistol duel with one quick set of highly abstracted rolls that nobody is really optimized for, pistol dueling is a lot less likely to take a central place in the headspace of the players. If, on the other hand, you have detailed step by step rules that tie into multiple characteristics such that everybody has something relevant to pistol dueling and some folks are especially good at it, the game is going to take more time and focus on that situation, and players will devote more time and attention to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other side of this coin is pretty important, though. And that is where rules substitute for roleplaying. Imagine a game where you simply said &amp;ldquo;Okay, roll to see how well your conversation went&amp;rdquo; with zero actual talking. Again with thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://arsludi.lamemage.com&#34;&gt;Ars Ludi&lt;/a&gt;, one common example is the spot check. Overuse of perception type skills takes players out of asking questions about their environment and becoming involved in it. And this brings me to another important element in &amp;lsquo;what rules are for in an RPG&amp;rsquo;: rules are for doing the things that the players can&amp;rsquo;t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might cover the fact that there are no actual goblins to hit with a sword, or it might cover the fact that most folks who want to play a scholar of arcane secrets probably aren&amp;rsquo;t themselves scholars of arcane secrets. But when it comes to deciding what a player pays attention to, or coming up with plans, that very much is in the player&amp;rsquo;s control. When it comes to running a game, my rule of thumb when deciding whether something should be handled by the player or by the character&amp;rsquo;s abilities is to go with what results in more interesting play. Thus, if a fairly dumb and unimaginative character is played by a clever player who comes up with a zany plan for a heist that will make the game more fun for everyone, then the dumb character has a brilliant flash of insight. Or, if a player doesn&amp;rsquo;t know much about astrophysics, but it will make the game go along better for his character to come up with something in that field, then he can break out the dice. But for writing rules, especially those meant to encourage roleplaying more than mastery of a particular game system, I want to build in the right preferences, rather than relying on individual GMs to &amp;lsquo;make it work&amp;rsquo; (though I&amp;rsquo;m sure they will, as GMs making fun games out of whatever rules they use is a long and proud tradition).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the way to go here is to create broad, flexible rules that deal more with generals than with specifics. Perhaps build in the option for players and GMs to delve deeper into specifics if they want, but if I have a choice between creating a game where you more frequently here &amp;ldquo;Well, there&amp;rsquo;s not really a rule for that, so just roll X + Y and we&amp;rsquo;ll see how it goes&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;No, you can&amp;rsquo;t do that, because you didn&amp;rsquo;t take X trait, Y feat, and Z specialization&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;d much rather go for the former. Some of the game rules I&amp;rsquo;ve read recently have introduced me to some really exciting ways to get a lot done with few, streamlined rules, and in the next few posts I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss some of these ideas. But in the meantime, what do you think about how rules encourage or discourage roleplaying?&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The RP in RPG</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:42:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/ -&lt;p&gt;In my last post I talked about my own introduction to RPGs through D&amp;amp;D and it&amp;rsquo;s possible shortcomings as a game for new players, and then a game I found particularly suited to the task, Teenagers From Outer Space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why set out to create a set of rules specifically for the purpose of introducing players to the hobby? Well, for one I have pragmatic reasons. I&amp;rsquo;m living and working in a place where I don&amp;rsquo;t know any other roleplayers, and so I don&amp;rsquo;t have the opportunity to indulge in my hobby of choice. But for another, I feel like it&amp;rsquo;s a niche that could use filling. Most people who try out roleplaying are talked through their first few sessions by a more experienced friend in whatever game that friend happens to be playing or to particularly like. Or else a group of friends stumbles on one of the big ones (usually Dungeons and Dragons, which has recognized it&amp;rsquo;s place as practically the only RPG with name recognition outside of roleplaying circles and introduced starter kits in a box and so forth).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the reasons outlined in my prior post with respect to D&amp;amp;D (though they apply to other established systems as well), I feel like the focus is often wrong in these introductory attempts. The D&amp;amp;D in a box games provide little background flavor or opportunities to delve into characters. Joining an existing game in a full-featured system can have a steep learning curve.   So, where do I think the focus should be? For one, I think the focus should be more on the RP and less on the G. Most folks already have a pretty good idea what a game is, and from childhood have been trained to follow some fairly arbitrary rules in order to have fun. What RPGs offer that parcheesi or checkers don&amp;rsquo;t is the ability to combine the imagination and storytelling involved with reading a good book or getting into a movie with the structure and social elements of a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to come up with rules powerful enough to cover whatever situation a wily group of players may find themselves in (or at least, powerful enough to give the GM a fighting chance in winging it) but simple enough to be picked up quickly and to take a back seat to character decision making and interaction. I figure that anyone whose interests lean to character development and interaction will either keep up with my system or find other games with a similar philosophy and enjoy their interactive storytelling. Likewise, those players who find themselves hankering for more definition to their actions and tactical decision making can be led to those games that better fit their tastes. But I think it&amp;rsquo;s easier to go from roleplaying focused games to &amp;lsquo;crunchy&amp;rsquo; games than it is to go the other way, and that there are more folks more likely to be turned off by too much mechanical detail than likely to be turned off of the whole hobby from too little of that and too much story focus.   But I could be wrong, and I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear feedback on why I could be totally mistaken here.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Dungeons and Teenagers from Outer Space</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/ -&lt;p&gt;I have a few ideas on what elements a good &amp;lsquo;starter&amp;rsquo; RPG needs, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through a number of games in order to find more ideas to add to that list. But I&amp;rsquo;ll start with some of my actual play experience with starting new players on RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with the start, my own (and I suspect many others&amp;rsquo;) first RPG was the venerable Dungeons and Dragons. I myself started out with Advanced Dungeons and Dragons Second Edition. I had many a great game of AD&amp;amp;D and it will always hold a special place in my heart, but I have begun to expect that it hooked me into RPGs more because of who I am than because of the rules themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first read through the Players Handbook, I was just a kid (nine years old). I found the rules bewilderingly complex. Once I actually sat down and played, that helped a lot, and when I reread the rules two or three years later, they seemed amazingly simple. For one thing, I&amp;rsquo;m sure my own increased maturity and mental faculties helped, and for another I&amp;rsquo;m sure that having play experience to map the abstract rules onto helped a lot, but recently I&amp;rsquo;ve started wondering if my initial reaction was solely due to my youth, or if perhaps older people with no prior knowledge might find them similarly bewildering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dungeons and Dragons rules, of all editions, show their tactical wargaming roots, with a strong focus on multiple exciting things to do in combat and detailed rules to cover them. Fourth edition has gone a long way towards making these rules easy to grasp, provide balanced play, and to be pretty darn neat, honestly. But as much as I love detailed games and rules systems, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s any of these features that made me grow to love the hobby. THAC0 never fired my imagination, hit dice didn&amp;rsquo;t keep me coming to the table, and encumbrance rules certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t make me think I wanted to branch out and try other roleplaying games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was always the roleplaying itself that gave the rules their spice, the imaginary people and creatures in their imaginary worlds that kept me coming to the table and rolling those neat polyhedral dice. The rules were a means to an end, albeit an interesting means. They were a tool for fleshing out personas and interacting with their surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t very long before I was introduced to one of my favorite RPGs of all time, which produced some of my fondest in-game memories and stories, and yet was one of the least serious approaches to roleplaying I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about Teenagers From Outer Space (R. Talsorian Games, 3rd Edition, when they got all the zany Anime stuff).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teenagers From Outer Space (TFOS) is a light hearted comedy roleplaying game about, well, teenagers, many of whom are from outer space. It helped that I was introduced to it by a talented and entertaining game master who made improvisation seem effortless and who seems to have been made to run wacky, alien-filled John Hughes style stories. He also frequently used TFOS as a &amp;lsquo;gateway drug&amp;rsquo; into the wonderful world of roleplaying games.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Starter RPG Project</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-01-31-starter-rpg-project/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2010 01:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-01-31-starter-rpg-project/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-01-31-starter-rpg-project/ -&lt;p&gt;Well, the first project I&amp;rsquo;m going to share progress on is my attempt to create a roleplaying game custom built to introduce new players, with a strong emphasis on quick character creation, one-off or pick up game playability, and ease of learning the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I&amp;rsquo;m going to layout some of my general philosophy behind what I&amp;rsquo;m doing, and in later posts I&amp;rsquo;ll get into more specifics and make references to games that have influenced me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my reasoning behind a &amp;lsquo;starter&amp;rsquo; focused RPG is pragmatic. I&amp;rsquo;m at a point in my life where I don&amp;rsquo;t have easy access to my gaming friends, but I still have a strong desire to run and play RPGs. So I want to create a gateway drug to get interested friends hooked on a hobby that has entertained me for over a decade already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also am intrigued in the process of refining down to the essentials of an RPG. The quintessence of roleplaying games, if you will. I imagine there&amp;rsquo;s something of a judgement call to be made here, but in reviewing minimalist and alternative roleplaying games, it&amp;rsquo;s become more clear what makes even more traditional games tick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in summary, my goal is to create a game that will be fun, easy to learn and run, and that emphasizes roleplaying and collective storytelling over tactical planning and fighting (not that fights won&amp;rsquo;t be involved, of course, they&amp;rsquo;re just going to be seen more through the lens of why they&amp;rsquo;re dramatic rather than how to most effectively tackle them). I&amp;rsquo;ve got lots more on where I&amp;rsquo;m coming from, with examples, but those deserve more detailed posts.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-01-31-starter-rpg-project/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Greetings!</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-01-29-greetings/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2010 12:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-01-29-greetings/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-01-29-greetings/ -&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone, this blog is going to be a place for me to keep my thoughts on game design and gaming in general, as well as encourage discussion on said thoughts. So, by all means, once the posts start coming, please dive right in.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-01-29-greetings/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 