<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LotFP on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/lotfp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in LotFP on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 23:32:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/lotfp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Review of The Pale Lady&#34; and &#34;The Squid, the Cabal, and the Old Man&#34;</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-07-13-review-of-pale-lady-and-squid-cabal-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 23:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-07-13-review-of-pale-lady-and-squid-cabal-and/</guid>
      <description>So, a couple of adventures that were add-ons to the Better than Any Man kickstarter have been published in the last few months, and I picked them both up today: The Pale Lady by +Zzarchov Kowolski and The Squid, the Cabal, and the Old Man by Andre Novoa. Since both are rather brief, and since I got both at the same time, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d do a double feature review, especially since there&amp;rsquo;s some nice compare and contrast items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emperor Forgive Us</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-30-emperor-forgive-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 11:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-30-emperor-forgive-us/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-IQ57k8grq_Q/VReWYLyKuZI/AAAAAAAAEHg/koeIn53rmSM/s1600/The_Emperor_Revenant.png ## Introduction To kick off my Heresies Without Number game with my home group, I was casting about for an adventure I could run with fairly minimal adaptation. I ended up settling on a D&amp;amp;D adventure that I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to run since I got it last year: Forgive Us from Lamentations of the Flame Princess*. *
As I went through, I discovered it took surprisingly little modification to get it ready for 40k, but since I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to mess up my book for future use as-is, I decided to type up my 40k specific notes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Red &amp; Pleasant Land Layout Review</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-01-27-red-pleasant-land-layout-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 13:43:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-01-27-red-pleasant-land-layout-review/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crapsack Goblins Home Game Report</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-06-24-crapsack-goblins-home-game-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2014 08:26:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-06-24-crapsack-goblins-home-game-report/</guid>
      <description>http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L8hPWdfkCPs/U6mZWjje4zI/AAAAAAAAAxo/1Zmomz1THZA/s1600/The_Great_Goblin_3.jpg
Commentary So last night I was able to run for the first time the game concept I outlined here. Since writing that, I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on the set up a little bit and I was able to subject my regular weekly group to the game rather than trying it out on strangers first. The summary version is that it was hilarious and fun and the combination of setting and rules created exactly the kind of mad-cap goblin shennanigans I was hoping for!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crapsack Goblin Game Idea</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-02-crapsack-goblin-game-idea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 20:02:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-02-crapsack-goblin-game-idea/</guid>
      <description>So, reading some blog entries and some Google+ posts has given me an idea for a game that I&amp;rsquo;d like to run, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know if/when I ever will. Basically, I want to combine the &amp;ldquo;dung ages&amp;rdquo; crapsack vibe from +Thomas Fitzgerald &amp;lsquo;s Middenmurk posts, the super-grungy goblin city-crawling of +Arnold K. &amp;lsquo;s Escape from Yoblin Town, and the &amp;ldquo;everything is scavenged, everything is precious&amp;rdquo; vibe of +Jack Mack &amp;lsquo;s Neanderthal post, along with a lot of encumbrance and equipment wear stuff that Arnold K, Jack Mack, +Logan Knight and others have been talking about a lot recently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of &#34;Better than Any Man&#34; and Mercenary Group Recruitment</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-19-review-of-than-any-man-and-mercenary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 16:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-19-review-of-than-any-man-and-mercenary/</guid>
      <description>So, after my enthusiastic blurb the other day, I figured “Better than Any Man” warranted a full review after I finished reading it last night. So, here that review is.

First off, for those that might not know, what is “Better than Any Man” (hereafter referred to as BTAM)? BTAM is a meaty adventure/mini-sandbox written by James Raggi for his Lamentations of the Flame Princess Adventures line and specifically for “Free RPG Day 2013”.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>