<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>How to Business on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/how-to-business/</link>
    <description>Recent content in How to Business on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 09:33:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/how-to-business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Business Part IV: Strategery</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-12-15-how-to-business-part-iv-strategery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 09:33:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-12-15-how-to-business-part-iv-strategery/</guid>
      <description>Why Strategy “Strategy” is one of those words that gets used so much that it becomes almost meaningless, especially in the business world. It gets used in completely different contexts and means different things depending (as in Magic: the Gathering versus business school versus Clausewitz). In a past life, though, I was a classicist, so I’m going to go with the literal Greek meaning of “Stuff that a General Does”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Business Part III: Negotiations</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-11-03-how-to-business-part-iii-negotiations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 11:29:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-11-03-how-to-business-part-iii-negotiations/</guid>
      <description>Terminology Leverage – Anything that strengthens your negotiating position or weakens undesirable parts of your counterpart’s position Best Alternative – The next best option if you do not come to an agreement in a negotiation Walk Away (Reservation) Point – The very least favorable terms you are willing to accept Goal – The terms you hope to achieve through negotiation Distributive vs Integrative Negotiating Okay, I’ve got some fancy terminology to drop on you, but I thought it was a bit technical to put in the key terminology section: Distributive Negotiation and Integrative Negotiation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Business Aside: Call for Cases</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-24-how-to-business-aside-call-for-cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 13:27:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-24-how-to-business-aside-call-for-cases/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iBU5fNhlyXI/VEoRTZ-I2ZI/AAAAAAAAB7s/iuq5guFnCiE/s1600/1185675043_4.jpg
I&amp;rsquo;d like to take a pause from the &amp;ldquo;How to Business&amp;rdquo; series to make a request of you, the reader. See, in business school, the primary vehicle of learning is the &amp;ldquo;case&amp;rdquo;. A case is a situation drawn from real life, selected because it is illustrative of certain business concepts, and then written up by fancy professors (usually from Harvard) to highlight the most teachable stuff and downplay the rest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Business Part II: Marketing &amp; Pricing</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-14-how-to-business-part-ii-marketing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 22:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-14-how-to-business-part-ii-marketing/</guid>
      <description>So, with all that build up, what is marketing? Let’s take a step sideways and start by defining the core purpose of all for-profit businesses: creating value for a customer and capturing a fair portion of that value. Marketing is not about getting something for nothing or ripping people off or tricking them. It’s not about polishing a turd or portraying a product as something it’s not. What marketing is about is making sure that your business gets some of that value created in the form of customer dollars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Business Part I: Basic Cash Accounting</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-08-how-to-business-part-i-basic-cash/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 20:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-08-how-to-business-part-i-basic-cash/</guid>
      <description>http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-HDQ7rZIizVU/VDYHGdVmYWI/AAAAAAAABvc/c_jiaJYczjw/s1600/scrooge.jpg
Template Ledger Remember my warning in the intro that some stuff sounds lame and boring, but it’s important? Well, big surprise, accounting is one of those. Much as designing games requires understanding some basics about probability, understanding business requires some basics in accounting. Think of this like that bit in the front of the DMG. Even though it’s not as much fun as the others, I hope that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to highlight what&amp;rsquo;s interesting and avoid the boring.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Business: a Primer for Gamers</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-07-how-to-business-primer-for-gamers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 18:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-10-07-how-to-business-primer-for-gamers/</guid>
      <description>Introduction and Philosophy Why Business? So, when I am not reading or writing about things like smelly goblins, interdimensional frog mind-palace adventures, or newer and better forms of magical undead, I am paid to do business things. I am paid to do this because I recently graduated from an institution of higher learning that seems to think that I am now a master of administering business. I say this not to toot my own horn, but just so you know where this stuff is coming from – I had like zero business experience before this.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>