<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 29 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 20:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;Last night’s session saw us with about half the usual group due to a confluence of work and finals for three of the players.  So, that left us with Caleb, Earn, and Yllgrad in the big city of Mickleheim.  Their players were pretty pumped about getting stuff sold and getting to the Volcano, but a) I wanted to flesh out Mickleheim some, b) I wanted to give some of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lotfp.com/store/index.php?route=product/product&amp;amp;product_id=75&#34;&gt;Vornheim city kit rules&lt;/a&gt; and others that I’ve compiled a test drive, and c) I needed some more time to properly prep the volcano adventure, so we ended up zooming in on their errands in the city.    &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/ss_art_gothmagog.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/ss_art_gothmagog.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;ss_art_gothmagog&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the group helped the gate guard come to a decision on whether giants warranted a Slave duty or a Beast duty by simply paying him for his guard duty (or lack thereof).  They decided to play up the whole spectacle of arriving with captive giants (again, why didn’t I cause more trouble with them, why?) so they hired street performers and tossed out coppers to the crowd and swung torches around and such.  Very prince Ali of them.  Well, Cnud, the seneschal for House Dagaeca is a rather poker-faced chap, so while he was impressed, he didn’t make a big fuss out of it.  He ended up offering the party a fair price (gold = xp for the critters, and they had already received full xp for capturing them) which they accepted on account of prior good relations, even though they were a bit disappointed by the value.  Due to some later events, I may end up helping them out some more from House Dagaeca so that they feel like the relationship is going as well as I mean for it to be so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/lepba5a.jpg&#34;&gt;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/lepba5a.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having offloaded their giants for some sort of amusement, they now decide they need to sell the wine discovered in the cellar with the hideous undead abomination.  They took Cnud’s advice and headed to the wine merchant his kitchen patronizes.  Well, let me just say that the Vornheim shopkeeper table is a lot of fun.  It made the whole business of trying to sell the wine a lot more complicated and interesting than it would have been otherwise. At least, I thought so.  Hopefully the players weren’t just frustrated.  At any rate, the first merchant turned out to offer terrible prices and tried to get the wine for a criminally low price, after helping himself to a bottle to sample.  They realized they were being had due to Sir Varian’s vague alcholic’s knowledge of wine, and so said good day, sir.  The next merchant was a crotchety old man with a monkey, who was just on the verge of giving them a reasonable (but not great) price when they made the mistake of being kind to his monkey.  They figured out their mistake, marched in, roughed up the monkey some and made an offer.  After some consideration, he accepted it, but then they told him they had to think about it (aah, intra-party debates).  Well, they tried one more merchant, and this fellow was an eccentric butterfly collector, but gave them an excellent price in exchange for the promise to bring him any butterfly specimens they find.    &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/150px-mr-monday.jpg&#34;&gt;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/150px-mr-monday.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the Vornheim shopkeeper chart was a lot of fun and opened the city up to being more characterful and weird than I probably would have let myself do on my own, so I’m grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and Yllgrad arranged with an apothecary to have some worg fangs turned into a berserker potion, half paid up front, and half to be paid upon receipt.  The apothecary was a fat, friendly fellow who rather cheerfully dealt with a somewhat dour Yllgrad.  More on him in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The party then had the option to rest for the night or to carouse.  Again, I was anxious to flesh out the game and introduce more wacky complications.  Up until this point, I’ve allowed players to blow money willy nilly on booze and wenching in order to convert unwanted gold into xp (we’ve been playing where gold/treasure only earns XP when spent or used, and you only get it once.  There’s some wonky bookkeeping for stuff like fine tapestries decorating their personal home, but it’s been working out).  I wanted carousing to be more interesting, and Jeff Rients’ awesome carousing table seemed to be just the ticket.  Unfortunately, though my players will act all manners of foolhardy in order to obtain gold, they balk in the face of risk in &lt;em&gt;spending&lt;/em&gt; gold.  I worry that it’s a bit fair to be putting strings on spending gold for XP just as they’re getting to the levels where you really need to spend &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; to level up, but hopefully this will result in them doing things like getting involved in local politics, building up their town, et cetera.  We’ll see. I also think some of the absent players (Sir Varian’s in particular) will dive right into carousing and potential mishaps with great abandon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/keg_endheader.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/keg_endheader.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;keg_endheader&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my players are chicken and decide to rest peacefully.  Yllgrad awakes to go pick up his potions and finds that poor Hengist – the fat, friendly merchant – has been brutally murdered at his work! Yllgrad looks around for some obvious clues, gathers the partially ground worg fangs, and then notifies a rather dim-witted city guard about the murder, but otherwise decides not to get involved.  Fair enough. For a moment I was afraid that my players, used to plotlines and quests would assume that I was dangling a “necessary” plot opening in front of them and that they would feel obligated to look into this random act of violence in order to find the fun.  I mean, I fully intended to wing an interesting and exciting investigation if they did, and things may still come of all this, but I don’t want to give them the impression that they “ought to have” investigated if they didn’t care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The others have started the morning by asking after rumors of the Volcano and ships that can take them there.  Earn’s player seems a little bored with the whole “buying rounds of drinks to learn rumors” thing, but the others are doing okay with it.  I end up naming a string of dockside bars after places in Austin (well, two of them, then I had to make up a third because I ran out of plausibly nautical themed names).  Investigating, they heard a number of interesting stories about the Fyrberg (the volcano): there’s a fishing village on the island, they worship the volcano by the name of Gurgu, there’s a giant ruby called the heart of the mountain, it was actually built by a wizard, the priests can make the volcano erupt at will, there’s a demon in the volcano, and so forth.  We’ll have to see how true they turn out to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the search for captains, I used the chart at the end of this entry that I came up with to randomly determine some ships’ captains that were in port and looking for work.  They ended up being referred to Acca, an enormously fat merchant with a crack crew and a high price, Guth &amp;amp; Spir, a gruff retired watchman and his sarcastic partner who are rumored to be treasure hunters, and Stol, a nervous, twitchy fellow who works for the great house Anlaf, but will take passengers on the side.  If you use the ship’s captain table, I’m sure you’ll recognize a few of the fellows, but just use names appropriate to your campaign and change a few details and they should fit right in.  Oh, and feel free to make any and all of them women, or randomly determine the sex ahead of time if you so desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They wrapped up the evening by going back to Cnud and letting him know that maybe Beorn is a bit of a rip off.  Cnud says they’d just always used the guy and he’ll look into it.  I’m sure he’ll be pretty grateful when he discovers one of the reasons his house has had trouble with finances.  They wrapped up the evening and decided that when we come back they’ll talk to the captains and settle on one of them, and then hopefully set sail for Fyrberg and adventure (Earn’s player is really anxious to get to that volcano).     &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/zpage119crop.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/zpage119crop.jpg?w=223&#34; alt=&#34;zpage119crop&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules: Random Ships’ Captains&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When characters wish to hire a ship, determine how many options they have/hear about/discover and roll a d12 that many times and consult the chart (or just pick).  If you need more than 12, scratch out any who are used and make up your own. “Base control stat” refers to what the captain and crew as described will need to roll under on a d20 to maintain control in a storm or other special circumstance. This can be modified by player actions, hiring additional/different crew, et cetera. If you have a different system, I arbitrarily decided that 15 was average for a professional captain and went from there.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***1)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sober, clean shaven, cautious.  Former smuggler turned honest.  Asks a high price, but crew is very skilled. Base control stat: 18.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***2)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reckless drunk.  Looking for work, unreliable, crew is drunk and unreliable.  He’s cheap, though.  Base control stat: 10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***3)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Charming smuggler and his mountain of a first mate.  A local crime boss has a bounty on their heads.  His ship is remarkably fast.  Base control stat: 15. Ship speed +5 miles per day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***4)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enormously fat merchant.  Dresses in high style, happy to take on passengers or high-value cargo, employs crack mercenaries as guards.  Expensive, but well connected.  Base control stat: 15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***5)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foreign, doesn’t speak the language very well.  Finishing up unloading a cargo that turned out unprofitable, sour mood, wants to get the hell out of here.  Base control stat: 14 (10 if crew is local)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***6)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stereotypically piratical.  Y’arrrr, parrot, peg leg/eye patch, flamboyant clothes, you know the guy.  May or may not actually be a pirate. Base control stat: 16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***7)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big talker, promises the moon, talks about his extensive exploits at sea.  Just purchased his first ramshackle vessel crewed by rank amateurs.  He starts out high, but can be bargained to extremely low prices.  Base control stat: 8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***8)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gruff, bearded retired watchman and his lanky sarcastic partner.  They take the jobs they can get, but mostly are after treasures.  Base control stat: 14&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***9)    *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Old man with a great big bushy beard injured by a great beast of the waves.  He seeks to hunt it down with a maniacal intensity.  Base control stat: 15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***10) *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Employee of a great house willing to take some passengers on the side for his own profit.  Thin, nervous, and flighty.  Base control stat: 12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***11) *** &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Captain is stubborn, quick witted former military officer who just wants his space and his freedom, and won’t look too closely into the legality of a job he takes.  He might have a light hearted pilot, a hard assed female first mate, a cheery female engineer, some hired muscle, and a sheltered surgeon.  Base control stat: 16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12) *** *** A cunning and accomplished reaver with a crew of seasoned raiders.  He considers passengers an unworthy source of income, but times are rough.  Base control stat: 16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Requiescat In Pace Mr. Harryhausen</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-05-07-requiescat-in-pace-mr-harryhausen/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 21:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-05-07-requiescat-in-pace-mr-harryhausen/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-05-07-requiescat-in-pace-mr-harryhausen/ -&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t grow up with Harryhausen the way a lot of the folks into this Old School stuff did, but I certainly love and appreciate his work.  And that&amp;rsquo;s why I think that &lt;a href=&#34;http://gamersandgrognards.blogspot.com/2013/05/rip-ray-harryhausen-way-to-honor-him.html&#34;&gt;the idea to make Friday an OSR blogfest&lt;/a&gt; in honor of the late, great Ray Harryhausen is a fantastic one.  So spread the word and tune in.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-05-07-requiescat-in-pace-mr-harryhausen/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 28 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 19:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see &lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7B%20site.baseurl%20%7D%7D%7B%25%20post_url%202019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith%20%25%7D&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after a two week hiatus due to my visit to the exotic orient for school, we resumed our regularly scheduled game on Monday.  Everybody, not least of all myself, were a little bit rusty, and a few players had connection issues and/or reasons to show up late and leave early, so it was a bit rocky, but overall a good time. Probably even more kibbitzing and joke making than usual, including a rather inappropriate one involving ents that had the whole group rolling, but is best left unrepeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed about campaign prep is that no matter how much time is taken, you never get everything you want ready.  I have great faith in my ability to improvise in just about every activity in my life, but I&amp;rsquo;m discovering that my D&amp;amp;D improvisation benefits from some robust support.  There are just so many cool things I want to incorporate from what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen online, read in published material, or stolen from heavy metal songs.  Oh well, the important thing is that the game keeps going so I keep having a chance to use this stuff and improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We picked up with the characters getting ready to high tail it away from outside of the giant cave after their fight with the trolls.  They decided to risk being surprised and injury/damage on the mountain path to move faster, not slowing down until they made it into the woods.  I spent a lot of my prep time coming up with some random adventure sites, focusing on the wilderness areas between the giant cave and Silverdelf, and overall I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with what was added.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://save.vs.totalpartykill.ca/grab-bag/kraal/&#34;&gt;The Kraal&lt;/a&gt; is a crazy awesome crowdsourced hex map of an arctic area, and I&amp;rsquo;ve stolen a lot of good stuff that has really started to make the wilderness feel like a living place, not just a vehicle for burning rations between marked locations on the map.  I still need to flesh some stuff out, but I like what&amp;rsquo;s there so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, as the group was coming to a stopping point near dusk, they spotted the ruins of a small inn and trading post, apparently as ancient as the Volsungril mine and probably serving the traffic that used to pass that way.  They burned some torches and got their hirelings in a police line and searched the place pretty thoroughly, but didn&amp;rsquo;t find much.  Then, during the night, Yllgrad the dwarf was on watch and heard a faint scratching sound.  Investigating, he found a trap door buried under some rubble, and when he opened it, he found a cellar.  He impetuously jumped into the cellar after sending calling for the rest of the party to wake up, but didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for their help.  He found a wine cellar, then a storage room and around that time everybody else showed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, they&amp;rsquo;re checking out the nondescript storage room with an enticing strongbox when BAM! a huge, disgusting undead beastie bursts through the cellar wall and attacks! Now, I made this monster up myself (rules below) because all I knew before they found this place was that there should be something creepy there at night.  I was all excited to run this (I thought) scary monster against unprepared and largely unarmored (!) characters, but you know what? They wasted it in like 3 rounds, with only a scratch to the dwarf, damage-wise.  And that was without their minions.  I really need to work on my sense of challenge scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve actually arrived at a new philosophy due to this, and other experiences: your players can handle it.  Anytime you&amp;rsquo;re wondering if you should spring something on the group, repeat that mantra.  It might take desperate creativity, multiple character deaths, and unorthodox solutions, but they will totally wreck every dangerous thing you throw at them.  So don&amp;rsquo;t pull your punches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after dispatching this fat nasty thing with a gaping maw, they break open the strong box, finding a fair amount of gold ,and then our alcoholic former nobleman checks out the wine and determines that he&amp;rsquo;s maybe heard of the vintage, somewhere, and it ought to be worth some money.  So they drink one bottle, then haul the other 159 out and take some special precautions to transport it, and hope to get some money for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, they start out again for Silverdelf, and one of the clerics (Caleb, cleric of Hrokr, the Crow Father) uses his favorite spell, speak with animals to try to get some info about the area.  I ended up doing a lot of animal impersonations this game (squirrel, sparrow, owl).  I try to give each animal a personality based on what they&amp;rsquo;re like, vague memories of Redwall characterizations, and what seems fitting at the time.  I also make it a point that they&amp;rsquo;re, you know, animals.  They can have perfectly intelligible conversations, but they don&amp;rsquo;t care about the same stuff we do or make the same distinctions.  They don&amp;rsquo;t have the same concepts of distance or time, they care a lot about food.  That sort of thing.  The more &amp;lsquo;supernatural&amp;rsquo; the critter (like crows and cats, maybe) the more person-like their thoughts and conversations will be.  At any rate, they heard about some Great Owl that &amp;ldquo;knows things&amp;rdquo; and decide maybe that&amp;rsquo;d be cool to find, so they vaguely set their course in the direction indicated by a helpful sparrow, but mostly keep heading for Silverdelf.  The next night of camping, they end up encountering the Great Owl. Now, they had learned from one of the animals or another that it will answer questions, but only a limited number (turns out it was 3).  Earn (Cleric of Dwyn, the Oak Mother) wastes the first question with &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s up?&amp;rdquo; and gets the response &amp;ldquo;the sky&amp;rdquo;.  The owl won&amp;rsquo;t engage in conversation besides answering questions, and mostly just stared at the party.  They ended up asking about the Volsungril mine and mostly just confirming what they already knew about it (I wish I had thought of more details to make it even cooler, I hate to waste a cool mystical question answer about something the players are already invested in), and then about what Trolls fear (fire, being bested in a deal, and their gods).  Then it mysteriously flew off to the Northwest.  They hope to find it again sometime and maybe learn some more things, and I think that&amp;rsquo;s cool.  I need to work on more connections across the map so things feel interrelated and point in different directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They made it back to Silverdelf and commission some wine racks for their new haul, and otherwise stock up on provisions and set out the next morning for Mickleheim, giant captives still in tow.  I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need to be making them more of a pain in the ass. So far all they&amp;rsquo;ve done is eat extra rations.  I ought to come up with escape chances and increased likelihood of wagons breaking down and all that jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the road to Mickleheim has been established as pretty safe, so I let them get there no problem, but we call it a night as we were coming up on our time limit (midnight, my time). I&amp;rsquo;ve adopted from Zak S. the incredibly wise procedure of stopping play about to go somewhere/start something rather than after resolving something.  This allows me to go &amp;ldquo;hey guys, what are you planning on doing next time?&amp;rdquo; Now, sure, often this changes or is just vague, but it allows me to triage prep time most effectively.  I certainly don&amp;rsquo;t try to plan out what they&amp;rsquo;re gonna do when they get places, I just try to make sure there&amp;rsquo;s stuff there for them to interact with, and I have enough of a rough idea of everything else that I can wing it for a session or so, it just might be a little flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, this discussion led to the decision to go check out the volcano on the newly detailed and awesomed map.  I think I discovered a principle of refereeing: Checkhov&amp;rsquo;s Volcano.  &amp;ldquo;If there is a volcano introduced on the map, players will go there eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s the one thing our usually fairly &amp;ldquo;along for the ride&amp;rdquo; player has strongly pushed for, so I want to do it justice and really bring the awesome.  I also see it as my chance to do my first real stand alone dungeon entirely from scratch for this campaign.  I&amp;rsquo;ve used lots of geomorphs, random generators, pieces from published adventures, and otherwise mostly kitbashed stuff rather than doing it from scratch.  And where it has been from scratch, it&amp;rsquo;s mostly been as part of Fellhold, which has its own stuff going on.  So the chance to do a stand alone, strongly themed dungeon of a decent size as a complete unit is new and both exciting and scary.  I just have to have enough for one night&amp;rsquo;s worth of play ready for next Monday night, and I want it to be awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For rules, the Disgusting Undead Abomination the players made short work of in the basement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disgusting Undead Abomination&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HD: 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC: 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attacks: Claw/Claw, Special: Bite (1d6/1d6, 1d8)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saving Throw: 12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special: On a natural hit of 16+, grapple and bite for 1d8 damage and drain 1 point of CON. Anyone reduced to 0 CON dies, and anyone killed by damage or CON drain raises in one round as a ghoul that will eventually turn into a Disgusting Undead Abomination&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move: 12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alignment: Chaotic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number Encountered: 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Level/XP: 7/600&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part II: Men &amp; Magic</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 21:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/menandmagiccoverart.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/menandmagiccoverart.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;menandmagiccoverart&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see &lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7B%20site.baseurl%20%7D%7D%7B%25%20post_url%202019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith%20%25%7D&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As promised, we&amp;rsquo;re beginning with the beginning - the Little Brown Books of the original white box.  Okay, yeah, yeah, you might call &amp;ldquo;the beginning&amp;rdquo; Chainmail or Braunstein or what have you, but this is the first thing released into the world as &amp;ldquo;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&amp;rdquo;, though not yet as a &amp;ldquo;roleplaying game&amp;rdquo;.  I&amp;rsquo;m no James Malieszewski when it comes to the history of the game, but for this analysis, I&amp;rsquo;m more concerned with differences in the products as rules manuals that I can use now than I am in their history.  I will touch on it briefly (as well as I&amp;rsquo;m able) in order to speculate on what changes tell us about the play experiences the designers were trying to address.  But enough jibber jabber, let&amp;rsquo;s jump in.    ### Men &amp;amp; Magic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Here is something better!&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; First off, a word about formatting and graphic design (in the sense that Zak S. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/2011/03/arrows-and-boxes-and-columns-and-bullet.html&#34;&gt;talks about it&lt;/a&gt;) - there isn&amp;rsquo;t any.  Well, that&amp;rsquo;s not true, there&amp;rsquo;s formatting of the sort some guys could do as hobbyists in 1974, and yes, there&amp;rsquo;s some charm to &amp;lsquo;slap it together yourself&amp;rsquo; aesthetic, but it&amp;rsquo;s a terrible in-play reference.  Material isn&amp;rsquo;t very clearly grouped, there&amp;rsquo;s no index, and rather important concepts get a mention and that&amp;rsquo;s it.  I honestly think a lot of the reputation OD&amp;amp;D has for being &amp;ldquo;incomplete&amp;rdquo; or needing high levels of referee involvement and prep stems from the fact that it&amp;rsquo;s not formatted in a way where you can pick it up and use it as an instructional manual.  As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, I started out with the purist vision of playing actual OD&amp;amp;D, but after the first session of character creation and brief play, I made the switch to Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox on account of its being easier to reference (and I actually have dreams of reformatting that in a more useful way, but it&amp;rsquo;s still loads easier to refer to in play than the LBBs). With these books, you have to read, re-read, internalize, interpret and otherwise work to make the text work for the game.  That&amp;rsquo;s okay, and there may even be some virtue in that, but overall I tend to come down on the position that RPG texts should facilitate learning the game and referencing the rules in play first, and being engaging and thought provoking works a distant second.  The engagement and thought provocation ought to come out in &lt;em&gt;play&lt;/em&gt; rather than the rules.  Given how rarely RPGs acquire new players by someone picking up a book out of the blue and getting an impression of it from that book alone, I think that&amp;rsquo;s a fair set of priorities.  That tangent out of the way, let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at Men &amp;amp; Magic section by section, even if they are inadequate as organizational tools.    #### Foreword&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s not much applicable to the rules here (as you&amp;rsquo;d expect), other than the emphasis on campaign play and the exhortation that these rules are intended for people with imagination. I like that.  As much as I admire a &amp;ldquo;scientific&amp;rdquo; approach to game design, where rules are crafted to attempt to guide players to the desired play experience, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot to be said for openly putting the onus on the players to use the toolkit provided.    #### Introduction, Scope, Preparation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, despite my smack talking about OD&amp;amp;D&amp;rsquo;s value as an instructional manual, it does go into charmingly specific detail on recommended equipment: &amp;ldquo;Sheet Protectors (heaviest possible).&amp;rdquo;  It also gives a piece of advice that remains good to this day, around which I&amp;rsquo;ve built the entire Fellhold campaign - start small and build up detail as you go.  Other than that, it emphasizes the expectation that the referee will house rule like the devil, and the flexibility of the rules, from the prehistoric to the futuristic.  I like to think of this as acknowledging the then latent potential of roleplaying games as a form combined with some understandable boosterism for a fledgling product.    #### Characters, Abilities, and NPCs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I find most interesting about the characters, abilities, and non-player characters sections is what they say about the play that produced them.  The character races that have become canonical are presented more in the sense of &amp;ldquo;hey, here&amp;rsquo;s the stuff we already figured out, but go ahead and make up something else if you want&amp;rdquo;.  Acquiring followers and armies, and their morale and loyalty scores get a lot of detail, showing the wargaming roots.  I like that abilities are &amp;ldquo;determined&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;created&amp;rdquo; - I think James Maliszewski hit on that on Grognardia, this notion that your character is randomly picked from all the possible characters in the world rather than crafted to your whim.    I&amp;rsquo;m still confused about the &amp;ldquo;use one stat for another at a 3 for 1 rate for experience purposes only&amp;rdquo;, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m alone in that.    #### Equipment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the prices here don&amp;rsquo;t show the same concern for medieval verisimilitude that later editions get to.  Though not listed here, it&amp;rsquo;s a running joke in my game that tents, as priced in Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox, costs something like a year&amp;rsquo;s soldiering wages.  Great fun was had by me in describing the giants&amp;rsquo; new loin cloths after they chased the party out of camp.    #### &amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo; Combat System&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we have the combat system that turned into D&amp;amp;D&amp;rsquo;s defining mechanic.  The tables are a little confusing, or rather the ways they try to save space by giving Magic Users and Clerics as relative values to Fighting Men.  Deep in my heart of hearts, I&amp;rsquo;m a THAC0 man myself, so I&amp;rsquo;m considering switching over, originalism be damned.  It&amp;rsquo;s interesting to me that AC only goes down to 2 and up to 9.  I&amp;rsquo;ll have to check out the Supplements to see when that was expanded.  The 10 to -10 spread is imminently logical, but it does divorce the idea that AC represents particular armor types.  That was probably inevitable, and possibly desirable, considering the diverse uses AC was already being put to to describe different monsters that are hard to hit for reasons other than wearing particular types of armor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saving throw matrix is also kind of terrible.    #### Spells&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 1 spells have a lot of overlap between Magic Users and Clerics, but after that they start to diverge quite a bit.  Clerics get &amp;ldquo;Remove Curse&amp;rdquo; as a level 3 spell instead of level 4, and obviously have all the healing spells.  Otherwise, perhaps what&amp;rsquo;s most surprising about the spells is how little many of them have changed.  Effects and mechanics are remarkably consistent for many of them, and despite the profusion of spells available in later editions, most of the most used and iconic ones are right here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up in the series will be &amp;ldquo;Monsters &amp;amp; Treasure&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For rules, here is the method I used recently for filling out &amp;ldquo;adventure sites&amp;rdquo; as determined with the previous rules adapted from Welsh Piper (which generated too many adventure sites and too many large outposts for the vibe I was going for, but would have been good for creating a dense, interesting small map)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adventure Site Generation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take stuff from a good source like &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpgcharacters.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Dyson Logos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://save.vs.totalpartykill.ca/grab-bag/hexenbracken/&#34;&gt;Hexenbracken&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://save.vs.totalpartykill.ca/grab-bag/kraal/&#34;&gt;the Kraal&lt;/a&gt;, or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.talesofthefroggod.com/toad.html&#34;&gt;Tome of Adventure Design&lt;/a&gt;, or your favorite published setting material or:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01-60: Monster Lair&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***            - Roll Random Encounter Chart for Terrain type***&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;61-70: Surface Ruins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***            - Use outpost generation rules to determine size and type of ruins, then either roll random encounter chart for monsters there, add intelligent but dangerous inhabitants, or come up with something to make it worthwhile***&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;71-80: Some Kind of Inhabited/Dangerous/Interesting Place besides an outpost&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;81-90: Small 1 Level Dungeon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***            - Generate Randomly, Wing it, or Grab a map***&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;91-00: Full Dungeon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***            - Generate randomly, grab a map, or go whole hog and make it***&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Problem</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 16:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/ -&lt;p&gt;So, in my ongoing &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.wordpress.com/tag/fellhold/&#34;&gt;Fellhold campaign&lt;/a&gt;, we’ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://akraticwizardry.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Akratic Wizardry&lt;/a&gt;’s rather good “&lt;a href=&#34;http://akraticwizardry.blogspot.com/2009/06/class-based-weapon-damage-it-always-has.html&#34;&gt;weapon damage by class&lt;/a&gt;” rule as a compromise between “all weapons do d6” and “all weapons have their own unique damage”.  I think if we weren’t already 6 months into using these rules, I’d probably tweak some of the damage a little bit, and maybe recategorize a few weapons (having short bows, long bows, and crossbows all do “medium weapon” damage, and treating hired swords as level 1 fighting men means that players have access to cheap and plentiful d8 damage – I gotta remember to play up the hirelings as people more).  Altogether, though, I like the rule, and it has allowed players to use stuff they think is cool while still giving the fighters a useful role as damage takers/dealers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran into a small problem recently, however.  In my zeal to go all OD&amp;amp;D, I gave everyone d6 hit dice.  &lt;em&gt;Everyone&lt;/em&gt;, even monsters.  Those of you more clever than I will have already spotted the problem it took me 6 months to deduce.  In OD&amp;amp;D, the baseline assumption of weapons and hit points was that an average guy has d6 HP, and an average weapon does d6, so any given blow has an average shot of killing someone if it connects.  So far, so good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you plug d8’s in as effectively the “default” damage (medium weapons in the hands of fighters and fighty hirelings) against d6 hit dice, all of a sudden the difficulty of monsters as related to their hit dice is thrown way off.  Mobs of hirelings offing hill giants in one round with a volley of short bow fire.  Trolls getting cut down faster than their regeneration can work.  In other words, we’ve gone from damage dealt scaling nicely to damage capacity to slightly (but significantly) favoring the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I am by no means suggesting I want carefully crafted “Challenge Levels” for encounters, or even that I want things to be harder for the characters per se.  What I think bothers me is that right now, the meaningfulness of player choice is being undermined, even if it is generally in their favor.  As it stands, fighting men, and employers of hired goons, choose between “bigger damage die than monster hit dice” or “way bigger damage die than monster hit dice” (the latter having the marginal cost of foregoing a shield).  Small weapons are pretty much completely ignored (except for the occasional thrown axe or knife).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By bumping monster HD up to d8s (as was done pretty early on – what, in Greyhawk? Definitely by AD&amp;amp;D) I get to a) keep using the damage scale we’ve been using and which has started to be automatic to players, b) increase the upside of going for a big, two handed weapon and foregoing a shield, making that a more meaningful choice, and c) make monster longevity more in line with their ability to hit, make saving throws, treasure awarded, XP given, et cetera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the rule for today is both short and easy: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All monsters have d8’s for hit dice.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Adventurer as a Meta-Class</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 21:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/hireling.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/hireling.jpg?w=162&#34; alt=&#34;hireling&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I’m reading through the excellent analysis of skills in D&amp;amp;D over at &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackslashmaster.blogspot.com/search/label/skills&#34;&gt;Hack &amp;amp; Slash&lt;/a&gt;.  It touches on what the functions of a resolution mechanic are at all, and especially digs into what 3.x/Pathfinder style skills bring to D&amp;amp;D (and don’t).  Considering some of my recent forays away from a pure lack of skill systems at all (using the “Good at” and “Bad at” cues, considering the use of roll under stat checks more often, et cetera), this is striking me as very useful analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main approach I’ve been taking when skill type things come up is to ask myself if I figure the situation is the sort of thing a class would cover.  Considering we’re still rocking the original 3 classes only (Fighting Man, Magic User, and Cleric), this gets broadly interpreted to “General Outdoorsy/Rugged stuff, smarty pants stuff, and healy/religious stuff” respectively.  With some consideration for the Dwarf knowing dwarf stuff.  In the Hack &amp;amp; Slash series, the author mentions in a couple of posts (those on ride and heal specifically that I can think of) that there’s some stuff that it’s just assumed adventurers can do, and I kind of like the idea of “Adventurer” as a meta-class for OD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I mean is a baseline assumption that all PCs know a thing or two about adventurery stuff in the same way that fighting men are assumed to know about combat and weapons and the like.  Now, this gets dangerously close to the whole “adventurers are a special class of people, a cut above everyone else from the get go” mentality of later editions.  I much prefer “your adventurer is just some schmuck until gameplay shows us otherwise.” Overall, though, I don’t think the idea that characters can be assumed to have a basic level of competence in things like riding horses, bandaging wounds, checking doors for traps and so forth clashes with the basic assumptions of a class &amp;amp; level game where fighting men start out tougher, magic users start out knowing a spell, and clerics start out, hmm, well, religious and able to swing a mace?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there are play styles where you would not want to approach things this way – a Dungeon Crawl Classics style 0-level “funnel” approach, a Lamentations of the Flame Princess Weird Fantasy Roleplay weird horror tale, a career or lifepath system like WFRP or a “our first adventure” story or whatever.  But I think that acknowledging “adventurer” as a factor for the referee when determining if a character can know or do something comes pretty close to what ends up being the default assumption at many tables anyway, especially in a skill system light approach, where the players have plenty of “dungeoneering/adventurism” experience and use it, regardless of who their characters are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the rules section is easy this time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adventuring Skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All characters are assumed to be basically competent at skills common to an adventuring life style – riding, camping, cooking, first aid, orienteering and so forth, unless stated otherwise by the player.  No tests are necessary related to these skills except in unusual or extremely difficult circumstances (riding a giant lizard, say, or determining directions in a sorcerous fog, et cetera).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part I: Introduction</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 21:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B1rzqcHHeoUyZlBnRVhMc21SUmc/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/ddsmall.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;DDsmall&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for some blog fodder, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided I&amp;rsquo;m going to take on the rather ambitious project of going through every version of D&amp;amp;D and comment on the rules.  To keep myself sane, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking to core books only.  I&amp;rsquo;m up in the air on OD&amp;amp;D if it will include the supplements or only the the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s.  The idea is to hit up White Box, Holmes, Moldvay, Mentzer, Rules Cyclopedia, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, AD&amp;amp;D 2E, D&amp;amp;D 3/3.5, and 4E.  And I&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to get to Next if it&amp;rsquo;s out by the time I get through all of the other stuff.  Then, maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll hit up the retroclones for the sake of comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&amp;rsquo;m sure somebody&amp;rsquo;s done something like this before, and I have read some &amp;ldquo;cover to cover&amp;rdquo; posts about specific editions, but my goal here is going to be to a) highlight the differences and think about why they are there, and b) identify those rules, tools, and ideas that are most useful to me for actual play, to aid me in kitbashing the Frankenstein&amp;rsquo;s monster of a &amp;ldquo;perfect version&amp;rdquo; for my campaign.   In large part, though, I just want to get to know the versions I&amp;rsquo;m not as personally familiar with (basically everything besides 2E and 4E). I expect it will take a while, but hopefully it will keep me gainfully blogging whenever I&amp;rsquo;m running short on ideas.  First up will be the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s in the next post in the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, &lt;em&gt;Fellhold Hex Stocking&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Using Welsh Piper&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.welshpiper.com/hex-based-campaign-design-part-1/&#34;&gt;Regional Hex Template&lt;/a&gt;, with 5 mile sub hexes and heavily cribbed from Lore.Keeper0&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://hexcrawl.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Hex Crawl&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lands around Fellhold are comparatively sparsely settled, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to modify the chances of an &amp;ldquo;outpost&amp;rdquo; (settlement type place) to be lower.  I&amp;rsquo;ll be running this for the regional hexes the players are currently traveling through first, and eventually flesh out the whole map.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For Each Regional Hex, determine the dominant terrain type (if you can&amp;rsquo;t tell, just use the center hex). In the case of dual terrain (like wooded hills) go down this list in this order for precedence. Roll the appropriate die for the number of outposts/settlements in the regional hex.  Then roll to determine size and inhabitants for each. Place as desired, or decide on a method to randomize placement:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terrain Type&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;Number of Outposts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;Size of Outposts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inhabitants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tundra/Glacier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1d2 – 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny (01-60)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Small (61-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dwarves (01-10)*, &lt;em&gt;Men (11-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mountains&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1d3 – 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny (01-60)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Small (61-89)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Medium (90-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trolls (01-40)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trollkin (41-80)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Giants (81-90)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dwarves (91-95)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Men (96-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Swamp/Fen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1d2 – 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny (01-70)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Small (71-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trolls (01-20)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trollkin (21-30)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Men (31-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1d3 – 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny (01-50)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Small (51-89)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Medium (90-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;*Trollkin (01-30), &lt;em&gt;Dwarves (31-35)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Men (36-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hills&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1d4 – 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny (01-50)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Small (51-80)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Medium (81-90)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Large (91-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trollkin (01-30)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dwarves (31-50)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Men (51-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plains/Grassland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1d6 – 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny (01-50)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Small (51-70)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Medium (71-80)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Large (81-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dwarves (01-20)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Men (21-00)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;outposts&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outposts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny: Individuals or very small groups, hermits, inns, mining/logging camps, homesteads&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Small: Villages, trading posts, forts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medium: Towns, keeps, market fairs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Large: Cities, castles, fortresses, tribal encampments&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Next, roll the number of adventuring sites per regional hex by dominant terrain type:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Terrain Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number of Adventuring Sites&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tundra/Glacier&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2D4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mountains&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Swamp/Fen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Forest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3D3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hills&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3D3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Plains/Grassland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2D4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;adventuring-sites&#34;&gt;Adventuring Sites&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adventuring sites are ruins, monster lairs, encounters, and so forth.  Detail as you like or use a cool random generator. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.random-generator.com/index.php?title=Main_Page&#34;&gt;Abulafia&lt;/a&gt; has lots of great stuff.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Brief Interlude on Rule Systems</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 16:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/dd-ibox.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/dd-ibox.jpg?w=224&#34; alt=&#34;dd-ibox&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see &lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7B%20site.baseurl%20%7D%7D%7B%25%20post_url%202019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith%20%25%7D&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after a discussion with Bryni’s player (GM of many of my favorite gaming moments, and fellow game design enthusiast) as well as working my way all the way through the archives over at Zak S.’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Playing D&amp;amp;D with Pornstars&lt;/a&gt;, I’m thinking rather a lot about rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started out the Fellhold campaign, I was pretty high on the “player skill not character skill” and “rulings, not rules!” rallying cries of the Old School Renaissance, and the accompanying rules light approach that I found appealing.  Now, don’t get me wrong, these are still principles I think are good and valuable, but I’m starting to wonder if my game is suffering from an overly strong attachment to some “pure” vision of those ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the beginning, I intended to take a similar approach to James Maliszewski in his &lt;a href=&#34;http://grognardia.blogspot.com/search/label/dwimmermount&#34;&gt;Dwimmermount&lt;/a&gt; campaign and add on rules as they became necessary or desired, but in practice I haven’t really regularized that many rulings or added that many brand new rules.  Even if I were to, Bryni’s player pointed out an interesting analogy in the above mentioned conversation.  He said that OD&amp;amp;D (or retroclones thereof, like our current S&amp;amp;W Whitebox) is an excellent bicycle – spare, efficient, gets you where you’re going.  But when you start adding on all sorts of gewgaws and motors and horns and whatnot, you end up with a crufty bike when maybe you would have been better off with a moped or a motorcycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This conversation came up because he is a fan of the crunch.  In addition to the tactical and outside the box thinking of play, he enjoys having a meaty rules system to sink his teeth into and engage with as a game. And I can certainly sympathize – I just tend to get that fix with board games and wargaming more than from RPGs.  When I suggested that we can add more systems and subsystems to the game as we go, he made the analogy above and it got me thinking about what the rules are doing now, what we might want them to do that they’re not, and how best to serve those goals.  Most of all, I don’t want to let some silly sense of pride in playing D&amp;amp;D “like it was” get in the way of playing it in the most awesome and fun way possible for me and my friends.  It’s not like I have any personal attachment to how D&amp;amp;D was played before I was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all that has me thinking about how the rules are contributing (or not) to the awesome in my campaign.  One area I’ve been giving a lot of thought to is rolling for skills and stats.  I’ve shied away from doing it much at all in the hopes of encouraging player creativity and problem solving, rather than using character stats and skills as a crutch.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/2012/10/keep-talking-or-tell-them-to-roll.html&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; by Zak S. made an excellent distinction about what rolling stats is &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; in D&amp;amp;D, though, and may be the necessary step to break my otherwise loathe to roll stats mentality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been so worried about letting the game slip into “roll vs. whatever stat/skill” in place of engaging with the fiction and actually thinking, that I may have gone the opposite direction and made the only useful character distinction how well you hit in a fight.  We’ve had some really good times with stats being little more than a way to color your impression of characters (and the occasional precious +1 hit point), but I think I’ve closed off whole sections of the game to the delights of the oracular power of dice that I’ve not only discussed before, but named my damn blog after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I mean is that when social interactions, or trying to notice things or whatever are entirely based on my rulings on what the players describe, then there is no unexpected content at the decision point. I may be surprised by the player’s actions, but I will have incorporated those actions into my mental model before making my decision, so there is no surprise (to me) from the actual decision. With dice added to the mix, I can shape the probability with modifiers, but the actual result still has the chance to surprise me and even force “unwelcome” outcomes, as Mr. Baker would say, which makes the game more interesting and textured overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embracing this notion, however, starts to point to some of the areas ripe for change in OD&amp;amp;D.  Though I never played D&amp;amp;D 3 or 3.5, the open endedness of ascending AC and difficulty kinda makes a lot of sense, and allows a little more range than roll under a stat.  On the other hand, moving to a totally open ended system like that quickly minimizes the role of the actual D20 that the system is named for.  If you’re adding and subtracting values over 20, then the probabilities get a little weird.  The very strength of having no limit to modifiers starts to become meaningless when they get big enough that the dice roll only matters to check for a critical hit or failure.  Of course, if you want huge amounts of granularity to base stats, skills, and modifiers, all within a reasonable range, you can go to a percentile system, but man, I just kind of hate them for aesthetic reasons that I can’t quite explain (sorry WFRP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what to do? I flirted with the idea of a Dungeon World style 2d6 + modifier derived from 3-18 stat with a 2-6 fail, 7-9 mixed success, 10-12 full success model, but again, Bryni’s player pointed out that the basic assumption of such a system is not “does this make sense?” but rather “succeeding while creating problems is the most interesting outcome, so it should happen the most.”  I think making that assumption for some parts of the game but not others is ultimately more problematic than it looks on its face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about 3/3.5 style modifies added to a D20 roll against an ascending DC set by me? I feel like this is only slightly different from a straight up decision on my part based on description.  Sure, it’s technically different to set a difficulty, then award a bonus or penalty to the player’s roll, but overall I’d still be largely shaping how a thing goes down based on what sounds right to me, minimizing the surprising effects of the dice.  I’m sure lots of GMs are super good at doing this fairly, but it’s not a skill I’m exactly practiced at right now, and I don’t know how long it would take me to train that skill to the same hard core old school “let the dice fall where they may” approach I’ve been taking so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started this post, I didn’t know exactly where I was going with it, but I think I’ve figured it out.  Rolling for stats will be a simple roll under affair.  Modifiers will be limited to +1/-1 for both the player and the difficulty, which is consonant with what I’ve been doing for combat rolls (I’ve based this on something I read in either DNDWPS or Grognardia, I can’t remember, which pointed out that the early rules intended a +1/-1 to be a pretty big deal, that was mostly all you got if you got anything).  This means a maximum swing of +/- 10% probability, which still makes the importance of the stat and the D20 roll itself important, which I like.  Plus, it makes my job of judgment a lot easier by making it effectively binary (well, trinary if you count “no effect”): Is this thing unusually hard (-1 to stat) or unusually easy (+1 to stat)? Is your description especially useful (+1 to roll) or especially not (-1 to roll)?.  We’ll see how this works out as time goes on.  So, I guess I’ll cheat a little bit and use the above as my “rules content” for this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellhold Ability Checks:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When a player cannot or will not expand on an action his character is performing, and the outcome of that action depends to some degree on an inherent trait of the character, then the referee will call for an ability roll.  The player rolls 1D20 and attempts to score the relevant ability or lower. The referee may modify the ability or the roll as follows:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the player’s description significantly improves his chance of
success: -1 to the player’s roll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the player’s description significantly detracts from his
chance of success: +1 to the player’s roll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the situation is unusually easy: +1 to the character’s
relevant ability for the purposes of this roll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the situation is unusually difficult: -1 to the character’s
relevant ability for the purposes of this roll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note that if using the “Good at” and “Bad at” skill rules, these should normally grant a -1 and +1 to the player roll respectively.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Swords &amp; Wizardry Appreciation Day!</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 10:48:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/ -&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the first official Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Appreciation day! Considering Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox is the ruleset we&amp;rsquo;re using for the Fellhold campaign, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d like to jump in on this.  I&amp;rsquo;ve expounded earlier why we went with Whitebox, but basically I found the simplicity attractive as a foundation to add house rules to, rather than trying to cut out pieces of other versions.  As play has gone on, it has both taught me to value and enjoy the lack of some rules but also it has pointed out exactly how other rules came to be by experiencing the desire to have them in game.  My only real regret about using Whitebox is that it means my beautiful full core rules I got in the kickstarter are only pulled out when I&amp;rsquo;m looking for guidance on making a ruling on something outside the scope of the Whitebox rules. A small price to pay for an excellent slim set of D&amp;amp;D rules that is far more in-play reference friendly than the actual Little Brown Books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m working on a quickstart character sheet that will hopefully have everything a player needs to create a character A) on one page, and B) logically sequenced and labeled to be as new player friendly as possible, but I&amp;rsquo;m traveling and wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to get it finished yet.  So, instead I&amp;rsquo;ll post my custom Fellhold character sheets (heavily inspired by the Dwimmermount character sheets), and, unimaginatively enough, a couple of magic Swords and an example of some Wizardry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellhold Character Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B1rzqcHHeoUyS2N2OVdPTlNmWDQ/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;Fellhold Character Sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some Swords&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grief, the Foemaker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grief is a finely made long sword with intricate knot and runework on the crossguard and round pommel.  The steel of the blade is dark, almost smokey, and the scabbard  is black leather with inlaid silver in the form of a knotwork wyrm.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When Grief comes into the possession of a new owner, it is a +1 sword that increases its wielder&amp;rsquo;s chance to fumble by 1 (so, a 1-2).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every time its owner rolls a fumble, increase the to-hit bonus by +1, to a maximum of +4, and increase the chance to fumble by 1. This works out to:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;+1 = Fumble on 1-2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;+2 = Fumble on 1-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;+3 = Fumble on 1-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;+4 = Fumble on 1-5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In addition to an increased chance of a fumble, as Grief&amp;rsquo;s to hit bonus increases, the severity of fumbles should increase.  This is left to referee discretion, but anything that increases discord and endangers allies should be preferred.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whenever the owner of Grief is present during an interaction with strangers, any reaction rolls will suffer a penalty equal to Grief&amp;rsquo;s current to hit bonus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grief cannot be freely given to anyone its owner considers a friend or ally.  If Grief is ever used in the presence of a former owner, any fumbles will automatically strike the former owner (provided it is even somewhat reasonable).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grief&amp;rsquo;s powers &amp;ldquo;reset&amp;rdquo; whenever it comes into the possession of a new owner.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woe, the Blooddrinker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woe is a &amp;ldquo;viking style&amp;rdquo; sword of regular size, effective at both stabbing and slashing.  The broad fuller is bronze, and the crescent shaped upper and lower guards are inlaid with copper knotwork polished to a bright red sheen.  The hilt is wrapped in simple, well-worn leather. It is currently housed in a weather and sweat stained simple leather scabbard.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woe gives no bonus to hit, but instead any damage dice rolled &amp;ldquo;explode&amp;rdquo;, meaning that if the maximum value is rolled, save that value, roll again and add them together.  If this second roll is also the maximum value for the die, roll again and add, and so on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On a critical hit, automatically consider the damage die to have rolled maximum value and proceed from there, in addition to any other usual effects from a critical hit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woe always inflicts vicious, nasty wounds when it is able.  Any time its damage die &amp;ldquo;explodes&amp;rdquo;, NPCs and monsters with HD equal to or less than the victim must test morale (yes, this applies to both friends and foes).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woe&amp;rsquo;s owner will find it hard to keep his or her hand off of the hilt and the blade in the scabbard anytime his situation is uneasy or dangerous, unless he exercises iron will (a good way to reflect this is for the referee to assume that the owner does these things in these situations unless the owner&amp;rsquo;s player specifically says otherwise).  NPCS will likely interpret such actions as hostile and react accordingly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some Wizardry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Altered Guise&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spell Level: 1st&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Range: Self&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Duration: 8 hours&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The caster may take on the appearance of any person of roughly the same size and shape provided he obtains something that belongs to the person being imitated. He may change appearance within the duration as many times as he likes, though once he returns to his own appearance the effect ends.  The greater the disparity between the caster&amp;rsquo;s appearance and the imitated person&amp;rsquo;s, the more likely something will seem off, and people familiar with the imitated party will have a greater chance of spotting the deception.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Humanoids of Fellhold</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 01:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/ -&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see &lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7B%20site.baseurl%20%7D%7D%7B%25%20post_url%202019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith%20%25%7D&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Player Spoilers!  This post might spoil some stuff if you’re playing in my Fellhold game!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so, with that out of the way, today we’re going to talk about the humanoid races we’ve encountered so far, with associated rules.  Rules stuff is in bold italic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The currently playable races:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Men&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/wizardsmall.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/wizardsmall.jpg?w=171&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men are pretty much what you’d expect.  Vaguely Germanic (Anglo-Saxon names by default), scattered settlements, one largish town outside of Fellhold, one big city a few days away on the coast.  There are probably more and different cultures farther away, but those haven&amp;rsquo;t come up yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All playable classes (Fighting Men, Magic Users, and Clerics).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Languages: By default, all men speak Mannish, and may choose additional languages in the usual manner.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dwarves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/dwarvessmall.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/dwarvessmall.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dwarves are a mostly insular race, though they once had many mighty holds dug into mountains across the land.  The greatest of these was Fellhold, conquered by sorcerors, now overrun with all manner of foul beasts.  Dwarves are pretty stereotypical super-nordic dwarves: hard working, expert craftsmen and miners, live in giant cities carved from the living rock, tendencies towards rampant greed, et cetera.  Know ancient secrets of weaponsmithing that men do not. Pretty much all magic weapons come from the dwarves, and most of those from long ago.  I’ve been pretty inspired by Burning Wheel and Warhammer’s versions of dwarves, but ultimately they come from the Norse myth (and Tolkien’s take on them, of course).  While their skill is better than humans, they don’t have any advanced technology like steam or clockwork or guns, because I don’t want it.  This may change in the future, who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Character Advancement: The only character class available to Dwarves is that of the Fighter, but they have no level limits.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weapon and Armor Restrictions: Like human Fighters, Dwarves have been trained in warfare and have no restrictions on the weapons or armor they may use.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fighting Giants: Giants, ogres, and similar giant-type creatures such as trolls are not good at fighting dwarves, and only inflict half the normal damage against them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keen Detection: Dwarves are good at spotting traps, slanting passages, and construction while underground.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saving Throw: Dwarves do not use magic and, as such, are somewhat immune to its effects; they receive a +4 bonus on saving throws vs. magic (whether or not the alternate “Saving Throw Matrix” is used).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Languages: Dwarves are able to speak Mannish, Dwarvish, Goblinic, and Trollish.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those encountered by the party&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trollkin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/planescapegoblin.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/planescapegoblin.jpeg?w=390&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trollkin are a group of related tribes of humanoids, with a fairly wide range of technological sophistication, physical size, and characteristics.  Men tend to refer to them based on size as “goblins” and “hobgoblins”, and there are rumors from the dwarves of even larger and more sophisticated Trollkin that dwell almost exclusively underground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so, stats-wise, I’ve to this point used standard goblin and hobgoblin stats, which is pretty boring and generic, I know.  Where I’ve tried to bring in some interest is to make Trollkin more than just two dimensional walking XP sacs guarding treasure.  The PCs even ended up as chiefs of a Trollkin tribe for a while, but then messed up their sacred rites and started a tribal war, and who knows how that turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, act what later versions of D&amp;amp;D would probably call “lawful evil” despite being dedicated to the forces of Chaos (demons).  They take their traditions and religious values seriously – but those traditions and values are kind of, you know, evil.  So, for example, when the PCs challenged the chief of the Sword clan to single combat, a champion fought him, and that champion became the chief (despite being a dwarf).  All the trollkin were like “them’s the breaks” and acknowledged him as chief, even though they thought it was pretty weird.  When the PCs tried the same stunt on another tribe and cheated, however, they made the mistake of telling their shaman, assuming that an evil guy would be all about cheating and backstabbing.  But to him (a demon worshipping cannibal), breaking the trust of the blood rite was a horrible blasphemy and could not be borne.  So, he summoned a demon as he was killed by the PCs, the tribe dissolved into Chaos, and that’s the last we heard of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, except for his assistant that the PCs captured, who adamantly refuses to go along with them, because he’s a devout believer in Mustakrakish, demon lord of trolls (yes, from the Dethklok song).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you’ve waded through all of that, here’s my quick and dirty blood magic rules (I want to find and/or come up with better ones, but this is simple and makes hordes of otherwise useless guys scary):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trollkin Blood Magic:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***A Trollkin shaman can invoke the powers of demonic patrons with appropriate sacrifice.  For every 1HD of sentient creature killed by a shaman, he can attack any target within sight for 1d6 damage.  If he begins a ritual, chanting and remaining stationary, drawing grotesque symbols with the blood of his sacrificial victims, he can “store” HD for an attack or a summoning. ***&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summoning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As stated, a shaman may perform a ritual, slaying a sacrificial victim each round and storing up the victim’s HD.  At any point he may finish the ritual to attempt to summon a demonic being with HD up to sacrificed HD -1.  Chances of success are 1 in 6 for every HD stored above the target demon’s HD. Damaging the shaman mid-ritual will disrupt the ritual.  Consider any fun “interrupted summoning” consequences you like.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example: Odo the head shaman of the sword tribe wants to punish the unbelieving upworlders for their blasphemous ways.  He begins chanting and grabbing nearby members of his tribe and viciously cutting their throats.  He can do that, because he’s the shaman.  The PCs hear his disturbing chant and see smoke starting to gather around him, so they direct their attacks his way, but are stopped by his bodyguards.  Each round, he sacrifices another hapless tribe member, until after 6 rounds, he announces he has completed the ritual and is attempting to summon a 4 HD demonic being (Erishkaltu, the sword clan’s totem demon and servant of Mustakrakish). He has a 2 in 6 chance (6 sacrifices – 4 demon HD = 2 in 6).  The PCs finally land a telling blow, killing Odo, but he had initiative and completed the ritual.  The referee rolls a 1, and the smoke begins to congeal into a tangible form. . .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trolls&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/troll.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/troll.jpeg?w=444&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in the world of Fellhold, Trolls are related to trollkin (goblins, hobgoblins, bugbears) but are their own race.  They’re sort of a mash up of ogres and trolls and look more like the guy above than like the classic green rubbery dude.  They’re size L, but smaller than giants (basically, think Warhammer scale Ogres). But they still regenerate.  Here’s a “normal” troll’s stats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Troll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HD: 6+3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC: 4 [15]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HD: 6+3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attack: Weapon (1d10) or Berzerk (claw/claw/bite for 1d4/1d4/1d8)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saving Throw: 11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special: Regenerates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move: 12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alignment: Chaos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number Encountered: 2d6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Level/XP: 8/8000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trolls regenerate 3 hp every round. They do not regenerate damage by fire or acid.  When below 10 HP, they go “berserk” and attack with claws and teeth instead of their weapon. Berserk fury ends when troll reaches 0 HP or the fight is over and he cools down, but not if he regenerates to over 10 HP.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t decided yet if Trolls regenerate from decapitation or total bodily destruction by means other than fire or acid.  The party has a mostly charred headless troll body in their caravan right now, and I’m really tempted to have it wake up in a few days, but we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Trollkin, trolls are intelligent and have a society with rules and values, and also like trollkin, they’re evil and worship demons.  They’re just rigidly principled about it.  Trolls are super transactional.  They see all interactions as exchanges of value for value.  They are extremely “letter of the law” sorts of people.  Probably from a long history of asking for things from demons.  Normally they are very calm and terse, but when severely injured or pushed too far, they go berserk and attack in a blind rage with their bare claws and teeth.  So, they can be dealt with as any other intelligent species, but their rules of behavior might be strange and unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major sources of inspiration visually are Paul Bonner’s stuff for Drakar och Demoner, along with every Warhammer ogre ever.  Behavior-wise, I gleaned some stuff from Magic: the Gathering’s Kamigawa (one of the few good things to come out of a misguided decision to read the novel that came in a “fat pack” of cards for the block), and now that I think about it, I’m ashamed to admit, from “Sword of Shannara” with its stoic, noble troll guys in thrall to the evil lord.  But my trolls &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; evil, just stoic and honorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giants&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/web-wb-cover-art.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/web-wb-cover-art.jpg?w=240&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Trolls and Trollkin, giants much more closely resemble men and dwarves.  The way I figure it, trolls and trollkin are one “genus”, and men, dwarves, and giants are another.  Not that I want to get too naturalistic with the ecology here, but I like folk lore giants that are just big, ugly, kinda dumb humans.  I’m keeping the scale of hill giant on up to fire giants and titans and the like pretty much the same, with a comparable ascending scale of sophistication.  Unfortunately for me, besides dishing out tons of damage, Hill Giants have proven to be kind of pushovers for well-equipped PCs and their army of hirelings.  I really need to rock the morale rules more carefully.  And it turns out that dwarves’ “half damage from giant type creatures” rule is &lt;em&gt;insanely&lt;/em&gt; useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giants speak a crude dialect of mannish (hill giants = mostly grunts and 1 syllable words, frost and fire giants = normal conversational skill, but sound like, well, monstery giants).  Giants aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;evil&lt;/em&gt; per se, just greedy, selfish, and prone to violence.  So, like I said, big, dumb people.  I’m thinking that the frost giants have a big ass keep up north and that they have the Trolls in unwilling serfdom, but we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elves?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/whiteelvessmall.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/whiteelvessmall.jpg?w=223&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I put this way down at the bottom to make it even less likely that my players will read it (shame on you if you’re here!), but I’m considering putting elves back into the mix.  Initially, I was so sick of ‘elf-bloat’ and I wanted to stick to a sword &amp;amp; sorcery kind of Germania that I thought elves wouldn’t fit (yes, I know elves come from Germanic myth, even Tolkien’s, but they’ve been so D&amp;amp;D-ified that I was sick of them).  Now, though, reading about Zak S.’s pitiless white elves, I’m thinking there might be a place for them as sort of Others-cum-Melniboneans living up in frozen palaces in the icy wastes, probably only a few decadent remnants of apathetic, cruel, graceful aristocrats.  Maybe with armies of frost wights, I dunno.  I’m still pretty torn.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Long Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 22:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/3777964035_fe27b572d4.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/3777964035_fe27b572d4.jpg?w=366&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Grasping, Avaricious PCs - the best kind&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, long time no recap.  As mentioned in my little apology for non-blogging/calling myself to action post, I’m going to completely change up my style for recaps.  The whole ‘pulp adventure narrator’ tone was dumb, and I was dumb, but now I’m better, and I’m going to actually talk about player decisions and my decisions and how the session went down and so forth.  Feedback on my refereeing style are quite welcome (even if they’re “wow, that sounds super boring, you suck”. If so, you’re a dick, but it might be useful input).   For the too long, didn’t read crowd, feel free to scroll down to the rules at the bottom of the post in bold italic (a method for determining what players have heard body parts of a slain foe might be good for).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, looking back, yikes, a lot has happened.  The last recap was for sessions 13 and 14, and last night we played session 27.  So, yeah.  Shortly after where we left of there, Blum the wizard wandered into a seemingly empty room full of scrolls and got himself killed by a poisonous giant centipede.  Considering Blum’s sleep spells had been astoundingly useful, and that he had been rather deadly with his quarterstaff (“The Widowmaker”), he was greatly missed.  Add to this that Blum’s player is the one with the most difficult schedule, and therefore the most often absent, his character took on a sort of “mascot” role for the party, and as the first PC death (astonishing, I know!) the party decided he deserved a proper memorial. More on the memorial later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for reasons that remain obscure to me even now, after returning to town to properly bury the body on their shared property, they decide that the best revenge would be to go take out the seemingly unending force of trollkin they fought and ran away from (I think the rationale &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; have been: they made us flee where we were exploring, the new place we went because they were scary killed Blum, therefore it’s their fault).  After another sizeable battle against prepared foes, a big scary chief showed up with his big scary bodyguard &lt;em&gt;from behind them&lt;/em&gt;, and feeling trapped (they were pretty trapped), they decided to try to call out the chief mano a mano.  Turns out, that’s actually a sacred and respected ritual to this tribe of trollkin (the “blood rite”) and the party had killed enough trollkin to make it a credible offer (trollkin are kinda weird that way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some haggling over how it’ll work, it ends up with Yllgrad (dwarf fighter) and Dag (former bandit sergeant now henchman of Bryni – and one of the most effective characters, not just because he started out level 2, but because he &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; rolls well) square off against the Trollkin chief (he had a name, but he’s dead now, so whatever) and his biggest, baddest champion.  Oh, with no armor.  With knives.  Yllgrad’s player tries to get clever by spreading some centipede venom on the blade, and I rule it’ll have a weakened effect due to being old (it’s already the weakest kind of centipede, so the poison had no effect on the fight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By ganging up on one guy at a time, and narrowly escaping death (I think 1 hit point left for Dag, the toughest character in the party at that point), they defeat the chief and his champion and, surprise, are now chiefs of the sword clan! So, what do they do with their newly acquired evil humanoid tribe?  Well, besides take half their loot, they put them to work cutting down one of the massive statues of an evil sorceror dotting this level, cut away walls of the dungeon so that the huge thing can be maneuvered out (thankfully they were only on level 2), and then transfer it to human workmen on the surface to take into town to be the giant monument to their fallen mage.  So now the party has a 20 or 30 foot tall statue of an evil demon-worshipping sorceror in their yard, with the name of their dead friend carved in the base buried under it. So that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the party also discovered a treasure map in the room that killed Blum, and it marked the location of a mine up in the Trellheim mountains.  They organized an expedition, got ambushed by giants, hid for a while, then snuck past them and found the mine.  It was haunted by the ghosts of the miners killed in the cave in.  Only by invoking Volsungr, the god of forge and craftsmanship (and mining, apparently) could they lay the ghosts to rest.  Oh, and the dwarf’s player came up with the death blessing of followers of Volsungr all by himself, and it was pretty cool (Volsungr, find my path).  This also narrowly avoided one of the clerics of other gods from invoking the wrong god in the mine and the ghosts turning all scary, so that was good for them.  Turns out it’s a mine of Volsungril, this world’s equivalent of adamantium/mithril/whatever, and they found a small nugget of the stuff (worth a crazy huge amount of money) apparently as a gift from laid-to-rest ghosts.  Of course now the game is about trying to secure the mine of infinite wealth and magical weapons and nothing else, but I figure that will have enough complications to be alright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, they returned the big city (Mickleheim) to hire a bunch of fighty hirelings, because Silverdelf is pretty much tapped out (too many killed and maimed), and decide to launch a huge expedition into the mountains to clear out the giants.  But first they figure they’ll get their tribe of trollkin and take them along too (not realizing that this is potentially problematic in all kinds of ways).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, while down there, they get the idea to get an even bigger hoard of trollkin to help them kill the giants, and so they attempt the same blood rite trick with the neighboring rival spear clan.  Turns out that the spear clan does their blood rite a little differently, and the rolls go a little better for the chief than for Yllgrad, and right when it looks like he’s going to lose, the players come up with the plan of interrupting the fight with a thrown spear made to look like it came from the watching spear clan reps.  Well, chaos ensues, the players slaughter all of the spear clan guys, and manage to convince the remaining sword clan guys that the spear clan started the trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they get back, though, they level with Odo, the sword clan shaman, about what happened, and they say they want to have a big party to get everybody fired up to go start a war with the spear clan.  Odo’s a devout (demon worshipping) shaman, though, and the blood rite is sacred, so instead of a party, he summons a demon to attack the party, the party kills him right as he completes it, and he curses them with his dying breath.  The party fights the demon, and it’s disappointingly easy for them to kill.  And the clan scatters in terror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poking around the now abandoned sword clan lair, they find Odo’s assistant and end up keeping him as a prisoner, and then decide to go down a set of ornate stairs and find themselves in what appears to be a temple and/or tomb of the old sorcerors, who they find out were called “the Urog”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While exploring the temple to this Iron God of the Urog, Yllgrad is struck by a terrible vision of a trollkin going crazy and murdering and dismembering and eating his whole tribe before running deeper into the catacombs.  So the players know this place is creepy.  They find a warning inscription with instructions about going into the sacred catacombs, and two of the three entrances are flanked by basins full of nasty water and teeth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, sure enough, they don’t follow the instructions, and are struck by horrible hallucinations after a few rounds of exploring and pushing a giant block around.  After they flee from the hallucinations, they decide maybe now’s not the time to explore the super creepiness, especially if the offering required by that room of skeletal hands is that they cut off somebody’s left hand, so they head back to town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in town, they once again decide to return to the mountains to clear out the giants so that they can have a safe passage to the mine.  Did I mention they hired 20 soldiers in addition to their usual retinue of hirelings?  I decided that if they were going to treat them like red shirts, so was I, so these guys are especially prone to dying horrible deaths, like when holding a trip line in front of the entrance to the giant’s cave and being sent flying off when the giant runs into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One distinguished himself by volunteering to be “bait” for a counter ambush on the giants, and he narrowly came out alive after getting clipped in the head by a mule flung by the giant.  This crazy old coot looks like King Bumi, is named Helm, and is apparently wiry, jaded, and willing to do incredibly stupid things for reasonably small amounts of money.  A perfect hireling, he’ll probably stick around even if the other surviving members of the 20 don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, they clear out this cave of giants, including the women and adolescents, make surprisingly short work of high HD, high damage opponents because apparently 20 to hit rolls + standard cross bow damage = dead giants.  So far everybody and everything has had D6’s for hit dice, but I’m &lt;em&gt;strongly&lt;/em&gt; considering upgrading monsters to D8’s, since a standard weapon in a standard fighting man’s hands does d8 damage (using Akratic Wizardry’s weapon damage chart).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s some debate about what to do with the surviving giants, but in the end, the party decides to keep one adult female, and one adolescent male alive to try to sell off to House Dagaeca back in Mickleheim (they’ve mentioned their desire to buy exotic beasts before. We’ll see whether giants qualify as “beasts” or not, assuming they get them back safely).  They’ve also heard conflicting rumors considering the medicinal and magical properties of giant testicles, hands, and tongues, but decide that cutting off those parts is a little too icky for rumors they don’t even know to be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a posse of 3 trolls rolls up, and ask for a parley.  Turns out the trolls are glad to see the giants gone, and offer safe passage along the path in exchange for being given the surviving giants.  Yllgrad’s player ends up flubbing the negotiation by demanding too much and insulting the trolls (and this is &lt;em&gt;minutes&lt;/em&gt; after introducing the “Good at” and “Bad At” skill system found here, and him picking “Bad at detecting lies, haggling, and negotiations”, so that was perfect).  When the troll gets all insulted, Yllgrad attacks him, and a general melee ensues.  The leader, who was negotiating, goes down, one of the other trolls grabs him and runs while the other holds off the PCs and their horde of hirelings (down to 13 out of original 20 at this point).  After downing that troll and chasing the others for a bit, they see a smoke signal going up, and they know that a troll village is nearby, so they decide to high tail it out of there.  Despite this being the first time the group has met trolls, and despite trolls being somewhat mysterious to people, Yllgrad’s player knows the score and scorches up the body, but they decide to keep it to see if troll parts will sell for anything.   Whew, and that brings us up to speed. Here’s some rules to make this long read through a little more worthwhile:  ***The characters have killed something and want to know if any of its parts are worth anything.  Ask the players which of their characters have heard anything about valuable body parts from this creature.  For every player that says his character has, roll a D10 and consult the following chart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“I heard that ________ is a cure for/ingredient in/component of. . .”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eyeballs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gallbladder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intestines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testicles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Penis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tongue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pick something that seems to go with it, or something totally out there (or use a random potion/spell chart of some kind).  Tell the players that’s what they’ve heard. If multiple dice come up for the same body part, feel free to make up different uses they’ve heard for it, or to say they’ve all heard the same rumor.  That’s what the players know.  It’s up to you to decide if the rumors are true, but you might assign a straight 50/50 chance or 10% per die that came up the same body part, or whatever else.  But don’t tell the players that until they’ve tried to unload the parts or make something out of them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title></title>
        <link>/gaming/2013-04-10-so-again-with-absence-of-blogging-thing/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 22:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2013-04-10-so-again-with-absence-of-blogging-thing/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2013-04-10-so-again-with-absence-of-blogging-thing/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/frazetta_15_crop.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/frazetta_15_crop.jpg?w=650&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see &lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7B%20site.baseurl%20%7D%7D%7B%25%20post_url%202019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith%20%25%7D&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, again with the absence of blogging thing.  You know, apologies, et cetera.  Reading through awesome OSR/DIY D&amp;amp;D blogs has made me realize something important, though: my “fictionalized” accounts of each session were ass.  Though in my heart of hearts I may have dreams of writing fiction, this here gaming blog is not the place for it.  More than my questionable literary style, in recounting a bunch of in-fiction actions, I’m leaving out the best stuff.  What’s fun and interesting about D&amp;amp;D (and especially what is fun and interesting about reading about &lt;em&gt;other people&lt;/em&gt; playing D&amp;amp;D) is the interactions at the table, the problem solving, the jokes, et cetera.  “The fiction” as a coherent thing only really matters to the participants, I think, other than as the context for and product of the interesting stuff.   The other big thing I realized is that I’ve been holding off on using this blog for hammering out some of the more nitty gritty stuff for Fellhold for fear of my players seeing it and spoiling the surprise.  I’ve decided that this isn’t useful or super necessary.  Any game content that might spoil stuff for the players will just get a big fat SPOILERS warning of some kind at the top, and that will be that.  If my players read it, they’re adults, they can still have a good time anyhow. Especially since most of what I’ll be hashing out here will be systems and tables rather than plot points or secrets or what have you.   Finally, after reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://jrients.blogspot.com/2006/09/how-to-awesome-up-your-players.html&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Mr. Rients, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/2011/03/how-i-want-to-hear-about-your-setting.html&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Zak S., I’ve decided that my campaign needs to be more awesome.  I’ll admit it, I’ve succumbed to the artsy fartsy urges that Mr. Rients talks about and limited my setting (no elves or halflings, for instance).  I need to continually remind myself that whatever cool aesthetic vision I may have for the world and adventures in it, primarily it is the setting for a game, the players’ characters are the focus of that game, and what makes this more fun than writing up a tedious fantasy novel is the surprises I get from interacting with other human beings.  So, I’m going to relax my iron self-imposed “genre restraints” in the face of things that are totally flippin’ sweet.   Oh, I lied. Finally finally, I’m going to strive for more posts with more gaming content (monster interpretations, stats, whatever).&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2013-04-10-so-again-with-absence-of-blogging-thing/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Sessions 13 &amp; 14 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;After fleeing from the seemingly endless hordes of large and aggressive trollkin, our adventurers spiked a door behind them and listened with baited breath. Not hearing any sounds of further pursuit, they decided against fleeing blindly, and continued to explore and map carefully. After discovering a secret door and defeating a hideous ooze that dissolved a few weapons, they secured a small clutch of gems, spiked another two doors behind them and decided to rest inside the dungeon. With a careful watch and secure location, their rest was uneventful, and after a few divine acts of healing from the groups clerics, they decided to make their way back out to the surface. They directly encountered no more trollkin, only the surprised sound of a guard coming from a newly constructed barricade and a poison trap that was defeated by Varian&amp;rsquo;s iron constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After successfully reaching the surface, the group made proper payments to the families of the deceased hirelings and proceeded to hire new soldiers and a few more torch bearers before returning to the grim mountain. Having decided that enormous hordes of angry humanoids might not be the best thing to face just now, the party returned once again to the Western entrance to Fellhold, where they encountered and defeated Dag&amp;rsquo;s former bandit group. Exploring more deeply and more carefully, they once again triggered a portcullis, trapping them within, but before they had to resort to the aid of strongman Mihtig the Mighty, they discovered a secret crank that opened the gate. Further exploration led to a secret door opening onto a stairway leading &lt;em&gt;upwards&lt;/em&gt;, in sharp contrast to what they&amp;rsquo;ve encountered thus far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climbing the stairs, they found an elaborate Dwarven antechamber holding six musical pipes. Experimentation revealed that playing certain pipes opened certain doors and closed others, until the proper sequence was found, opening all three sets of huge, impressive double doors. Entering, they found first a rough, unfinished section of halls and chambers, but then more beautifully crafted Dwarven architecture and sculpture, including a massive statue of Aki, the father of all Dwarves, carved from the living rock of the mountain. Though there was a plethora of doors to explore, the party found a large staircase leading farther upwards and pressed on, surprising a small band of trollkin at the top landing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even hemmed in by the stairs, the group made short work of them, with Yllgrad stopping the final one as he fled with a well placed thrown dagger. Following the path the dead trollkin seemed to be heading for, they fell upon another small band of trollkin, these obviously searching and rummaging around in what appears to have once been an officer&amp;rsquo;s quarters. Outside the chambers was a large, magnificent hall with pillars carved in the likenesses of Dwarven heroes, warriors, and smiths. Crossing over they found a doorway directly opposite and entered a room in even worse repair, this one the nest of eight disgusting giant rats! The rats were quickly dispatched, with Sir Braxton the war dog taking especial pleasure in tearing apart one of the foul vermin. Catching their breath, our intrepid band prepares to continue to explore this mysteriously upwards reaching section of Fellhold.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 12 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 17:40:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;We left off with our adventurers deep within the Ashfell, and as we joined them this week, they continued to explore . They returned to the relief mural depiction of the founding of Fellhold and followed the carvings around a large hall, reading a story of dwarves comes to Ashfell, delving into the mountain, and ending with a scene of trade, craft, and fellowship between dwarves and men. Having satisfied themselves that this mural did not contain any further clues about how to proceed, they set off to continue down a wide passageway leading from the imposing statue of a sorceror. Along the way, they found a large, crude set of double doors with a sword painted on and decorated with human and goblin skulls. After listening at the door and hearing some sort of chanting or cheering coming from beyond, they set to and kicked down the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This alerted a group of trollkin bigger than the goblins previously encountered to rush the party and slam the door closed. The party hacked open the door, and made pretty short work of these unarmored trollkin, but they were followed by fully armed and armored trollkin warriors in seemingly endless numbers. The group stood their ground and fought, felling scores of the humanoids. The fight began to take its toll, however, with Blum the magic user seriously wounded, the other members of the party reaching the limits of their endurance, and the deaths of four hirelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deciding that surviving to fight another day was better than a valiant last stand. Flinging recovered gelatinous cube slime behind them to slow pursuit, they fled to a previously discovered narrow hallway with a door and spiked the door closed in the faces of their pursuers. As we leave them, deciding to put more space between them and the howling hordes, they flee deeper into the pitch darkness of Fellhold too quickly to map. . .&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 11 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 22:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;Our brave adventurers consolidated after cutting down wave after wave of goblin fighters, and decided that the best course of action was to camp outside of the goblin lair they had extensively mapped out. Spending the night in quiet, they proceeded to thoroughly map out every nook and cranny of the goblin delving, and then turned their eyes to the previously explored excavated stairs deeper into the mountain. Following these stairs down, they found a brief encounter with vicious giant rats, a long since abandoned market place, many empty store rooms, and a painful but ultimately unremarkable needle trap. After an unsuccessful strike by a surprising gelatinous cube, Yllgrad cleaved it in half with a mighty critical hit. Unfortunately, after a string of successes, Varian fared less well against a stoutly built door, and found himself on the ground in pain after one too many attempts to kick down doors in dramatic fashion. Altogether, the group covered a lot of ground, finding stairs deeper into the mountain, multiple large statues of sorcerors, and a variety of rooms and corridors, mapping perhaps a greater extent of the tunnels under the mountain than any previous expedition. What lies in store for them as they proceed forward? Will their blase ways continue to serve them well, or will doors prove more treacherous than foemen? Only time will tell!&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>First Fellhold Rules Post</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 15:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/ -&lt;p&gt;Howdy folks. The bulk of this post will be the first actual rules I have written for Fellhold coming out of my reading &amp;ldquo;An Echo, Resounding&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Dungeon World&amp;rdquo;. I was initially afraid I would simply be using pieces from each with no original material whatsoever, but in the process of figuring out what I really wanted to do, I ended up coming up with something more different than I expected, though the influences are obvious. Without further ado, here&amp;rsquo;s the section on creating a level for a megadungeon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Create a Dungeon Level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These rules are presented to give you a toolbox for creating the levels of your megadungeon. They can also be used to make smaller lair style dungeons. The toolbox analogy is pretty fitting, though, because just as a hammer, nails, saw, and so forth are necessary to build a house, so too is the lumber and the time putting in the work. These rules are not a substitution for your imagination and creative work, but hopefully they are a useful guiding framework that limits your work to the fun stuff of coming up with what’s interesting, and somewhat mechanizing the more tedious parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a Level Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the wider ranging and more amorphous sources of adventure of the surface world and wilderness, your preparation for the dungeon is organized as &lt;em&gt;Fronts&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dangers&lt;/em&gt;, though being dungeon fronts and dangers, they are a little different in nature. You will follow a step by step process, and when you finish, you ought to have a living, breathing dungeon space ready for adventurers to stomp into and cause trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Pick Tags for Original Purpose&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is a list of tags that describe what the original purpose of any given area was broadly speaking. These don’t have any particular mechanical effect except to remind you what kind of hazards and monsters to put in there, how to lay out the rooms, and so forth. Somewhere between one and three is usually good for the level overall. Use these to capture a broad theme to guide you when maknig decisions about the level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arcane -&lt;/strong&gt; Either built for some kind of Arcane experiment, or an area magical in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandits -&lt;/strong&gt; Brigands, human or otherwise, built or modified this area for their purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caverns -&lt;/strong&gt; The natural forces of the earth opened these tunnels and chambers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chaos -&lt;/strong&gt; Twisted by the intrusion of forces antithetical to reality, there is something deeply wrong with this part of the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cult -&lt;/strong&gt; Constructed or modified for use by a secretive and sinister cult of some sort&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demonic -&lt;/strong&gt; This area has received the attention of a demonic entity and reflects its twisted nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divine -&lt;/strong&gt; When constructed, this area was imbued with some sort of divine energy - be sure to name the deity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dwarven -&lt;/strong&gt; This part of the dungeon was originally delved by dwarves. It is likely orderly and heavily decorated with dwarven designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fungus -&lt;/strong&gt; Extensive and large fungi grow in this area, whether wild or cultivated by underground denizens for food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gate -&lt;/strong&gt; This area contains a passageway to somewhere else - a different environment, realm, or even world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mines -&lt;/strong&gt; These tunnels were dug in pursuit of gold, silver, gems, or something else valuable under the earth, and are likely to be rougher hewn and less orderly than others, twisting to follow veins of precious materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monsters -&lt;/strong&gt; Some kind of intelligent monster made this place for its own use, it may be crudely done or well made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nest -&lt;/strong&gt; This area was burrowed out by some kind of bestial creature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prison -&lt;/strong&gt; A dungeon in the truest sense, this area was built to confine prisoners, and maybe worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Temple -&lt;/strong&gt; This area was dedicated as a temple to some power, whether divine or profane, or something stranger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tomb -&lt;/strong&gt; Parts of these halls and rooms were built to serve as catacombs to house the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Religion -&lt;/strong&gt; This area was dedicated to some particular religious figure, you should specify which.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volcanic -&lt;/strong&gt; Whether active or dormant, this area was formed by movement of hot molten rock and gases from deep within the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Pick Tags for Current Nature&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the original purpose tags, these tags are meant to guide you in making decisions about crafting the level. You’ll notice that many of the tags are the same as from the original purpose section, even if their descriptions are a little different. The idea is that you don’t need to double up on something that is still true (If it was created divine and is still divine, no need for a separate current nature tag). Instead, these tags allow you to set up interesting contradicitons that show the way the dungeon has changed and developed. What was once the proud market place of the Dwarves may have become the scene of sorcerous displays by an evil cabal, and is now where bandits bed down their horses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient -&lt;/strong&gt; Whatever formed this location, it was long and long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arcane -&lt;/strong&gt; This location serves some magical purpose, or is imbued with arcane energies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandits -&lt;/strong&gt; Some kind of humanoids that prey on others have set up shop in this part of the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chaos -&lt;/strong&gt; This part of the dungeon is twisted and tainted from the touch of something beyond any rational world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cult -&lt;/strong&gt; A sinister and covert religious group uses this area for its mysterious ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demonic -&lt;/strong&gt; One or more demons maintain contact with the world in this place, and it carries their taint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divine -&lt;/strong&gt; Blessed by some deity, name which god has bestowed his or her benefits on this section of the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fungus -&lt;/strong&gt; Omnipresent and possibly huge fungi cover this section .of dungeon, whether overgrowth or cultivated by subterranean inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gate -&lt;/strong&gt; This section of the dungeon serves as a gate to elsewhere - whether mundane or supernatural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mines -&lt;/strong&gt; These tunnels are actively worked to extract the riches of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monsters -&lt;/strong&gt; Creatures, whether humanoid or not, infest this area. Use each significant monster type present as a tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nest -&lt;/strong&gt; Something monstrous and non-humanoid has made this area its home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prison -&lt;/strong&gt; Captives are held or tortured here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Religion -&lt;/strong&gt; Some religion is practiced here. The tag should specify the deity’s name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Temple -&lt;/strong&gt; This section is used for worship of some force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tomb -&lt;/strong&gt; Whatever its original purpose, this section now houses the burials of some intelligent group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volcanic -&lt;/strong&gt; Active magma and hot gases can be found in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Decide Total Treasure Number&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As discussed in the Domain Play section, one Treasure is equal to 500 GP. A good rough formula for how much treasure a level should have is to multiply 10 times a number of D6s equal to the level of the dungeon &lt;strong&gt;(this is untested still!)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4. Create a Danger for each Section&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where most of your work creating dungeon levels will come in.  Follow the steps below in the &lt;em&gt;Create a Section Danger&lt;/em&gt; section in order to detail each section of the current level. Any tags you’ve selected for the level overall will apply to the sections unless you decide otherwise. Also, it’s important to point out that an entire level can just be one section. This is a great way to make either“lair” type dungeons, smaller megadungeon levels, or parts of larger megadungeon levels. In the original Fellhold campaign, most levels were divided into quadrants which were statted up as sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;5. Create any level-wide monster assets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any especially large monsters or wide ranging monster groups that you want to be prevalent throughout the entire level and not associated with any particular section, go ahead and follow the rules for creating a monster asset detailed in the chapter on &lt;em&gt;Assets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a Section Danger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be most regular for a level to represent a number of rooms and corridors roughly the same distance above or below ground, and for sections to be some subset of those rooms and corridors. This is not the only possible way to use these rules, however. You might have a tower that counts as all one “level” and each section is a floor, or even a grouping of floors. Don’t feel bound to create a new “level” and “section” just because the player characters will have to go up or down some stairs to access it. You could also create a sprawling ruin of a city and have each neighborhood be a section. The rules are purposely flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The included Section Reference Sheet provides space for recording most of the decisions you make here, but all that’s really needed is a pencil and some paper (preferably graph paper).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Create a Ruin Location for the Section&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is fairly straightforward, and is mostly a content holder for all of the work you will do in the rest of the steps. If it is ever interacted with using the Domain Play rules, it will be a ruin with a Treasure value of whatever you assign from the overall level Treasure, a nature of whatever Original Purpose and Current Nature tags you pick, and any monster assets you create for the section. If you want to keep the dungeon feeling “alive” you can have each section function as a small domain and take domain turns using the monster assets and transfer treasure around and modify assets accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Pick Tags for Original Purpose&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the same tags as for the overall level, but they allow you to fine tune a particular section of the level. Perhaps the level overall is an ancient Dwarven city, but this section was their fungus farm, yuou could add the &lt;strong&gt;Fungus&lt;/strong&gt; tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arcane, Bandits, Caverns, Chaos, Cult, Demonic, Divine, Dwarven, Fungus, Gate, Mines, Monsters, Nest, Prison, Religion, Temple, Tomb, Volcanic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Pick Tags for Current Nature&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as with the Original Purpose tags, these are identical to the Current Nature tags for the overall level, but allow you to call out a particular section as different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient, Arcane, Bandits, Chaos, Cult, Demonic, Divine, Fungus, Gate, Mines, Monsters, Nest, Prison, Religion, Temple, Tomb, Volcanic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4. Assign portion of Level’s treasure to section&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use your own good judgment here, but unless you have crafted one section of the level to have more treasure than others (like, say, because a dragon has its lair there or an entire tribe of trollkin store their loot there) it’s just fine to split it up evenly among the sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;5. Choose or Draw the Floor Plan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part has always proved challenging to me, and so I remind you that you can repurpose sections of the many, many dungeon maps available for free or for purchase. It is satisfying in a different way to work within the constraints of an existing floor plan to find your vision than it is to think through the placement of rooms and halls and make your own decisions. Both are fun, and both lead to good dungeons, so honestly, go with whatever you’re most comfortable with, and feel free to mix it up from level to level, section to section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing you’ll want to concern yourself with, whether drawing or copying a map, is to make sure there is interaction with the rest of the dungeon. Make sure sections connect in multiple ways, have stairs up and down levels, and so forth. It’s especially fun and interesting to make multiple connections of different sorts, such that one part of level 1 leads down to level 2, but another goes to level 3, and still another leads to a sub-area of level 1. Layouts like this encourage thorough exploration and lots of backtracking, giving you the chance to showcase the dungeon as a living, changing place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;6. Create the Stocking Tables&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stocking tables are really where the section comes to life. It may seem dry at first to make a bunch of tables, but they allow you to combine your creativity and judgement and random chance in a way that really fosters a dynamic, living feeling for the dungeon. If you haven’t experienced it yet, you’ll be amazed at the way motives and plot hooks and history just pop into your brain as you work your way through the rooms with a random table. They also make it really easy to restock the dungeon after the adventurers have massacred their way through a section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;6a. Create Monster &amp;amp; Treasure Frequency Table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Monster &amp;amp; Treasure Frequency Table allows you to determine whether a given room contains a monster and/or treasure. When checking to see if a room contains either a monster or treasure, you roll on this table. The default table, modified from the original adventure game is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roll 1st Die&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Result&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roll 2nd Die&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Result&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monster&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treasure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monster w/Treasure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use this default table, the procedure is to roll 1d6 to see if there is a monster with or without treasure, and then to roll a 2nd die if there is no monster to see if there is unguarded treasure. To save time, you may wish to roll 2d6 of two different colors, designate one the “monster die” and the other the “treasure die” and ignore the treasure die on a result of 1 or 2 on the monster die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you choose to create an alternate monster/treasure frequency table, simply choose a die size, how many dice to roll and then assign values. I’d recommend sticking with the default until you get a feeling for how populated a dungeon you want to face in play. Having a good mix of rooms that are genuinely empty and rooms that just need a little searching to find somethign of value, and rooms that represent a potential threat is necessary to keep the exploration aspect of the game fun and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;6b. Create Monster Stocking Table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This table is where your section really gets the flavor that your players are going to notice the most. Monsters provide the most interactive part of what the players will face in a dungeon section, and so help define places. As you choose monsters for the table, don’t think only about how many hit dice they have, or how large a group they travel in, think also about how they fit together, and what they’re doing in this section of the dungeon. In a section of the dungeon you’ve designated as Hobgoblin controlled, most of your entries will probably be Hobgoblins. If you want a section of caverns to feel more wild and untamed, don’t put any intelligent monsters in your table. You get to exercise some discretion and taste in what you include and at what frequency, but then the random die rolls will give a pleasantly unexpected specific mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important consideration is the rate of refresh for your stocking table. The dungeon should be a living place, and just because the adventurers have been through an area before doesn’t mean it should be a barren, safe wasteland from then on out. Tweak your stocking table to reflect changes (maybe driving out the hobgoblins opened up the area to goblins now), and after the right amount of in-game time has passed, go through the stocking process again. A good starting point is 1 week, but up this for rarer creatures or lower it for especially prolific ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create your table, simply select a die size and then assign an entry to each value, using the guidance above. Do yourself a favor, though: don’t go nuts on the die size. If you try to pick d100 monsters, or even d100 discrete entries for every single section, you’ll end up throwing your referee’s binder at the wall in no time. Now, if you have broad percentages that amount to 20 or less entries, that’s just fine. For starting out, D6, D8, or D10 gives you plenty of room to play with, but won’t leave you stumped on those last few entries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;6c. Create Room Dressing Table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Room Dressing is whatever random stuff you place in rooms to give them some character beyond their bare dimensions and the composition of their walls. It’s not necessary to have or to specify dressing in every single room, but you’ll want to be careful about only describing items in detail when they warrant being searched or flat out telling players a room is empty if it is. Let them explore! Try to include things that suggest something of the section’s purposes throughout the ages. As with the monster tables, choose a die size that seems appropriate and fill it with things that seem evocative of the tags you chose at the beginning, but that can be reused a few time without it being weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on how frequently you use the room dressing table, you may want only things of especial interest or curiosity, or you may want a bunch of random nothing. Just remember that anything of value is treated under treasure, and has probably long ago been carried off by monsters unless hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe roll a D20 along with your monster/treasure frequency rolls and treat 1-10 as nothing, and then have results for 11-20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10. Place any special monsters or treasures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often you will have one or a few creatures or items that you know exactly what you want to do with - the troll chieftain, the dragon, and so forth. Don’t put these guys in your monster chart! They deserve to be treated as individual threats placed with care. So before you use any of your shiny new tables, place the things that are special to the section. Remember to deduct any treasure so placed from the available section treasure to be assigned using the stocking tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;11. Run through remaining rooms using Stocking Tables&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having hand-placed the important monsters and their hoards, you identify any rooms that seem like they might contain monsters and/or treasures (I tend to leave out tiny storerooms or rooms that are extremely repetitive, or to only pick a few of them). Go through each in turn and roll on your monster and treasure frequency chart. If they indicate monsters and/or treasure, use the appropriate charts. Place treasure with monsters according to the monsters’ description, and when placing treasure randomly, it should be D100% of 1 Treasure (500 GP), and it should be well hidden and/or trapped. This is an excellent excuse to include a trap you hadn’t thought of yet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you go through placing monsters and treasure, you may find it easier to convert the sections Treasure total into a GP value and then assign the Gold Marks, Silver pennings, Copper Skillings, jewels, weapons, and so forth accordingly. If you reach the total treasure value for that section, then do not place any more treasure. If you have a lot of rooms left without any treasure, consider altering the level’s overall amount of treasure to better reflect what ought to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;12. Create Wandering Monster Table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This table will quite likely be fairly similar to your stocking table (sometimes they can even be identical), but you can add some nuance by having a distinction between the monsters that wander this area and those who actually reside there in a more permanent fashion. In addition to choosing a die size and assigning monsters (or evecn strange sounds or events) to each result, you need to choose how often to check for a wandering monster in this section. Once per hour (6 exploration turns) is fairly typical, but you can vary how dangerous and draining an area is not just in the difficulty of monsters, but in how often they show up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;13. Create Monster Assets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the rules for Monster Asset creation detailed in the Assets section of the Domain Play chapter in order to create assets representing any large monster forces or particularly powerful individual monsters. Again, this will let you play out “domain actions” between dungeon inhabitants to keep the dungeon dynamic, as well as giving you the information you need if any enterprising domain ruler tries to deal with a dungeon through main force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;14. Place Traps&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go through the level and place any fiendish traps or puzzles you care to. Sometimes you’ll do this step as your draw the floor plan and see where traps would make sense. Other times you’ll being to see a sort of logic emerging from your stocking rolls, and you’ll set up traps that way. Give traps some thought: were they put there by the original constructors? Can they be reset? How do the dungeon’s denizens deal with them? On the other hand, don’t overthink them too much: dungeons have traps, they’re part of the territory, so if you think you need some, put them in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;15. Final Touches and Tweaks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you have an entirely playable dungeon section that you’re prepared to restock or have interact with other dungeon levels and sections as necessary. It’s helpful, though, to take a moment to look at everything together and make any final tweaks that suggest themselves, whether regarding monster placement, treasure amount, or just what makes sense or not, this is your chance to double check that the section actually makes good on the creative vision you codified in the tags you chose at the outset.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules, Part 4</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 22:05:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/ -&lt;p&gt;So, for this post I&amp;rsquo;m taking a bit of a departure from the campaign and domain play rules that I&amp;rsquo;ve been kitbashing from &lt;em&gt;Dungeon World&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;An Echo, Resounding&lt;/em&gt;. This is mostly because it&amp;rsquo;s been awhile, and I&amp;rsquo;m having to reconstruct all the stuff I had figured out from what are now opaque notes, and instead of figuring all that out tonight, I went instead for a simpler problem and decided to tackle some planning/layout issues, and then to address equipment tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipment tags are one of my very favorite nitty-gritty details from the &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse World&lt;/em&gt; family of games. I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for broadly modular systems that have a framework for incorporating very flexible input (now that I&amp;rsquo;ve figured them out, I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of tags for blog posts as well). Perhaps best of all, incorporating DW style tags does not require a lot of work on other rules. For all of the &amp;ldquo;fictional cue&amp;rdquo; tags, it&amp;rsquo;s really just a matter of systematizing and highlighting what&amp;rsquo;s already there in OD&amp;amp;D. OD&amp;amp;D referees are already supposed to account for the fact that a Glaive isn&amp;rsquo;t something you&amp;rsquo;re going to use in a wrestling match and that daggers might have trouble getting around a determined shield wall. The trouble is, as I&amp;rsquo;m discovering actually running an OD&amp;amp;D game, is that when the ref gets caught up in keeping track of exploration rounds and combat rounds, tracking monster hit points and special attacks, remembering to check morale, and so forth, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; too easy to succumb to &amp;ldquo;Roll to hit. Roll damage. Next guy.&amp;rdquo; Equipment tags are a fantastic way to remind refs about the cool stuff to pay attention to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the most significant mechanical alterations are in terms of range and encumbrance. I really rather like DW&amp;rsquo;s method of handling weight and encumbrance, and so I&amp;rsquo;m converting the pound weights of S&amp;amp;W WhiteBox into &amp;ldquo;Weight&amp;rdquo; tags. I&amp;rsquo;m going to go ahead and reexamine the movement and encumbrance rules to square them with the changed weight method. Range is pretty straight forward. I&amp;rsquo;m straight up converting ranges in feet into the broad categories of &amp;ldquo;near&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;far&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge is coming from converting prices for things not included in the WhiteBox rules, but overall I&amp;rsquo;m really excited about including equipment tags going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 10 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 22:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;Our intrepid adventurers, after having destroyed a wolf pack, venture through a secret door into hewn underground passages. Joined this time by Yllgrad and Earn and their cohorts (though still not by Blum) the strengthened party takes  a few moments to regroup and take advantage of magical healing before venturing into the underground passages. Finding no sign of the goblins they heard exclaim earlier, they push into to the passages and find a room full of rubble with stairs leading steeply downward. Following these stairs, they find themselves in apparently dwarven rooms, including a small chamber and a barracks room. They also find the entrance to an enormously large chamber with decorated columns, but decide that exploration of it can wait and instead go back up the stairs and check out the passageways closer to the surface more closely, worried about Goblins harassing them from the rear. They send a party of 3 hirelings (all hired by Yllgrad) to a passageway to the south, and themselves go north and east. They trigger a few crude, apparently improvised traps, with Yllgrad bearing the brunt of it, before stumbling upon the lair of a hideous Gelatinous Cube!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group decides to run back to a room full of trash and attempt to satiate the horrendous creature. Unfortunately, despite its apparently pleasure at the garbage flung into its mass, the monster keeps coming for live flesh! After very little time, an effective hit from an arrow fired by one of Earn&amp;rsquo;s men coupled with a devastating axe blow from Yllgrad serve to dissolve the noisome and foul cube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The adventurers continue to explore and find a room full of apparently waylaid trade goods as well as a cave entrance directly out to the hill side that was initially missed due to the heavy vegetative cover. Knowing a quick way out and having gained no report from Yllgrad&amp;rsquo;s men, they returned to the putative meeting point and found no one waiting for them. Venturing further south, they blundered into the goblins&amp;rsquo; own great hall, with dozens of combatant goblins present!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long fight with many multiple-goblin cleaving blows, and including astounding fortitude and viciousness in the face of mounting casualties by the goblins, our party found themselves victorious, but wondering where the goblin women and children had fled to, and whether that boded further trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 9 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 10:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;Due to various obligations in Silverdelf, Yllgrad, Blum, and Earn remained behind, but along with their hirelings and henchmen, Bryni, Caleb, and Varian set off to explore the heretofore unknown eastern path up the spur to Fellhold. They found that the path petered out in a heavily wooded and gently sloping portion of mountain, with crags and boulders suggesting caves. On further exploration, they found a large cave opening, and an initial scan of the cave revealed a heavy bed of pine needles as well as the grisly remains of creatures large and small, accompanied by a horrible smell. Deciding that discretion is the better part of valor, our explorers prudently set the pine needles alight to smoke out whatever may lair in the cave, taking up positions to meet whatever fled the cave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were confronted by an enraged Owlbear! This massive and ill tempered brute charged straight for Varian on his horse, as the most direct target, and landed a moderately injurious blow with its talons, but Varian&amp;rsquo;s shield and plate deflected the beast&amp;rsquo;s other attacks. The party engaged in a vicious melee, killing the monster without suffering any casualties. They drained the monster of its blood and stowed the carcass in the cart, hoping to turn some sort of profit, or at least have an impressive trophy for their now under construction home base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After allowing the fire to burn down, they entered and found nothing of interest except for a small gem and scorched longsword and helmet (now beneath their well armed notice) on an unfortunate skeleton. Moving on to the other obvious cave opening, they sent a hireling in to investigate, who came fleeing out when he heard growls and smelled wet dog. Sure enough, a pack of 8 wolves came surging out of their den to fight viciously. The alpha charged straight for Varian (again the most obvious target) while the rest of the wolves spread out to harry as many of the human intruders as they could. Erna was severely wounded, but quick action by Aelfsigr saved the remaining sister soldier. Varian once again sustained a moderate wound, but Caleb magically cured his wounds so that he could finish the fight with the diminishing wolf pack. Sir Braxton, Caleb&amp;rsquo;s trusty war hound, personally tore out the throat of the alpha wolf, but the pack was too frenzied to acknowledge what would normally be clear sign of dominance to wolves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a hard fought battle, all eight of the wolves were killed, and the party carefully inspected their den, finding a fairly large cave complex. In the rearmost chamber, they found a litter of four wolf pups, which they took back to the cart to sort out later, though there was talk of either vicious pets or sale to specialty merchants. During their careful inspection, they found a knob that opened a secret entrance to what appears to be a worked passageway. Peaking around the corner, they heard an exclamation of surprise in Goblinic (the language of trollkin). They retreated to regroup and plan at the wagon, and in our next episode they plan to push in to the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 8 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 08:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;After last week&amp;rsquo;s harrowing encounter with arm-hungry statues and pit traps, our daring band of adventurers decided it was time to attend to some matters outside of Fellhold&amp;rsquo;s dark halls. Acca, the hireling who lost his arm, survived his grievous injury, and his family was so grateful for the pension his employer offered him that his son Weorc took service in his place. The party set out on a quiet trip to Mickleheim where they once again strengthened their ties to Clan Dagaeca through the steward Cnud, selling them the splendid necklace of fire opals lifted from Earn the bandit chief and discovering that an exotic beast brought in alive for the midwinter festival would  make a fine offering to Hrokr, fine enough that a bounty might be offered.  Bryni also once again besought Mihtig the Mighty, strong man extraorinaire, and found his fee more reasonable after the encounter with the portcullis. Having secured such specialist service and finding themselves flush with more money than they knew what to do with, the group decided it would be best to invest in a permanent base in Silverdelf, and so headed back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the return journey, they were ambushed by a group of small trollkin, out in the daytime oddly enough. In their first onslaught they managed to kill the hireling Gytha, leaving her sister Erna distraught  The rest of their attacks were largely ineffective, except for a glancing wound to Yllgrad. When the adventurers responded, Blum once again unleashed his devastating sleep spell, putting half of the attacking humanoids out of commission. The remaining half were dealt with fairly easily by the largely mounted party and their hirelings. They also had fewer qualms with slitting goblin throats than men&amp;rsquo;s, and so dispatched the sleeping trollkin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon return to Silverdelf, they employed the engineer hired to travel back with them from Mickleheim to seek out and survey an adequate spot for a great hall. Finding a suitable spot along the Silverrun river, they employed him to begin construction of a great hall with rooms enough for the party and their favored henchmen and a good stout cellar for the storage of treasure, a stables, a smithy suitable to function as an armory, and a surrounding palisade wall. This project will take quite some time to complete, but should give our heroes a welcome safe haven in which to celebrate and lick their wounds.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 7 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 10:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;Our intrepid band of adventurers finished up their business in Mickleheim, recruiting even more hirelings for renewed expeditions. They returned to Silverdelf without incident and discovered that the captured bandits had been sent off to whatever rough justice awaited them in Mickleheim along with the rescued shipment of whiskey. They also caught wind of an armed group buying supplies and setting off in the direction of Fellhold, but for what purpose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deciding to deal with Earn and his bandits once and for all, they returned to the bandit lair, leaving Varian and his retinue to guard the baggage train in the ruined outpost. Once again, they managed to surprise a large group of bandits and Blum employed the sleep spell to great effect, downing all ten of Earn&amp;rsquo;s new hires, but leaving Earn himself standing, slightly woozy, but ready to fight. Quickly ganging up on him after a few ineffectual bow and crossbow attacks, our band surrounded Earn and set to with deadly earnest. Yllgrad the dwarf landed a mighty blow, as did Caleb, and the others and their hirelings chipped away at his defenses. At his time to act, Earn proved to be a puissant warrior, delivering blow after blow, but to only limited effect. Once again the party set to him with continuing gradual effect, and one of Earn the Cleric&amp;rsquo;s hirelings hilariously fumbled his morning star, waking an entranced bandit. The remaining hirelings subdued this bandit as the party finished it&amp;rsquo;s exchange with Earn the bandit chief. He landed a vicious and potentially lethal blow on Yllgrad, but Caleb&amp;rsquo;s nurse Alfsigr staunched the bleeding until the newly empowered clerics could see to him with magical healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fittingly enough, Dag, the former bandit sergeant and now loyal retainer of Bryni&amp;rsquo;s, landed the killing blow on Earn, and the party subdued and searched the remaining new bandit recruits. They recovered a magnificent necklace from the vain and luxury loving Earn, as well as a sizable personal stash of gold. After some debate, the party decided that these new recruits hadn&amp;rsquo;t had much time for actual banditry, and settled for disarming them and letting them loose to fend for themselves, after being relieved of their purses, of course. After dealing with these logistics, the adventuring band camped out in the ruined outpost to prepare for further exploration, and besides a shouted alarm at small, shadowy figures observing the camp and darting away, the night passed without incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning to the dark halls of Fellhold, the party finally had the opportunity to explore deeper into the dungeon. Blum fell into a pit trap and would have been out of action, but for the quick work of Earn, being lowered into the trap with rope, curing his wounds with the power of Dwyn, the Oak Mother, and raising him back out. More carefully advancing, the party found a large room with several openings and two door ways. After carefully checking a small chamber behind one door, they found the second door the trigger to release a portcullis, blocking the way they came! The strongest hirelings in the retinue were unable to lift the portcullis, but Bryni devised a mechanism from a spear, helmet, and several iron spikes, creating a makeshift pulley, allowing almost the entire party to bring their strength to bear and to heroically lift up the gate enough to prop two doors under, so that everyone could crawl through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glad to have their path of escape clear, but still desiring to explore, the party proceeded north at the T-intersection where they had previously gone south, and then turned east, discovering a blasphemous and disgusting temple of the Sorcerors who once ruled Fellhold. In addition to the relief sculptures on the walls and pillars of repellent and sensuous revels of humans and demons, there were three large statues of grotesquely fat and vicious frog demons, two with glittery eyes, and the largest on a raised dais with a fist-sized gem in it&amp;rsquo;s obviously hinged jaws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some discussion of how best to avoid tripping what appeared obviously to be a trap, they decided it most likely to be a pressure plate, and so tasked a hireling with carefully swapping a waterskin estimated to be the same weight out with the stone. Unfortunately for this poor fellow, the jaws snapped closed, severing his arm immediately! Despite this grisly sight, the group continued to search. Caleb and his helpers removed the eyes from the southern of the two glittery eyed statues and found them to be only glass and to release a cloud of poison gas! After some hacking and coughing, he and his hirelings were severely weakened, but still in fighting shape. Bryni, learning by the examples of his peers, was far more careful with the northern of the two statues, throwing stones until he could dislodge one of the eyes, and found them to be ordinary topaz, and no traps. With the use of crowbars, the party also recovered the unfortunate hireling&amp;rsquo;s arm and the gem. Deciding not to press their luck further, the party left for Silverdelf to have their items appraised and to see to a proper pension for the now one armed former hireling and to see to various other matters of resupply and logistics.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Session 6 Recap</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 08:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/ -&lt;p&gt;Last night, our intrepid band set out on the road to Mickleheim. The first two days of the three day journey passed quietly, but on the third day just after sun up they were set upon by a pack of vicious wolves! Though the only serious injury was to one of Earn&amp;rsquo;s retainers, who was viciously mauled, Earn leapt to his aid and stemmed the bleeding. After the players dispatched one of the wolves, the rest turned tail and ran, losing three more to parting blows and crossbow quarrels. The party made efficient but grisly use of the bodies, skinning them to sell the pelts, and making a meal of the meat to take their strength and save precious trail rations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They pressed on and reached Mickleheim by nightfall, finding lodging in the Drunken Giant Inn. The next day they checked the Craftsman&amp;rsquo;s Bazaar to see what they could get for their plunder, and were unsatisfied with the prices offered, and spent good coin drinking and spreading the word and gathering information. After three days of greasing the wheels, they discovered the Steward of the House of Daglaeca, a family of some esteem fallen on hard times. They managed to strike a deal satisfactory to both sides, and our adventurers found themselves flush with cash in a way none of them was familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Varian immediately discharged his ruinous debt, Ulf the lender being somewhat disappointed to see such a potential huge cash flow cut off early. The party jointly secured a larger wagon and draft animals, and several sought the services of more men at arms and other hirelings. The party has concluded most of its business in Mickleheim and will probably return to Silverdelf and Fellhold in our next installment, but their options are open.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, Part 3</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 10:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/ -&lt;p&gt;Though the title of this post shortchanges the role &lt;em&gt;An Echo, Resounding&lt;/em&gt; is playing in my development of the referee rules in my campaign, I figured it was best to stay consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of the role AER is playing, though I&amp;rsquo;m working my way up to the domain rules, rather than down, I am broadly using the categories and concepts from AER&amp;rsquo;s domain play, so that most of the framework for reconciling &lt;em&gt;Dungeon World&lt;/em&gt; style GMing tools with the AER domain play should already be there. So, last night I figured out how I want to work steadings (which include cities, towns, and keeps), ruins, resources, and assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inspiration I stumbled upon was that Gangs in Apocalypse world already provide an example of the intersection of statted out groups with the GM organization tool of Fronts and Threats. Dremmer&amp;rsquo;s biker gang is a &amp;ldquo;threat&amp;rdquo; when it comes to figuring out what things are happening off stage and how they will react to player actions and/or threaten things the players care about, but when they throw down in a shoot out, they are a &amp;ldquo;gang&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by way of comparison, in Fellhold, there might be a bandit group that is written up as a threat to help me keep track of them as elements of the world, but if that bandit group starts threatening a domain&amp;rsquo;s trade in a significant way, they&amp;rsquo;ll be statted up as an asset that can move around and interact with other assets at a domain level. If it comes to personal combat, the existing D&amp;amp;D rules (well, Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox, as modified) will come into play as per usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend for assets to be able to exist for all three domain values: military, social, and wealth. Assets of different types will have different explanatory tags (for example, a social asset like a town council, won&amp;rsquo;t likely have a damage/harm value, nor will it be mobile). But all assets will have a type tag (military, social, or wealth) and a size tag (the amount it adds to the listed value for the steading that owns it, or the amount it possesses on its own).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assets are basically a way to enable increased granularity than the DW steading rules. They don&amp;rsquo;t supersede them, they just supplement them. So, a Defense value of &amp;ldquo;Militia (1)&amp;rdquo; implies that the citizens of the village can be organize somewhat effectively with some real weapons, and it&amp;rsquo;s given as a characteristic of the Village. On the other hand, let&amp;rsquo;s say that we have a big city that wants to detach a small unit to go attack a neighboring town. Its overall Defenses might be &amp;ldquo;Legion (6)&amp;quot;, but the referee decides that its important to keep track of how that military might is dispersed, and so creates an asset to represent the detachment sent away and gives it a value of &amp;ldquo;Watch (2)&amp;rdquo; and then assigns it various descriptive tags. At this point it become an asset of type Military with a size of 2. The city&amp;rsquo;s defenses go down to &amp;ldquo;Garrison (4)&amp;rdquo; until the asset returns or enough time passes to replace it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, assets should only be prepared for things that have enough of an independent existence to matter (like a powerful merchant guild) or are likely to be dealt with separately from the town as a whole (so, for a big city, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to make an asset for the watch, the garrison, and every unit of the standing army unless and until they become important to game play).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, groups of monsters can be statted up as assets that live in Ruins or Resources, but this is only necessary if Domains take Domain level action against them, or if you want them to take domain level actions. So, that tribe of Trollkin squatting in the abandoned gold mine can just be written up as a threat as usual if the players are coming to root them out personally with sword and torch, but if a player owns a small domain and sends his troops to deal with the matter, then the goblins will need to be statted up as an asset so they can interact with the domain level troops action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I toyed with the idea that Ruin and Resource locations would have monstery/wild versions of population, wealth, and military, I decided that it was a bit forced and hindered the flexibility of threats and fronts. Instead, Ruins will mostly be collections of descriptive tags and associated assets. All Ruins will have a Treasure tag which is like wealth, but finite. So, if adventurers recover 1 Wealth worth of treasure from a Ruin that started with 3 treasure, it now only has 2 unless more is brought in. I probably need to figure out a good conversion from actual gold amounts to treasure, but that&amp;rsquo;s difficult since 1 wealth is supposed to be enough for a small village to get by on. There may be some scaling issues involved, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources will also be pretty minimal. All resources will have a &amp;ldquo;Type&amp;rdquo; tag that describes what they are, and a &amp;ldquo;Size&amp;rdquo; tag that represents the amount of wealth that resource adds to a steading that owns it. A size of 1 will be typical, whereas 2 represents a truly noteworthy reserve, and 3 would be a once in a world source of a resource (something like South Africa is for diamonds). Like Ruins, Resources can have threat and other descriptive tags to make them more than just a place on the map that makes other steadings richer, and they can &amp;ldquo;house&amp;rdquo; assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with the structure of how tags will work with the categories I got from AER, but I need to dive into AER&amp;rsquo;s methods of generating Ruins, Lairs, Cities, and Towns in order to write more tags and new threat types with new instincts and moves. After that I&amp;rsquo;ll look at Domain Actions in more detail and and combine it with DW&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Updating the Campaign Map&amp;rdquo; to finalize the domain level rules.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Into the Wilderness (Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, part 2)</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/ -&lt;p&gt;As the party is about to venture forth to Mickleheim, I&amp;rsquo;ve started giving some thought to wilderness/sandbox adventure, which I&amp;rsquo;ve intended from the start to be a facet of the Fellhold campaign. I cheated a little bit up front by asking my players to do me the courtesy of agreeing that their characters had come together with the intent to explore Fellhold, at least initially, and we&amp;rsquo;d go from there. This let me devote my initial focus to having mapped and stocked dungeon locations (as it turns out, far more than I&amp;rsquo;ve needed so far - before play, I overestimated the speed with which the party would explore). Now they&amp;rsquo;re heading to the big city to sell off some of their more specialized loot, and hopefully get some better prices on fancy things. I was prepared to let them make this trip safely, and only get into the difficulties of wilderness travel later, but they assumed that the journey would involve some play, so who am I to stop them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I&amp;rsquo;m giving some thought as to how best to handle this. As mentioned in previous posts, I thoroughly like &lt;em&gt;An Echo, Resounding&lt;/em&gt;&amp;lsquo;s philosophy of building in later domain level threats and interactions into early play, both because it makes the setting seem more &amp;ldquo;alive&amp;rdquo;, but also so that when the players start concerning themselves with higher goings on, it won&amp;rsquo;t have come out of nowhere. However, as also mentioned above, I find &lt;em&gt;Dungeon World&lt;/em&gt;&amp;lsquo;s fronts (as modified from &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse World&lt;/em&gt;) to be a fantastic tool, and so I want to modify them to work here. As such, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do a bit of thinking out loud about their value and how that will fit into an Old School approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, for those not familiar with fronts and threats from either AW or DW, they are a fantastic bit of gaming technology thought up by Vincent Baker that quite elegantly reconcile GM prep and vision with wide open player action. The way they manage this is to have a general characterization of the threat (say, a Cult of Demon worshippers) which may be part of a larger &amp;ldquo;Front&amp;rdquo; (like eastern front or western front) such as the Incursion of Chaos, or whatever. The GM decides what these things want, and what they will do if left to their own devices, and then figures out some specifics and when/under what circumstances they will happen. So far, nothing that different from what GMs have been doing since ever. Here&amp;rsquo;s the paired techniques that make these something special: first, the GM is specifically charged with making sure these things the baddies are doing will in some way threaten or intrude upon the player characters, and secondly, that these things &lt;em&gt;only happen if the players don&amp;rsquo;t do anything about it&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s where the key difference with pre-planned story lines comes - the GM does not &lt;em&gt;under any circumstances&lt;/em&gt; pre-plan a guaranteed outcome about anything that involves player action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, examples are more useful than vague descriptions. Under a post Ravenloft/Dragonlance idea of &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; in an adventure, I would probably decide that there&amp;rsquo;s a Demon worshipping cult, and that they are gonna kidnap the mayor&amp;rsquo;s daughter, and then the players are expected to go rescue her, and the climactic sacrifice will be about to happen whenever the players show up. On the other hand, with the fronts and threats system, I&amp;rsquo;d create a threat about the Cultists, describe what they&amp;rsquo;re like, and what they&amp;rsquo;re prone to do, and come up with a few special things they might do differently than other folks (call upon their Demon lord, make strange pronouncements, whatever) as cues for play. Then I&amp;rsquo;d decide that if left to their own devices, they&amp;rsquo;d kidnap and eventually sacrifice the Mayor&amp;rsquo;s daughter. Here&amp;rsquo;s the key thing, though: the timing of those things will be based on the internal logic of the Cultists, not on what seems appropriate to a preplanned idea of the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if the players are astute and figure out the cultists plan and wait to ambush them before they even kidnap the mayor&amp;rsquo;s daughter, that&amp;rsquo;s what happens. If the players don&amp;rsquo;t particularly care about the mayor&amp;rsquo;s daughter for a month or two, well, she got sacrificed while they weren&amp;rsquo;t paying attention. At their most basic, fronts and threats are simply ways of organizing what happens outside of the players&amp;rsquo; immediate influence, and how to react when they shift their attention to them. For this Old School game, a further difference will be that I&amp;rsquo;m not particularly interested in pushing on issues of character (&amp;ldquo;man, this really threatens his core beliefs, let&amp;rsquo;s see how they hold up!&amp;quot;) and more interested in pushing on resources, strategic and tactical decisions, and exploration (&amp;ldquo;man, this really threatens that keep they&amp;rsquo;re building as their new headquarters, let&amp;rsquo;s see how they deal with it!&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;m running into in applying these ideas now is that they tend to treat maps as things that should be flexible and vague, whereas there is a lot of Old School value in the map being a key part of the game, with locations just as if not more important than whoever happens to be there right now. Tying threats to locations limits some of their flexibility in responding to player actions, but I feel like without developing theme as a goal, location may provide the answer to &amp;ldquo;when to push this thing instead of that other thing.&amp;rdquo; And it is because of this desire to link place strongly to play that I put forward last time the idea of &amp;ldquo;nega-steadings&amp;rdquo; for dangerous places like lairs and ruins. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time last week to sit down and actually put those ideas to use, but I&amp;rsquo;m hopeful that I&amp;rsquo;ll the time this week, and so hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll have something more like a finished idea in a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Some Challenges in Judgement</title>
        <link>/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/ -&lt;p&gt;So, I wanted to separate these thoughts from the recap post, as I intend to keep those almost entirely descriptive of the fiction that works out in the game, rather than the rules and inter-player interactions, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see what works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After accepting a player&amp;rsquo;s more reasonable interpretation of how Sleep affected a group with mixed hit dice, I was faced with the situation where the party got the drop on a lone, as yet unarmed, surprised 3rd level fighting man with a boat load of hit points (here&amp;rsquo;s me realizing some of the dangers of incorporating unmodified AD&amp;amp;D module encounters into my OD&amp;amp;D game). Now, the problem here was the fact that by the combat rules, this guy probably could have eaten a round of attacks from the whole party and their hirelings, especially because he was wearing plate, and then proceeded to cause horrendous casualties while they tried to wear him down.  On the other hand, by my judgement of what was happening in the fiction, you had one tough and skilled guy looking more than a dozen armed folks with weapons to his throat, and he had no idea how tough or skilled they might be (other than suspecting that they were responsible for killing two thirds of his compatriots in prior encounters).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to go with the judgement more related to the fiction and play his actions as a man at sword point (though I was careful to watch for the players getting lax in their treatment of their dangerous prisoners). I found myself a little bit worried that one sleep spell &amp;ldquo;undid&amp;rdquo; a difficult encounter, but then I reminded myself of a few things: one, the party has had a couple of dangerous, costly fights with these guys and gotten relatively little treasure to show for it so far, two, that encounters don&amp;rsquo;t always mean fights, a point I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to convey, and three, that my role is not to set difficulty but to create a setting and situation and then adjudicate what happens from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even though it goes against some of my instincts of what the referee/game master is supposed to be about, I think I made the right call. On the other hand, I feel like I may have had the character roll over and be cooperative too easily, even if he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to fight. Oh well, we&amp;rsquo;ll see how it goes in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 