<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/tags/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>KHS Series Part 1: Bringing In New Knowledge</title>
      <link>/thinking/2020-08-06-khs_1-bringing_in_new_knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/thinking/2020-08-06-khs_1-bringing_in_new_knowledge/</guid>
      <description>KHS Series Part 1: Bringing In New Knowledge Opening This is all about input By definition, to learn, you have to find stuff you don&amp;rsquo;t already know. This post is all about that step. Clearly that&amp;rsquo;s not all there is to learning, but it lays the groundwork for the other steps we&amp;rsquo;ll talk about in this series. For me, the main thing to keep in mind for input is &amp;ldquo;Garbage In, Garbage Out&amp;rdquo; - if you don&amp;rsquo;t start with worthwhile stuff, you won&amp;rsquo;t learn deep, meaningful things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Knowledge Handling Set Up - Part 0 - Introduction</title>
      <link>/thinking/2020-05-26-khs_series_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/thinking/2020-05-26-khs_series_intro/</guid>
      <description>Intro Today I&amp;rsquo;m kicking off a series on building a Knowledge Handling Set Up (KHS). There are many tools, frameworks, and ways of working out there for learning and holding onto knowledge, and it can be hard to fit them together into a whole that works for you, what I call a KHS.
This series is a bit unlike some of my others, in that I&amp;rsquo;ll be working it it out as I go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Level Up Your Process to Learn Better, Faster (Learning Overview Part 1)</title>
      <link>/coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few months, I’ve put some time into improving how I learn, and I’d like to share some of that in a series on “metalearning” (learning how to learn). While there are many things I want to cover, from mental models to specific tools, the underlying logic will be to look at learning as a process. Taking a process focus has several benefits - let’s walk through some of the biggest to kick off this series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Expanded Definition of Reading</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/</guid>
      <description>We tend to think of “reading” as the time we have a book in front of our face, but when you stop to ask why you are reading, a number of other activities suggest themselves as part of the bigger enterprise. If you are reading to learn, simply passing your eyes over the words will only get you a fraction of what’s there. I’ve been spending a lot of time thinking about how to make reading as effective as possible, and below I share my current thinking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Through Storytelling</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>Stories are not only a great way to communicate information, they are also a powerful tool for learning it. People remember information better when it comes in the form of a story. In fact, we are so good at putting stuff together into stories that we often get things wrong with it. Fortunately, you can take advantage of our natural tendencies to learn better. Besides making your process more fun, there are three main ways stories can help you learn: forcing careful thought, assisting recall, and providing deliberate practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Depth Before Breadth - Why You Should Learn One Thing at a Time</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</guid>
      <description>Many of us have a hard time limiting our effort to one field at a time - there’s so much interesting stuff out there and it’s more available than ever. All of this stuff can lure us into paying hidden costs when we try to learn everything all at once - costs that prevent us from getting the benefits breadth is supposed to bring. On the other hand, if you pursue depth, while you will only focus on one field at a time before moving onto the next, you will get much more out of each field, with a more robust breadth down the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Dunning-Kruger Effect for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</guid>
      <description>We all labor under a whole pile of cognitive biases day to day, but let’s talk about an especially pernicious one: the Dunning-Kruger effect. This extremely subtle bias afflicts us all, affecting our very ability to assess whether we are suffering from a bias or not. So it’s super important to be aware of it and take appropriate counter measures.
David Dunning and Justin Kruger have experimentally documented the long recognized tendency of people to suffer from “illusory superiority,” and so have had the effect named after them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling as Thinking</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-12-4-journaling-as-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-12-4-journaling-as-thinking/</guid>
      <description>Journaling doesn’t just mean recording your life for when you become super famous, you can accomplish a lot of different things by journaling. Sure, you absolutely can create a record for yourself and your family (and future biographers). You might instead want to get the neurotic and depressed thoughts out of your head and onto paper so that you can get on with business. Or perhaps you want to reinforce habits, like being grateful or generating ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some of the Things I Learned in 2017</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-2-some-of-the-things-i-learned-in-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-2-some-of-the-things-i-learned-in-2017/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important habits I have been building over the past couple years has been to be more deliberate in my reflection. So I wanted to close out this year with an inventory of what I’ve learned, both to solidify it and to figure out where I might spend my efforts next year. To figure out how to structure such a list, I turned to my daily practice modeled on the one suggested by James Altucher, but with a few additions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 70/20/10 Model for Skill Development</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-05-5-the-702010-model-for-skill-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-05-5-the-702010-model-for-skill-development/</guid>
      <description>If you spend any time around corporate learning and development types, you will likely run into the “70/20/10 Rule”. Today we’re going to talk about what it is and what it isn’t, some important cautions in making use of it, why it can be a useful heuristic, and what each component of the ratio is and how it applies to learning valuable skills. If you’re not familiar, I hope you find it a new and useful tool, and if you are, I hope to shed some new light on the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned at Forefront 2017</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-10-6-what-i-learned-at-forefront-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-10-6-what-i-learned-at-forefront-2017/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I attended a conference called Forefront in Chicago, and I had a great time. I met a ton of great people and learned a lot. So, I wanted to record what I learned here, both so that I could keep it fresh, and also to share some of the great material with a wider audience. I learned how great it is to connect with people that are weird the same way you are, how to be happier, how better to hold myself and my clients accountable, and the value of belonging to a supportive community when trying to accomplish anything challenging.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>