<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 13:17:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Smash it up, Smash it up!</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 03:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/ -&lt;p&gt;So, a recent trend I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading about at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.story-games.com&#34;&gt;cool kid&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com&#34;&gt;forums&lt;/a&gt; is a sort of game where you say &amp;ldquo;need book X to play&amp;rdquo;. Basically people put out more or less detailed conversion notes for using one set of rules with material from another game (whether just the fluff or some of the actual rules). Shadowrun is a popular target, as it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty universally loved world, with a pretty poorly regarded system. Another popular thing is to take Old Skool D&amp;amp;D and mash it up with a more modern rulesset, like the upcoming &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com/apocalypse/&#34;&gt;Apocalypse World&lt;/a&gt; (that one dubbed &amp;ldquo;Apocalypse D&amp;amp;D&amp;rdquo;). Basically, this notion excites me, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been discovering recently that a) a lot of the rules I&amp;rsquo;ve &amp;ldquo;grown up with&amp;rdquo; are pretty dumb, but b) I still love the worlds that they&amp;rsquo;re made for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, right now I&amp;rsquo;ve got two main ideas for my own approach to this trend. The first one involves an old favorite and a new discovery: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ninjaburger.com/&#34;&gt;Ninja Burger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.memento-mori.com/inspectres/&#34;&gt;InSpectres&lt;/a&gt;. For those that don&amp;rsquo;t know, Ninja Burger is a wacky little game available as an RPG or a card game by Steve Jackson games that revolves around, well, Ninjas delivering hamburgers. Anywhere. Anytime. In 30 minutes or less, or we commit suppuku! Inspectres is a Ghostbusters flavored game that uses both wacky paranormal activity and start up company stereotypes to good and humorous effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up the Ninja Burger RPG rules and gave them a read through, and, well, I was less than thrilled. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had a chance to play them, so maybe they&amp;rsquo;re more fun than they look, or maybe right now I just have too much of a bug up my ass about hippy-dippy new fangled games, but reading through them they seemed to be rules for serious simulation of fighting and infiltration and such for a supremely silly game. They don&amp;rsquo;t seem to fit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Inspectres has a franchise and mission based structure, good but flexible rules that support humor, and very little &amp;lsquo;overhead&amp;rsquo; or prep for running it. So I was struck by the idea of running Ninja Burger with the Inspectres rules. I&amp;rsquo;m going to make sure it&amp;rsquo;s okay to post such a conversion from the publishers before I pursue it too far, though. But it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;d love to play sometime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other idea I have is to run a dark horror/madness type game (like Call of Cthulhu or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fantasyflightgames.com/edge_minisite.asp?eidm=50&amp;amp;enmi=Dark%20Heresy&#34;&gt;Dark Heresy&lt;/a&gt;) using the Otherkind Dice rules I posted below. Dark Heresy has loads of evocative source material, and I think does an excellent job of expanding the 40k universe into its dark corners and really playing up the madness and horror of confronting Chaos and demons and aliens and what not. But the rules do a few things I don&amp;rsquo;t like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, percentile systems rub me the wrong way for some reason. Sure, they&amp;rsquo;re imminently logical, and easy to tune, but they just seem so dry and boring. Secondly, your goal is to roll under your score (which makes sense), and rolling low to do well just strikes me as counter-intuitive. That&amp;rsquo;s mostly silly, but still real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More seriously, the game is, well, super crunchy. It has very detailed stats and combat systems and you keep track of your rounds of ammunition and take a half action to reload and yadda yadda yadda. If I want tactical combat in the 40k universe with characters I care about, I&amp;rsquo;ll play Necromunda! (or the alternate rules I&amp;rsquo;m working on that allow more &amp;lsquo;roleplaying&amp;rsquo; like elements). I feel like all of that stuff will tend to detract from the focus on investigation and horror and madness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So right now I&amp;rsquo;m debating between two ways to make the Otherkind system work with such a setting. I have some reservations, fearing that perhaps the inherent control of the narrative that this system gives players will take away from some of the horror, but I do like how &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; story focused it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the two ways. One would be to allow &amp;ldquo;dangers&amp;rdquo; that you risk with a roll to be discrete things like a phobia or &amp;ldquo;going insane&amp;rdquo; or whatever. Unfortunately, this would take away the &amp;ldquo;death spiral&amp;rdquo; that you get with lowering insanity making your more likely to lose sanity, and it might take away the gradual erosion of sanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other way would be to just import the sanity/corruption tracks from those games and their effects, and make it a &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; associated with rolls to lose X number of points. The main downside here is that you lose the feedback from the sanity/corruption points into the main rules, since the resolution mechanic would still function separately from these things. One of the cool things in Call of Cthulhu is that the more &amp;ldquo;Cthulhu Mythos&amp;rdquo; you know, the less sane you are, but the more effective at battling monsters. So there&amp;rsquo;s an incentive to do stuff that drives your character mad. One feature/issue of Otherkind dice is that &amp;ldquo;character effectiveness&amp;rdquo; can&amp;rsquo;t really be reflected manually, at least not with any degree of precision (basically you either get to roll an extra die or you don&amp;rsquo;t).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, my goal with any sort of mash up like this is to find a set of rules that not only don&amp;rsquo;t get in the way of the world you&amp;rsquo;re playing in, but actually expose new things about it and make it more fun to play. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty confident InSpectres will do that for Ninja Burger, less so for Otherkind dice playing CoC or Dark Heresy.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Quick Playtest Update</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 11:41:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/ -&lt;p&gt;So, the online playtest has kicked off and been going strong for a little over a week, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d give a progress report. We&amp;rsquo;re still in the clan creation phase, but it&amp;rsquo;s working out well. I was afraid that the online format might kill some of the collaborative goodness of the group setting crafting, but so far we&amp;rsquo;ve had lots of that nonetheless, which is really encouraging. Everybody&amp;rsquo;s different ideas are inspiring and spinning off everybody else&amp;rsquo;s, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be happier so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, Google Wave is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; useful for online RPGs. I&amp;rsquo;m totally sold. In addition to running this playtest, I&amp;rsquo;m playing in a friend&amp;rsquo;s Big Eyes Small Mouth game, and it&amp;rsquo;s going along swimmingly, even with jumping right into a combat scene. It tailors nicely to a variety of time frames for update availability, and easily supports people jumping in with contributions to different portions (the &amp;lsquo;nested reply&amp;rsquo; option, which allows you to reply directly to a specific message in a wave, is particularly good for this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some more experience with both games, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably post my thoughts on using Wave for online games, with some recommendations and such like, but for now, I say go for it if you have any desire to play traditional RPGs online.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Quick Update</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-19-a-quick-update/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2010 03:38:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-19-a-quick-update/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-19-a-quick-update/ -&lt;p&gt;So, the &amp;ldquo;Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; playtest is getting rolling, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty excited about the opportunities Google Wave is offering for online pencil and paper roleplaying. But since it hasn&amp;rsquo;t gotten very far yet, no commentary so far on the game, and my energies towards it are more focused on getting this game running than on doing more tweaking until I see where it&amp;rsquo;s going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I have still been thinking about this whole starter RPG concept, and right now I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards a core resolution that looks a lot like the &amp;ldquo;Otherkind Dice&amp;rdquo; I talked about a few posts back, with the inclusion of something similar to the &amp;ldquo;Secrets&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Keys&amp;rdquo; seen in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.onesevendesign.com/ladyblackbird/&#34;&gt;Lady Blackbird&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://tsoy.crngames.com/&#34;&gt;The Shadow of Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;. But I want to go a little different than that, otherwise I&amp;rsquo;d really be better off just running Lady Blackbird straight, I think. The key is that I want the rules to be darn simple, but still evocative. So, I&amp;rsquo;m tossing that stuff around. Let me know if you have thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-19-a-quick-update/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Online Playtest</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2010 08:38:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/ -&lt;p&gt;So, with the revised conflict resolution rules settled as a starting point, I think it&amp;rsquo;s time to take the leap and start playtesting. But my current environment is barren not only in water, but also gamers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m going to give Google Wave a try for an online playtest of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in participating, comment here or email me, and I&amp;rsquo;ll set you up with a Wave account invite. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to get the clan and character creation process kicked off sometime next week, depending on how quickly I can get together 4 or 5 folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about what would be involved, how the online thing would work, or whatever, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Revised Conflict Resolution</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2010 08:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/ -&lt;p&gt;Well, after thinking about the issues raised in Conflict Resolution Conflict, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to what I think is a workable starting point for moving forward with the core resolution rules for &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to go with letting both sides put forward a set number of dice, and for that number to be equal to the leader&amp;rsquo;s current Wealth score. This gives wealth something to do as a static value, and ties it directly into conflict resolution, so now all three resources have something to do in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the revised conflict resolution rules here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/conflict-resolution-2.doc&#34;&gt;Revised Conflict Resolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ed:&lt;/strong&gt; the main playtest document now contains this updated section in place of the old one. It was crap anyway. But I&amp;rsquo;ve left this separate document up for easier reference of the first major change since posting the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Ragonarok!</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-12-ragonarok/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2010 03:55:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-12-ragonarok/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-12-ragonarok/ -&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s done! I wrote a quick little hack for &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agon-rpg.com&#34;&gt;Agon&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; to play in a Norse flavor called &amp;ldquo;Ragonarok&amp;rdquo; (see what I did there?). The rules changes are available as text here on the blog or as part of a PDF that includes custom character and reference sheets, and a pretty neat little picture of Odin I whipped up. Let me know what you think! Even if you haven&amp;rsquo;t played Agon, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear what you think of the layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.wordpress.com/games/ragonarok/&#34;&gt;Ragonarok Page&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/ragonarok.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;[](&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/ragonarok.pdf&#34;&gt;http://dicegods.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/ragonarok.pdf&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-12-ragonarok/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Otherkind Dice</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-10-otherkind-dice/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 11:02:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-10-otherkind-dice/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-10-otherkind-dice/ -&lt;p&gt;Okay, all my thinking about conflict resolution in the prior post is, as I said, tied into reading about really cool conflict resolution systems that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; require addressing the fiction and &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; push the players into directions they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have taken their character themselves, but in a satisfying way. One dirt simple but totally awesome way of doing that is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com/archive/148.html&#34;&gt;Otherkind Dice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link above is really short, it takes like 2 minutes to read, and if you don&amp;rsquo;t check them out, the rest of this entry will be pretty vague and possibly confusing. Just a caveat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So anyhow, these rules are really cool. I dig them a lot, and I&amp;rsquo;d love to use them at some point. But I don&amp;rsquo;t think they&amp;rsquo;re necessarily right for &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; for a couple reasons. First of all, they don&amp;rsquo;t emphasize teamwork or leaders/allies at all, which is a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; part of TBoT, obviously. Secondly, I want the game rules to reflect somewhat the &amp;lsquo;sort&amp;rsquo; of character you have. I didn&amp;rsquo;t go for an out and out description of everything your character is or can attempt to accomplish, as with more traditional games like D&amp;amp;D, because, frankly, if it makes sense at all and would be cool, I want you to be able to give it a shot. But I did want the rules to reflect whether you have a smart guy, a buff guy, or a spirited guy (or whatever) to a degree, not for that to be &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; decided moment to moment during play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about what makes them awesome, with an eye towards how that can influence my designs (&amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; and whatever else). First off, they&amp;rsquo;re wicked simple. You can play an exciting and engaging RPG with 3d6, some friends, and some imagination. Next, they give the player a lot of control over what shape the narrative takes, but without just being &amp;lsquo;say what you want to happen&amp;rsquo;. Within that control are some interesting decisions to make. This gets right to my pet concept of &amp;lsquo;opportunity cost&amp;rsquo;. Sure, you have the chance to just out and out get what you want the way you want (as you should have a chance of doing), but when the dice don&amp;rsquo;t come up perfect, you have to make tough choices about what&amp;rsquo;s really important to you (and your character). This is the joy of tactical decision making married to character/story-focused play! Hurrah! Also, by separating accomplishment of the action and suffering negative consequences for it, you get a much more interesting range of accomplishment than just success/failure. You get everything from &amp;lsquo;you fail and it sucks a lot&amp;rsquo; to &amp;lsquo;you succeed and its awesome&amp;rsquo;, but most importantly, you get the in-between stuff of &amp;lsquo;you fail but don&amp;rsquo;t get messed up&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;you succeed but pay for it&amp;rsquo; with some degrees of separation there too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an awesome example of elegance in design. You have a simple, easy mechanic that produces complex, fun results. I would love to bring this quality to my designs. I&amp;rsquo;m currently pondering how this and some other resolution mechanics can color my ideas for the rules I&amp;rsquo;ve written. There might be some big changes coming, but I&amp;rsquo;m at a wall right now. Play would probably suggest some good ways to go.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-10-otherkind-dice/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Return of Conflict Resolution</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 10:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/ -&lt;p&gt;So, in an earlier post I talked about some sticking points with conflict resolution as it currently stands in &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m having some more fundamental questions about the system than just the number of dice that should be put forward by participants in a round. I&amp;rsquo;m wondering how much the current conflict resolution rules contribute to what I want the game to be and how players will actually, you know, play the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a couple concerns in this area, which I want to discuss, and then I&amp;rsquo;m going to outline what I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; like about the rules as they stand. I would love to get comments both on the rules as written, and any suggestions for ways to better achieve my aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, first off, &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; is supposed to be about creating story. That is the main goal of the rules. I don&amp;rsquo;t want a tactical game that might happen to produce story, or a simulation of fictional physics that also might happen to come up with stories. If you play the rules as written, you should get fun, compelling stories that hit issues the players are interested in and put their characters into situations that provoke thought and emotional response from the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word about what I mean when I say &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; since it is a marvelously vague word. I don&amp;rsquo;t just mean &amp;ldquo;a sequence of events logically connected&amp;rdquo;, nor do I mean something that can or necessarily should be transcribed into fiction. There&amp;rsquo;s no point in trying to out-fiction fiction with a game. Any player could just write a short story or a novel to scratch that particular itch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discuss what I mean by &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; in the &amp;ldquo;Running the Game&amp;rdquo; chapter (which I&amp;rsquo;m afraid might be a horrible mess right now). I&amp;rsquo;m using a theory of story from Lajos Egri via various game designers, primarily Ron Edwards (Sorceror, Trollbabe, and more) and Vincent Baker (Dogs in the Vineyard, In a Wicked Age, Poison&amp;rsquo;d, et cetera). As defined by these guys, story has three elements: fit characters, dynamic situations, and premise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fit characters are characters that can and will cope with the situations they come into in ways that address the premise. It&amp;rsquo;s not much of a story to have a peasant wander around and get stomped on by a dragon. A peasant trying to fight a dragon, discovering he&amp;rsquo;s in no way fit to do that, then pursuing various goals to become able to fight that dragon, though, would be a story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic situations are situations that by their nature have to change. They&amp;rsquo;re not stable. When the characters are introduced to them, they will have to make choices and/or come into conflict. The peasant knowing there&amp;rsquo;s a dragon out there somewhere isn&amp;rsquo;t a dynamic situation, necessarily. Learning that the dragon is working his way from village to village towards the peasant&amp;rsquo;s home village probably would be, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you have premise, which ties the other two together and gives them their meaning. In the sense I&amp;rsquo;m using it here, premise is the parent of theme. Theme is what you get when premise is addressed. So, if a theme is a statement of some sort of judgement or value (like, say, &amp;ldquo;ordinary people will do extraordinary things in the face of great danger&amp;rdquo;), a premise is a pointed question that leads to such statements (&amp;ldquo;what will ordinary people do when faced with great danger?&amp;quot;). Theme is what you want to work with in a solo work, cos you make all the decisions that will illustrate that theme. In a collaborative work like an RPG, though, part of the fun is not knowing for sure what conclusions you will come to about the story your characters are involved in. But you can select a premise that forces you and your characters to drive towards some kind of answer. As an example, in &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; the premise encouraged by the rules is &amp;ldquo;when is violence an appropriate solution to moral issues?&amp;quot;, and the whole game is set up to put the characters in situations where they can do violence to try to sort out moral issues, but to throw up complications that make that question interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I went through this little overview here to frame my current concerns about the game. I wrote the rules with the intention of pushing the characters (the creation of which should make them fit) to come up with difficult questions (premises) regarding loyalty, duty, and friendship, and to strongly encourage the GM and players to put them into difficult spots that require making tough choices (dynamic situation). I pulled a lot of what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from reading some really impressive games together to try to arrive at these goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, though, as I mentioned above, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid that the conflict resolution rules as such don&amp;rsquo;t push these goals specifically enough. I like the way that oaths, grudges, and loyalty points give incentives to work with other people, and how the personal interests, family interests, and clan interests create unstable situations that generate conflict, and how the acquisition of glory points is an incentive to get into trouble with other people. But as for the actual conflict resolution rules, do they do enough to force you to make difficult choices and to be used to address the kind of conflicts that the other rules encourage. The tension between getting what you want and risking injury is good, I think, but I worry that the conflict rules themselves are just something that are there because I felt like I should have them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I don&amp;rsquo;t want the rules just to be something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t get in the way of fun, exciting play, but rather something that &lt;em&gt;creates&lt;/em&gt; fun, exciting play. I want them to push the players in directions they might not go on their own, because if they don&amp;rsquo;t, you might as well just be doing group improv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to this is an issue that Vincent Baker talks about a lot on his blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com&#34;&gt;anyway&lt;/a&gt; a lot, which is the rules meaningfully addressing the shared fiction of the game. The canonical example is &amp;ldquo;+1 bonus for height advantage&amp;rdquo;. The only way this rule makes any sense at all is if the players around the table have a clear picture in their head which characters could be said to be &amp;lsquo;on the high ground&amp;rsquo;, which you only really get when everybody is communicating and paying attention. In this instance, the fictional situation that everybody is imagining actually has bearing on the game rules, rather than it only going the other way (you rolled a 19, so that orc just got hit with your sword).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worry that my rules as written don&amp;rsquo;t do enough to reinforce a connection with the in-game fiction. Sure, the traits are supposed to be used based on how your character is doing something, and abilities based on what specifically he&amp;rsquo;s doing, but if a player can just go &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll use D8s since I want to get glory vs his D12s, and my ability &amp;lsquo;Expert Swordsman&amp;rsquo; because it has the highest rating&amp;rdquo; and then just roll the dice and not pay attention to what the actions in the fiction are, then I haven&amp;rsquo;t done my job. The rule that each rounds described events are decided and done at the end of the round is an attempt to force the players to have some idea of what&amp;rsquo;s going on fictionally before rolling into the next round, but a rule that just says &amp;ldquo;do this&amp;rdquo; without anything else depending on you doing it isn&amp;rsquo;t very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you take a look at the rules, or already have done so, I would like to hear back two main points: do the conflict resolution rules as written (or with tweaks major or minor) a) contribute to addressing premise and otherwise creating an engaging story, and b) require the players to be paying attention to the fictional environment and actions of the characters? If not, please tell me why so I can fix them!&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Conflict Resolution</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2010 09:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/ -&lt;p&gt;Okay, so, I&amp;rsquo;ve been posting some stuff about the game over at this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com/forum/index.php?topic=29764.0&#34;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; on the Forge, both to try to target some hard-core design oriented folks and to draw traffic towards the blog and game :) At any rate, a commenter over there pointed out a glaring deficiency with the conflict resolution rules as written, and then proposed a great solution for one part of it, and some potential solutions for the other, that I wanted to hash out here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so first off, the easy part. It was brought to my attention that the &amp;lsquo;aggressor&amp;rsquo; despite his name, actually usually gets little to do in the conflict, and has little effect on the direction of the conflict unless his roll is super good. Which is lame. So, I probably need to change the whole &amp;lsquo;only put forward your highest die&amp;rsquo; thing. That&amp;rsquo;s the hard part I&amp;rsquo;m gonna get onto next. But whatever change I make to that, there&amp;rsquo;s a simpler and I think better way to handle &amp;lsquo;the aggressor&amp;rsquo;. Usually, a conflict is gonna have one party or another who says &amp;ldquo;okay, let&amp;rsquo;s do this! No more pussy footing around, I want to force the issue!&amp;rdquo; That guy&amp;rsquo;s gonna be the aggressor. I might need to put in something for if two guys both simultaneously say they want to go for it, but I think that&amp;rsquo;s gonna be pretty rare. So the aggressor is whoever initiates the conflict in round one, and thereafter whoever scores a partial success is the aggressor in the next round. Easy, and it makes sense. It also keeps the &amp;lsquo;back and forth&amp;rsquo; feel I wanted to get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the hard part. So, as alluded to above, right now it sucks to be the aggressor. Rolling the highest die, especially against an opponent with a dice pool of any size, makes it really easy to get hosed. So, I think the aggressor needs to have the option to a) put forward more than 1 die, and b) decide which dice go out there. I don&amp;rsquo;t want it to just be &amp;lsquo;as many dice as you want&amp;rsquo; as it currently is with the responder, because then an aggressor with larger dice can just decide the contest in round one by putting forward gobs of high dice. I also think that the current responder rules prioritize super committing in round one to get a decisive outcome, rather than the tactical use of dice over multiple rounds like I want to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I see three (heh) options here right now. I would love to hear more if y&amp;rsquo;all have some suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, assign an arbitrary value of dice you can use per round (3 is
tempting)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, you can assign 1 die per person on your side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third, some value based on a characteristic. I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards
your current &amp;lsquo;wealth&amp;rsquo; value to give it some in-game use as a static
value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, with the arbitrary value, this muzzles large groups somewhat, and I think would give more power to larger dice size than currently exists (3d12 are usually going to be higher than 3d8). This might fit the &amp;lsquo;uphill fight&amp;rsquo; against stronger traits that I want to have, but it also might make using lower traits darn near impossible to actually gain anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With 1 die per person, we have the opposite effect. Larger groups of minimally skilled guys become more effective than small groups of skilled guys. Which might be okay, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know. It would also mess with my &amp;lsquo;minion&amp;rsquo; rules where you just have a named NPC and his goons represented as &amp;lsquo;an ability&amp;rsquo;. It would, however, emphasize the role of allies somewhat more, which is a core concept for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, with a characteristic, this adds a bit more &amp;lsquo;crunch&amp;rsquo; to the character traits/resources/abilities/whatever. Loyalty and glory both have something to do in conflicts, and I kind of wanted Wealth to have a more direct effect than just buying abilities. This would also give your wealth sitting there on your sheet something to do besides bribe other characters and save up for ability purchasing at the end of the chapter. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really have any flavor justification at all (all of the armbands and rings I have make me super effective!) but from a resource-interaction standpoint, it has some appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, d4s might just be totally worthless. That same commenter pointed out that a d4 is half a d8, but a d8 is two thirds of a d12, so there&amp;rsquo;s an uneven spread there. On the other hand, d6 might be too close. Curse you Euclidean space for not allowing a d9!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I end this post with a question: which method makes sense to you? Or do you have a better suggestion?&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Do the Wave</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-07-do-wave/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2010 11:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-07-do-wave/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-07-do-wave/ -&lt;p&gt;So, in a comment to a previous entry, Joon Phil mentioned this &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2009/10/google-wave-we-came-we-saw-we-played-dd.ars&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;. It highlights the uses of Google Wave as an online roleplaying venue. I&amp;rsquo;ve applied for an invitation to start using wave, because I want to check it out. If anyone else is interested, you can request an invite &lt;a href=&#34;http://wave.google.com/help/wave/closed.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m considering using it to playtest &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; down the road a bit, and I&amp;rsquo;m always hungry for as much roleplaying as I can get my hands on, so I think this might help.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-07-do-wave/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Name Day</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 04:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/ -&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s decided!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to go ahead and go with Tyler&amp;rsquo;s suggestion of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; until it dies or I find a better one. So feel free to throw down with any suggestions or to tell me that&amp;rsquo;s crap, but &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; is the new working title.   Beats the Annuvin out of &amp;ldquo;Celto-Germania&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>These are Neat</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-05-these-are-neat/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 07:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-05-these-are-neat/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-05-these-are-neat/ -&lt;p&gt;Okay, real quick post here. I just added &lt;a href=&#34;http://mightyatom.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;The Mighty Atom&lt;/a&gt; to my blogroll. It&amp;rsquo;s the blog for John Harper, author of that Agon game I reviewed earlier. His blog has some good posts on gaming, but what I want to point out here are the games in the left side bar. In addition to Agon, which you can buy as a PDF or regular book (and I highly recommend you do), you can also get three quick, clever little games for free. That&amp;rsquo;s right, free. They&amp;rsquo;re called &amp;ldquo;Lady Blackbird&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Ghost/Echo&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;The Mustang&amp;rdquo; in descending order of complexity (and &amp;ldquo;Lady Blackbird Weighs in at a hefty 16 pages, 13 of which are character sheets).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind all of these is that they give you a very specific starting scenario, very simple rules, and more or less pre-defined characters and you go with it, and they go in cool directions. The very brevity is inspiring, and the elegance is pretty neat. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to give them a try, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about them pretty intently since I read them last night. Check em out!&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-05-these-are-neat/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Insert Title Here</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 11:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/ -&lt;p&gt;No really, this post is about titles :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as mentioned before, I have no idea what to name this bad boy as yet. I&amp;rsquo;ve been engaging in some correspondence with my friend Tyler who&amp;rsquo;s pointed me in some good directions, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share the stuff that&amp;rsquo;s working for me, and see if anyone else can take it in a better direction than I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my goals for the title are for it to be simple and evocative of the milieu, without locking in any really specific flavor elements (so, while &amp;ldquo;The Crow Father&amp;rsquo;s Children&amp;rdquo; has a cool ring to it, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to lock in the Crow Father as one of the gods your group has to use or assume is real). Likewise &amp;ldquo;In the House of Winter&amp;rdquo; sounds awesome, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much to do with the game as it stands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &amp;ldquo;list&amp;rdquo; sort of name, particularly one that features three elements (if you hadn&amp;rsquo;t noticed &amp;ldquo;three&amp;rdquo; is a theme throughout the rules) might be good. Something like &amp;ldquo;Bronze, Bone, and Birch&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Oak and Bronze, Ash and Iron&amp;rdquo;. Especially since lists feature so prominently in the clan creation rules. If I could come up with better names for &amp;ldquo;Loyalty, Wealth, and Glory&amp;rdquo; then those would be prime candidates for the title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep wanting to steal the name &amp;ldquo;The Book of Three&amp;rdquo; from Lloyd Alexander&amp;rsquo;s Chronicles of Prydain, but that might be too obvious/stealing-y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, thoughts on names?&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Initial Design Thoughts</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 04:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/ -&lt;p&gt;So, I wanted to keep these thoughts separate from the announcement post so that it didn&amp;rsquo;t get overwhelmed with the information here. I just wanted to lay out a few of the thoughts I had while designing the rules, with the hope that this will open up more avenues of approach for improving the rules (like &amp;ldquo;you wanted this rule to do &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;? You&amp;rsquo;re way off base!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, the ideas that got me going on this game were notions of conflicting loyalties, and the idea of loyalty impairing your ability to act independently. I wanted to create a game where your character was likely to be torn between a variety of groups (family, friends, associations, himself) on how to act. But I also wanted to leave all the actual decisions in the hands of the player (so no &amp;ldquo;if you fail this roll you have to do what your family says!) so I tried to set up a system of incentives to act in various ways. I think the &amp;lsquo;three resources&amp;rsquo; are more the core of the game than the resolution rules themselves, but I tried to get them to interact in interesting ways, giving each resource something to do with conflict resolution, as well as a way to gain them through conflicts. The one thing I didn&amp;rsquo;t quite achieve was tying each of the three resources directly into relationships with the clans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the three resources, my guiding principle there was opportunity cost. I wanted every resource to have multiple viable uses and compelling alternatives, so that it&amp;rsquo;s painful to miss out on one for another, but not so painful that you get paralyzed. Since they haven&amp;rsquo;t been playtested yet, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I achieved that or not!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also pretty pleased conceptually with Oaths and Grudges, but they might be super broken. Guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conflict resolution rules are essentially a mishmash of every game by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com&#34;&gt;Vincent Baker&lt;/a&gt;. I tried to make them distinct, but his thinking on what conflict resolution is and how it should be handled was super super influential on my design. Even still, in my desire not to outright copy him, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid  I created something awkward and inelegant. I have a feeling the core resolution is going to change a lot in playtesting (it usually does, if my wargames design experience is any indicator).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another area where I was influenced by Mr. Baker and others was in concepts of player ownership of the fiction. The whole notion of creating the world as a group and as you go was stolen wholesale from In a Wicked Age (I was &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; close to straight up using an oracle system), and the extensive use of lists was another Bakerism. Much of the clan creation rules were inspired by/stolen from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpgnow.com/product_info.php?products_id=68924&amp;amp;src=FrontPage&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sartar: Kingdom of Heroes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Greg Stafford and Jeff Richard, and the &amp;lsquo;demographics&amp;rsquo; were lifted with extremely little modification, since they jived with what I know about Anglo-Saxon society from college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I meant by &amp;lsquo;player ownership of fiction&amp;rsquo; is that in addition to everyone in the group participating in the world and the story building, I wanted to stress the collaborative nature of the game, and make explicit the way that everyone has something of a &amp;lsquo;hold&amp;rsquo; on everyone else&amp;rsquo;s character. If I say something about my character, but every other player flat out refuses to acknowledge it or accept it into the game&amp;rsquo;s fiction, then it&amp;rsquo;s not really true for the game. That&amp;rsquo;s where stuff like other players defining your family and clan interests came in (I also thought that was a quick and easy way to make sure they&amp;rsquo;re at odds with personal interests!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, interests/ambitions were another steal from &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;. The basic concept behind abilities is awful similar to how they work in Heroquest, along with the idea of &amp;ldquo;impaired&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;injured&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic rules are all mine. Once I got the conflict rules into a workable shape, the answer just suggested itself. I suspect it might be bah-roken, though, so again, playtesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of conflict resolution, that went through a whole hell of a lot of conceptual phases. At one point it was based on drawing runes instead of rolling dice! I think that would have been neat, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get the group/ally rules I wanted and figure out the probabilities. Plus, asking players to make/find some runes is probably a little much. As it is, I&amp;rsquo;m already asking for largish pools of the most uncommon die types. Take that D10, D6, and D20!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid that the current &amp;ldquo;running the game&amp;rdquo; chapter is crap. Actually running the game will probably help with this, but I tried to convey what I have in mind the rules supporting, as well as some great GMing advice I&amp;rsquo;ve been exposed to recently, but it was near the end of the writing, and my brain was turning to  mush.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you&amp;rsquo;ve read through the rules, or even run through some examples with the rules, please post your thoughts, questions, observations, et cetera here or on the&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.wordpress.com/games/celto-germania/&#34;&gt;game page&lt;/a&gt;. Also post if you have any requests for clarifications, examples to try out, or anything of the sort.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>That Will Remain Nameless at this Time</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 03:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/ -&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s here! Well, actually it&amp;rsquo;s right &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.wordpress.com/games/celto-germania/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but I mean it&amp;rsquo;s done. And by done, I mean ready  to start the process of becoming a real game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the vague &amp;ldquo;its&amp;rdquo; all over the place? Because I still don&amp;rsquo;t have a good name! I&amp;rsquo;m totally stumped. I keep trying to think of one, trying to put it out of my head hoping an answer will pop up unexpected, trying to steal other people&amp;rsquo;s good names, but none are working so far. I hoped maybe the full game would suggest a name for itself, but it remains quiet. So I&amp;rsquo;m stuck with the extremely unsatisfying working title of &amp;ldquo;Celto-Germania&amp;rdquo;, which is my vague term for the region in which my mish-mash culture would live. So, if you have suggestions for names, post them here! Next up, some design notes on what I&amp;rsquo;m up to with this game.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Tale that Grows in the Telling</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 12:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/ -&lt;p&gt;So, that first draft of the game rules I promised? It&amp;rsquo;s progressing nicely. A little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; nicely. What I intended to be a barebones mechanics document is quickly turning into the first draft of the complete rules. I just can&amp;rsquo;t stop writing!   So, new ETA for the first draft is May 1st (T minus 5 days).&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Excitement!</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2010 11:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/ -&lt;p&gt;Exciting News!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last game project that I mentioned, with the reading list? I&amp;rsquo;ve been scribbling away notes on the rules, and I&amp;rsquo;m ready to begin typing up the very rough, totally beta, untested at all draft. I would prefer to do some personal playtesting before releasing it into the wilds of the internet, but I&amp;rsquo;m not going to be in a position to do that for awhile, so I will post it for review and solicit recommendations once it&amp;rsquo;s typed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m taking this bad boy to publication, but it might take a while to get it all the way where it needs to be. Tentatively, I expect it to be ready for &amp;lsquo;real&amp;rsquo; playtesting  by other people by January, and hopefully it&amp;rsquo;ll be done and ready to publish by this time next year, at the latest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post a teaser soon, and the rules after that.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A New Direction for Now</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2010 03:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/ -&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be taking a bit of a break from my starter RPG project for two main reasons. First off, I&amp;rsquo;ve found a wealth of games I&amp;rsquo;d really enjoy to run, some of which I think would make good introductions to what roleplaying is for adult, non-gamer type people. But secondly, I still take the starter RPG notion seriously, but I realized that paradoxically, an RPG designed for beginning players should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be my first full-fledged RPG design. I should maybe know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing before I tackle that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an idea for another game that is now consuming every ounce of my game design juices (okay, a few ounces are spared for stray thoughts). I am channeling the bad shit, here. I&amp;rsquo;ve filled out a whole notebook, and I take it&amp;rsquo;s replacement everywhere I go. I wake up in the middle of the night with ideas. Talking about it at this point would probably solidify some things that are still better off nebulous as I work them together, though. That being said, as a &amp;ldquo;sneak preview&amp;rdquo;, here&amp;rsquo;s a recommended reading list for the setting/color:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(In roughly descending order of relevance)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chronicles of Prydain by Lloyd Alexander&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beowulf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Poetic and Prose Eddas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mabinogion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Iliad and Odyssey of Homer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire series by George R.R. Martin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dark is Rising by Susan Cooper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mythago Wood by Robert Holdstock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Volsunga Saga trans. by J.R.R. Tolkien&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various Irish Myths and Legends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully that gives you a pretty good idea of the &amp;lsquo;flavor&amp;rsquo; I&amp;rsquo;m going for, but I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll be pleasantly surprised by what I come up with for rules.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>What has Come Before</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-04-10-what-has-come-before/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 09:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-04-10-what-has-come-before/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-04-10-what-has-come-before/ -&lt;p&gt;So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bit quiet this past week, but not because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been thinking about game design. Actually rather the opposite. Instead, as I linked in a past post, I&amp;rsquo;ve been checking out the design theory over at &lt;a href=&#34;http://indie-rpgs.com&#34;&gt;The Forge&lt;/a&gt;, specifically the articles (still trying to wade into the forum, which is daunting) and at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com&#34;&gt;anyway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to put too fine a point on it, but this shit has blown my mind. Seriously, though, some theory that I originally met with skepticism, on full read through has totally altered how I think about RPGs, what my design goals are, and how to achieve them. I look back at what I&amp;rsquo;ve posted over the last couple months, and I&amp;rsquo;m slightly embarrassed, as it seems to be hopelessly amateurish dilettante work at its worst, trying to address issues from what I now see as a constricted and unaware viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I am currently at an awkward place. This new theory has made me look at what I was talking about and go &amp;ldquo;yuck&amp;rdquo; because it&amp;rsquo;s ground that has already been covered better and in more detail by people who&amp;rsquo;ve thought harder about it than me. On the other hand, I am not yet comfortable enough with said new theory to really address it as someone who &amp;ldquo;gets it&amp;rdquo;. I am still learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as I said, it has so fundamentally altered my perception of RPG theory and the notion of design that to try to continue without incorporating it would be stultifying and frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as a warning to anyone who&amp;rsquo;s been following along so far: from this point forward, I will be discussing RPG design theory using terms from &amp;ldquo;The Big Model&amp;rdquo; as presented in the essays by Ron Edwards on the Forge website (see especially, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com/articles/1/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;GNS and other matters of RPG Theory&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com/articles/15/&#34;&gt;Simulationism: The Right to Dream&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com/articles/21/&#34;&gt;Gamism: Step on Up&lt;/a&gt;, and&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com/_articles/narr_essay.html&#34;&gt;Narrativism: Story Now&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d recommend reading as many of the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com/articles/&#34;&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; on that website as possible, but those four are what I consider the most essential, with the first as practically required reading).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be happy to clarify any terms I use or what have you, but please understand that it will be as someone still learning - this stuff isn&amp;rsquo;t mine, I just found it thoroughly convincing. Also, if you want to debate the conclusions drawn, that&amp;rsquo;s cool too, but bear in mind that gobs of people have done so to death on the Forge, like, 5 or 6 years ago. So, what you&amp;rsquo;re looking at when you read those articles is something that was pretty heartily discussed, challenged, and refined, and from what I can tell, has continued to be largely useful to designers since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first it may seem like annoying intellectualism or elitism or whatever, but it&amp;rsquo;s already doing wonders for my creative process, and I look forward to what the tools and methods of thought presented will help me come up with, and I hope everyone enjoys the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-04-10-what-has-come-before/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Social Contract</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-04-04-social-contract/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2010 04:09:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-04-04-social-contract/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-04-04-social-contract/ -&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk about something I touched upon in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicegods.wordpress.com/2010/03/29/in-a-wicked-age/&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of the rules of &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;social contract&amp;rdquo; of roleplaying games. This is an idea that has come up a lot in my recent reading at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com&#34;&gt;anyway&lt;/a&gt; and the articles at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indie-rpgs.com&#34;&gt;The Forge&lt;/a&gt;. This is a topic that is so obvious that it is usually ignored or taken for granted, like the sky or the ground. Basically, what I mean by &amp;ldquo;social contract&amp;rdquo; is the understanding, usually implicit, that everyone participating in an RPG has regarding what it is they&amp;rsquo;re getting together to do. The trouble with it staying implicit and taken for granted is that different people may interpret it in very different ways, and that can lead to real-life conflict and hurt feelings and the dissolution of a game group. So, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d talk about the social contract in very vague terms, and then address some specific issues. As a side note, a lot of what I&amp;rsquo;m producing here may be going over ground others have covered, or amateurish, or what have you. I&amp;rsquo;m in the process of reading up on the field of RPG design, but I&amp;rsquo;m still stuck in the late 90&amp;rsquo;s/early 00&amp;rsquo;s in terms of what I&amp;rsquo;ve been covering recently (having decided to start with the start at the afore mentioned sites, so that I&amp;rsquo;m not lost when I get to the current stuff). So, basically, be aware that I may change my mind on stuff I post up here or look back at it and be embarrassed or such, and hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll keep the same awareness and continue to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this social contract business, what is it? It is something that exists regardless of the rules system you use, but can involve the rules system directly or indirectly. For example, if everyone you know who roleplays just loves (D&amp;amp;D/Call of Cthulhu/Fuzion/Whatevs), then it might be explicit that y&amp;rsquo;all are getting together to play that particular game. Or it could be more subtle, like you&amp;rsquo;re playing D&amp;amp;D, but everybody involves just kind of knows that D&amp;amp;D as is doesn&amp;rsquo;t address what they want out of a game, so they are okay with the game master changing rules or they suggest changes and so forth. But it&amp;rsquo;s relationship to the rules system is probably not it&amp;rsquo;s most significant feature. Like I said, a lot of time the social contract is entirely implicit, and everybody ends up with slightly different ideas of what it entails in their heads, and when this happens, problems can arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s cut to an analogy for a moment, because I&amp;rsquo;m fond of analogies. In searching my imagination for an adequate analogy to the social contract of roleplaying, I realized that there&amp;rsquo;s no direct correspondence, which makes sense, I suppose, for such a specialized form of entertainment. But, being social in nature, and being associated with the use of rules, it does share similarities with some other, better known social situations. I think that roleplaying, socially speaking, is somewhere between a dance (as in, the event, like a prom, or a ball, or a hoe down, or whatever) and a sporting event. I actually think that the social contract of most RPGs differs quite markedly from board games or strategy games, despite the overlapping interest and sometimes overlapping methods. For one, most board games and strategy games of all sorts have much better defined rules that restrict what choices players can make, and everybody knows what they are going into the game. Usually, there&amp;rsquo;s very little notion that those rules can or should be bent to serve other ends, and also usually, the rules presented adequately address whatever can come up in such a game. So, let&amp;rsquo;s get back to my analogy. Like a sporting event (and like those board games and wargames mentioned), there is in fact a set of rules used to decide what can and can&amp;rsquo;t happen, and how to play and so forth. Unlike sporting events, however, it is usually less well defined what actions (by people, not characters. Remember, this whole essay is about the actual physical players participating in a game) explicitly violate what you all came there to do. In a soccer game, picking up the ball and running around knocking people over is very clearly not what everyone came there to do. That one guy may enjoy the attention, or being wild, or whatever, but everyone else will be pretty pissed off that he is preventing them from doing the activity they came together to do. In roleplaying games, there are definitely things people can do that have similar effects, but unfortunately, they&amp;rsquo;re usually less obvious, and a lot of times people put up with it thinking it&amp;rsquo;s the only way they can continue to roleplay. So if everyone is really digging on rescuing a princess from a dragon, but one dude says he hauls off and stabs the king  and runs around the court with his head knocking people over, that &lt;em&gt;player&lt;/em&gt;, by deciding his character will do that, has made it impossible for the other players to do what they came there to do, forcing them to react to his actions or bicker about whether that &amp;lsquo;could&amp;rsquo; happen or not, or stop playing. The trouble is, kingslayer there may not have realized that he was pissing in their porridge when he did that. He might have thought that going in an unexpected direction, or staying true to his wild, unpredictable character was what he was there to do, and assumed that everybody else felt like that was what he was there for too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that hockey provides an interesting example of this gray area in sporting events. FIghting technically isn&amp;rsquo;t allowed in the rules, but it&amp;rsquo;s an accepted part of the game. Everyone participating in a professional hockey game expects some fighting and has some idea what amount will be allowed by the refs, what penalties it&amp;rsquo;s okay to take for doing it, and how to use it within the context of the game. The reason I stress this is to show that in other forms of social leisure activity, there is also a distinction between the &amp;lsquo;official rules&amp;rsquo; and the socially understood guidelines for what the event will be. Now, I said that I didn&amp;rsquo;t think that sports were a perfect metaphor for roleplaying, and that&amp;rsquo;s because in sports, the relationship between what is socially agreed upon when you get together to play, and what is printed in the official rules, is usually very close. The baseline assumption for most sports is &amp;lsquo;we will show up and follow these exact rules. Not following them is cheating and will get you penalized.&amp;rsquo; So, I want to bring the other half of my analogy, a dance. Like roleplaying, dances are social events with varying levels of formality, and even at the most formal of balls, there is usually a distinct difference between the &amp;lsquo;official&amp;rsquo; purpose and guidelines for behavior and the socially understood aims and allowable behavior. Also like roleplaying games, there can be a wide range of variations in the stated aims of a dance, and different people will show up with different expectations of what&amp;rsquo;s socially acceptable (though, being more mainstream, the social contract of these events, though implicit, tends to be better understood by everyone involved). So, a prom is going to have different &amp;lsquo;rules&amp;rsquo; than a military ball, just as a hoe down will have different rules from a cotillion event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine, if you will, someone who thought that all dances were proms. He would show up to a hoe down in a tux, expect to hear a mix of nostalgic music and modern dance music, and would want to focus on dancing alone with his date. When he encountered jeans and cowboy hats, country music and fiddle playing, and complicated group dances, he would think they were doing it wrong, not have a good time, and most likely spoil it for other people there. The shame of it is that he would have a great time at a prom, he would do it right, and everyone there would enjoy, or at least tolerate, his presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what in the hell does all this talk of hockey and hoe downs have to do with roleplaying? I think that since the idea of the social expectations of a roleplaying game are so rarely discussed or thought of explicitly, you end up with the equivalent of people showing up expecting one kind of dance and getting another. But it&amp;rsquo;s usually so subtle, and even worse, a lot of times, despite a game &lt;em&gt;claiming&lt;/em&gt; to be one kind of dance, it might actually be another, that nobody realizes that&amp;rsquo;s the source of the dissatisfaction and bad feeling. Further, if you go to the prom and your best friend took the girl you wanted to bring, you and everybody else knows that&amp;rsquo;s why there&amp;rsquo;s tension between you two at the prom. But at a roleplaying game, the focus is so much on the rules and the imaginary world of the game, that people like to convince themselves that real-life interpersonal tensions don&amp;rsquo;t enter into it. So, when the two best friends go to play their weekly RPG a few days after that same prom, people might not realize, or at least not acknowledge, that the game is going poorly because there is still tension between them over a real-life social issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I make of all this? I think that it is a healthy and useful step for a roleplaying group to all &lt;em&gt;explicitly&lt;/em&gt; lay out, before play, what they&amp;rsquo;re doing and what they want to accomplish. And I think this needs to go a little deeper than &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;re here to play D&amp;amp;D, and our goal is to have fun&amp;rdquo;. I think even the densest of socially challenged folks is going to get that you&amp;rsquo;re there to play the advertised game and the overall goal is to have fun. But what makes a game fun varies from group to group and person to person, and I think an enhanced awareness of what that is will help out a lot. I&amp;rsquo;m riffing pretty hard here off of things I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading in those Forge articles. In those articles, they go into different approaches to rpgs and what sort of abstract things different people pursue and enjoy in a game, but I&amp;rsquo;m not going to go into that here. But in general terms, I think the group should make a few things clear (as in, actually talk these things out and hear everyone out on them, then come to a decision. Maybe even write it down for reference later) before they start gaming, and here are some suggestions of mine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How active does each player want to be in making deciding what dramatic things happen to their characters?   How much detail do you want to explore of the game&amp;rsquo;s setting?   How comfortable is each player with in-character conflict?   Are there any topics or issues that you are uncomfortable addressing in play?   How concerned are you with your character&amp;rsquo;s success as measured in some objective way (missions completed, xp earned, et cetera)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re playing with people new to roleplaying, they might not know the answers to some of these things, and I think a good solution is for the GM, or whoever is organizing the game (presumably with more gaming experience) to put forward as honestly and in as much detail as possible what his goals are and how he intends to address the game. So, if you are the GM, and you want your players to have a good deal of active narrative control, tell them! If you have a finely crafted world with lots of detail, and you are expecting them to want to explore it and work within it&amp;rsquo;s fictional parameters, be clear about that. If you think it&amp;rsquo;d be fun to have the players compete for who can kill the most kobolds, or gain the most levels the fastest, or survive the longest without going insane, let them know. But be prepared to listen to their reactions to these things. If everyone in your group says &amp;ldquo;whoah, I don&amp;rsquo;t care about levels and stuff, man, I want to do whatever would bring my character into the most dramatic situations for an exciting story&amp;rdquo;, then &lt;em&gt;pay attention&lt;/em&gt;. If everyone has a different idea of what would be fun, or nobody much is interested in what you&amp;rsquo;re pushing, you might need to find a new game or a new group. Finally, an important point stressed in the essays I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading about different play styles and what different people want out of their games, is that no one way is &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;more fun&amp;rdquo; objectively. It&amp;rsquo;s largely a matter of personal taste. Some people will have the most fun ever cleverly avoiding traps and slaughtering monsters to steal their treasure with no real concern for dramatic tension or addressing ethical or moral issues. Other people will really get into accurately working within a detailed feudal system and maneuvering in a complex social network of lords and families and churches. But still others might have the most fun playing characters who do nothing but come up against agonizing conflict and make decisions to set up the next agonizing conflict. All of these approaches, and more, are great and can be fun. But they&amp;rsquo;re not necessarily all compatible in the same game. So, do your best to figure out what everyone is showing up for, and try to stick with it, and your games will be a lot more fun and more likely to work well.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-04-04-social-contract/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Secret Ingredient</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-04-02-the-secret-ingredient/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 11:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-04-02-the-secret-ingredient/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-04-02-the-secret-ingredient/ -&lt;p&gt;Is love, dammit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And love I have in spades. Love of games, love of game design, love of theorizing and pontificating. But it in all seriousness, I worry that I lack a no less crucial secret ingredient for my design plans: actual play. I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through the archive at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com&#34;&gt;anyway&lt;/a&gt;, the blog of D. Vincent Baker, author of &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;, and he points out, correctly I think, that without real game play to ground your theories in, it&amp;rsquo;s all too easy to build sand castles of wonderful intricacy but no lasting substance or usefulness. I haven&amp;rsquo;t played in an actual, live on going RPG for ten years now! Ten years! Oof. I&amp;rsquo;m getting some good online play, and I&amp;rsquo;ve played in various one-off games or abortive attempts at starting up a game over the years, not since I moved away from my adolescent gaming group have I played RPGs as often as I&amp;rsquo;d like. So, what to do about this? I have in mind three potential solutions to not only enjoy my favorite hobby, but also to get the gaming experience I need to solidly frame my designs with things that actually come up in real game play. So here they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology&lt;/strong&gt;: Through the power of the vast and multifarious internets, all kinds of communication options exist that never did before. I have maintained friendships over vast distances through frequent communication, and perhaps gaming is another application of this connectivity. I am currently playing in such a game, and it&amp;rsquo;s been going smoothly and enjoyably for a good 6 months or so now. But, at least as played, it is a different creature from roleplaying at the table, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t wholly satisfy my inclinations. For one, being forum based, it takes place somewhat &amp;lsquo;in slow motion&amp;rsquo;, with GM and player interaction usually being via private messages, which are then clumped together in &amp;lsquo;scenes&amp;rsquo; posted for everyone to read. The GM is excellent, so it&amp;rsquo;s making for some creative story and character moments, but thus far there&amp;rsquo;s quite limited character/player interaction. That would be easier with scheduled &amp;lsquo;live&amp;rsquo; chats, and perhaps even better would be some sort of audio and/or video live chat. I don&amp;rsquo;t have the capability for that just now, but I will in the near future, and that might bear looking into. That being said, there&amp;rsquo;s something to gathering in one physical place, eating the same snacks, seeing each other&amp;rsquo;s faces, and shooting the breeze before and after that even the most advanced online options lack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Converts&lt;/strong&gt;: Here, my idea is to take my friends and bring them into the hobby. Obviously, this is a huge motivation for my whole &amp;lsquo;Starter RPG&amp;rsquo; project. The benefits here are pretty obvious: not only do I get to roleplay in person and increase the number of roleplayers I know, I already know that I like them and get along with them and will want to spend valuable social time with them. Unfortunately, the negatives are almost as obvious: roleplaying is not for everyone, no matter how amazing a group/game/rules/gamemaster/etc you introduce them to, many of my friends that would be interested in trying RPGs are scattered across vast geographical distances (the same issue with my friends that already do game), and even if they do find they like it, it will have to compete with all of their other social plans to become something that happens regularly. They might see it as a fun once in a while thing, but not something you spend a few hours at every week. So, I&amp;rsquo;m going to pursue this plan, but not count on making any huge strides in my mission work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Hobby&lt;/strong&gt;: Finally, I&amp;rsquo;m going to discuss what many might consider the most obvious plan, but one that I&amp;rsquo;m a bit leery of. There is a local game store where I live (better than some, but worse than others) that hosts gaming of all sorts every weekend and is generally a meeting place for hobbyists in the town. So, the plus sides are that these are people who are already invested in roleplaying and may be just as interested in a chance to game more than me, I might meet new, cool people that I otherwise would not, and those people I do find are most likely to be interested in playing regularly and perhaps even in playtesting rules of my design or such like. The down sides are a little more subtle. I&amp;rsquo;m growing curmudgeonly, and though I&amp;rsquo;ve made some great friends in my life through gaming, for some reason, at this point in my life, I&amp;rsquo;m not enthused about the idea of meeting people via gaming. I&amp;rsquo;d rather play games with people I already know and like otherwise. But alas, that&amp;rsquo;s not working out satisfactorily so far. The trouble is twofold. For one, despite my firm belief that there is nothing inherently awkward, nerdy, or weird about roleplaying, a lot of roleplayers are in fact, well, awkward, nerdy, or weird. I have a pretty high tolerance for all of these qualities, but it makes it harder to weave new friends into my existing social life and so forth. Secondly, while there are certain personality and character traits that tend to go with people who enjoy roleplaying, the single fact of a strong shared interest does not necessarily make for compatible people. Obviously, this is part of the benefit of having shared interests: it exposes you to people different from yourself and your friends, sometimes to create new friendships, but it can also lead to getting stuck with someone you don&amp;rsquo;t really want to spend time with, but you keep around because without him you won&amp;rsquo;t have a group. And that&amp;rsquo;s not a situation I&amp;rsquo;m eager to try again. All that as it is, I think I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to bite the bullet and start hanging around the game store more and try to find some new gamer buddies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does anybody have any recommendations that I&amp;rsquo;ve missed out on?&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-04-02-the-secret-ingredient/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Magic and Obligations</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-03-29-magic-and-obligations/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 10:53:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-03-29-magic-and-obligations/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-03-29-magic-and-obligations/ -&lt;p&gt;Okay, as I said last time, I&amp;rsquo;m now going to take a break from reviews for a while (I&amp;rsquo;m out of games to read, for one) and start talking about my own game. It is still fragmentary and hazy, but I&amp;rsquo;ve come to a few decisions that will help guide the process from here. First off, I think I have decided that the genre will be &amp;ldquo;sword and sorcery&amp;rdquo; in a setting of my own devising. It&amp;rsquo;s a setting I began generating as a campaign setting for Dungeons and Dragons, but I realized that I was making so many fundamental changes that it would probably benefit rather than be harmed by separating it from the venerable system. As discussed in &amp;ldquo;A Question of Genre&amp;rdquo;, I believe that a fantasy setting is fairly accessible, and it also has the benefit of being &amp;lsquo;expected&amp;rsquo; as what an RPG is about, due to the whole D&amp;amp;D thing. Also, most of the rules ideas I&amp;rsquo;ve had recently seem to mesh with a fantasy setting better than something else. That being said, I&amp;rsquo;m open to being swayed by arguments for a different milieu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I said that I&amp;rsquo;d been having rules ideas suited to a fantasy setting, I had two in mind, primarily. The first is rather vague at this point, and that is magic. I&amp;rsquo;ve always loved magic in games, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve read some very creative uses of magic in stories, and this has inspired me to want to design a new, different, and elegant magical system for my game. I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing research on various real world and fantasy traditions of magic so that whatever I come up with will have an &amp;lsquo;authentic&amp;rsquo; feel about it, but at its core, I want the system to simple and elegant, having complexity through a combination of simple factors rather than complexity through sheer exhaustiveness. What I would like to avoid is the &amp;lsquo;magic as super powers&amp;rsquo; kind of effect that seems to me to be the dominant paradigm these days. By this I mean you have mages (or sorcerors or warlocks or whatever) who are &amp;ldquo;magic&amp;rdquo; and so they can do magic things from list A) a set number of times based on the day or magic points or whatever. Sure, most games try to distinguish flavor wise between people who study arcane secrets, or those who make pacts with otherworldly forces, or those who pray for their magic, but especially in 4th edition D&amp;amp;D, the mechanics are basically identical, with only the specific effects of each spell differing. I want to represent magic as a force that exists, that some people figure out how to manipulate (perhaps through multiple ways, such as rituals, pacts, prayers, or what have you) rather than an inherent trait that some people have and some don&amp;rsquo;t. Obviously, I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet come to any concrete decisions on how to make this happen, so I&amp;rsquo;m looking for suggestions and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I have a rather better developed mechanic in mind that popped into my head almost fully formed while watching HBO&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Rome&amp;rdquo; series and reading &amp;ldquo;A Song of Ice and Fire&amp;rdquo; by George R.R. Martin, in addition to various medieval/fantasy influences. I started thinking about how in the historical ancient world and middle ages, family was hugely important. The idea of individual rights and privileges was somewhat foreign, and most people accepted that your family took care of you, so you had duties to them, and that anybody without kin to back them up was facing a hostile, dangerous world. This got me to the idea that a fantasy setting ought to have inter- and intra-family relationships play a bigger role in game. And like aspects in &amp;ldquo;Spirit of the Century&amp;rdquo;, I decided that family would best be represented by a trait that could both help and complicate things, and that made me think of other similar double edged resources that would be relevant, and for a sense of wholeness, I came up with three that I think work nicely. These are Family, Wealth, and Authority. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I envision these three traits working. Every character at creation will have a set number of points to distribute between those three categories. Family represents how strongly your family supports you and how much it expects from you. Wealth represents your ties to the commercial world and how much your character can personally accomplish with coin. Authority represents your character&amp;rsquo;s position in a hierarchical system of some sort, be that governmental, official, illegal, or informal. The point is that the higher the number, the more each category can help you out, but the more is expected of your character in return. With family and authority, a higher number can mean a more influential family or a higher position in a large organization, or it might not. I think I will leave such decisions to the player to decide. What&amp;rsquo;s important here is the level to which it helps/complicates your life. So, someone with high family might be the heir to a powerful political family expected to marry as he&amp;rsquo;s told and rule over his holdings responsibly and so forth, or it could be a low-born person with a truly massive family that has representatives in every village and holdfast throughout the land. Both can expect large amounts of help (in different ways), but both also have enormous responsibilities in exchange. Likewise with wealth (commercial contracts, debts, social obligations to support the kingdom or the poor or whatever) and with authority (duties and responsibilities, people who depend on you, ability to be ordered by superiors). I haven&amp;rsquo;t quite worked out how it will work mechanically yet (I think that will depend a lot on how the rest of the game works mechanically) but the goal is get a good balance of benefit and complication whatever level you take in each category. The catch is that you can&amp;rsquo;t opt to not put the full number of points into the categories: your character has to have help and obligations to somebody or something, but what it is is your choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;rsquo;s what I have so far, besides what I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in the prior reviews. My end goal is a fluid, action-packed game with simple rules and engaging play (hah, not asking much here). I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss further rules ideas as they come to me, and probably start elaborating on my setting a bit if there&amp;rsquo;s any interest, but it&amp;rsquo;s strongly influenced by the likes of Robert E. Howard, Fritz Lieber, and H. Rider Haggard, with dashes of mythology, history, and folklore for good measure.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-03-29-magic-and-obligations/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Spirit of the Century</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-03-29-spirit-of-century/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 10:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-03-29-spirit-of-century/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-03-29-spirit-of-century/ -&lt;p&gt;For my last Indie game review for a while, I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.evilhat.com/home/sotc/&#34;&gt;Spirit of the Century&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.evilhat.com/home/&#34;&gt;Evil Hat Productions&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve saved this one for last for a couple of reasons. For one, despite some creative and innovative mechanics and approaches, of the games I&amp;rsquo;ve reviewed, I&amp;rsquo;d say it&amp;rsquo;s the most traditional: PCs each have a character, they all cooperate in an adventure the GM comes up with and controls, and their characters have skills and stunts and gadgets that work much like any other RPG. The other reason I&amp;rsquo;ve saved this one for last, though, is that it is very close to what I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for already. It bills itself as a &amp;lsquo;pick up RPG&amp;rsquo;, designed to be great for one-off adventures, new players, and on the fly gaming. As a matter of fact, it does this job so well, and in a setting near and dear to my hear (20&amp;rsquo;s pulp action!), that I was sorely tempted to just make this game my default &amp;lsquo;starter RPG&amp;rsquo; and be done with all of this design nonsense. Alas, the game design bug has me but good, and not only do I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to design a game of my own, I also feel like SoTC is just a touch more suited to a one-off game full of experienced roleplayers than it is to people new to the hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I get into discussing how the game itself works, I want to point something out that I read in a review before purchasing the game. The rules of &amp;ldquo;Spirit of the Century&amp;rdquo; are chock a block full of great GMing advice. There&amp;rsquo;s a whole chapter on GM craft, but tidbits are scattered throughout the entire book. This GM advice is better and more comprehensive than 90% of &amp;lsquo;how to GM&amp;rsquo; chapters I&amp;rsquo;ve ever read in various RPGs. It is geared towards running an exciting Pulp flavored game, but I think that most of the advice that is good for that is good for other games. Sure, you could be running a serious, dramatic game full of intrigue and politics, but advice on keeping things moving and compelling is just as useful in that milieu as it is in a rip-roaring aerial dogfight. As I said, all of the GMing advice is good, but there are a few key take-aways I want to highlight. The single best piece of advice is in regard to situations where the characters attempt an action with a roll. Simply put, make sure there are interesting consequences for success or failure. Obviously, &amp;ldquo;interesting&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t always good for the characters, but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; always good for the players. This simple guideline guides all sorts of decisions, like avoiding &amp;lsquo;make this roll or die&amp;rsquo; situations. Dying because of a failed roll is not interesting, it&amp;rsquo;s cheap and sucks. Character death happens, but it should be more meaningful and interesting than just that. Second is the advice on information management. This applies to any way the GM gives information to the characters. Too little, and they don&amp;rsquo;t have any idea what to do. Too much and they get overloaded and stop paying attention to details. Beyond that advice, though, these rules recommend that you aren&amp;rsquo;t stingy with things like clues and important plot information. The whole point of such information, after all, is to drive the characters towards further action. Sitting around not acting is boring, so give them what they need to make decisions! What makes the game interesting is the decisions players make for their characters, not the tension of knowing or not knowing. I think that the tendency for GMs to want to &amp;lsquo;keep secrets&amp;rsquo; comes from other entertainment media where that is a dramatic and interesting effect, like movies and mystery novels and such. The trouble with applying this particular technique to RPGs is that the characters don&amp;rsquo;t have a script to follow. In a movie or book, the main characters are guaranteed to eventually stumble across what is necessary to make the plot go forward or have an exciting reveal of previously secret information, but RPG characters have no such guarantee, unless you railroad them in the most horrible and boring way. So, sure, mysteries are fun and exciting and a great thing to introduce into RPGs, but rather than making the drama come from whether or not the characters find the clues, make the drama and tension come from putting the clues together. Give them as many clues as they need, then let them figure out what they mean. Finally, in the spirit of a pick up game with limited play time, SoTC advises that &amp;ldquo;dead air&amp;rdquo; time where nothing significant is happening is just a plain waste of game time, and gives a whole raft of ideas on combatting such boring down time. Things like keeping an in-game &amp;lsquo;clock&amp;rsquo; element so that the adventure is a race against time and ensuring that action is a viable solution to the ills of the characters. And perhaps my favorite specific example of how to cure downtime is an old GM-favorite: send in the ninjas. Players totally off course? Have a squad of thugs break in and start shooting. At the end of the fight, one gets captured and interrogated, or runs off, leading the players to their secret base, or whatever. Action scenes pick up the pace, and if you plan them right, they can provide a way to gently nudge the characters back on the right track to taking further action. But you gotta be careful with this, because it might get obvious if you do it too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to reiterate, the GMing advice of SoTC is worth the price of admission alone. If you have any interest in running RPGs at all, and you haven&amp;rsquo;t read it, I highly recommend you pick it up and at minimum give the &amp;lsquo;tips and tricks&amp;rsquo; chapter a read. Besides the general advice I mentioned above, it gives three different ways to come up with an adventure (a pre-plotted story, a cluster of decisions based on the characters&amp;rsquo; main interests and traits, and a web of conflicting interests that will cause action and drama no matter how they turn out, or best of all, a combination of all three). For as good as the advice on crafting adventures is, I was actually pretty disappointed with the sample scenario included in the rulebook. To my mind, it seemed to not follow the advice given in the preceding chapter, giving a fairly straight and narrow plot line, not enough information to guarantee the players can act properly, and little focus on the characters as the stars of the show. That being said, it did have some pretty creative pulp elements and a decent initial situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to actually discuss the rules, the core mechanic was one of my least favorite parts of the rules to start with, but it grew on me a bit. First off, it&amp;rsquo;s based on special &amp;ldquo;fudge dice&amp;rdquo;, which is irritating to me. The good news is that &amp;ldquo;fudge dice&amp;rdquo; are nothing but specially marked D6&amp;rsquo;s that can be reproduced using normal-person D6&amp;rsquo;s, which rather than being a pain in the ass to get, are in fact the most common dice on this island earth. Basically, 1-2 equals a -1, 3-4 equals a 0, and 5-6 equals a +1. So, skills are rated on a &amp;lsquo;ladder&amp;rsquo; of -2 to +8, with a corresponding adjective (0 is &amp;lsquo;Mediocre&amp;rsquo;, +8 is Legendary and so forth). Difficulties are also set at some level on the ladder. To attempt a challenge, you roll 4 dice, add up the results, add that to your relevant skill, and compare against the difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for example, let&amp;rsquo;s say that Two-Fist Bob is trying punch out a disrespectful young man for an insult to his girl. Two-Fist Bob is a local amateur boxing champion, so he has a rating of &amp;ldquo;Great&amp;rdquo; (+4) in Fists. The GM decides that the drunk and lecherous fellow with a rude mouth isn&amp;rsquo;t going to take much to go down, but he&amp;rsquo;s a little tougher than a random schmoe, so he sets the difficulty at &amp;ldquo;Average&amp;rdquo; (+1). Two-Fist Bob&amp;rsquo;s player rolls his four dice getting a -1, -1, 0, +1. Add those together, and you get a net -1, which you add to his +4 from his skill, for a total of +3. He handily knocks the guy out with two &amp;ldquo;shifts&amp;rdquo; (each level over the required level for success is a &amp;lsquo;shift&amp;rsquo;, which comes into effect for some combat mechanics and the like).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since characters are heroic paragons of their age, any skill they don&amp;rsquo;t specifically take is rated at &amp;lsquo;Mediocre&amp;rsquo; (+0), and they take a &amp;lsquo;skill pyramid&amp;rsquo;: 1 skill at &amp;lsquo;Superb&amp;rsquo; (+5), 2 skills at &amp;lsquo;Great&amp;rsquo; (+4), 3 skills at &amp;lsquo;Good&amp;rsquo;(+3), 4 skills at &amp;lsquo;Fair&amp;rsquo; (+2), and 5 skills at &amp;lsquo;Average&amp;rsquo; (+1). No &amp;lsquo;stats&amp;rsquo;, just skills, but their use is intentionally pretty broad. The way the skills shake out, it is at once hard to be super specialized or an extremely broad &amp;lsquo;jack of all trades&amp;rsquo;, since every character will have the same number of skills at each level of competence. It&amp;rsquo;s fairly balanced, and allows characters to still have a strong main area of interest while being useful in a broad range of situations, but like I said, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to make a hyper-specialized character or one specialized in not being specialized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character creation system given is actually a pretty cool process. After coming up with your skills and a broad concept, you go through the phases of your life - initial background, the Great War, and then 3 pulp novels about your character&amp;rsquo;s adventures. In each novel, you choose a &amp;lsquo;co-star&amp;rsquo; from among the other Player Characters, and you thus come up with a background of helping each other out and interacting. There are also mechanics associated with this background, but more on that in a minute. As with the challenges in &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; and the best interests in &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of having a mechanical process at character creation that binds the characters together and gives them a reason to interact in play. It beats the hell out of &amp;ldquo;An old man speaks to each of you in a tavern. . .&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, that mechanical feature I talked about is perhaps the coolest and most striking trait of the SoTC rules, and that is &amp;ldquo;Aspects&amp;rdquo;. Aspects interact with another mechanic called &amp;lsquo;fate points&amp;rsquo; that on their surface look pretty familiar: a bonus point to get you a reroll or add to an existing roll when you really need to succeed. But those are just the boring uses of fate points. Where their real coolness comes in, your character can spend a fate point to do things like declare that their happens to be a convenient fire escape in this alley, so he can follow the high-jumping villain. Or for your academic to announce that he&amp;rsquo;s come across this tribe in his studies and that the proper way to show respect to them is a feat of strength. In other words, players can inject a bit of narrative control. The GM can still overrule such things, but a good GM will go with it if it&amp;rsquo;s cool and let the player spend his fate point. So what about these aspects I mentioned, and what makes them so cool?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Aspects are the way that players can use fate points or gain them back. At first glance they look a lot like perks and flaws, but they&amp;rsquo;re actually much broader than that. They can be a tagline, a significant person, a prop, or just traits about the character. Anything from &amp;ldquo;Sworn enemy of the Secret Brotherhood of the Flame&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Unspoken Love (Sally)&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Ancient Family Sword&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Fiery Latin Temper&amp;rdquo;. Players have total leeway in picking their aspects, but the rules give some great advice on what&amp;rsquo;s good to pick and what&amp;rsquo;s not. More on that in a sec. Mechanically, if a player wants to use his aspect to help him out, he can spend a fate point, and then either reroll the relevant dice, or add 2 to his result. So, in a fight with minions of the Secret Brotherhood of Fire, a &amp;lsquo;sworn enemy&amp;rsquo; might &amp;ldquo;invoke&amp;rdquo; his aspect, spend a fate point, and rain down righteous fury. On the other hand, the GM can &amp;ldquo;compel&amp;rdquo; an aspect, in which case he makes something happen to the character with the aspect, but pays him a fate point for the trouble. So, the &amp;ldquo;Sworn Enemy&amp;rdquo; notices a ring on the hand of an important politician that denotes his membership in the brotherhood, and the GM compels him to act against the politician and pays him a fate point. A player can choose to &amp;lsquo;buy out&amp;rsquo; of such a compel. An interesting twist is that a player can even ask a GM for a compel - in other words, he says he&amp;rsquo;ll act in a complicating/negative way in accordance with one of his aspects, but he wants a fate point for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules also cover temporary aspects (like &amp;ldquo;dizzy&amp;rdquo; for someone who just got hit in the head in a fight), environmental aspects for scenes (like &amp;ldquo;shadowy&amp;rdquo;) and so forth, and there are some neat mechanical ways they come into play, but it&amp;rsquo;s as a character trait that I find them most interesting and most useful. This is one of the best ways I think I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen to handle &amp;lsquo;perks&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;flaws&amp;rsquo;, as well as just general character information. One issue with traditional &amp;lsquo;flaws&amp;rsquo; that give character points for a negative effect is that many are on the player to incorporate, or at most the GM can be like &amp;ldquo;well, you did take unfriendly, so I&amp;rsquo;m not going to let you make a charm roll here&amp;rdquo;. And when those flaw points are used to buy extremely useful in-game abilities (like a one-eyed, one-legged, stinky, drunk, midget combat monster) munchkinism is born. The beauty of the aspects system is that it gives in-play uses to aspects to both player and GM, and it mechanically rewards &amp;lsquo;double sided&amp;rsquo; aspects the most. With aspects that are occasionally useful and occasionally trouble, you can both spend and regain fate points using them. If you have nothing but out and out useful ones like &amp;ldquo;Lucky&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Great Shot&amp;rdquo;, you&amp;rsquo;ll never get fate points back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aspects are also a great way for players to let the GM know what kind of things they want their character to do, what kind of situations they want to be in. If a character has aspects like &amp;ldquo;In the Nick of Time&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Dramatic Entrance&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Not this time, Dr. Zambago!&amp;rdquo; he probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to research ancient scrolls in the library or mingle in high society balls. Even better, with those aspects, the GM has both story and mechanical back up for making those things happen! And when characters have aspects that involve each other, it creates an even tighter bond between the play group. The GMing chapter recommends one method of adventure creation where you look at your PC&amp;rsquo;s aspects and use those to come up with &amp;ldquo;decision points&amp;rdquo; involving those aspects, and then just see where the players go from one decision to the next, or if you are doing a more scripted adventure, to keep aspects in mind as you write what sort of conflict and drama will be going on. In short, aspects permeate every facet of this game, and I think are a delightfully subtle yet powerful tool for integrating story and mechanics, and as with the rest of the rules, the advice on their use is top-knotch character creation and play advice, even when applied to a system without &amp;lsquo;aspects&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After gushing so much about this system, I feel like I should mention some of the reasons I did not choose it as my go-to starter RPG game, in addition to those I mentioned in the introduction. First off, as much as I do love early 20th century pulp adventure with Action! Science! and Action Science! it is not everybody&amp;rsquo;s cup of tea. I also find the core mechanic to be just a bit awkward. After fully reading through the rules, it makes a lot more sense than when first presented, and I feel that it would play fairly smoothly, but I also get the impression that adequately explaining it to new players would be a bit of a challenge. Likewise, the way things like sidekicks, gadgets, and other &amp;lsquo;stunts&amp;rsquo; are handled is flexible, but not my favorite ever. With the fairly limited &amp;lsquo;skill&amp;rsquo; options, stunts are the main directly mechanical way you distinguish your character from others, and for all that they felt somewhat limited. Perhaps most importantly, however, the game strongly discourages character advancement, and with good reason for what it is, but still. The philosophy put forth is that a &amp;lsquo;pick up game&amp;rsquo; is one that you play when and how you can, without necessarily having the same players or characters present every time. To provide in-game rewards based on amount of play time effectively punishes players for having other things going on in their life. So, that makes sense. On the other hand, though, I feel like character advancement is the most rewarding and &amp;lsquo;hooking&amp;rsquo; part of roleplaying, and not allowing new players to enjoy it would rob them of an experience that would likely help cement their enjoyment of the hobby. So, as with all the other games I&amp;rsquo;ve reviewed here, I will shelve this as a game I&amp;rsquo;d love to play sometime, and in the meanwhile, ruthlessly pillage it for good design ideas to include in my own project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting next time, I&amp;rsquo;ll finally begin the development process of my actual game! It&amp;rsquo;s exciting that it&amp;rsquo;s starting to take shape, bits and pieces at a time, and I plan to make the process as open as possible via this blog, both as a record for myself, and as an opportunity for input from readers to shape the game as it develops. Once again, any comments are a welcome source of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-03-29-spirit-of-century/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>In a Wicked Age</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-03-29-in-wicked-age/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 04:45:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-03-29-in-wicked-age/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-03-29-in-wicked-age/ -&lt;p&gt;Tonight I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about the game that got me excited about this whole Indie RPG business: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com/wicked.html&#34;&gt;In a Wicked Age&lt;/a&gt;. This is the second game in my survey by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lumpley.com/&#34;&gt;D. Vincent Baker&lt;/a&gt;, author of &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; of a couple posts back. First off, some generalities: IaWA is a wonderfully fluid and story driven game, with an emphasis on low to no preparation for play. It does this in a few innovative ways that I want to discuss as inspiration. Also, like &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;, but perhaps even more so, &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; hones in on what makes RPGs compelling with laser like focus, namely, conflict. It also gives a great deal of narrative control over to the players, with the game master essentially just being the controller of NPCs, with little direct control over what happens in the story or with the characters. As such, while it strikes me as a fantastic game I&amp;rsquo;d love to play, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s quite suitable in and of itself for a first time RPG. I think it would be good to prepare players for a more traditional game structure, and to stress interplayer cooperation, rather than conflict. Changes to these core assumptions, such as you see in IaWA, are interesting and fun, but I think a little more suited to advanced gamers. That being said, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good concepts that I intend to incorporate into my starter RPG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and most prominent element of &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;, and also the one easiest to port to other games, is the &amp;ldquo;Oracles&amp;rdquo;. Every game of IaWA begins by choosing one of four &amp;ldquo;Oracles&amp;rdquo; and then drawing four standard playing cards. Each oracle is a list of 52 entries broadly grouped by category. The oracles supplied with the game have a subtle but strong sword and sorcery flavor, and are entitled &amp;ldquo;Blood &amp;amp; Sex&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;God Kings of War&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Unquiet Past&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;A Nest of Vipers&amp;rdquo;. Each entry (corresponding to a card drawn from the deck) contains a brief setting/story element and/or characters. All of the players, including the GM, then decide which characters are mentioned and which are implied, and each player besides the GM picks one to be their PC. The game master then takes control of any others. Players then develop characteristics for their characters and the GM comes up with slightly less detailed stats for the NPCs. The beauty of this system is that it generates a situation with tons of  conflict and story development, while still leaving plenty of room to fill in the blanks as you go, so it can create detailed, engaging stories on the fly. Another great thing about it is that with a little bit of imagination, you can create a set of oracles for just about any setting. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.random-generator.com/index.php?title=In_a_Wicked_Age&#34;&gt;The Abulafia Random  Generator&lt;/a&gt;has a list of oracles that will randomly generate 4 entries for each whenever you click on them, and shows the breadth of possible options, with oracles for everything from Wuxia to Battlestar Galactica. The oracle system and the island generation system for Agon are two of the best &amp;lsquo;on the fly&amp;rsquo; adventure generators I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is, the Oracle system makes no distinction between which characters generated or implied will be PCs or NPCs, leaving the choice up to the players. And the entries are cleverly crafted to create lots of potential conflict between any given characters. This creates lots of opportunities for making choices and intense roleplaying  using the fluid and simple dice mechanics to be discussed momentarily. With a little work, the system can also be integrated into a more traditional RPG. For example, the GM could use an oracle to come up with an adventure, making any characters so suggested into significant NPCs that the existing PCs will interact with. Likewise, the GM can draw up some choices from the oracle and allocate some characters as pregenerated PC options and leave others as NPCs for a pick-up game. But one of the core strengths of the oracles is that everyone involved brainstorms the connections between the disparate elements and so has a say in the setting and the story. I&amp;rsquo;d say that Mr. Baker has a real knack for creating evocative yet sketchy settings with lots of room for customization while still having enough meat to fire the imagination. As I said, I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of this whole concept and plan on incorporating something similar to my game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next innovative thing about this system is its core mechanic. Like &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; uses combinations of dice as the &amp;lsquo;stats&amp;rsquo;. In DitV, however, the core stats are somewhat are a bit whimsical, but still map onto pretty standard concepts like &amp;ldquo;Body&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Spirit&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Acuity&amp;rdquo; and so forth. IaWA, on the other hand, focuses instead on the &lt;em&gt;manner&lt;/em&gt; in which actions are performed, rather than on the core abilities that allow you to accomplish them, with stats like &amp;ldquo;Covertly&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;For Myself&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;With Violence&amp;rdquo;. These stats give the player a lot of leeway in how they affect the story, and allow you to fill in the details as you see fit. For example, two characters with high scores in &amp;ldquo;With Violence&amp;rdquo; would both be good at getting what they want through force, but one might be a lightning quick fencer while another is a burly barbarian. Other than what the &amp;lsquo;forms&amp;rsquo; (the name for stats in this game) imply, characters can have a &amp;lsquo;particular strength&amp;rsquo;. This strength can be a magical power, or a legendary weapon, or a particular skill. The rules are intentionally very broad. Each particular strength can be only be used in conjunction with one form, and has several options to customize it, such as that it&amp;rsquo;s unique, or that it&amp;rsquo;s particularly powerful, or whatever. As with &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;, there&amp;rsquo;s very little mechanical enforcement on game balance, and a lot of trust is put on the players to choose things that are appropriate and interesting to play. On the other hand, the rules are so broadly defined anyway, it would be hard to come up with situations to be especially munchkiny anyhow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another really cool element of character creation, and one that really drives the conflict assumed by the game, is that each character picks 2 or 3 (but 2 are recommended) &amp;ldquo;best interests&amp;rdquo;. These are story-descriptions of what your character wants to achieve. For your character to become recurring in future &amp;lsquo;chapters&amp;rsquo;, you have to attempt to achieve your best interests by challenging other characters (PC or NPC, there is no distinction made) where they are strong, so you are encouraged to set up your best interests in conflict with the strengths of the other characters. This is a delightfully subtle way to push characters into contests, whether of wills, words, or swords. Now, like the oaths in Agon, I like the way that best interests weave the characters together into a coherent storyline, almost automagically. I think when integrating this concept into a more traditional game, it would be a good idea to have the PCs focus on best interests that overlap and compliment, but don&amp;rsquo;t repeat one another, but likewise come into direct conflict with significant NPCs. When combined with the oracles, these can create really meaty storylines surprisingly easily.  Along similar lines, I think the concept of &amp;ldquo;Best Interests&amp;rdquo; is a good tool for GMs to clarify &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; their NPCs come into conflict with or choose to aid the PCs. Even with a straight up traditional game, I think that a modified version of oracles and best interests would be a great asset for generating adventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I go onto to describing the core conflict resolution mechanic and how the dice are used, I want to take a second to talk more about what I said is at the heart of &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;: conflict. I think it is a valuable insight that conflict is what makes stories interesting and engaging, and it is also what leads to the &amp;lsquo;game&amp;rsquo; part of roleplaying games: the dice come out to decide conflicts. Earlier, I said that I didn&amp;rsquo;t think a default position of PC on PC conflict was a good habit to instill in starting roleplayers, but I think the idea deserves a little more attention. First off, as numerous entries at &lt;a href=&#34;http://arsludi.lamemage.com&#34;&gt;Ars Ludi&lt;/a&gt; point out, the only truly valuable resource in an RPG is playtime. It&amp;rsquo;s what everyone is there for. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how much in-game treasure or mighty stats your character gets if you just sat there with no say in things the whole time. Having the majority of the storyline be conflict between PCs automatically means more play time for players: instead of every conflict being one or more players and the GM, the majority will be two or more players, sometimes with the GM involved. The rule system has a neat way to handle this, more in a moment. So, the plus side of all this conflict is that players get more time in the spotlight, and the GM takes a more subtle background role. The reason I&amp;rsquo;m leery of such inter-PC conflict, however, is that it&amp;rsquo;s all too easy for inter-character conflict to become inter-player conflict, and I think the chance of that is increased with people less used to making the distinction between player and character persona. If you get really attached to your character (and why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t you?) it might be hard to forgive your buddy for thwarting his every aim and ending up crippling or killing him despite the fact that all of it was &amp;lsquo;in character&amp;rsquo; and made for an interesting and complex story. So, I think the take away for me is a renewed commitment to make the players and their characters the stars of the show, but still to encourage overall cooperation. Also, there&amp;rsquo;s some solid GMing advice on how to set up conflicts and vary them up, as well as how to set the scene and describe details and focus in on the parts of the story that will be most interesting (those directly leading to or involving conflict, specifically).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, on to the dice system itself. Like &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;, the core mechanic of &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; is very back and forth, with a heavy narrative element interwoven with the dice rolling itself. First off, the rules say that the dice only come out when a character acts in some concrete way, and another character can and would interfere. No matter how heated a conversation becomes, the dice don&amp;rsquo;t come out until a character takes some action other than talking. I think this is a nice way to put the focus of character interaction on the roleplaying, rather than something like &amp;ldquo;okay, I successfully rolled my lie test, so he believes me&amp;rdquo; or what have you. For an example, I&amp;rsquo;m just going to talk about one on one conflict, but the rules provide for conflicts involving multiple parties. First off, when an action happens, each character chooses two forms that apply to the action. More than two might plausibly apply, but you just pick two. So, for example, if my character is stabbing yours to steal the jewel he needs to enact a dark ritual, he might roll &amp;ldquo;with violence&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;for myself&amp;rdquo;.  Each player rolls his two dice, and whoever has the highest single die roll takes the first move. The player taking the first move leaves his dice on the table and describes an action that fits with the two forms rolled. The other player picks up his dice, and after the first player finishes describing his action, he rolls them again. If the highest roll doubles or more the first players roll, he wins absolutely. If he equals or beats the first players roll, he takes the advantage and gets to roll an extra die subsequently. If the dice are lower, but more than half of the first players roll, the fight continues and the first player takes the advantage and rolls an extra die subsequently. If the second players dice are less than half, then the first player wins absolutely.  Play continues to the second round. In between rounds, the players can choose to negotiate rather than continuing to roll, and if both agree on some outcome, that&amp;rsquo;s what happens. Otherwise you keep rolling. The advantage die is always a D6 with pips, and it adds its score to the highest roll of whoever has it. Any fight will only go on for 3 rounds max. At the end of the 3rd round, there&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;lsquo;taking the advantage&amp;rsquo;. Instead, whoever rolls higher wins, and whoever rolls lower loses. Once the fight is over, the winner either exhausts the loser, or injures him, or else both parties negotiate. Exhausting lowers two forms, injuring lowers two others, and negotiated results can lower forms or be in-story outcomes, or some combination. But the winner can always choose to pick exhaustion or injury, so he has a &amp;lsquo;stick&amp;rsquo; in the negotiations, and has no reason to accept a negotiated outcome that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t please him at least as much as exhausting or injuring his opponent. If a character ever has two forms go down to 0, he is out of the chapter. He might be dead, incapacitated, or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this brings us to an interesting game mechanic that makes this largely PC dominated game work without the usual GM editorial discretion. There is a mechanic called &amp;ldquo;the owe list&amp;rdquo;. The way you get put on the owe list is to go up against another character who has higher dice in the conflict than you do, and to still be in the fight after the first round. Once your name is on the owe list, you&amp;rsquo;re guaranteed to go on to the next chapter, if you want to. Or you can scratch your name off for an advantage die in some conflict. NPCs never go on the owe list. What this means is that a character can&amp;rsquo;t be killed outright unless the controlling player decides that&amp;rsquo;s the coolest thing for the story. He can be &amp;lsquo;out&amp;rsquo; and not be on the owe list and so not come back, which might make the most sense for him to be dead, but that&amp;rsquo;s still up to the player. I imagine this lack of ability to kill enemies outright might be frustrating to new players, though. Another cool thing about the way the owe list works, specifically the way you get on it, is that it drives characters to go for risky (and therefore more likely to be interesting) conflicts. You don&amp;rsquo;t just have two guys equally good at stuff always going at it. It rewards gumption and desperate moves, the meat and mead of compelling stories. The player at the top of the owe list also gets a special advantage: he is for sure in the next chapter (other players can choose to bring a character back by scratching them off the owe list) and he gets to pick what oracle will be used for that chapter, and to pick one of the four elements, rather than drawing it randomly. Interestingly, chapters can be before or after ones already played, and characters can come back at different ages, in different roles, or whatever. Particular strengths can be increased if a character returns &amp;lsquo;as is&amp;rsquo; (i.e. from being on the owe list), but the forms never increase, you can just choose to shuffle them around. I think that this very limited character advancement takes some of the fun out of campaign play that a more traditional RPG provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, not so much the rules, but the &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; the rules are written for &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; provides some cool inspiration. The description of what the game is, and how to go about it, suggests you get your cool, creative friends, and that you serve wine and cheese and nuts. In other words, it presents the game as something for classy adults to do, not something for awkward teenagers with mountain dew (nothing against awkward teenagers with mountain dew roleplaying, I was there). Given where I&amp;rsquo;m at in my life, as well as my beliefs about RPGs, I thought this was a nice touch. I think a lot of people view RPGs as immature or hopelessly nerdy or just plain an odd way to spend your time. For whatever reason, it does seem that a good deal of roleplayers are awkward or odd, and this is off-putting to new players not used to such company. Having been awkward and odd myself, with a number of awkward and odd friends throughout the years, this isn&amp;rsquo;t something that bothers me, but it&amp;rsquo;s not a stereotype that helps bring in new players, which is the whole goal of my project! So, in addition to whatever decisions I make regarding the game rules and the genre and the setting and what have you, I will keep in mind the advice here to make the actual event, the physical space and attitude towards the game, something welcoming and intriguing to those who may be skeptical. Things like where you choose to play, what kind of snacks and drinks you have on hand, and so forth, can have a big impact on new players&amp;rsquo; experience. The &amp;ldquo;quick start&amp;rdquo; nature of these rules is one thing that helps with that, since the long prep and character creation process has killed many a prospective roleplayers interest in the hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in summary, &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; has numerous elements I wish to use as inspiration, both philosophically and mechanically, but is a game I will wait to play &amp;ldquo;as is&amp;rdquo; until my players are a little more experienced with the hobby. As always, I look forward to discussing the above in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-03-29-in-wicked-age/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Agon</title>
        <link>/gaming/2010-03-18-agon/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 12:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2010-03-18-agon/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2010-03-18-agon/ -&lt;p&gt;In this installment, I will continue my reviews of &amp;ldquo;Indie RPGs&amp;rdquo; that have recently made an impression on me. Today I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agon-rpg.com&#34;&gt;Agon&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, a game of mythical Greek heroes. First off, &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; is awesome. I absolutely love it, and if I had like minded players around me, I would run a game tomorrow. It is simple but rich, and it captures the feel of Greek mythology and the whole Greek ethos masterfully. And I&amp;rsquo;m not just talking out of my ass when I say that, as I have a degree in Classics, so consider it my semi-expert opinion that this game is very &amp;ldquo;Greek&amp;rdquo; in feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it achieves this feel is right there in the title: &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; is the Greek world for struggle or competition, but the meaning was much wider than either of those English words. In the ancient Greek mindset, everything was a competition, and it was the struggle for glory between men that the gods found most pleasing. Inherent to the Greek worldview was that everything could be done with more or less arete, or excellence, whether that was mending a shoe or killing a rival warrior, and that the only way to judge a person&amp;rsquo;s arete was through direct competition to see who came out on top. Who made the most beautiful tapestry? Who sang the best song? Who fought with the greatest valor? These questions, and the implicit question behind them, namely &amp;ldquo;Who is the better man (or woman)?&amp;quot;, could only be answered by directly striving against one another. Whoever achieved more rightfully gained more glory and was accorded better status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sets the stage for the key philosophical difference between &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; and other roleplaying games. In most RPGs, the player characters cooperate against foes and threats presented by the game master and succeed or fail as a group, pooling resources and winnings and gaining experience as a whole, divvied up evenly. In &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo;, you still have a game master (the &amp;ldquo;antagonist&amp;rdquo;) and a group of PCs who help each other achieve quests, but the PCs are really vying against one another to be the best and most glorious. They don&amp;rsquo;t fight one another, but each player wants to make sure his character kills the Gorgon, steals the treasure, or wins the maiden, so that he gets the most glory. And the game tracks glory and unabashedly uses it as a scoreboard for which hero is winning. The analogy presented by the author, John Harper, is that it&amp;rsquo;s like a black jack game. The antagonist is the dealer, and the PCs are the players at the table. Everybody is competing against the dealer, but the real competition is against the other players. But like a card game among friends, since everyone comes to the table knowing they&amp;rsquo;re trying to beat the pants off of each other, there&amp;rsquo;s no hard feelings. I think this spirit of friendly competition is helped by the fact that the player heroes never directly fight each other, instead they do help each other fight, but they&amp;rsquo;re still trying to each achieve the most individually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting into the game, the antagonist doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about ambiguity of what the players need to accomplish, as the default way of setting up adventure is for a god to literally descend from the heavens and impart a quest upon the heroes. Sure, it lacks subtlety, but it lets the players get right into what they&amp;rsquo;re there for: heroic exploits! Also, it&amp;rsquo;s entirely in keeping with the Greek mythological flavor, and the game makes no bones about not being about subtle character development or complex storylines. That being said, some adventures available for free from Ben Robbins, the author of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arsludi.lamemage.com&#34;&gt;Ars Ludi&lt;/a&gt; game design blog I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, do a good job of showing that stories can be straight forward and still have plenty of flavor and interest.   The quest system also comes with defined objectives that the antagonist determines for the quest (usually 3-5 per quest). These aren&amp;rsquo;t necessarily laid out at the beginning of the quest, allowing for some roleplaying and investigation opportunities, but there&amp;rsquo;s some solid GM advice given here that is repeated in &amp;ldquo;Spirt of the Century&amp;rdquo;, to be reviewed later: the GM&amp;rsquo;s job is not to hide information from players or keep secrets, it is to provide exciting situations for them to interact with. In other words, you should give more than enough clues for players who are trying at all to find out what they should be doing and where. There&amp;rsquo;s another reason for the codified quest and objective system that allows the fiercely competitive nature of Agon to be fair: strife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strife is a pretty cool innovation. In most games, the GM has total fiat over everything that isn&amp;rsquo;t directly under a player character&amp;rsquo;s control. His only restraint is the real-world social restriction of ending up with no players if he abuses his in-game authority. In Agon, however, the GM has a budget called &amp;ldquo;Strife&amp;rdquo;. If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with wargaming, strife works a lot like points systems in many games. The GMing rules provide costs for using strife to create obstacles, NPCs, and villains. During game play, he can also use left-over strife on the fly to make given conflicts more difficult. Having a budget like this gives the GM license to be as tough as possible on the players, because the game is designed so that he only gets as much strife as the players can theoretically handle (though it will be challenging). The flip side of the coin is that the harder the GM makes any villain or situation, the more glory the players win for beating it. This whole notion of restraints on the GM fits into the similar ethos present in &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo; where traditional player/GM roles are questioned and modified, usually giving more in-game power and responsibility to the players. I&amp;rsquo;m all for such changes, as even if you decide you still like a more traditional roleplaying format, having played games like this will make you better at being either a player or a GM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if it hasn&amp;rsquo;t become apparent by now, Agon is a heavily rules-dependent game. Almost everything that happens in the game from an argument to GM NPC creation, is governed by defined rules rather than loose guidelines.This would have the potential to be stifling, except that the rules are admirably straight forward and the competitive philosophy of the game is straightforwardly and unashamedly presented everywhere to remind you &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the rules are so stressed. This brings up one of the guidelines of the game, notable in the use of strife: nobody gets anything for free. Any time there&amp;rsquo;s a conflict of interest, the dice come out. Nothing happens because &amp;ldquo;it should&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;d be good for the story&amp;rdquo;. No rewards are free, but then neither are any challenges free for the GM. This guideline also seems to me to be a helpful rule of thumb to keep in mind for less competitive or rules-focused games on when to break out the dice and when not to: dice are for conflicts of interest. Any time there&amp;rsquo;s not a conflict of interest, don&amp;rsquo;t bother with dice. But when there are, it&amp;rsquo;s probably more satisfying to the group to have the dice decide it, unless you&amp;rsquo;re purposely playing a game with a more communal storytelling feel to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so, having said that the rules are very important, let&amp;rsquo;s shakedown the core mechanic. Stats are listed as dice, from d4 up to d12, with d4 being &amp;lsquo;not very good at&amp;rsquo; and d12 being &amp;lsquo;legendary/divine&amp;rsquo;, and d6 being average. For a conflict you roll all relevant dice (usually 2 or 3) and whoever has the highest single number showing wins. Ties go to the aggressor. And that&amp;rsquo;s it! See what I mean about simplicity? Now, of course there are wrinkles to make the game interesting, such as being able to spend divine favor points for extra dice or rerolls, but as with &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; the scale of dice means that bigger dice are more likely to win, but not guaranteed. Unlike &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; you don&amp;rsquo;t have as much leeway with rolling more of a lower die rather than fewer dice with more sides.  I like the fact that ties go to the aggressor, as this is a subtle but useful incentive to players to do things decisively, as befits Greek heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way that larger sided dice come in, besides giving you a better probability of winning is that for every 4 points you beat your opponent by, you gain a &amp;ldquo;victory&amp;rdquo;, and additional victories are useful in various ways. In combat, they provide more injuries, and in other situations they determine with how much flair you&amp;rsquo;ve overcome your opponent or an obstacle. In situations where all heroes are rolling against the same challenge (like fording a raging river) the one with the most victories does it best/fastest and gets a bonus glory point!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cool factor is that your &amp;ldquo;base die&amp;rdquo; that is used in all rolls is your &amp;ldquo;name die&amp;rdquo;. Mortals start with a d6, half divine characters start with a d8. In addition to your name, you choose an epithet (fleet-footed, clever-eyed, et cetera) that grants you bonuses to certain kinds of rolls as appropriate. This is a subtle but awesome way to hammer home the Greek/Heroic flavor, making your name have in-game effect.  All of your stats are divided into 4 categories of 4 stats each. Arete includes Insight, Grace, Might, and Spirit. Craft includes Lore, Music, Orate, and Heal. Sport has Athletics, Cunning, Hunt, and Wrestle. Battle includes Aim, Shield, Spear, and Sword. And that&amp;rsquo;s it on stats. You don&amp;rsquo;t have any skills in addition to stats, rather different situations are modeled by combining different stats, and more complicated weapons rules are avoided by combining two facts: one, the weapons listed (bows, javelins, spears, swords, shields) were pretty much the only weapons used by heroic Bronze Age Greeks, and two, you can pretty much &amp;lsquo;map&amp;rsquo; other weapons onto the existing weapons without too much trouble because the combat is tactical but somewhat abstract. So it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter if you roll exactly the same thing for a javelin as for a &amp;lsquo;furious charge&amp;rsquo;, since the only parts that matter in game are range and damage. This makes creating monsters really easy as whatever nutty natural attacks they have, they just count as bows, javelins, spears, swords, or shields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four categories of stats are important because you can trade around &amp;lsquo;points&amp;rsquo; in each category to get different dice. For example, within &amp;ldquo;Arete&amp;rdquo;, if you want to up Insight from a D6 to a D8, you can lower Grace from a D6 to a D4. But you couldn&amp;rsquo;t trade a die from the &amp;ldquo;Craft&amp;rdquo; category to up Insight in the  &amp;ldquo;Arete&amp;rdquo; category. Also, in some types of non-combat conflict, the categories are important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aspect of character creation that I really like is the &amp;ldquo;achievements/oaths&amp;rdquo; method. In this, at character creation, every character engages in a simple contest with each other character. When it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to go around to each character, you get to pick what the contest is, but then that person will get a chance to choose a contest with you. These can either be direct like &amp;ldquo;we wrestle each other&amp;rdquo; or less direct like &amp;ldquo;we both engage in stealth to see who is more successful at sneaking into the enemy camp back in the war&amp;rdquo;. Whoever wins the contest gets an &amp;ldquo;oath&amp;rdquo; from the other player. Oaths are an actual mechanic whereby a player owes another player direct in-game help of a mechanical nature. The player holding the oath can choose any time to call in the favor. This system is neat for two reasons. For one thing, the little vignettes of each contest give the heroes a built-in history, explaining why they&amp;rsquo;re traveling together killing monsters and liberating maidens and such. Secondly, it creates a mechanically-reinforced mutual dependence between players. Oaths can force cooperation that might be held back, but you have to deal with the shame of needing help on something (and you have to share the glory when you call in oaths). Also, as the game goes on, oaths are the primary currency in inter-player bargaining (or even bargaining with NPCs). You can say &amp;ldquo;okay, I&amp;rsquo;ll rid your village of these pesky harpies, but you owe me three oaths for it&amp;rdquo; or you can be like &amp;ldquo;hey, heal me in this break, and I&amp;rsquo;ll give you an oath&amp;rdquo;. This encourages at the same time friendly competition as well as cooperation (even if grudging cooperation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, going back to the core notion that any time someone has a conflict of interest or seeks an advantage a contest happens, it is important for players to clearly state their goals whenever they take an action. This allows the antagonist to determine if it would gain the hero an advantage or come into conflict with some other entity. If not, the action happens, no problem. If it does, then a contest happens. There are two types of contests, simple, and battle. Battle is not necessarily physical combat, as you can have a rhetoric battle or a lute playing battle, or an involved wrestling match, or whatever. But obviously the most common more in-depth contest is actual fighting. Simple contests are where all involved parties roll the relevant dice, compare results, and you&amp;rsquo;re done. Any heroes participating who succeed gain glory, but the winner gets an extra glory. Battles are more involved affairs with a series of exchanges between opponents and usually have more at stake than simple contests. A neat feature of the rules, though, is that player characters reserve the right to &amp;ldquo;Invoke Hubris&amp;rdquo; after any simple contest. This escalates a simple contest into a battle, and the loser of the simple contest goes into the battle with a number of wounds equal to the victories rolled by the winner of the simple contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t do a play by play of the battle system here, but essentially it&amp;rsquo;s a series of simple contests with the addition of an initiative system and an abstracted range rule (you have a vertical strip divided into zones. On your turn you can move either yourself or an opponent a certain number of zones closer or farther. Different weapons work optimally at different ranges) that allows a surprising amount of tactical interest while remaining quite simple.   With any contest, simple or battle, things are at stake. Something tangible, besides glory points, always comes out of a contest, whether that&amp;rsquo;s an advantage against a foe in an upcoming battle, or an impairment for the loser or vital information (don&amp;rsquo;t look at the medusa or you&amp;rsquo;ll be turned to stone, or you have to burn the heads off the hydra, or whatever). Impairment is where one of your abilities goes down by a die level, and the first level of impairment is always against the stat used in the contest. In a contest, either the antagonist will dictate which ability is used, or the players will be able to phrase what they&amp;rsquo;re doing in a manner to make it clear what ability applies. A neat exception, though, is that you can opt to use a &amp;ldquo;creative ability&amp;rdquo; to add an extra die to your roll. All you have to do is describe adequately how the ability is being used in the contest. If you use an extra ability, though, it gets impaired afterwards win or lose (all that extra effort!). So, for example, say a foot race calls for a name + athletics roll. But you explain that your character is going to use his cunning to find a short cut, while I explain that my character will use hunting to find a deer trail through the dense woods. So you&amp;rsquo;d roll name + athletics + cunning, while I&amp;rsquo;d roll name + athletics + hunting, but afterwards no matter how we did on the contest, your cunning would be impaired as would my hunting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the one semi-exception to the &amp;lsquo;nothing happens just because it should&amp;rsquo; rule is with &amp;lsquo;obstacle contests&amp;rsquo;. In these contests, the outcome will happen one way or another, but winning allows the heroes to do it easily and with style, while losing makes them tired and struggle harder. Examples include things like crossing a river or purchasing from a hard-driving merchant. It would be boring for the hero to be stuck on one side of the river or not to acquire the necessary item, but if he wins he swims across easily and without danger or strikes a good deal with the guy, but if he loses he wears himself out crossing or gets cheated. Either way he&amp;rsquo;s across the river or in possession of the object, but the in-game effect doesn&amp;rsquo;t come for free. Contests can also be &amp;lsquo;dangerous&amp;rsquo; where losing causes wounds in addition to impairment, but heroes gain extra glory for beating them, and antagonists must spend strife to make them dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to go into the battle system, but I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize by saying that it&amp;rsquo;s relatively simple but detailed enough to be interesting. Also, since glory is awarded based on individual action, there is an inherent tension in needing to cooperate to defeat foes, but wanting to prevent the other heroes from doing better than you. In addition to being the game&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;scoreboard&amp;rdquo;, glory works as the experience of the game. 10 glory = 1 advance, and advances buy you bigger dice at a rate equal to half the sides of the current die. So, to go from a d6 to a d8, you&amp;rsquo;d pay 3 advances. From a d8 to a d10 would be 4 advances, and so on. You must advance to each die in turn, you can&amp;rsquo;t skip any. Each advance also ups your &amp;lsquo;legend&amp;rsquo; which is the scoreboard of the game. The hero with the highest legend gets to add +2 to any orate rolls to determine who makes decisions for the hero band (yup, you even roll who&amp;rsquo;s the leader!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to glory, you have another tracker called &amp;ldquo;Fate&amp;rdquo;. Mortals start with 0, but half-divine heroes start at 8. Fate only goes up, never down. Your fate goes up when your hero is defeated in a battle, when you complete a quest successfully, or when you challenge a god to a contest in order to resist their demand that you go on a quest. In addition to these, you can chose to up your fate for in game benefits like not taking damage from an attack. or to get rid of impairment. Also, as your fate goes up, your name die increases to a d8, d10, and d12. Here&amp;rsquo;s the catch, though. Fate is quite literally a ticking clock on your heroic career. When your fate is filled up (16 boxes, so half-divine characters start out more powerful but have half the time to be glorious) your hero is done. You can look at a handy little chart to see how your final legend score means you meet your end (glorious battle, horrible shame, or old and fat and happy). Once your hero retires or is dead, you get to create a new hero who&amp;rsquo;s a little more powerful (based on how many quests your prior hero completed, so no running up the fate on purpose to get to a better hero!) than your old hero was to start. I rather like the tension between cost and benefit and various trade-offs here, and I think it&amp;rsquo;s a nifty game mechanic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole game, really, is all about cost/benefit trade-offs. GMs have to spend strife to make challenges. Players end up giving the GM more strife whenever they rest to heal and recover. Players may expect oaths if they help you out. And so forth. It makes for interesting decision making and gives yet another thing to be competitive over.   Like with the town creation in &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; has a really nifty island creation system. It can be used randomly or you can choose elements from the various tables (terrain types, residents, monsters, et cetera) to your taste. But it provides ready made sources of quests and conflict to get involved in. I fully plan on taking the idea of rich, interesting random setting generation and adding it into my toolbox for pick-up games that have to be created on the fly. Other elements of the GMing chapter I really appreciated were really good minion rules for mowing through hordes of lesser enemies, and the advice on NPC creation. It says that you should remember that the PCs are the stars of the show, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean NPCs should be flat or boring. Rather, you should ensure that your NPCs have motivations that will create interest &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; the characters. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s someone who thinks the heroes will solve all his problems or someone who thinks killing them will solve all his problems, his focus of action should lead to the PCs so that he remains relevant and interesting to the group and keeps the focus on the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, at the back of the book, the author provides a list of suggested variants and what rules changes would be necessary. He points out that a Norse variant would require almost no mechanical changes and only really flavor ones. This idea struck me as so cool that I&amp;rsquo;m working on a Norse variant. I emailed Mr. Harper about permission to do this and any restraints he wanted on distribution, and he gave me the go ahead on making it and distributing it however I like, so expect to see it here when I finish! I&amp;rsquo;m equally excited about either running a straight-up Greek Agon game or the Norse variant once I get it hammered out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don&amp;rsquo;t think Agon would be the best starter game for new RPG players. I don&amp;rsquo;t want my players&amp;rsquo; first experience with RPGs to be in competition with each other, since most games do not operate that way, and it can in fact be quite rude to be actively competitive with your fellow party members in some games. I feel like a better method of development would be to get used to cooperating and then learn to compete in a friendly fashion rather than the other way around. Also, Agon is less narratively/story focused than I&amp;rsquo;d like to start players out on for reasons discussed in some of my other posts. Still, with the right group of players (maybe ones more used to strategy board games than RPGs) this might be just the ticket, as you&amp;rsquo;re still competing against your friends, but you&amp;rsquo;re controlling a single hero rather than armies or gathering resources or what have you. As always, questions, comments, and even attacks are all welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2010-03-18-agon/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 