<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 13:17:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Best Spam Comment Ever</title>
        <link>/gaming/2019-06-12-best-spam-comment-ever/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 13:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2019-06-12-best-spam-comment-ever/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2019-06-12-best-spam-comment-ever/ -&lt;p&gt;Wow, I normally wouldn&amp;rsquo;t give any sort of attention to a spam comment, but this was too fantastic to pass up (posted to several of my posts as comments and removed, but good job, spammer, your post is getting immortalized here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vampires is not at all like in the movies or books. Sure, I understand. You are young you have the whole world open to you. You can be anything that you choose if you apply yourself and try hard to work toward that goal. But being a Vampire is not what it seems like. It’s a life full of good, and amazing things. We are as human as you are.. It’s not what you are that counts, But how you choose to be. Do you want a life full of interesting things? Do you want to have power and influence over others? To be charming and desirable? To have wealth, health, and longevity? contact the Vampires Lord on his Email: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Richvampirekindom@gmail.com&#34;&gt;Richvampirekindom@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2019-06-12-best-spam-comment-ever/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Level Up Your Process to Learn Better, Faster (Learning Overview Part 1)</title>
        <link>/coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/ -&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months, I’ve put some time into improving &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I learn, and I’d like to share some of that in a series on “metalearning” (learning how to learn). While there are many things I want to cover, from mental models to specific tools, the underlying logic will be to look at learning as a &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt;. Taking a process focus has several benefits - let’s walk through some of the biggest to kick off this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, an assertion: bettering your process is the best way to get better at learning. Sure, you could work harder, do smart drugs, or try any number of things to learn better, but I think process is the way to go. Why is that? For one, I’m a former consultant, so I loves me some process design. More seriously, I like processes because they are effort-based, holographic, and compoundable. Let’s step through those:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Effort Based&lt;/em&gt; - processes are not defined by what outcomes you achieve, but rather by what work you do to try to get there - that means that you can focus more on what’s under your control and less on what’s not, because life happens&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holographic&lt;/em&gt; - if you improve one piece of a process and leave the rest alone, you still improve your overall work. You can largely separate out improvements into discrete chunks and work on one at a time, which is helpful for building habits and sustaining motivation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Compoundable&lt;/em&gt; - Since processes focus on getting the  work right, rather than only on the outcome (which likely includes factors outside of our control) and you can work on one piece of that work at a time, every improvement you make builds on all previous improvements. Further, since processes are an explicit way of looking at the work you do, you can find where processes influence each other and improve those connections, making both  processes better. If you set a goal of losing 15 pounds, once you’re there, you’re done. But if you build a process of living healthier, every tweak you make to your diet, exercise, and sleep will add up until you’re living a significantly different life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, I’ve been talking about “process” a lot already without defining it. Since I &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/10/27/storytelling-part-1-introduction&#34;&gt;like&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/11/creativity-part-1-defining-creativity&#34;&gt;define&lt;/a&gt; terms in the first post of a series, let’s do it with our key term, “process”: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A process is a sequence of specific, repeatable actions, or a collection of such sequences.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Processes don’t have to be documented, but doing so makes them clearer and easier to make better. You’ll also notice that processes need not be habitual - though it’s best to make the most important ones habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the definition above, we already have some processes we follow to learn - we just might not know what they are, and we might not know how well they work (or don’t). So, what’s the first step for making them better? Write them down. To do so, I’m a big fan of mapping them in a diagram (again, former consultant). If you don’t know &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_process_mapping&#34;&gt;process mapping&lt;/a&gt;, you might check out some of the finer points, but if you’ve ever seen a &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/210/&#34;&gt;flowchart&lt;/a&gt;, you know enough to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If visuals aren’t your speed, lists or outlines will often do the trick. Since these are our own personal processes, we’re not trying to make them readily usable by anybody. Instead, we want to get to a level of clarity where you, and more importantly, &lt;em&gt;you in the future&lt;/em&gt;, can pick it up and know what it means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, before you think about any ways to get better, you might find it very helpful to map out your “as is” learning process - or at least a subset of it. You might pick one thing you do to learn - say, reading or taking notes or the like. Whatever you pick, write it down in all its messy, haphazard glory. If you already see stuff that you want to change, hold off for now - you want to start with an accurate picture of where you are today. Whatever flaws your current learning process might have, if you’ve been honest and careful in documenting it, it has one, huge positive in its favor: &lt;em&gt;you actually follow it&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.inc.com/craig-bloem/this-1-tip-from-tim-ferriss-will-propel-your-startups-productivity.html&#34;&gt;so-so approach you do is better than the perfect one that you abandon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we’ve got our process down on paper, we can start looking at bettering it. The rest of this series will go into lots of nitty-gritty details, but here’s a few overall thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and easiest, make it a system you will truly follow. Look for things you &lt;em&gt;mean to do&lt;/em&gt;, but never follow through. Then make these easier. In the long run, you will likely fail at anything that feels &lt;a href=&#34;https://markmanson.net/self-discipline-youre-doing-it-wrong&#34;&gt;too hard&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve talked before about &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/House-That-Cleans-Itself-Steps-ebook/dp/B00BFH3UX6/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1552596081&amp;amp;sr=8-1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The House that Cleans Itself&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and its twofold wisdom of setting “good enough” goals and making the right thing as easy as possible. Find ways to make it easier to consistently get close to what you’re after. Find it hard to read for 30 minutes every day? Try 5. Never have your book? Get the Kindle app on your phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, look for things that you find hard or irksome, even if you consistently do them, and look for ways to make them better/faster/easier. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/via-negativa-adding-to-your-life-by-subtracting/&#34;&gt;Getting rid of the bad&lt;/a&gt; will likely help more than adding new good stuff, most of all when you’re starting out. Pain in the ass typing your notes? Find a way to export them automatically. Miss writing something down because it’s a hassle to get your notebook?  Buy a smaller one you can keep in your pocket. Sometimes forget to go over flashcards? Get &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&#34;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; and set a reminder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, look for “processes” that are poorly defined. Maybe your “as-is” process just says “Read books sometimes.” In which case, good for you for accurately documenting that. Your next step might be to give yourself some bare-bones steps, like: “1) Find a book that sounds interesting, 2) Skim it to confirm I want to read it, 3) Read it and take notes.” Just by adding those steps, you now have three specific areas where you can look for improvement moving forward instead of the big and fuzzy “reading.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you’ve no doubt gathered, there’s a lot of ground we might cover in this series. So I’m not entirely sure where we’ll go. That being said, some of the topics I’d like to dig into include specific learning processes, digital and physical tools, quirks of how the brain works (and how to use them), thinking tools and methods, and selecting learning materials. With such a range of things to talk about, we’ll have to settle for breadth over depth, but I want to really tie together the way that a process-focused approach can help your learning efforts across the board. If any of these topics really get your motor going, please let me know and share your favorite resources.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Removing Support from Zak Smith</title>
        <link>/gaming/2019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 15:51:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith/ -&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE February 14th, 2019: Zak has issued a statement responding &lt;a href=&#34;https://officialzsannouncements.blogspot.com/2019/02/the-statement.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am not convinced to change my position below, but it introduces some doubt. I may have further thoughts as more information comes out, but I encourage you to read and evaluate it for yourself.   UPDATE February 16th 2019: I reworded the bit about what it would take to change my stance to include adequate evidence that the claims were false, rather than only saying evidence of growth on Zak&amp;rsquo;s part would do it.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As anyone reading this has likely already seen, Zak Smith/Sabbath&amp;rsquo;s longtime girlfriend Mandy Morbid has posted that Zak has done some rather awful stuff to her and others. I came across it as re-shared (with permission) over on &lt;a href=&#34;https://dungeonsdonuts.tumblr.com/post/182722330779/mandy-morbid-comes-forward-about-zak-s-violence&#34;&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Donuts by Kiel Chenier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then read Patrick Stuart&amp;rsquo;s response to the news here on &lt;a href=&#34;http://falsemachine.blogspot.com/2019/02/you-should-read-this.html&#34;&gt;False Machine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why I have chosen to believe these claims:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two folks who I have had enough online interaction with to find sane
and credible are saying their claims are consistent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The claims are to specific instances and patterns of behavior by an
individual, rather than relying on rhetorical dirty tricks, like
saying an &lt;a href=&#34;http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2122&#34;&gt;unwillingness to admit to guilt is evidence of
guilt&lt;/a&gt;, or arguing based on group
membership rather than individual action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I cannot discern any gain or motivation for lying about these
claims, except perhaps to hurt Zak to &amp;ldquo;get back&amp;rdquo; for hurt done, but
see above for why I don&amp;rsquo;t think that&amp;rsquo;s the case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To change my mind, I&amp;rsquo;d need to be presented with some pretty damn compelling counter-evidence that goes beyond the usual standards of internet-proof (something like a video of someone involved saying &amp;ldquo;I made that shit up&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s take down Zak whatever the cost&amp;rdquo; or the findings of a court of law).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This news makes me rather sad. I have admired Zak&amp;rsquo;s work and his critical judgement and explanation of works of art for a long time now. He introduced me via his blog and Google+ to most of my favorite RPG creators and helped provide the impetus for a number of awesome collaborations. I still think &amp;ldquo;DIY&amp;rdquo; is a better rallying ethic than &amp;ldquo;Old School&amp;rdquo; (but continue to use &amp;ldquo;OSR&amp;rdquo; as a more helpful, if vague, label for the sort of D&amp;amp;D and sort of blogs I find most interesting). I have found his assertions about the Socratic method, the importance of truth, and the need to have and enforce standards in creative communities to be helpful in shaping my own thinking, even when I have disagreed with parts. Unfortunately, now he gets to help me by providing another example of a creative person who makes great stuff but seems to be personally reprehensible, leaving all of us to figure out how to make use (or not) of their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until and unless I am presented with credible evidence of major personal development and change on Zak&amp;rsquo;s behalf [NEW 2/16/19: or evidence of the sort mentioned above that the claims are baseless], I will take the following actions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will not direct future attention or money to Zak, as the
personality and behavioral problems described by Mandy and Patrick
and others are pervasive and poisonous enough to make all of his
discourse suspect, and I wish to help provide consequences for such
behavior - concretely, this means I&amp;rsquo;m removing him from my blog
roll, unsubscribing from his Patreon, and will not buy things in a
way that will benefit him&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As for gaming works already bought and blog posts already read, I
will continue to use and enjoy them, but with perhaps a more
critical eye to any implicit beliefs that may be in them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I go over any elements of my own thinking and view of the world,
if it comes up that it was influenced by Zak, I&amp;rsquo;ll have to
re-evaluate with a more critical eye - for example, at the moment I
still believe in the value of a commitment to truth over &amp;ldquo;niceness&amp;rdquo;,
and the socratic method as a way of finding truth, but I&amp;rsquo;m
re-thinking some of the more abrasive implementations of it that Zak
had convinced me might be worthwhile, if painful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will not be removing my past posts on Zak&amp;rsquo;s material here on the
blog, including reviews and the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/search/label/Middenheim&#34;&gt;Vornheiming
Middenheim&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;
series, but I will post a link to this post at the top of them to
give anyone encountering him for the first time the chance to decide
for themselves how to approach his work (or not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On my &lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/2014/07/psa-this-post-is-full-of-lies-and.html&#34;&gt;old post publicly supporting him against negative
claims&lt;/a&gt;,
I have added a more explicit retraction, but I am leaving it on the
site in the interest of transparency on what I have believed in the
past&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- /gaming/2019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Fellhold Fiend Race, Class, and Magic</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-08-23-fiends-in-fellhold/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 12:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-08-23-fiends-in-fellhold/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-08-23-fiends-in-fellhold/ -&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, who doesn&amp;rsquo;t like demons? They are awesome, and from the moment I started the Fellhold reboot, I knew they&amp;rsquo;d play a big role. Please find below Fiends as a Race, Fiends as a Class, and Fiendish Magic. But first, a quick intro on just what a Fiend is in Fellhold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fiends-in-fellhold&#34;&gt;Fiends in Fellhold&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said in &lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/2018/06/the-soul-economy-in-fellhold.html&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, fiends in Fellhold were born when the gods were killed and their blood rained down on the dumb things of the earth. As such, fiends are somewhat like nature spirits or Kami, bound to plants, or animals, or inanimate objects. On the other hand, because they were born out of an act of sorcerous malice, they are twisted and malicious, so they are also somewhat like Chaos Demons. Finally, because they come from divine blood, they have an inborn need for lawfulness and keeping agreements along with a yearning for the true life denied them, and so they are also somewhat like Christian Devils. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, basically they&amp;rsquo;re a bunch of assholes. Guess what the most popular PC race is in my home campaign so far?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fiends-as-a-race&#34;&gt;Fiends as a Race&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fellhold uses split race and class. If you use a race-as-class game, I would recommend smashing this together with the Fiend class below, as the class assumes the restrictions and benefits of this race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;fiends&#34;&gt;Fiends&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiends are the warped and wicked remnants of the world’s nature spirits. They vary greatly in both power and form from minor animalistic sprites of rocks and saplings to mighty humanoid powers worshiped as gods. A player character fiend is far more powerful than many of these minor beings, but is still pretty far down the ladder. Fiends thrive on souls and worship, and most turn all of their doing towards those goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;special&#34;&gt;Special&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every fiend must have a stead, a place or thing that it is bound to. The fiend cannot move farther away from it than its level in miles (or level in districts, if more useful). Steads can be carried with fiends of the PC’s size and power, but if a  stead is destroyed, the fiend truly dies. If otherwise killed, the fiend will reform at its stead in 1d4 urbancrawl turns (weeks). If a fiend swears an oath or signs a contract, it cannot willingly break that deal (but of course, the word of the deal, not necessarily the spirit). If the fiend involuntarily breaks a deal or oath, it takes D6xLevel damage. Fiends can also be summoned, compelled, and bound as NPC fiends. Fiends must have a Use Name, Greater Name, and True Name. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fiends-as-a-class&#34;&gt;Fiends as a Class&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one was a lot of fun to design - it was one of the first ideas I had for the reboot, but getting it to work right took a long time and exposure to some cool new ideas. This class is mostly derivative, smashing together Mateo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://gloomtrain.blogspot.com/2015/03/cult-class.html&#34;&gt;Godling&lt;/a&gt;, Skerples&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://coinsandscrolls.blogspot.com/2018/03/osr-class-sorcerer.html&#34;&gt;Sorcerer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://coinsandscrolls.blogspot.com/2018/08/osr-class-witch-coven.html&#34;&gt;Witch Coven&lt;/a&gt;, and Joseph Manola&amp;rsquo;s/Skerples&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://udan-adan.blogspot.com/2016/09/bx-class-extras.html&#34;&gt;Extras/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coinsandscrolls.blogspot.com/2018/04/osr-class-many-goblins.html&#34;&gt;Many Goblins&lt;/a&gt;. I will say that I&amp;rsquo;m pretty pleased with how the &lt;em&gt;Soul Hoarder&lt;/em&gt; class feature worked out, though - that one&amp;rsquo;s mine, as is the &lt;em&gt;Possess&lt;/em&gt; feature, though that&amp;rsquo;s certainly based on other stuff I&amp;rsquo;ve seen before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This class is maybe super powerful? I haven&amp;rsquo;t had a chance to playtest it yet, but I suspect that the starting crappiness combined with the hefty strain dice cost will keep there from being too many shenanigans. See the Fiendish magic section below for more on the buying souls thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that my starting equipment is extremely stingy, because I do random equipment by class &lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/2018/07/money-equipment-in-fellhold.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Base Class&amp;rdquo; below is for those folks who don&amp;rsquo;t use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/05/the-glog.html&#34;&gt;GLOG&lt;/a&gt;. Just take that class for experience, saves, gear restrictions, and so forth, and then apply these powers at levels that seem appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;fiend-class&#34;&gt;Fiend Class&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiends as a class are tiny beings that wish to grow their power by gathering souls and worshippers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prime Ability&lt;/strong&gt;: Soul Hoarder&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Per Template&lt;/strong&gt;: +1 Casting Die&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Starting Equipment&lt;/strong&gt;: Stead&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; Word &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; Ghost Talk, Possess &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; Fools &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; Second Word&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RESTRICTIONS  You cannot take templates in the Fiend Class unless your first template is “Fiend”.  You cannot take souls by force or steal them, you must buy all souls and bits thereof by coming to an agreement, and as a Fiend, you are bound to follow that deal to the letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PERKS  You can turn insubstantial at will (can only interact with the physical world through sense and speaking).  You can disappear and reform at your Stead in 1d3 rounds at will.  You can grow or shrink to any size from that of a mouse to your maximum (1 Size up from Tiny per 6 Con, rounded down)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CLASS FEATURES&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Soul Hoarder&lt;/em&gt;  You begin play Tiny (~2’ tall) and barely substantial, and your Strength, Dexterity, and constitution begin at 1 (roll other stats normally). You have disadvantage on any physical attacks or other rolls against larger foes. You can improve your stats by buying soul bits. You lose any benefits if you lose the associated soul bits. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Word&lt;/em&gt;  You have power over one random fiendish word and can cast fiendish spells using it. See Fiendish Magic in the Magic section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghost Talk&lt;/em&gt;  You can talk to ghosts at will, but not any other kind dead that you wouldn’t normally be able to speak with. Most ghosts are somewhat faded or mad, and might not have much useful to say, but some might be willing to make deals. Note that ghosts are made up of soul bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possess&lt;/em&gt;  You can strive to take over living beings. To do so, choose a number of casting dice to roll. Add [SUM] to your Wisdom and make an opposed Wisdom save (both sides roll, highest roll that still passes wins). Take Strain Dice as usual. You are now in control for a number of rounds equal to your level. Retest at the end of each interval. Three failed rolls in a row change the duration to “Concentrate&amp;rdquo;.  When you leave the body you are possessing, you reappear at your stead. You may not take the body further from your stead than you can normally go.     &lt;em&gt;Fools&lt;/em&gt;  You gain a gaggle of worshippers convinced that you will grant them power, wealth, fame, and so forth in exchange for their devotion. They are not skilled, clever, or hardy, but they are very loyal. You may whisper in their minds at any time. The number seems to vary from time to time and place to place, and they stay together as a group, taking up roughly 20’x20’.  If you must know the precise number, there are 1d12+6, but this will vary every time you check. They will strongly prefer to remain within 10’ of you, and their ability to follow complex instructions decreases dramatically if you are not within sight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they are within 10’ of you, any ranged attacks targeting you will hit them instead. Treat all fools as one hireling, with a shared pool of HP at one HD less than you and one action per round. When they lose HP, that number of fools die in a background sort of way. Area of effect spells only affect them once. If reduced to zero HP, they lay on the ground moaning and wounded, and if reduced below zero HP, they die in a tragicomic fashion. New fools will be drawn to you in 1d3 weeks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fools cannot be trusted with any gear, and so have no gear slots and will never fight with anything more than shivs and bites and scratches (1d6, Close).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If put to work, Fools count as 10 workers for the first hour, 5 for the next, and give up after that without specific threats, promises, or gifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fools may perform a ritual to call on your power. It takes two full rounds (automatically act last in second round) of chanting and waving their arms about and grants 1 Casting Die toward a use of your Word. You may not invest further casting dice in this spell, but you also take no Strain Dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second Word&lt;/em&gt;  You gain a second Word that you use just like your first, or even put them together for new effects. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPELL LIST&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beasts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Craft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Death&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Envy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flesh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hunger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Might&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pride&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Riches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secrets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sickness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sloth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strength&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strife&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tinker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIEND MISHAPS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gain 1 Strain Die&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take 1d6 damage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effect targets random person or thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lose 1 Casting Die&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insubstantial 1d6 rounds (can’t interact with physical world, except to sense and speak)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lose your physical form. Reform at your stead in 1d3 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIEND DOOMS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unstable: lose your physical form. Reform at your stead in 1d3 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unreal: you are insubstantial for 3 days. Cannot interact with the physical world at all except to sense and speak.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rejected by the World: reality no longer allows your intrusion, your stead is a mundane item, and you are trapped in the ghost world. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BASE CLASS&lt;br&gt;
Elf. (Magic-User if Elf is not a class).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fiendish-magic&#34;&gt;Fiendish Magic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the rest of this stuff, this magic system is based on Arnold&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/09/the-glog-wizards.html&#34;&gt;GLOG stuff&lt;/a&gt;, but with a heavy influence from Skerples&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://coinsandscrolls.blogspot.com/2018/03/osr-class-sorcerer.html&#34;&gt;sorcerer&lt;/a&gt;. I also checked out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/185959/Godbound-A-Game-of-Divine-Heroes-Free-Edition&#34;&gt;Godbound&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/3482/Sine-Nomine-Publishing&#34;&gt;Kevin Crawford&lt;/a&gt;, but other than some inspiration on which words to use, I ended up not using much of that system - it&amp;rsquo;s neat, but I think it works better in a game where that&amp;rsquo;s the whole point, rather than one class&amp;rsquo;s powers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t run this yet, so I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how creative players will be or how much of a pain in the ass it will be to GM. Half the reason fiends work this way is that I&amp;rsquo;m too lazy to write spell lists if I can avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and see above for Word List, Mishaps, and Dooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiendish Magic  Fiends are made of the stuff of magic, and so can wield powers over a broad range of things related to the kind of magic they’re made of. As such, they have open-ended powers related to a word (or two for higher level fiends). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WORDS&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Using Words&lt;/em&gt;  You are a being with power over one random word from the list below, which will be clearly reflected in your nature. When you wish to shape the world through your word, describe to the GM what you wish to do, who will give you a TN. Roll a number of casting dice of your choice and compare [SUM] to the TN along with your full pool of &lt;em&gt;Strain Dice&lt;/em&gt; (see below). The GM will describe what has actually happened. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guidelines&lt;/em&gt;  Setting Target Numbers and assigning Strain Dice are up to the GM, but the below guidelines might prove useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy: 3  Challenging: 7  Hard: 10  Mind-Blowing: 14&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damage: [SUM] + [DICE]  Effect Permanent: Requires 4 CD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each Use of Power: +1 SD  More Targets: +1 SD  Area the size of a wagon: +1 SD  Area the size of an apartment: +2 SD  Area the size of a building: +3 SD  Effect lasts [DICE] minutes: +1 SD  Effect lasts [DICE] hours: +1 SD  Effect lasts [DICE] days: +1 SD  Create Something Tangible: +1 SD  Each Step of Size of Thing Created Above Tiny: +1 SD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EXHAUSTION AND STRAIN DICE&lt;br&gt;
Unlike other spellcasters, Fiends never exhaust their Casting Dice. Instead, every time they make a casting roll, they add a number of &lt;strong&gt;Strain Dice&lt;/strong&gt; to their dice pool determined by the use. Use a different color of dice. Whenever the Fiend casts, they must roll all Strain dice. They do not count for [SUM] or [DICE], but do count for doubles or triples to determine mishaps and Dooms. Strain dice disappear at the witching hour or can be removed through rituals performed by the Fiend’s worshippers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WORSHIP&lt;br&gt;
A fiend’s Fools can perform rituals to grant the fiend more power when casting a single spell or to remove strain dice. Rituals last a number of hours equal to the total number of casting dice to be used or Strain Dice to be removed. If used to cast a spell, the ritual grants one additional casting die, to a maximum number of dice equal to the Fiend’s level (maximum of five casting dice ever). If used to remove Strain Dice, it removes a number equal to the number of hours spent, to a maximum of the Fiend’s level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUYING &amp;amp; SELLING SOUL BITS&lt;br&gt;
A person may sell one or more of their Soul Bits, either while living, or upon their death. Fiends may buy souls in order to gain specific effects. Anyone else buying a soul or a soul bit simply has the right to do as they please with that bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
- /gaming/2018-08-23-fiends-in-fellhold/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Managing a Living World with Flexible Reaction Rolls</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-08-22-managing-living-world-with-flexible/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 11:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-08-22-managing-living-world-with-flexible/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-08-22-managing-living-world-with-flexible/ -&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate to be a cliche, but this idea literally came to me in the shower, though only in the form of &amp;ldquo;how might I smash together Flexible Reaction Rolls and John&amp;rsquo;s method of using reaction rolls to change rumors?&amp;rdquo; I then went back to current draft of how to handle jobs the PCs have been offered but passed up and saw a note to consider treating them like &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20130613034002/http://intwischa.com/2011/05/house-rule-for-tracking-ammo/&#34;&gt;Usage Dice&lt;/a&gt;. I then had to noodle a bit on what each die would represent, and the below is what I came up with. All this might be way too fiddly, as I haven&amp;rsquo;t had a chance to try it out in play yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;status-of-unattended-jobs-or-rumors--when-to-check--as-with-all-rolls-this-is-at-the-gms-discretion-but-some-options-include&#34;&gt;Status of Unattended Jobs or Rumors  &lt;strong&gt;When to Check&lt;/strong&gt;  As with all rolls, this is at the GM&amp;rsquo;s discretion, but some options include:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every week for especially big/important jobs or rumors, or those of
PC&amp;rsquo;s home district&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whenever a new rumor is picked up by the PCs, update the others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When specifically asked by the PCs (&amp;ldquo;Hey, what&amp;rsquo;s up with that job
the fence offered us?&amp;quot;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you need ideas for adventure hooks or complications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What to Roll&lt;/strong&gt;  Each rumor or job will have a &amp;ldquo;source die&amp;rdquo; and a &amp;ldquo;world die&amp;rdquo;. The source die represents whatever started the rumor or the person offering the job. The world die is for how it&amp;rsquo;s interacting with everyone else. In the case of a job, it will likely reflect those trying to complete it, whereas with a rumor it will most often represent the scope and fervor with which it is spread. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default for each die is a d6, but it may be any die along the usual die chain for reaction rolls (d4, d6, d8, d10, d12). Whichever dice are selected, note them separately next to the rumor (Such as &amp;ldquo;d4, d6&amp;rdquo; to indicate a rumor with a d4 source and a d6 world die).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checking Status&lt;/strong&gt;  For any rumor which you are checking, take out dice matching your source and world dice. If the same size, use two different colors and note which is which. Roll the dice and interpret using the same framework as a reaction roll, with lower pointing towards failure, falsehood, or complications, and higher pointing to success, resolution, or more truth. You can use the below table as a guide, but use your judgment based on the particular rumor or job. Change the rumor in your notes appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Size Changes&lt;/strong&gt;  If either die comes up a maximum result, step it up to the next die size for future rolls. If either die comes up a &amp;ldquo;1&amp;rdquo; step it down one size for future rolls. Update the dice in your notes for the rumor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Losing a Die&lt;/strong&gt;  If either die comes up a &amp;ldquo;1&amp;rdquo; on a d4, that die is removed. This will require some interpretation, and you should use the total of the roll to color that interpretation, but in the case of a source die, it will likely mean that either the true thing that inspired the rumor is resolved or that the rumor has been found to be totally false. For a job, the source die disappearing likely means that the person or group offering the job is no longer able or willing to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the world die, in the case of rumors, a lost die might mean that no one is talking about it anymore, or that the exaggeration around the core of truth has been discovered. For jobs, it likely means something has happened to someone or some group that tried to accomplish the job, but it might also mean that the situation has changed to make the job no longer workable (a time window has passed, better guards have been put in, and so forth). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use your judgment on whether the rumor or job should persist in some new form or be replaced in this case - again, use the total result of the roll to get some idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;examples--rumor--crabman-great-house-mud-known-for-its-great-artistic-sensitivity-and-wisdom-has-slipped-over-the-line-into-depravity-and-madness&#34;&gt;Examples  &lt;strong&gt;Rumor&lt;/strong&gt;  &amp;ldquo;Crabman Great House Mud, known for its great artistic sensitivity and wisdom, has slipped over the line into depravity and madness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source Die Represents: The intensity of the nugget of truth at the core of the rumor. In this case, one spawning has indeed come out off, but the rest of the house is trying to keep its members contained (some truth, but not as big a deal as the rumor says - d6)  World Die Represents: How much does the public care about this rumor (juicy enough to spread, not immediate enough to really grab you - d6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2: A full spawning of insane crabmen murdered several of their family members and escaped, hiding somewhere in the city, preying on their neighbors  3-5: House Mud is buying an unusually high number of thralls, at an alarming rate. What are they doing with them?  6-8: Nothing changes  9-11: House Mud has been quietly locking up some of their members for unnatural tastes  12+: The head spawning of House Mud completely wiped out the most recent spawning and has been quietly paying weregild to local families&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Job&lt;/strong&gt;  Biblook, a passionate crabman Sage of Soul Economics, is hilariously out of fashion on account of his insistence of affecting the look, mannerisms, and worldview of the Witch Kings of old, wants the humiliation of his mother, whom he accuses of plagiarism, and will in return grant whoever does so safe haven secured through his considerable wealth.  Source Die Represents: Biblook&amp;rsquo;s wealth, power, influence, and general ability to motivate something to get done (quite a lot, he&amp;rsquo;s a well paid consultant by Soul Banks and Witch Kings - d8)  World Die Represents: How much anyone else cares about his petty family/academic squabble and helping to resolve it (not much - d4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2: Biblook&amp;rsquo;s mother conclusively proves that her son&amp;rsquo;s work is entirely derivative of hers, major blow to prestige and livelihood  3-5: All of Biblook&amp;rsquo;s charges have brought extra scrutiny on his own materials, other sages are beginning to question their theoretical validity  6-8: Nothing changes  9-11: Biblook&amp;rsquo;s mother starts a smear campaign of her own, but it&amp;rsquo;s received as obviously desperate and in poor taste  12+: Biblook&amp;rsquo;s mother issues a public apology for her false claims, theories discredited, retires in disgrace  ### Design Notes &amp;amp; Considerations  So, as I mentioned above, this might be far too fiddly. The good news is that I think it ought to &amp;ldquo;fail gracefully&amp;rdquo; like Apocalypse World - if you ditch the usage dice, you lose out on the dynamic of things happening to the actors involved, but you still have different chances for success or failure. If you skip the different die sizes, you miss out on differentiating between rumors/jobs chances to resolve, but you still have a way to make living modifications. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t do any of it, you still have rumors to supply flavor and adventure hooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of judgment calls to make here, but I hope that the rolls provide enough structure to the improvisation to keep things interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2018-08-22-managing-living-world-with-flexible/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>GLOG Instant Character Generator</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-08-20-glog-instant-character-generator/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 08:03:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-08-20-glog-instant-character-generator/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-08-20-glog-instant-character-generator/ -&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a character generator for Arnold&amp;rsquo;s excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/05/the-glog.html&#34;&gt;GLOG&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty jazzed about it. To use, simply set the toggles at the top to any inputs you want specified (or leave them random) and it&amp;rsquo;ll spit out a fully fledged character. Goes from levels 1 to 20. If you want to set Level, Class, or anything else (instead of random), you&amp;rsquo;ll need to make a copy on your own Drive or download it. Check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Or open in its own tab &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1jsdfz7WGcVoFsd4KEGcYsyN8PFpExFddB1Qhtc7gPmw/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Races are Arnold&amp;rsquo;s and come from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/12/designing-races.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2013/10/i-killed-all-humans.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classes are also Arnold&amp;rsquo;s and come from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/05/the-glog.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/09/the-glog-wizards.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Random items are also also Arnold&amp;rsquo;s and comes from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2017/06/adventuring-gear-alchemy-items.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Names, some of the looks, and some of the quirks are from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/197158/Maze-Rats&#34;&gt;Maze
Rats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by Ben
Milton&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic methodology from Brendan S
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.necropraxis.com/2018/07/22/random-table-format-wars/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-modify-for-your-own-nefarious-purposes--first-learn-the-basics--1-read-brendans-explanation-of-the-underlying-method-herehttpwwwnecropraxiscom20180722random-table-format-wars-------next-create-your-own-copy-to-work-in--1-either-download-the-sheethttpsdocsgooglecomspreadsheetsd1jsdfz7wgcvofsd4kegcysyn8pfpexfddb1qhtc7gpmwedituspsharingas-an-exel-file-or-else-make-a-copy-on-your-own-drive-so-that-you-can-edit-it&#34;&gt;How to Modify for Your Own Nefarious Purposes  &lt;strong&gt;First, Learn the Basics&lt;/strong&gt;  1. Read Brendan&amp;rsquo;s explanation of the underlying method &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.necropraxis.com/2018/07/22/random-table-format-wars/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;  **   **  &lt;strong&gt;Next, Create Your Own Copy to Work In&lt;/strong&gt;  1. Either download the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1jsdfz7WGcVoFsd4KEGcYsyN8PFpExFddB1Qhtc7gPmw/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;sheet&lt;/a&gt;as an Exel file or else Make a Copy on your own Drive so that you can edit it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If You Modify An Existing Table&lt;/strong&gt;  Make sure you double check that the named range it&amp;rsquo;s a part of covers your changed entries and no empty space. All named ranges correspond to the title at the top of the range (except with real spaces instead of underscores)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If You Want to Add an Entirely New Table&lt;/strong&gt;  Make some space for it on the &amp;ldquo;Character&amp;rdquo; tab, then follow Brendan&amp;rsquo;s instructions above&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If You Want to Add a New Race&lt;/strong&gt;  1. Create a new column  2. Use the top row to label it &amp;ldquo;[NAME] Race Template&amp;rdquo;  3. Put all racial information in cell immediately below that  4. Click on cell, then click the &amp;ldquo;Data&amp;rdquo; menu and select &amp;ldquo;Named Ranges&amp;rdquo;  5. Select &amp;ldquo;Add a Range&amp;rdquo;, title it &amp;ldquo;[NAME]&lt;em&gt;Race_Template&amp;rdquo; - for example &amp;ldquo;Ratman_Race_Template&amp;rdquo;  6. Add the name of the race to the &amp;ldquo;Races&amp;rdquo; table. Make sure any spaces are underscores &amp;ldquo;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; - example: &amp;ldquo;Iron_Ghost_Men&amp;rdquo;  7. Check to make sure the &amp;ldquo;Races&amp;rdquo; named range includes your new name, modify it to include if needed  8. If the race modifies any stats (attributes, move, stealth, et cetera), you&amp;rsquo;ll have to modify the appropriate stat output to look for that race name in &amp;ldquo;Race_Output&amp;rdquo; with a conditional&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If You Want to Add a New Class&lt;/strong&gt;  1. Create a new column  2. Use the top cell to label it &amp;ldquo;[Name] Class Templates&amp;rdquo;  3. In first through fourth cell, put Templates A, B, C, D for that class. I recommend you just put the names of the abilities, not a full explanation  4. In the fifth cell, put the class&amp;rsquo;s Prime Ability  5. In the sixth cell, put the class&amp;rsquo;s Starting Equipment  6. In the seventh cell, if the class allows for spellcasting, put &amp;ldquo;TRUE&amp;rdquo;  7. Highlight the cells you just filled and click on &amp;ldquo;Add a Range&amp;rdquo; (Data&amp;gt;Named Ranges) and name it &amp;ldquo;[NAME]_Class_Templates&amp;rdquo; - note the plural (for example &amp;ldquo;Fighter_Class_Templates&amp;rdquo;)  8. Add the class name to the Classes table, being sure to use underscores for any spaces, then check to make sure the &amp;ldquo;Classes&amp;rdquo; named range covers it  9. Under these seven cells, create a label for &amp;ldquo;[Class Name] Skills&amp;rdquo;  10. On the three rows below, write in the three background skill options for this class to begin with  11. Name the three skill range &amp;ldquo;[Class Name]_Skills&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If You Add a Spellcaster and Want to Add Their Spells&lt;/strong&gt;  1. Create a new column  2. Label it &amp;ldquo;[Class Name] Spells&amp;rdquo;  3. Add spells in cells 1-14  4. Select list of spells and &amp;ldquo;Add a Range&amp;rdquo; (Data&amp;gt;Named Ranges), naming it &amp;ldquo;[Class Name]_Spell_List&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes-and-assumptions&#34;&gt;Notes and Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your &amp;ldquo;primary&amp;rdquo; class is assumed to the one you have the most
templates in, and in the case of a tie, the one you had first&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Spells&amp;rdquo; are assumed to accumulate at one per level, and I have not
been able to figure out how to prevent duplicates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This &amp;ldquo;effective levels&amp;rdquo; nonsense was my stop-gap way of making sure
that multi-class spellcasters don&amp;rsquo;t have oodles and oodles of spells
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it multiplies your level times the number of templates out of 4
you have in that class, and then assumes you have that many levels
worth of spells from the template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Duplicate spells are quite possible - feel free to either re-roll or
assume duplicates are wasted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No matter the level, every character starts with first level gear -
you might want to adjust if you&amp;rsquo;re creating higher level characters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characters are assumed to have the minimum experience for the level
selected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characters get 3 skills at level 1 and then up to their level in
random skills at a random rank capped by level - if any skill comes
up a &amp;ldquo;0&amp;rdquo;, then no further skills are known&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Class Templates, rows 1-4 are what you get for each level of a
class you take, Row 5 is the Prime Ability for that class, and Row 6
is the class&amp;rsquo;s starting equipment, Row 7 specifies whether it&amp;rsquo;s a
spellcasting class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This does not yet calculate encumbrance or assign gear to slots,
sorry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The other pain in the ass thing to modify will be the stats that are
upgraded by different class templates (Movement, Initiative,
Stealth, HP, Save) - removing classes won&amp;rsquo;t hurt the calculations,
but if you add new classes that modify stats, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to do that
manually. I could have done a stat line modification per template,
but there werent enough to make it seem worthwhile, and doing the
&amp;ldquo;every two templates&amp;rdquo; thing would have been challenging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I went ahead and made Dog a race template and removed it from the
first level template for &amp;ldquo;Really Good Dog&amp;rdquo; and made &amp;ldquo;Really Good
Dog&amp;rdquo; the only playable class for that race. This does currently have
the effect of making Really Good Dog slightly more common than it
would be if it was random among the classes (more classes than
races), which I&amp;rsquo;m fine with. If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to play a dog, just
reroll. Also, if you specify a class but go for a random Race, you
may end up with &amp;ldquo;Really Good Dog&amp;rdquo; instead of your specified class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most classes don&amp;rsquo;t have a prime ability because that&amp;rsquo;s something
Arnold came up with after putting out the Martial classes. I thought
about inventing my own, but decided to go &amp;ldquo;by the book&amp;rdquo; for now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The different wizards can only get spells 1-6 at level 1, 1-8 at
level 2, 1-10 at level 3, and 1-12 at level 4 and beyond. I
arbitrarily decided that level 19 and 20 characters have a shot at
the Legendary spells (13 and 14)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- /gaming/2018-08-20-glog-instant-character-generator/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Creative Problem Solving Types in D&amp;D</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-08-09-creative-problem-solving-types-in-d/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 15:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-08-09-creative-problem-solving-types-in-d/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-08-09-creative-problem-solving-types-in-d/ -&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see &lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7B%20site.baseurl%20%7D%7D%7B%25%20post_url%202019-02-12-removing-support-from-zak-smith%20%25%7D&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be the first to admit that a lot of the frameworks, methodologies, and concepts that come out of the business world are shallow nonsense. Anytime I hear the word &amp;ldquo;synergy&amp;rdquo;, I can&amp;rsquo;t help but hear in my head &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qRuNxHqwazs&#34;&gt;SYNERGY&lt;/a&gt;. That being said, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share one that I believe provides a useful model for identifying and thinking about how different folks approach the creative process. Below, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone through and applied that to RPGs for both GMs/Designers and for players. As always, questions and comments are most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;brief-overview-of-the-basadur-applied-creativity-framework--the-basadur-applied-creativity-frameworkhttpwwwbasadurcomwas-developed-by-dr-min-basadur-and-details-both-an-eight-step-creative-problem-solving-process-and-four-problem-solving-preference-types-were-going-to-be-talking-about-the-problem-solving-types-today-but-if-you-find-this-interesting-i-urge-you-to-check-out-the-website-to-learn-more-one-of-the-great-things-about-this-framework-and-one-that-makes-it-especially-relevant-to-rpgs-is-that-it-focuses-on-groupproblem-solving-where-many-how-to-be-creative-approaches-look-only-at-individual-creativity&#34;&gt;Brief Overview of the Basadur Applied Creativity Framework  The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basadur.com/&#34;&gt;Basadur Applied Creativity Framework&lt;/a&gt; was developed by Dr. Min Basadur and details both an eight-step creative problem solving process and four problem-solving preference types. We&amp;rsquo;re going to be talking about the problem-solving types today, but if you find this interesting, I urge you to check out the website to learn more. One of the great things about this framework, and one that makes it especially relevant to RPGs, is that it focuses on &lt;em&gt;group&lt;/em&gt; problem solving, where many &amp;ldquo;how to be creative&amp;rdquo; approaches look only at individual creativity. &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-framework-for-the-profiles--first-off-a-caveat-these-profiles-are-not-personality-types-none-of-them-is-better-than-the-others-and-no-one-is-confined-to-only-one-everyone-can-and-does-use-each-of-the-four-types-but-almost-everybody-has-a-strong-preference-for-one-type-and-finds-that-piece-of-problem-solvingcreativity-easier-than-others&#34;&gt;The Framework for the Profiles  First off, a caveat: these profiles are not &amp;ldquo;personality types&amp;rdquo;, none of them is better than the others, and no one is confined to only one. Everyone can and does use each of the four types, but almost everybody has a strong preference for one type and finds that piece of problem-solving/creativity easier than others.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This model is built on two axes: Generate-Evaluate and Action-Knowledge. &amp;ldquo;Generate&amp;rdquo; refers to folks&amp;rsquo; preference for coming up with ideas - think &amp;ldquo;brainstorming&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Evaluate&amp;rdquo; refers to looking at ideas and judging them against criteria - think looking at the long list of things brainstormed and picking the good ones. &amp;ldquo;Action&amp;rdquo; describes a preference for &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; something like writing, manipulating, experimenting, moving to learn about the challenge, where &amp;ldquo;Knowledge&amp;rdquo; refers to a preference for research, abstract thinking, and analysis. Put the two together and folks fall into one of the quadrants pictured above and described below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;applying-the-profiles-to-rpgs--one-benefit-this-approach-has-compared-to-some-player-types-stuff-is-that-its-empirically-backed-another-is-that-it-profitably-suggests-how-the-types-can-work-together-to-make-something-better-together-zak-and-others-have-already-pointed-out-how-great-rpgs-can-be-for-allowing-multiple-levels-of-engagementhttpdndwithpornstarsblogspotcom201001how-much-do-you-want-to-be-wizard_15html-but-this-framework-goes-in-a-slightly-different-direction-by-talking-not-about-engagement-per-se-but-rather-what-pieces-of-problems-are-rather-to-make-certain-folks-sit-up-and-take-notice-each-of-the-profiles-is-listed-with-what-they-find-easyenjoyable-along-with-some-stuff-that-they-might-find-challenging-ill-note-again-that-you-can-train-yourself-to-get-over-these-challenges&#34;&gt;Applying the Profiles to RPGs  One benefit this approach has compared to some &amp;ldquo;player types&amp;rdquo; stuff is that it&amp;rsquo;s empirically backed. Another is that it profitably suggests how the types can &lt;em&gt;work together to make something better together&lt;/em&gt;. Zak and others have already pointed out how great RPGs can be for &lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/2010/01/how-much-do-you-want-to-be-wizard_15.html&#34;&gt;allowing multiple levels of engagement&lt;/a&gt;, but this framework goes in a slightly different direction by talking not about engagement per-se, but rather what pieces of problems are rather to make certain folks sit up and take notice. Each of the profiles is listed with what they find easy/enjoyable, along with some stuff that they might find challenging. I&amp;rsquo;ll note again that you can train yourself to get over these challenges.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a note, my analysis here assumes a fairly OSR-ish &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/02/osr-style-challenges-rulings-not-rules.html&#34;&gt;challenge-based&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; approach to play, where actual problem-solving will be a big part of the game. For games with a more narrative/emotional bent, your mileage may vary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;ve included some names and links to folks who I think might lean towards these styles, but this may vary for the same person when they&amp;rsquo;re a player versus a GM, and they are based on nothing but my own reading blogs, play reports, and occasional shared online sessions. Pure speculation on my part. Note &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; that any of the challenges given for the profiles aren&amp;rsquo;t being imputed to the examples I name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generator&lt;/strong&gt;   Generators are the people who looked at 1d100 tables and asked &amp;ldquo;why not 1d1000?&amp;rdquo; Having a preference for Action and Generation (surprise), these folks like to come up with any and every possible idea related to the matter at hand. Or maybe not related. Their problem is not coming up with stuff, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;stopping&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a GM/Designer/Blogger&lt;/em&gt;: Astounding new material, often with a lot of variation. Stuff where you ask yourself &amp;ldquo;how did they come up with that?&amp;rdquo; Perhaps some trouble following through with getting those astounding ideas into a finished form because they found something else new and awesome that they had to get out of their head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a Player&lt;/em&gt;: A million schemes. &amp;ldquo;Oh wait, but we could also. . .&amp;rdquo; Delights in the openness and possibility of a whole imaginary world where they could try something. Deeply torn between going to Voivoidja, Yoon-Suin, or the Swordfish Isles. Once they get there, will have an endless font of ways to engage with the place. Might have some trouble settling on just one, and might respond to attempts by the rest of the group to settle on something and get on with it with &amp;ldquo;oh, wait, but what about [something totally new to consider].&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Folks I Suspect Might Lean This Way&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://middenmurk.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Tom Fitzgerald&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://maziriansgarden.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Ben L.&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://monstermanualsewnfrompants.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Scrap Princess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptualizer&lt;/strong&gt;   Preferring to generate ideas through analytical thought and abstract thinking, conceptualizers tend to enjoy taking one hazily defined thought and then dig into it and find every nook and cranny of that idea. &amp;ldquo;What if the dungeon really &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; have a functioning ecology?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;What would a society look like where everyone was psychic?&amp;rdquo; These folks often have whiteboards or other ways to easily visualize/mind-map stuff always at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a GM/Designer/Blogger&lt;/em&gt;: Deeply interesting stuff that starts from a fairly simple premise. Finding the bizarro logic that underlies something seemingly gonzo. Picking something they know they like and figuring out what makes it tick. Scenarios that present lots of open-ended challenge just from taking the implications of something seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a Player&lt;/em&gt;: Once a scheme/course of action has been picked, figuring out all of the angles, every contingency that might work. Thinking about all the ways we might break into the castle to get to the archpriest. Asking the GM about the logic that &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be behind the detail they were given. May have some tendency toward completionism, wanting to see every room, find every secret, learn every nuance. Might have some trouble looking at the &lt;em&gt;effectiveness&lt;/em&gt; of potential plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Folks I Suspect Might Lean This Way&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Zak S.&lt;/a&gt; (with strong Generator leanings?), &lt;a href=&#34;http://falsemachine.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Patrick Stuart&lt;/a&gt; (as a Blogger/Designer), &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Arnold Kemp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://monstersandmanuals.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;David McGrogan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimizer&lt;/strong&gt;   Here we move over from the &amp;ldquo;generator&amp;rdquo; types to the &amp;ldquo;evaluator&amp;rdquo; types. Optimizers find it much easier to look at an existing set of ideas/thoughts/evidence and group them, rank them, or cut them. Editors rather than writers. Like conceptualizers, they prefer to work with research and abstract thinking, but instead of figuring out &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; nuance of a certain concept, they want to find the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a GM/Designer/Blogger&lt;/em&gt;: Likely a lot of thoughtful, nuanced discussion on mechanics, as those are easy to test and tweak and make &amp;ldquo;better.&amp;rdquo; Might take published content and carefully curate/hack it to fit into their conceptually-consistent world. Possibly write insightful and detailed reviews, with lots of material on how it could have been better. Might find it challenging to come up with mind-blowingly original stuff from scratch. Might get lost trying to make something &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; before putting it into their game/getting it published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a Player&lt;/em&gt;: Will lovingly plan the heist. When the Generator says we could kidnap the archpriest, rip off the brewers&amp;rsquo; guild, sail to the new world, or become famous artists, and the Conceptualizer finds 10 different ways into the archpriest&amp;rsquo;s castle, the Optimizer looks at them and goes &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s do this one. And here&amp;rsquo;s how. We know the guards are on this schedule, the lighting is like this. . .&amp;rdquo; Will come up with and share the best tactics against certain foes with the party. Will find the most lucrative ways to spend treasure. Might tend toward min/maxing. Might get frustrated with non-&amp;ldquo;optimal&amp;rdquo; decisions by fellow adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Folks I Suspect Might Lean This Way&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://thealexandrian.net/&#34;&gt;Jason Alexander&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.necropraxis.com/&#34;&gt;Brendan S&lt;/a&gt;, Myself, &lt;a href=&#34;http://dungeonofsigns.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Gus L&lt;/a&gt;(?), &lt;a href=&#34;https://diyanddragons.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Anne Hunter&lt;/a&gt; (but maybe more conceptualizer?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implementer&lt;/strong&gt;   Finally, we have the people that wonder why can&amp;rsquo;t we just get the damn thing done. Implementers prefer to evaluate by way of more tangible action - try it, see what happens, adjust, try it again. Doers. Often the driving force that keeps the other three types from getting lost in their particular preference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a GM/Designer/Blogger&lt;/em&gt;: Shut up and let&amp;rsquo;s play! Might make heavy use of published modules or settings. Might not worry too much about the aesthetic perfection or coherency of their world and more about &lt;em&gt;but does it affect play&lt;/em&gt;? Will build tools ruthlessly whittled down to what is needed at the table. More likely to create interesting content based on giving the players buttons to push than to flesh out the fictional world in great detail. Might find it challenging to make a rich, vivid setting. Might not give some players the chance to plan and scheme deeply that they&amp;rsquo;re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(There might not be that many Implementer bloggers, as blogging is inherently kind of navel-gazey).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a Player&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;ldquo;Fuck this, I stab the guy.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;I pull the lever.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Great, yeah, what was the last thing you said? The tomb? Yeah, let&amp;rsquo;s go rob that, it&amp;rsquo;ll be awesome.&amp;rdquo; This style of play can sometimes get a bad rap, but it &lt;em&gt;makes the game happen&lt;/em&gt;. In a world of buttons to push, levers to pull, and structures to topple, the Implementer player will make the chaos that gives all the other types interesting situations to think about and chew on. Likely less concerned with succeeding the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; way as with &lt;em&gt;getting to the challenge so we can beat it&lt;/em&gt;. Might cause some heartburn to other problem-solving types by mucking up their assumptions. Might bite off more than they or the party can chew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Folks I Suspect Might Lean This Way&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://tenfootpolemic.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Patrick Young&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://falsemachine.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Patrick Stuart&lt;/a&gt; (as a player), &lt;a href=&#34;http://rememberdismove.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Dunkey Halton&lt;/a&gt;(?), &lt;a href=&#34;http://jrients.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Jeff Rients&lt;/a&gt; (?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;putting-it-all-together--the-beauty-of-this-framework-is-that-to-most-effectively-solve-problems-you-need-to-do-all-of-the-things-that-the-different-types-find-easyenjoyable-some-folks-find-it-easier-to-switch-between-one-mode-and-another-but-if-you-have-a-group-where-different-people-excel-at-different-parts-of-the-problem-solving-process-and-they-know-about-it-you-can-start-consciously-taking-advantage-of-it-right-then-alice-generator-will-come-up-with-ten-possible-schemes-bob-conceptualizer-will-then-flesh-out-the-details-on-what-we-all-think-the-top-3-are-carolyn-optimizer-will-take-the-one-we-pick-out-of-those-and-streamline-it-and-daryl-implementer-will-kick-our-asses-into-gear-with-getting-it-done-theres-more-to-the-problem-solving-method-applied-creativity-teaches-but-i-can-write-about-that-another-time-if-anybodys-interested&#34;&gt;Putting It All Together  The beauty of this framework is that to most effectively solve problems, you need to do all of the things that the different types find easy/enjoyable. Some folks find it easier to switch between one mode and another, but if you have a group where different people excel at different parts of the problem-solving process, and they know about it,  you can start consciously taking advantage of it: &amp;ldquo;Right then, Alice [Generator] will come up with ten possible schemes, Bob [Conceptualizer] will then flesh out the details on what we all think the top 3 are, Carolyn [Optimizer] will take the one we pick out of those and streamline it, and Daryl [Implementer] will kick our asses into gear with getting it done.&amp;rdquo; There&amp;rsquo;s more to the problem-solving method Applied Creativity teaches, but I can write about that another time if anybody&amp;rsquo;s interested.&lt;/h3&gt;
- /gaming/2018-08-09-creative-problem-solving-types-in-d/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>&#34;The Sages Say&#34; Monster Generator</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/ -&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a thing that makes monsters. I&amp;rsquo;m terribly pleased with it right now, but let me know what you think. If the embed below is giving you weird formatting (on a phone or tablet, say), or if you just want to mess with it, check out the sheet &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/10IPuObMhs2Tajf79ewc5tUKsfOrwG0fCdLS_T62U7ZU/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used Brendan&amp;rsquo;s excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.necropraxis.com/2018/07/22/random-table-format-wars/&#34;&gt;methodology&lt;/a&gt; to build it in Google Sheets. Every time you refresh this page, you should get a new result. If you open it up as a sheet, you&amp;rsquo;ll get a new result whenever you refresh the page. If you make a copy for yourself that you can edit, you&amp;rsquo;ll get a new result whenever you make a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-got-here--this-all-started-because-i-was-trying-to-think-up-monsters-for-fellholdhttpblessingsofthedicegodsblogspotcomsearchlabelfellholdand-im-kind-of-bad-at-that-the-monster-forgehttpwwwthewinglesscomforgeforgehtm-is-awesome-but-still-puts-most-of-the-heavy-lifting-on-me-so-i-started-looking-through-various-monster-manuals-to-get-ideas-as-i-took-notes-it-struck-me-that-i-could-decompose-what-i-found-cool-about-monsters-that-caught-my-attention-into-elements-of-some-kind-then-id-be-able-to-create-a-generator-so-i-switched-my-notes-over-to-excel-i-arbitrarily-picked-six-things-i-had-to-write-down-about-each-monster-and-purposely-did-not-create-categories-until-after-i-had-gone-through-all-the-monsters-in-my-list-then-i-took-each-line-item-and-copypasted-it-into-a-column-if-i-felt-like-they-went-togetherhttpsgeneralassemblydesignuser-experience-designaffinity-mapping-once-everything-had-a-home-i-smashed-some-columns-together-removed-others-and-ended-up-labeling-each-of-them&#34;&gt;How I Got Here  This all started because I was trying to think up monsters for &lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/search/label/Fellhold&#34;&gt;Fellhold&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;rsquo;m kind of bad at that. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thewingless.com/forge/forge.htm&#34;&gt;Monster Forge&lt;/a&gt; is awesome, but still puts most of the heavy lifting on me. So I started looking through various monster manuals to get ideas. As I took notes, it struck me that I could decompose what I found cool about monsters that caught my attention into elements of some kind, then I&amp;rsquo;d be able to create a generator. So I switched my notes over to excel. I arbitrarily picked six &amp;ldquo;things&amp;rdquo; I had to write down about each monster and purposely did not create categories until after I had gone through all the monsters in my list. Then I took each line item and copy/pasted it into a column if I felt like they &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://generalassemb.ly/design/user-experience-design/affinity-mapping&#34;&gt;went together&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. Once everything had a home, I smashed some columns together, removed others, and ended up labeling each of them. &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere around here I recalled David McGrogan&amp;rsquo;s epic &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://monstersandmanuals.blogspot.com/2014/05/housekeeping.html&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Read the 2E Monstrous Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; thread and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lulu.com/shop/patrick-stuart-and-scrap-princess/fire-on-the-velvet-horizon/paperback/product-23550253.html&#34;&gt;Fire on the Velvet Horizon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://falsemachine.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Patrick&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://monstermanualsewnfrompants.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Scrap&lt;/a&gt;. Both make much of &amp;ldquo;the sages&amp;rdquo; that tell us things in monster manuals and how it&amp;rsquo;s a really weird but very effective way to write about stuff in a book that is simultaneously giving you the god-like &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; of the world but also trying to inspire you. So I figured that I&amp;rsquo;d arrange the generator into a natural language sentence flavored as if a sage were telling you about this thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great thing about this approach was that it let me hit a sweet spot between providing enough concrete detail to get your imagination going but also enough vagueness that it&amp;rsquo;s psychologically easier to ignore or massage any outright contradictory or uncool stuff that happens to come up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wanted this to be fairly usable, though, so after I got the natural language bit worked out, I went back and added some stats. I had grand ideas about tying these into all of the abilities and behaviors, but a) that&amp;rsquo;s not all that helpful, as thinking up stats once you have the idea isn&amp;rsquo;t too hard, and b) I couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure out how to do it at all cleanly. So, what we ended up with was size affecting HD and AC, and whether some kind of humanoid came up in the type putting a lower limit on intelligence and animals shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get weapons as attack types, but other than that, the stats are randomly determined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;design-notes&#34;&gt;Design Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The core of the description is one or sometimes two monster or
animal base types - I did this to maximize the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/2009/10/imaginable-monsters-sci-fi-monsters-etc.html?zx=14c3c88963fb2fde&#34;&gt;imaginability&lt;/a&gt;,
but also because I wanted something a little more naturalistic than
James Raggi&amp;rsquo;s (excellent, but super random) &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/58916/Random-Esoteric-Creature-Generator-for-Classic-Fantasy-RolePlaying-Games-and-their-Modern-Simulacra&#34;&gt;Random Esoteric
Creature
Generator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, it&amp;rsquo;s not as comprehensive as it might be, because my input
monsters were all ones that I felt would fit in Fellhold, which is
pretty aesthetically restricted compared to &amp;ldquo;kitchen sink&amp;rdquo; D&amp;amp;D - I
ended up adding a few things in that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily &amp;ldquo;fit&amp;rdquo; in
Fellhold, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t try to capture all of D&amp;amp;D&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That being said, it should be pretty easy to adapt this to your own
game world by changing up which origins, animal types, abilities,
behaviors, and so forth are in the random tables - feel free to
contact me if any of the formulas are unclear for customizing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the entries (size, intelligence, combat stats) have
normal(ish) distributions, so you&amp;rsquo;re a little less likely to get
totally gonzo stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the stats, I normalized them around a B/X Grizzly Bear,
following Jack Shear&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;http://talesofthegrotesqueanddungeonesque.blogspot.com/2016/08/just-use-bears.html&#34;&gt;advice&lt;/a&gt;,
so you might need to beef up a solo monster for 5E or higher levels,
or reduce stats if you&amp;rsquo;re going for an organized and intelligent
monster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I totally pulled the No. Appearing numbers out of my hat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used descending AC cos that&amp;rsquo;s how I roll - I figure we&amp;rsquo;re all used
to converting back and forth by now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the monsters that come out will be somewhat unpleasant and
hostile, so this isn&amp;rsquo;t a great generator for coming up with more
sympathetic or neutral creatures. If you want that sort of thing,
just ignore the motivations/internal state and maybe the behavior
and come up with your own&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything of human level intelligence or more is more likely to have
weapons listed as attacks than animal-type attacks, which may give
some weird results - as with everything else, ignore if necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- /gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>OSR Classes: The Mastermind and the Rook</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 08:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/ -&lt;p&gt;After my last post on &lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/2018/07/flexible-reaction-rolls.html&#34;&gt;Flexible Reaction Rolls&lt;/a&gt;, I found myself thinking about how to build Character Classes that fit with the schemey, urban style of play I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for with Fellhold. The trouble for me until now was that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t think of ways to get that stuff without impinging on the Old School playstyle I enjoy. What cracked it for me was turning the Reaction Roll into a mechanic with more knobs to play with. From there I also realized that Advantage/Disadvantage opened up a lot of new possibilities, and so I built one class on each of those realizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-V0v1CmEJWQk/W09SgXeKcPI/AAAAAAAAG80/cDAOvhNljqsyNz_Hr5fn2njlNZvHDxvhQCLcBGAs/s1600/johnhannibalsmith.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-V0v1CmEJWQk/W09SgXeKcPI/AAAAAAAAG80/cDAOvhNljqsyNz_Hr5fn2njlNZvHDxvhQCLcBGAs/s320/johnhannibalsmith.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Mastermind&lt;/strong&gt; is the classic brains behind the operation. It struck me that advantage/disadvantage are a pretty great way to model careful planning without having to go full-on storygame metagame city. Their first level ability &lt;em&gt;Forethought&lt;/em&gt; can potentially be quite powerful, but requires clever thinking and skill on the player&amp;rsquo;s part. Their final ability (&amp;ldquo;I Love It When A Plan Comes Together&amp;rdquo;) &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get awfully close to the storygamey end of things, and might in reality just be &amp;ldquo;use in case of boss fight&amp;rdquo; - but I&amp;rsquo;ll test it. The class also serves as a secondary adventure hook generator through the extra contacts, their starting gear, and their second level class ability (&amp;ldquo;A Little Bird Told Me&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-JJ_pVBuIi4E/W09S0CswnBI/AAAAAAAAG88/1zmU_pQ4h5c_UM0jU5rrowlssU0n9O-ZwCLcBGAs/s1600/Dirk-benedict-the-a-team.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-JJ_pVBuIi4E/W09S0CswnBI/AAAAAAAAG88/1zmU_pQ4h5c_UM0jU5rrowlssU0n9O-ZwCLcBGAs/s320/Dirk-benedict-the-a-team.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Rook&lt;/strong&gt; is &amp;ldquo;the face&amp;rdquo; - hyper-sociable, built around understanding and tweaking NPC reactions. Getting +1 to reaction rolls per two templates is &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; (especially when combined with the class features) and kind of guarantees this character will speak for the party all the time - I haven&amp;rsquo;t decided if that means I need to remove it or if that&amp;rsquo;s awesome. This class pretty much has super powers in one area that has very little to do with fighting, which right now seems pretty cool. Someone with 4 levels in Rook becomes a best-friend factory and basically gives the party an off-switch for combat with anybody even possibly open to parley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Incidentally, if you&amp;rsquo;re following the classic trinity of group dynamics, I figure PCs will collectively provide the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MYtjpIwamos&#34;&gt;wild card&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting equipment is stingier than in &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/05/the-glog.html&#34;&gt;Arnold&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://coinsandscrolls.blogspot.com/2017/10/the-index.html&#34;&gt;Skerples&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; classes, but that&amp;rsquo;s because I plan on building them into my &lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/2018/07/money-equipment-in-fellhold.html&#34;&gt;Equipment Tables&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi-classing 2/2 with these two classes might be terrifyingly powerful in social situations, but I think I&amp;rsquo;m okay with that, given the usual lack of options for that sort of thing in OSR classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Note on Mechanics&lt;/strong&gt;   If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar, &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/05/the-glog.html&#34;&gt;Arnold K&amp;rsquo;s GLOG&lt;/a&gt; is his homebrew/Philosopher&amp;rsquo;s Stone, and I rather like it. See the link if the format below doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not use this most excellent modification, fear not! The classes below have a &amp;ldquo;base class&amp;rdquo; - use this for XP, HD, Saves, Attack Bonus, gear restrictions, and so on. As for the class abilities, you have a few options:   - Follow the same steep, ultimately low power curve of the GLOG and give one template per level up to 4   - For a more spaced out progression that assumes 10th level is about as high as you go, give the prime ability at level 1 and then a template every odd level (1, 3, 5, 7, 9)   - Look at the templates and eyeball when to give them to the character to match the power level of your other classes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough intro, here are the classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastermind  Clever folks who think ahead and help their team get things done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Base Class: Thief)  Prime Ability: Meddlesome  Per Template: +1 Willpower Save, +1 Contact  Starting Equipment: Disguise Kit, Incriminating Letter  A Forethought  B A Little Bird Told Me  C True Sight  D I Love It When a Plan Comes Together&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Class Features  MEDDLESOME  Once per day, you may give another character (PC or NPC) advice. If they follow it, you may decide to give them either &lt;em&gt;Advantage&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Disadvantage&lt;/em&gt; on one roll related to the advice. To give &lt;em&gt;Advantage&lt;/em&gt;, the advice must be sound and something that either you or your character know enough about to advise on. To give &lt;em&gt;Disadvantage&lt;/em&gt;, they must believe it to be good, but there must be something wrong with it (convincing bullshit counts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FORETHOUGHT  Choose one or more of the following: activity, place, being, conditions. For each that you specify, gain one use of &lt;em&gt;Advantage&lt;/em&gt; on rolls that meet all of the criteria. For example, if you said “Hand to hand fighting in an alley with humans while its raining”, you would get advantage on four rolls involving hand-to-hand fighting with humans in an alley in the rain. The GM may rule that any of the criteria are too broad and require more specificity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A LITTLE BIRD TOLD ME  Once per week, choose one: 1) Name a known NPC and the GM will tell you one true secret about them, which might be boring,  2) Learn a juicy rumor about a previously unknown NPC - might be true, might not, and the identity might be unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TRUE SIGHT  As long as you can see their face, you always know when someone is lying to you - not necessarily about what &lt;em&gt;specifically&lt;/em&gt;, just that there is untruth there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I LOVE IT WHEN A PLAN COMES TOGETHER  Once per adventure or dungeon, you can declare that you’ve been planning for this very situation all along. Everyone in the group gets advantage on every roll this round. Gain an extra round of this if you come up with an especially convincing narrative of how you influenced prior actions to lead to this outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rook  Affable folks that know how to say just what others want to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Base Class Thief, or Bard if You Have It)   Prime Ability: Read Folks  Per Template: +1 to Reaction Rolls for every &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; templates, rounded down, +1 Contact  Starting Equipment: Flattering Clothes, Disguise Kit, Invitation to a Shindig  A Well Read  B Likable  C Tempting  D Charming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Class Features  READ FOLKS  You have an uncanny knack for seeing what folks are thinking and feeling. Once per a meeting, you can ask the GM what the NPC die will be on the next reaction roll if you take a certain approach, make a given argument, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WELL READ  You know lots of interesting things to talk about. Any time you make a knowledge-based test in a social situation, you count as having the skill at rank 3. Note that you only know enough to talk &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; these things, not to &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; anything with them. You could have a wonderful conversation about quadratic equations with a mathematician, but you could not then plot ballistic parabola.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LIKABLE  When the GM makes a reaction roll where you are the spokesman, your PC die will be one step higher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TEMPTING  If you put the moves on someone amenable to your advances, and a reaction roll comes up middling or better, they are very attracted to you, which will color their reactions to you (improved reaction rolls, more willing to hear you out, and so forth). Note that it does not guarantee they will &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; you, just want you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CHARMING  Once per week, you can declare you are laying the charm on thick before a reaction roll is rolled. If the roll comes up pretty good or better, they are affected as &lt;em&gt;Charm Person&lt;/em&gt;. If after a week you haven’t done anything to push them away or piss them off, the friendship becomes genuine. Add them as a contact.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Flexible Reaction Rolls</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 11:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/ -&lt;p&gt;Reaction rolls are one of my very favorite set of rules. They&amp;rsquo;re quick, easy, and help me to come up with more interesting stuff than I might on my own. I use them as a general purpose social sub-system, though not nearly to the same extent as &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackslashmaster.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Courtney Campbell&lt;/a&gt; in his excellent &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lulu.com/us/en/shop/courtney-campbell/on-the-non-player-character/ebook/product-21094127.html&#34;&gt;On the Non-Player Character&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, I use them more as an oracle when I&amp;rsquo;m unsure of how the NPCs would react. With Fellhold being an urban game, social interaction is even more of a big deal than I like for it to be in dungeon or wilderness games, so I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about them a lot recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was while trying to figure out how best to track PC&amp;rsquo;s reputations with different factions that I hit on the core idea below: the PC(s) and the NPC(s) each &amp;ldquo;bring&amp;rdquo; a die to the roll. A couple years back, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lastgaspgrimoire.com/&#34;&gt;Logan Knight&lt;/a&gt; suggested I move reaction rolls up and down die steps (so, say, 2d4, 1d4+1d6, 2d6, 1d6+1d8, and so forth). Then the other week I read Mateo Diaz&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://gloomtrain.blogspot.com/2018/04/this-isnt-even-my-final-form.html&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, which introduced me to the idea of having different sources for the two dice. What you see below is what I came up with based on all that. As always, let me know anything that doesn&amp;rsquo;t work or could be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaction Rolls  Reaction rolls are hugely useful for an urban game, given the high number of social interactions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Context is very important for reaction rolls in Fellhold, and you will need to use some judgement in interpreting rolls. Guests at a dinner party are much less likely to attack on sight than a wild troll in a dungeon. The table below gives some guidance for common situations.  &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Roll&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Dungeon&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Merchant&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Social&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;General&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; 2 or less &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Attack &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Swindle &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Mean &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Worst Possible &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; 3-5 &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Wary &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Tightfisted &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Rude &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Pretty Bad &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; 6-8 &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Willing to Deal &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Fair &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Polite &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Middling &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; 9-11 &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Interested &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Helpful &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Friendly &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Pretty Good &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; 12+ &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Friendly &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Generous &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Best Friends! &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Best Possible &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-Sided Reaction Rolls  All reaction rolls are made with two dice - d6s by default. Each side brings one die to the roll. The die for the player character(s) will be based on their demeanor and approach, while the die for the NPC(s) will be based on their disposition and prejudices, including how they feel about the factions the PCs belong to. Adjust the roll using the spokesman’s CHA modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game master determines both die sizes, but the PC die should be based on what steps the PCs are or aren’t taking to make a certain sort of impression - acting threatening or friendly? Somewhere they belong or not? Well dressed or filthy? Asking clarifying questions is a good idea here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Steps for Reaction Dice  For both sides of the reaction roll, dice can step up or down from a d4 (the worst) to d12 (the best). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NPC’s die size is up to the game master’s discretion, but some common situations are covered below.  From a hostile faction: down one step  From a friendly faction: up one step  From a faction you belong to: up two steps  In hostile turf: down one step  On friendly turf: up one step&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple Reaction Rolls  Reaction rolls are helpful any time you need to gauge how an NPC feels about something, not just when first meeting the PCs, so some interactions will have multiple rolls. In such interactions, you may adjust one or both of the dice depending on how the encounter is going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example: the PCs meet a group of Pickers deep underground, you initially roll 2d6 because neither group is doing anything particularly helpful or harming and you get a 7. The Pickers begin speaking with the PC group, who try to overawe them with talk of how fierce they are. Pickers aren’t much impressed by this kind of thing, so when the PCs demand the Pickers hand over 50% of what they’ve found so far, you adjust the PC die down to a d4 and roll to see what they think of the offer, getting a 10, amazingly. The Pickers Laugh and say no way, but they like the stones on these guys. For further interaction, you bump it back up to 2d6.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Player Character Races in Fellhold</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-07-11-player-character-races-in-fellhold/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2018 17:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-07-11-player-character-races-in-fellhold/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-07-11-player-character-races-in-fellhold/ -&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve put together an eclectic set of PC races for my Fellhold setting, but I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with them. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to follow Arnold&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://goblinpunch.blogspot.com/2016/12/designing-races.html&#34;&gt;advice&lt;/a&gt; to avoid passive modifiers that lead to builds, but man, after decades of that being &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way races get distinguished, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get around.  Let me know what you think, and especially if you see anything that doesn&amp;rsquo;t quite work. All art by the awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://lexiconmegatherium.tumblr.com/tagged/erickochart&#34;&gt;Eric Koch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crabmen were inspired by
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/144820/YoonSuin?&#34;&gt;Yoon-Suin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;,
but I&amp;rsquo;ve taken them in a very different direction. Artsy-fartsy
merchants and intelligentsia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fiends are like the Kami in &lt;em&gt;Princess Monoke&lt;/em&gt;, but they want your
soul. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Half Dwarves are the descendants of humans and dwarves
interbreeding, and take on traits that you might find associated
with dwarves or
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dndwithpornstars.blogspot.com/2013/06/this-is-what-halfling-cities-are-like.html?zx=650a9612c5cd7759&#34;&gt;halflings&lt;/a&gt;
in other settings. Most of them are bitter about their lost glory
and are in the mafia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humans are humans, but in this cosmopolitan city, they&amp;rsquo;re the most
adept at getting along with all the strange shit. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ratmen are basically
&lt;a href=&#34;http://warhammerfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Skaven&#34;&gt;Skaven&lt;/a&gt;, but instead
of being riven by internal factionalism and backbiting, they have
the strongest mono-culture in town, are matriarchal, and happen to
be the best cooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tieflings have fiend blood. Yes, I need to find a name that isn&amp;rsquo;t
WOTC copyright. Everybody thinks they&amp;rsquo;re sexy and clever and
untrustworthy, but they mostly roll their eyes at that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t decided whether Draugr (full or partial undead from
selling parts of your soul) should be a PC race or something that
can just happen to PCs if they sell bits of their souls - right now
I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards the latter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pc-races-in-fellhold&#34;&gt;PC Races in Fellhold&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game Master Note  The races presented below are the default for Fellhold. Depending on how you place Fellhold in the world, you may have some changes. You might allow other races not included here or restrict some of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, if you want to stress the weirdness of Fellhold, start out with only human PCs and let players choose new races as they’re meaningfully found in play. Crabmen just don’t feel that weird if your buddy sitting next to you is one of them. On the other hand, if you want to stress the cosmopolitan, urban feel of Fellhold, allow all of the races below (or even more) - this will give a feeling that Crabmen are just another sort of folk you’re likely to run into daily. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Rules  Each race below includes a brief, general description of the race and its characteristics along with any special boons or banes that come with being a member of that race. Note also that race will be a factor in some other areas of the game not covered here, such as the ability to progress in, or even join, some of the factions of the city, the sorts of stereotypes NPCs will hold about you, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player Character Race Descriptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-o46kRdO5ahc/W0afn1uOkiI/AAAAAAAAG70/pAkMtd2zIT8u2nKl35PtYUiXidUxrl4pwCLcBGAs/s1600/CrabMan_merchant_concept01.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-o46kRdO5ahc/W0afn1uOkiI/AAAAAAAAG70/pAkMtd2zIT8u2nKl35PtYUiXidUxrl4pwCLcBGAs/s320/CrabMan_merchant_concept01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crabmen  Despite their large, hulking appearance and natural armor, crabmen tend towards philosophical and artistic temperaments. They make up a large number of the sages of the city, and of course their enormously wealthy Merchant Houses are known to all. Generally, crabmen are extremely cooperative with members of their own family, especially their own birthing group, and have a hard time helping out or even caring about anyone outside of it. Many crabmen have gotten around this through fairly widespread “adoption” of friends and business partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL  Crabmen’s natural exo-skeleton means that their unarmored AC is 2 better than a human’s. Armor is much harder to make for crabmen, as it is not much in demand by them and must be made larger, so any armor costs 2x the normal cost. Their reactions to anyone not in their “family” will tend towards apathy and ignoring them. Crabmen receive advantage on any rolls related to intellectual or artistic pursuits besides magic (study, crafting, and so forth). Their large size and rigid bodies means that they will have difficulty squeezing into some tight spaces, or in situations that require great flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mskh-B-khk0/W0af3Jy6fDI/AAAAAAAAG74/sVxR1JACLww8XFvgfhmNMfo8tFqAza9BwCLcBGAs/s1600/Demon_concept02.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mskh-B-khk0/W0af3Jy6fDI/AAAAAAAAG74/sVxR1JACLww8XFvgfhmNMfo8tFqAza9BwCLcBGAs/s320/Demon_concept02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiends  Fiends are the warped and wicked results of the godsdeath. They vary greatly in both power and form from minor animalistic sprites of rocks and saplings to mighty humanoid powers worshiped as gods. A player character fiend is far more powerful than many of these minor beings, but is still pretty far down the ladder. Fiends thrive on souls and worship, and most turn all of their doing towards those goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL  Every fiend must have a stead, a place or thing that it is bound to. The fiend cannot move farther away from it than its level in miles (or level in districts, if more useful). Steads can be carried with fiends of the PC’s size and power, but if a  stead is destroyed, the fiend truly dies. If otherwise killed, the fiend will reform at its stead in 1d4 urbancrawl turns (weeks). If a fiend swears an oath or signs a contract, it cannot willingly break that deal (but of course, the word of the deal, not necessarily the spirit). Fiends can also be summoned, compelled, and bound as NPC fiends. Fiends must have a Use Name, Greater Name, and True Name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-IHgsKgoLHFA/W0agABbd9ZI/AAAAAAAAG8A/yVverhf6K88bgIe5rNth6ACng1QhYsKmACLcBGAs/s1600/Untitled_Artwork%2B%25283%2529.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-IHgsKgoLHFA/W0agABbd9ZI/AAAAAAAAG8A/yVverhf6K88bgIe5rNth6ACng1QhYsKmACLcBGAs/s320/Untitled_Artwork%2B%25283%2529.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half Dwarves  Half Dwarves are the mixed descendants of the original dwarf settlers of Fellhold and humans. They have become a stable race of their own, but still stubbornly refer to themselves as true dwarves, claiming the inheritance of the Dwarven Great Kingdom as theirs by right. Their society is organized by huge extended families, run by Forefathers and Foremothers, the Fathers and Mothers of member families, and so on. Formerly the masters of trade and craft in the city, their wealth has been surpassed by the Crabmen, and they are eternally bitter for it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL  Half Dwarves are extremely hardy and gain advantage on any and all saves against poison, drugs, or disease and ignore their first pip of exhaustion in a day. Their reactions to crabmen will be generally negative, unless they know the person well and have come to like them. Their small size means both that they can more easily slip into tight spaces, but also that large foes can more easily knock them down, pick them up, or otherwise use brute force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-C5xod-R-hEQ/W0agFhB_vmI/AAAAAAAAG8E/2YlDka4jCsgq5GTxq0DO9tpB4iRQ3i5AwCLcBGAs/s1600/Untitled_Artwork%2B%25289%2529.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-C5xod-R-hEQ/W0agFhB_vmI/AAAAAAAAG8E/2YlDka4jCsgq5GTxq0DO9tpB4iRQ3i5AwCLcBGAs/s320/Untitled_Artwork%2B%25289%2529.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans  Humans are both the most numerous race within Fellhold and the least represented in its most powerful groups, unless you include the undead Witch Kings as still being “human”.  Descended from every culture ever conquered by the Dwarves or the Witch Kings, humans are a varied lot made up of many groups, each with their own distinct look, belief, and way of living. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL  Humans by need have come to understand and live with wildly different groups of people of every race, and so reaction rolls with new or otherwise unknown people will always be one step higher when dealing with a human. Humans are also a remarkably stubborn race, and so may re-roll one failed saving throw to avoid death once per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-nCAnEplcUr0/W0agLjbHDWI/AAAAAAAAG8I/n18Fg7pkx8cbV7MF3rJLoFwMv-Q4hSSmgCLcBGAs/s1600/Ratman_thief.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-nCAnEplcUr0/W0agLjbHDWI/AAAAAAAAG8I/n18Fg7pkx8cbV7MF3rJLoFwMv-Q4hSSmgCLcBGAs/s320/Ratman_thief.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ratmen  Ratmen are one of the most insular races, living as one unified clan under the rule of their Queen and their Fiend God. Despite being seen as sneaky and not to be trusted by most other races, they are also regarded as the finest cooks in all of Fellhold, and most people don’t believe the rumors that they don’t care too much what or who goes into the cookpot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL  Unless a player chooses otherwise, all Ratmen are presumed to belong to the Ratmen Clan faction to begin with. Ratmen are especially lithe and stealthy, and so receive advantage on any rolls where they are attempting to sneak. Their AC against ranged weapons is improved by one due to their keen senses and quick wits. Any other race besides fiends will have their reaction rolls reduced by one step unless they know the ratman from before. Their small size also means that their maximum hit points are one lower per hit die than normal (minimum of 1). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-NaRgHFnyuM4/W0agb2QJg8I/AAAAAAAAG8Y/NGNswPydpBQO3ui_PwDdJYZ94_-ZnX4cwCLcBGAs/s1600/Env_concept01_bad.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-NaRgHFnyuM4/W0agb2QJg8I/AAAAAAAAG8Y/NGNswPydpBQO3ui_PwDdJYZ94_-ZnX4cwCLcBGAs/s320/Env_concept01_bad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tieflings  The descendants of the other races with the addition of fiend blood, tieflings are not quite a distinct society of their own, but instead largely integrate themselves into others, usually that of their mortal kin. That being said, they have some ties to one another, and others view them as a distinct group. They are regarded as sexy, clever, untrustworthy, and ambitious, but they tend to roll their eyes at this. How much of their look they get from their fiendish forebearers varies widely, with some having nubby little horns under their hair or a small tail, while others could pass for fiends themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPECIAL  Tieflings’ fiendish blood makes them resistant to magic, so they gain advantage on any saves against magic. Their mysterious allure also allows them, once per week, to have an immediate Charm Person effect on anyone who makes a neutral or better reaction roll toward them. This effect lasts for a number of days equal to the tiefling’s level, but they might actually become your friend in the meantime. Also due to their fiendish blood, if a Tiefling’s true name is used in making a deal or contract, they cannot willingly violate that deal. Also, having fiendish blood themselves, they cannot believe strongly enough in another fiend to receive any benefits from magic gained by worship of fiends.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2018-07-11-player-character-races-in-fellhold/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Money &amp; Equipment in Fellhold</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 12:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/ -&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but I find coming up with equipment lists a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; pain in the ass. Coming up with starting equipment packages? Even harder. So why don&amp;rsquo;t I just use one of the perfectly serviceable equipment lists already out there? Because I definitely buy into the thought that equipment lists are a great way to convey implicit setting and approaches to the game. So I bit the bullet and cranked the below out. It could definitely use some work, and the equipment packs owe a great deal to Brendan&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.necropraxis.com/2012/07/20/odd-equipment/&#34;&gt;excellent OD&amp;amp;D ones&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any and all thoughts on how to spice this up are welcome, but I&amp;rsquo;m especially looking to make an evocative random item table so that everybody gets at least one interesting but not-obviously-useful piece of kit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9TnQWVbR4kU/W0UEgZ7ZeFI/AAAAAAAAG7o/c2WNKXmSW98AeT953_bmgwvPb52GyYDMgCLcBGAs/s1600/The_potion_seller.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9TnQWVbR4kU/W0UEgZ7ZeFI/AAAAAAAAG7o/c2WNKXmSW98AeT953_bmgwvPb52GyYDMgCLcBGAs/s320/The_potion_seller.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coins of Fellhold  Fellhold has three kinds of coins, issued by the Soul Banks based on the Soul Standard (theoretically, you can take your coins into a bank and demand the current market rate for bottled souls in exchange for your cash, but why would you want to?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copper Pennings: The common coin used in most business in Fellhold - a triangle about an inch on a side with a hole in the middle. One copper penning equals one experience point. (CP)  Silver Skillings: 100 Copper Pennings make up one Silver Skilling, so they are used for settling contracts and loans, day to day business between merchants, and the like. A thin, rectangular piece of silver, both sides show fine old-dwarven knotwork.  (SP)  Gold Marks: Worth 100 Silver Skillings, Marks are rarely seen outside of large business deals or the hoards of the wealthy. These fat gold hexagons have a raised outer lip and show a leering devil face on one side and the mark of the bank that stamped it on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting Cash &amp;amp; Gear  Player characters begin with 3d6x10 CP, or else can roll for a starting equipment pack by class. Either of these can be supplemented by loans as seen shown below. All characters begin with a backpack, blanket, a waterskin, three helpings of pack food, one torch, and a tinder box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking Out Loans  During character creation, PCs may take out one or more loans to secure additional gear. To do so, create a random specialist NPC - this is the PCs creditor. The PC receives a loan of 3d6x10 copper pieces to be used however they see fit. Assign the PC a d4 Loan Usage die. For every week that goes by that the PC does not pay their loan, roll the die. On a maximum result, step the die &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; one step. The PC can move the Loan Die down one step by paying the original loan amount. If it every reaches a d10, their creditor has lost patience and sends out goons to collect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sellers  If you wish to make finding the right place to buy goods as much a part of your game as where to fence adventuring loot, you may create a seller using the Merchant Table in the Specialist NPCs section for each category of gear below. Adjust prices accordingly. The first seller generated carries the entire category of gear. If a player wants to buy something at character generation, they must use the first seller generated - but if players are unhappy with this particular seller, they may search out others by using urbancrawl actions during play. Every new seller has a 50% chance of carrying each item when visited (this can change on future visits, or items can be special ordered for a fee). Every new seller should be added to the game master’s list of NPCs and placed in a neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipment Packs   To speed up character creation, players can elect to roll for a starting equipment pack rather than “shopping” with starting money. This method is especially recommended for new players and when adding a new character to an existing game. Specific items can be substituted with the Game Master’s permission. Players can also step down one or more steps and take 10 CP per step down. All characters begin with a backpack, blanket, a waterskin, three helpings of pack food, one torch, and a tinder box. To generate an equipment pack, roll 3d6 and look in the column for your class. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipment List  The lists below give a good flavor of what adventurous types might be most interested in buying in Fellhold, but just about anything can be had in the vast city. Talk to the Game Master about anything you’d like to buy that you don’t see below. All characters begin with a backpack, blanket, a waterskin, three helpings of pack food, one torch, and a tinder box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blessingsofthedicegods.blogspot.com/2016/06/lifestyles-of-poor-and-adventurous.html&#34;&gt;Lifestyle&lt;/a&gt;  Homeless (0) Free  Poor (d4) 20 CP  Comfortable (d6) 50 CP  Luxurious (d8) 1000 CP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weapons  Axe, Hand (Cleave) 30 CP  Axe, Lumberjack (Heavy) 40 CP  Axe, Tomahawk (Ranged, Light) 20 CP  Blackjack (Close, Light, Knockout) 5 CP  Blunderbuss (Firearm, Spread) 200 CP  Bow (Ranged) 30 CP  Brass Knuckles (Close, Knockout) 20 CP  Club (Knockout) 10 CP  Knife/Dagger (Close) 10 CP  Musket (Ranged, Firearm) 240 CP  Pistol (Ranged, Reactive, Firearm) 160 CP  Spear (Reach) 40 CP  Sword (Smooth) 30 CP  Throwing Knives/Stars (Close, Ranged, Light) 30 CP  War Shovel (Reach, Heavy) 50 CP  Warcrow (Crush, Cleave) 60 CP  Warhammer (Crush) 40 CP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armor  Light (AC 7) 75 CP  Medium (AC 5) 500 CP  Heavy (AC 3) 1500 CP  Shield (-1 AC, Sunder) 50 CP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gear  Acid (vial) 20 CP  Arrows (per usage die) 5 CP  Ball Bearings 10 CP  Barrel 20 CP  Bell 5 CP  Blanket 2 CP  Blasting Stick 50 CP  Block and Tackle 10 CP  Bucket 5 CP  Caltrops 10 CP  Camp Blanket 5 CP  Candle 2 CP  Cards, Playing 1 CP  Chain, 10’ 5 CP  Chalk 1 CP  Cooking Kit 15 CP  Crowbar 10 CP  Dice 1 CP  Disguise Kit 20 CP  Fuse (1 usage die) 30 CP  Galdrabok 30 CP  Grappling Hook 10 CP  Hammer 10 CP  Iron Spikes 5 CP  Ladder, 10’ 10 CP  Lantern 20 CP  Mirror 2 CP  Oil Flask 5 CP  Pack 30 CP  Pickaxe 10 CP  Pipe 5 CP  Pole, 10’ 2 CP  Rope, 50’ 15 CP  Sack 10 CP  Shot &amp;amp; Powder (1 usage die) 10 CP  Shovel 10 CP  Sledgehammer 10 CP  Thieve’s Tools 30 CP  Tinder Box 5 CP  Torch 5 CP  Water Skin, quart 2 CP  Wheelbarrow 40 CP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food, Drink, and Drugs  Beer, pint 3 CP  Lard, quart 5 CP  Pack Food, Meal 15 CP  Roasted Coffee Beans 10 CP  Seaweed Cigar 10 CP  Seaweed Cigarettes (per usage die) 10 CP  Seaweed, Loose (per usage die) 10 CP  Whiskey, quart 40 CP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critters  Cat 10 CP  Chicken 10 CP  Crab, Pack 60 CP  Crow 10 CP  Dog 30 CP  Goat, Pack 40 CP  Pig 30 CP&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Soul Economy in Fellhold</title>
        <link>/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:07:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/ -&lt;p&gt;So, back when I first started rebooting my home campaign setting from a Tentpole Megadungeon generic D&amp;amp;D world that owed a lot to Dwimmermount and into something a little funkier, one of the ideas I hit upon was that the economy would be based on souls. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really know what that meant, but it seemed cool, so I ran with it. Well, after lots of reading and thinking and coming up with other parts of the world, it finally clicked together into something that makes some (warped, D&amp;amp;D, in-game) sense. To sweeten the deal, I&amp;rsquo;ve included some awesome art that my co-creator &lt;a href=&#34;http://lexiconmegatherium.tumblr.com/tagged/erickochart&#34;&gt;Eric Koch&lt;/a&gt; has done so far. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-SIeNTw4qhvk/Wzaepz09jxI/AAAAAAAAG6s/J-pZb6ThJpsTAUkZJtmrNkHoPenveN4iwCLcBGAs/s1600/Fellhold_City_View%2B%25281%2529.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-SIeNTw4qhvk/Wzaepz09jxI/AAAAAAAAG6s/J-pZb6ThJpsTAUkZJtmrNkHoPenveN4iwCLcBGAs/s320/Fellhold_City_View%2B%25281%2529.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brief Word on How We Got to Now  Far back in dimly remembered times, the Dwarves arose as the first mighty kingdom and took over all the peoples of the lands they could reach. After tens of hundreds of years of dwarven overlordship, nomads of the steppe swept over the empire and made it their own with the help of dark sorcery. These witch kings took on much of the Dwarven culture, liking what they found, but they kept their magical ways, lengthening their lives through many means. After many, many kings, a group of them enacted a ritual to give them unending life - of a sort. The ritual worked, creating the mighty Lich Kings, but so great was their work that it killed the gods. The world turned wrong after that, and eventually the kings and the remnants of their folk had nowhere to run but to a far flung outpost on the edge of the world across the sea - Fellhold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-xeIEnLffgV0/Wzae3xvsQEI/AAAAAAAAG6w/wCnOW7SQmXQ6SvXjV5TrCKM6irIEekLswCLcBGAs/s1600/Fellhold_-_plague_demon.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-xeIEnLffgV0/Wzae3xvsQEI/AAAAAAAAG6w/wCnOW7SQmXQ6SvXjV5TrCKM6irIEekLswCLcBGAs/s320/Fellhold_-_plague_demon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birth of the Fiends  When the gods were murdered, their blood fell to earth - pure, concentrated soulstuff, stronger and more fearsome than anything tied to a mortal body. Where it struck, the dumb things of the world - sticks, rocks, beasts, and birds, and so forth - took on the twisted mockery of a soul. Some tiny and petty, others mighty and awful. So were born the fiends. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Closing of the Underworld  Something in the liches’ ritual or its aftermath closed our world to the underworld, and the souls of the dead were left to wander around this world unseen and unfelt but by those with the power to do so. Fellhold is wholly full of ghosts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Souls and Soulstuff  It is well known that souls are made up of many parts, each its own bit of the whole man or woman. All of these bits are made of soulstuff, the same stuff that godsblood and fiends are made of. Like energy or matter, soulstuff cannot be created or destroyed, but it can change form and state and be moved around. When someone dies, some bits of their soul hang together and become a ghost - others pass on to family or back into the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bits of the Soul  1. Lyke - The Body   2. Hame - Shape, Seeming  3. Ond - Breath  4. Hugh - Will and Wits  5. Myne - Memory   6. Wode - Inspiration  7. Hamingja - Luck, Might  8. Fetch - Guardian/Magical Spirit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone dies, they lose their Lyke and their Ond, and most of the time lose their Wode, Hamingja, and Fetch. The Hamingja most times passes to close kin, children if the dead had them. Sometimes the fetch goes along to a child, but more often goes out into the world on its own, and rarely finds its way into fiendhood of its own. The wode most often fades back into the world, to be mixed with that of others and taken up by new life, just as the flesh is in the world we can touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghosts  So, when folks die, they are left with some bit of their Hame, their Hugh, and their Myne. Of these, Myne is far the strongest. Over time, ghosts lose more and more of their Hugh and their Hame, becoming lost, confused, and vague, but their Myne ties them to those things most weighty in their life - often home or kin, but betimes hatred and death. Ghosts sometimes fade together to strengthen the bits that go together - so, your many dead forefathers and foremothers might all fade into a vague set of ancestor spirits. Others are so tied to their homes or other steads that they’ll become a part of the soul of the place - very old and well loved (or hated) buildings have a strong character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-KYUkyLqmUf8/WzafBXh5qoI/AAAAAAAAG64/6cpO4bLyWDcm8pN1uPb178ujw-2JJZpyACLcBGAs/s1600/Fellhold_dungeonHacker.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-KYUkyLqmUf8/WzafBXh5qoI/AAAAAAAAG64/6cpO4bLyWDcm8pN1uPb178ujw-2JJZpyACLcBGAs/s320/Fellhold_dungeonHacker.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottling Ghosts  At some time in the past, someone clever came up with a way to put ghosts into bottles. When done well, using the right kind of glass, these bottles stop the bleeding away of a ghost’s soulstuff over time - at least so far as anyone can tell since ghosts have been bottled. So, ghosts who are bottled get to keep their selves, and can come out sometimes, like when the great grandkids come over. The rest of the time it’s awfully lonesome, though. At least unbottled ghosts have each other to see and talk to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiends and Souls  The souls of living beings belong to them, fair and square - they take no thought in how readily they call upon the different bits of their soul, nor even feel any difference between them. For fiends it is otherwise. Fiends are squatters on their own souls, and their soulstuff comes from the dead mess of the godsblood. Some started with more, others less, but all hunger and thirst for as much soulstuff as they can get - always more. Soulstuff, though, cannot be eaten, drunk, or taken - only given or lost. Over the years, fiends have tried many ways to get what they yearn for, some combing the unseen world for the leavings of fled Wode or Ond, others eating the flesh of the dead, until they found something truly deep: they gain the same strength from owning a soul as from taking it into their own soulstuff. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-vQVK7EJbHE4/WzafWUL0mZI/AAAAAAAAG7I/5kKxzJGmJHU5giIsX72C5C5OPTjmp3ICQCLcBGAs/s1600/Env_concept02.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-vQVK7EJbHE4/WzafWUL0mZI/AAAAAAAAG7I/5kKxzJGmJHU5giIsX72C5C5OPTjmp3ICQCLcBGAs/s320/Env_concept02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rise of Soul Banks  Some fiends took note of the bottling of ghosts and the lore of soul ownership and thought up something truly clever. They saw that they could own bottled souls and get everything they wanted. Overtime, further cleverness came about: learning that holding a loan as collateral counts as “owning”, that the bits of the soul could be bottled on their own, and that ownership can be shared without breaking up the soul - only the shares of ownership. And so what started as piles of ghost bottles squirreled away in dark holes grew into great shared vaults, which grew into huge joint stock businesses that now back all of the ebb and flow of commerce in the great city. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Quick Word on Worship and Magic  Worship and Magic both involve efforts of the Hugh, though magic also needs to draw on the Hamingja. Worshipping and making magic create a kind of energy from these bits of the soul - not pulling away the actual substance, but made by it, like heat or sound coming from a place of friction. Such &amp;ldquo;heat and sound&amp;rdquo; can then pass energy into other soulstuff, strengthening it without enlarging it. So some fiends seek out the worship of living beings, and others make deals with mighty wizards as other ways to gain strength beyond owning souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-FuZscmxJQu8/WzafdJj2H3I/AAAAAAAAG7Q/WgsOYzBLIDshU7HjMi0d3r-N6JCR5jmAgCLcBGAs/s1600/Env_concept01_bad.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-FuZscmxJQu8/WzafdJj2H3I/AAAAAAAAG7Q/WgsOYzBLIDshU7HjMi0d3r-N6JCR5jmAgCLcBGAs/s320/Env_concept01_bad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling Your Soul  All of this means that the folk of Fellhold have many ways they can “sell their soul”, whether they want to set up a will to be bottled and kept safe upon their natural death, or if they reckon they don’t need their Luck as much as they need to make this month’s rent, all the way up to signing on to a stint as a draug thrall, bottling their soul in the meantime and loaning out their Lyke, Hame, and Ond to work for others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-qyXB0elUO7w/WzafIdLNroI/AAAAAAAAG7A/mGKuog-tnKsrdcUKrCVCHm_tLD5tYY6cQCLcBGAs/s1600/Coins.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-qyXB0elUO7w/WzafIdLNroI/AAAAAAAAG7A/mGKuog-tnKsrdcUKrCVCHm_tLD5tYY6cQCLcBGAs/s320/Coins.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Souls and Coins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when you put all of this together, you have a thing that is very worthwhile to some and somewhat worthwhile to everyone (bottled souls), that takes a fairly fixed amount of work to make (a life). You can’t spend that thing day to day, however, so you need something else. Over time, the banks took over from the Witch Kings in minting coins, each a token worth some tiny bit of a one of the souls in their vault. If you truly wished, you could take a pile of coins, go into your bank, and walk out with bottled ghosts, maybe to seek a better payout at a neighboring bank - but day to day, almost no one does this. So souls work the way that gold used to work for bank notes and pre-fiat currencies in our own world - the underlying asset that the money gets its worth from.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Culture is a Story that Isn&#39;t Over Yet</title>
        <link>/coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/ -&lt;p&gt;Stories are essential for building and maintaining strong cultures. They help everyone learn the group&amp;rsquo;s way of doing things, create belonging, and make meaning out of what they do every day. In fact, you can define culture as an ongoing story that a group tells together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cultures share a way of thinking about things. All of us shape our thinking with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fs.blog/mental-models/&#34;&gt;mental models&lt;/a&gt;, which help us to see blind spots, work better, and understand what we learn. In fact, you might say culture is nothing but a bundle of mental models shared by a group. One snag with mental models is that they have a lot of inertia - it takes a while to think with them day-to-day, and it takes at least as long to stop. So when we want to craft a culture that brings new folks in, like that of a business, we have to find a way to not only teach those models that make the group tick, but also overcome some of the mental models show up. It turns out that stories are a great &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://danielcoyle.com/2018/02/06/how-to-think-about-culture/&#34;&gt;delivery mechanism&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; for mental models. Not only are stories easier to call to mind, which helps the mental model get a foothold in your head, they also show the mental model at work, rather than as a lifeless concept . Those new to Southwest learn a lot more about how to deal with each other from the story about that time &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herb_Kelleher&#34;&gt;Herb Kelleher&lt;/a&gt;, drove to the airport to give a flight attendant a ride home than it does to tell them &amp;ldquo;we take care of each other.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides teaching mental models, stories are how folks work out what happens around them and give it meaning. &amp;ldquo;Meaning&amp;rdquo; can be a tough word to pin down, but for the culture of a group it comes down to: &amp;ldquo;why do I wake up and come here every morning?&amp;rdquo; For many folks, their own stories will answer this: &amp;ldquo;I worked hard learning skills to land a good job, and now I work hard to take care of my kids, and some day I&amp;rsquo;ll retire and fish all day.&amp;rdquo; On the other hand, truly great groups with strong cultures, craft larger stories that everyone can weave themselves into: &amp;ldquo;someday, the work I&amp;rsquo;m doing today will help this company cure cancer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we put together the thoughts that cultures are a bundle of ways to understand the world and that stories can give meaning to day to day work, we get an insight into what cultures truly are: an unfolding story a group tells itself about the world and what it might be. If a story is a thread stringing together deeds and outcomes, then a shared way of working toward meaningful outcomes is just a story that isn&amp;rsquo;t done yet. In the same way that the technology in a science fiction story sets what sort of plots can or can&amp;rsquo;t happen, so do the mental models of a culture give the framework for which actions will or won&amp;rsquo;t fly in the culture&amp;rsquo;s shared world. And just as a good story has a theme that tells us something about ourselves or the world we live in, so the goal of a team makes meaning for those on it. Following the thread of the group&amp;rsquo;s mental models to get from where they are now to where they want to go tells a story day by day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories help people know how to act, get them working together, and give meaning to that work. With that understanding, we can look at cultures as stories that are being told together by the groups that have them. What story does your organization tell?&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Power of Intuition</title>
        <link>/reading/the-power-of-intuition/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/reading/the-power-of-intuition/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /reading/the-power-of-intuition/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Gary Klein&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very same things are what excited me and disappointed me the most in this book. It presents intuition as a very no-nonsense ability that is critical for effective decision making, and gives advice on how to train to be better at it. Exactly what I wanted! On the other hand, it describes &amp;ldquo;intuition&amp;rdquo; as simply the ability to learn to detect patterns and apply past experiences to current situations, without consciously realizing  you&amp;rsquo;ve made that match - which is rather less romantic than I might hope for something as big and spooky as &amp;ldquo;intuition&amp;rdquo; to be. Once I set aside my childish disappointment, though, I found this book to be full of gems, and more importantly, to include detailed instructions on how to practice and train your team on these skills. I was expecting some help on decision making and ended up walking away with great techniques for leadership and creativity as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Power-Intuition-Feelings-Better-Decisions-ebook/dp/B001334J00/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1517861417&amp;amp;sr=8-1&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /reading/the-power-of-intuition/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Building Connections with Oral Storytelling</title>
        <link>/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/ -&lt;p&gt;Humans have been telling stories face to face since forever, and doing it well gives you a leg up personally and professionally. Compelling business presentations are critical for success, and natural storytelling techniques can take them to the next level. Even outside of business, stories help you build relationships and entertain your friends. You can improve your oral storytelling today by paying attention to structure, shortening your stories, using your voice well, and supporting what you say with your face and hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oral storytelling doesn’t just happen around a campfire - it’s something you can do anytime you’re the center of attention, whether presenting, at a party, or yes, even camping. By &amp;ldquo;oral storytelling&amp;rdquo;, I mean telling a story to an audience that can see and hear you. Many of the techniques will also work with sound only, but our baseline assumption is that you are telling your story to someone in the same room. In the digital age, many folks overlook how rich a channel face to face interaction is - you have the content of the words themselves, of course, but also your tone of voice, facial expression, timing, volume, hand gestures, referencing things in your immediate environment, and so on. The most important differentiator, though, is feedback - you can actually watch how your story is landing and tweak as you go - an enormously powerful gift that authors and painters would kill for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any storytelling, always start with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/3/storytelling-part-2-structure&#34;&gt;structure&lt;/a&gt;. For oral storytelling, structure is especially important, because it lacks some of the other cues that might help people follow the thread of the story. In written stories, paragraphs, headers, and typographic styles help to make clear how thoughts are organized. In a movie or graphic novel, visual actions can make obvious the intent of even subtle or confusing dialog. With oral storytelling, everything must happen in our audience&amp;rsquo;s heads - which is both the challenge and the strength of the form. When your audience is engaged, they are an active participant, not a passive consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make participation easy, help them out with a solid structure. Dan Roam&amp;rsquo;s PUMA tools introduced &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/3/storytelling-part-2-structure&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; were created for in-person presentations, and the most time-tested template is Drama, modeled on the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero%27s_journey&#34;&gt;Hero&amp;rsquo;s Journey&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. This is the form that stories have taken all over the world for as long as there have been stories to tell. Every Disney movie, every episode of the week, every bedtime story follows this form. All of this means that we really know this structure deep in our bones, and we won&amp;rsquo;t get lost in stories that follow it - even with unfamiliar characters, stakes, and action. When in doubt, try to structure any personal stories this way, and if you can get away with it, do the same thing with business stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you have a good structure, the next most critical factor is length. Unlike a book, where people can put it down whenever they want, they&amp;rsquo;re stuck listening to your whole story in one go. As storytellers it&amp;rsquo;s on us to give our audience something worth paying attention to. While great storytellers can keep audiences enthralled for a long time, you make your job a lot easier by reducing how much &amp;ldquo;good story&amp;rdquo; you have to craft - which you do by keeping your stories short and sweet. As guidance on how to achieve this, my favorite advice comes from Ramit Sethi:  &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/how-to-tell-killer-stories/&#34;&gt;Start late and end early&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. Get to the good stuff quickly, and don&amp;rsquo;t linger too long once you&amp;rsquo;ve covered it. Without training, most of us err on the side of too much context - lots of set up and wrapping up. &amp;ldquo;Start late&amp;rdquo; means you should come in as close to the main point of the story as possible. &amp;ldquo;End Early&amp;rdquo; means don&amp;rsquo;t detail all of the follow up after the climax. You need a little bit of resolution for a story to feel complete, but rather than detailing all 107 times you&amp;rsquo;ve used that life lesson from summer camp, just sum up how it has changed you for the better. If you find it hard to remove details, remember one of the strengths of oral storytelling: people can always ask for more if they want it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you&amp;rsquo;re recounting your story, besides what you&amp;rsquo;re saying, you&amp;rsquo;ll also want to pay attention to how you&amp;rsquo;re saying it. Your voice is the main way you do this. All of us do an incredible amount of sophisticated stuff with our voices without even realizing it - conveying complex emotional undertones, subtly altering timing for comedic effect, raising and lowering volume to match energy levels, and so on. Many of these techniques can be learned as specific tricks or tips - for example, try humming &amp;ldquo;Happy Birthday&amp;rdquo; before you speak, and your voice will come out a little richer. These are the kind of things you can consciously learn from singing or speaking classes. As a starting point, though, I encourage you to take advantage of the lifetime of practice you have using your voice unconsciously. Rather than trying specific techniques with your voice, instead focus on the emotional and psychological state you want portray to your audience and then do something you did as a kid - play pretend. Need to depict the angry drunk from the bar? Imagine yourself feeling mad and drunk. Describing the life changing emotional experience of the sun rising over the mountains in Yellowstone? Vividly picture being back there, and let your voice do the work. As you start doing this more often, you&amp;rsquo;ll develop more awareness of what you&amp;rsquo;re actually doing - &amp;ldquo;oh, when I&amp;rsquo;m acting mad, I raise my voice this much&amp;rdquo; - which you can later tweak as you pick up some conscious techniques or see how people react to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides your voice, you also have a wealth of visual aids at your disposal: your hands, expressions, and posture. Even though your voice and words are the stars of the show, your hands and face are important supporting actors. The same advice for &amp;ldquo;embodying&amp;rdquo; emotions applies to facial expressions as it does to tone of voice. You may want to learn to slightly exaggerate your facial expressions for a greater impact - it&amp;rsquo;s a lot of fun to practice making the biggest, most ridiculous expressions you can while looking in a mirror. For posture, you generally want to stand up straight and confident, but sometimes you may want to hunch over or lean in to bring parts of the story to life. Hand gestures are much harder to pin down for advice. Depending on your background and culture, you may naturally and frequently &amp;ldquo;talk with your hands&amp;rdquo;, in which case, keep doing what you&amp;rsquo;re doing. If not, though, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to start using some intentional gestures when telling your stories. A few basics to get you started are things like holding your hands out palm up to offer something, bringing them down forcefully to convey drama or surprise, or gesturing back towards yourself to emphasize your own role or feelings in the story. As with the other techniques, the trick is to find movements that feel natural and support what you&amp;rsquo;re saying. Practice and feedback will help out a lot here, but start out by making sure your hands are not in your pockets, behind your back, messing with your hair, or the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s all kinds of resources on oral storytelling you can check out if you want more, but if you have tightly structured, concise stories told with energy and animation, you’ll have audiences hanging on your words in no time. Take advantage of this very rich, very human channel by using the &amp;ldquo;hero&amp;rsquo;s journey&amp;rdquo; where possible, tighten up your stories to be short and sweet, and use your voice and expressions to heighten the emotion of what you&amp;rsquo;re telling at the time. As with any other skill, practice with good feedback is what will get you there. Fortunately, telling stories is something you&amp;rsquo;ll have lots of opportunities to practice in low stakes settings: hanging out with friends, going out, dinner with your family - anywhere people gather.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Jeff Russell Storytime</title>
        <link>/coaching/2018-01-22-jeff-russell-storytime/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2018-01-22-jeff-russell-storytime/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2018-01-22-jeff-russell-storytime/ -&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite memories from the Army is “Jeff Russell Storytime”. It seemed like a silly way to pass the time, but ended up teaching me a lot that I still use today. Out of way too much free time, it evolved into a regular occurrence that we all enjoyed a lot. I got to share some of my favorite gems from history and mythology, and over time I learned a thing or two about storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember precisely how it became a “thing”, but somewhere along the line, my buddies started specifically requesting “Jeff Russell Storytime”. I’m sure it started out as at least half-joking, but over time I think they enjoyed listening as much as I did telling. You see, in the Army you have a lot of time standing around with nothing much to do, especially in the infantry. Guard duty, police lines, waiting around for assignments - we all became very accustomed to the different flavors of waiting around. So, I started telling my friends stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the stories I told came from history and mythology, thanks to my classical education, but a few were personal anecdotes. I was pleasantly surprised to find a bunch of grunts interested in hearing about, say, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synod_of_Whitby&#34;&gt;Synod of Whitby&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hector#Duel_with_Achilles&#34;&gt;Achilles and Hector&lt;/a&gt;, or how the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexican%E2%80%93American_War#Origins_of_the_war&#34;&gt;Mexican-American War&lt;/a&gt; got started. I was slightly less surprised at their interest in personally embarrassing stories, often involving a bit too much to drink. A few were favorites, requested multiple times, others were whatever I could come up with at the time. Some fell a little flat, obviously, but I was helped out by the afore mentioned “nothing else to do”. That helps make for a pretty forgiving audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, I was just entertaining myself and my friends, and didn’t give much thought to what I might be learning from it. Looking back, though, telling these stories in front of a live audience taught me a lot of important lessons that I’ve been able to apply in my business and personal life.  Listening to which stories were requested and how people reacted helped me learn what was interesting. Watching interest wax and wane gave me a sense of how to pace things. Paying that kind of attention gave me lots of practice reading the nuances of a crowd’s reaction, and as I learned to be aware of that, I figured out how to use my voice and gestures to get certain effects and heighten the drama of the telling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve explored a lot of different sorts of storytelling here on the blog, but old-fashioned in-person oral storytelling has a lot to recommend it, and you can use it in all sorts of situations. As the above shows, to get the practice you don’t even have to tell your own stories - you can tell anything you know and find interesting, and over time you’ll get the knack for reading an audience and altering your telling to suit them.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2018-01-22-jeff-russell-storytime/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Consolations of Philosophy</title>
        <link>/reading/the-consolations-of-philosophy/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/reading/the-consolations-of-philosophy/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /reading/the-consolations-of-philosophy/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Alain de Botton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book provides a great overview of the tradition of Western philosophy. Besides providing useful summaries of some of the major thinkers and what their philosophy can do for you in your life, it shows the the connecting threads between thinkers that might seem totally unrelated at first glance. Each chapter gives a brief thumbnail of the biography and thinking of a major philosopher, which is great, but what&amp;rsquo;s really useful about this book is that every chapter addresses a specific concern that everyone faces - such as unpopularity, money, and frustration. Alain&amp;rsquo;s style is warm and gentle, with a hint of detached humor that makes for enjoyable reading. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever thought &amp;ldquo;I wish I knew more about philosophy&amp;rdquo;, this is the place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Consolations-Philosophy-Vintage-International-ebook/dp/B00ATLA8RU/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1516594375&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=consolations+of+philosophy+alain+de+botton&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /reading/the-consolations-of-philosophy/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Zen &amp; The Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</title>
        <link>/reading/zen-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/reading/zen-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /reading/zen-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Robert Pirsig&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my initially somewhat negative reaction to this book, it has become one of my &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;operating manuals&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; for life. Even when I first read it and disagreed with much of what it said, I found a lot of compelling food for thought. Paradoxically, the very thing that made me uncomfortable initially has become its greatest value to me: the questioning of received ideas of values and building new ones up from scratch. A fascinating look at depth, focus, and quality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Zen-Art-Motorcycle-Maintenance-Inquiry-ebook/dp/B0026772N8/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1516062885&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=zen+and+the+art+of+motorcycle+maintenance&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /reading/zen-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>My Approach for a Virtuous Life</title>
        <link>/coaching/2018-01-15-my-approach-for-a-virtuous-life/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2018-01-15-my-approach-for-a-virtuous-life/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2018-01-15-my-approach-for-a-virtuous-life/ -&lt;p&gt;Today I run the risk of sounding  a bit preachy. Let me state for the first (but not last) time that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to tell you how to live your life or what “being good” means. We all want to be good people, but many of us have different perspectives on what that means. Even worse, almost every terrible ethical lapse you read about in the news began years ago with a gradual slip. We can all fall prey to this, so it helps to clearly spell out our code of behavior. That’s why I’ve laid out below the process I followed to settle on my own virtues, and the steps I take to try to live up to them. I hope that you get some ideas on how you might think about and reinforce your own principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little over a year ago, I was struck by something &lt;a href=&#34;http://jockopodcast.com/&#34;&gt;Jocko Willink&lt;/a&gt; said about needing to know what your values are so that you can be sure you are living up to them. He further suggested that it was a good idea to periodically check in and confirm that your stated principles really are what you believe and want to uphold. This struck me as quite good advice, and so I decided to figure out what virtues were important to me along with a way to keep track of how I was doing. Obviously this is an ongoing struggle, and I make no claims on being particularly virtuous. Rather than trying to convince you to live by my virtues, I hope that I provide a model of how you might identify and live by your virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, I realized with some horror that I had no identifiable virtues of my own, just a lot of vague moral intuitions and behavioral codes I had followed in the past. Since I do not follow any of the major religions, going by one of their lists was out, so I reckoned I had to define my own. I sought out sources which spoke to what I thought was right: everything from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.army.mil/values/&#34;&gt;Army Values&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism#Ethics_and_virtues&#34;&gt;Stoic Virtues&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Awaken-Giant-Within-Immediate-Emotional-ebook/dp/B001EM101Q/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1516034506&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=awaken+the+giant+within&#34;&gt;Tony Robbins&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.angelfire.com/nc/broomcloset/aetheling.html&#34;&gt;Anglo-Saxon Thews&lt;/a&gt; and more. From each of these sources, I created a mindmap on &lt;a href=&#34;https://realtimeboard.com/&#34;&gt;Realtime Board&lt;/a&gt; with each separate virtue as a node, first grouped by their sources. I then created connections between the virtues that seemed to be related to each other somehow, and then I clumped together those that seemed to reflect similar concepts - &lt;a href=&#34;http://asq.org/learn-about-quality/idea-creation-tools/overview/affinity.html&#34;&gt;affinity mapping&lt;/a&gt;, basically. The end result was something my friend described as an “Ant’s Nest” and looked like a crazy person’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/www.weirdshitpodcast.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/download-1.jpg?resize=672%2C372&#34;&gt;conspiracy board&lt;/a&gt;. I did not create a visual that would help other people, but the process of building it forced me to look very closely at dozens of potential virtues, figure out what I believed in and how they were similar or different, and otherwise deeply immerse myself in them. The end result was a deep internalization of the values put forward in all of the sources I chose as well as my own understanding of how they fit together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that work, I ended up with nine virtues in three groups. As I said, I do not say that these are the right virtues for anyone but myself, but for the sake of example, here they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;head&#34;&gt;Head&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these virtues involve thinking and using your head. They are related to humanity’s innate capacity for reason, as separate from the animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Groundedness&lt;/strong&gt;: Presence, humility, moderation. The ability to pause and step outside of emotions and impressions and remain calm. In many ways, this virtue enables all of the others when they would otherwise be hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Truth&lt;/strong&gt;: Dedication to facing the world as it truly is and reflecting that in word and deed. Besides speaking the truth, it includes curiosity, rationality, and the willingness to accept hard truths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisdom&lt;/strong&gt;: Applied smarts. Wisdom is both the love of knowledge and the active application of that knowledge to living a good life. Many of the virtues tell me what to do, but wisdom usually encompasses how to achieve that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;chest&#34;&gt;Chest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These virtues are the higher sort of emotional virtues - the kind of thing that makes you shed a tear at a powerful scene in a movie. They provide the bridge between the colder virtues of the Head and the heated virtues of the Belly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt;: Kindness, generosity, humor, and cheerfulness. Treating everyone well, not just those close to you. Without this virtue, all of the others might turn overly inward or selfish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Troth&lt;/strong&gt;: Loyalty, hospitality, duty, and respect. An old timey word now mostly only seen in the word betroth. This virtue covers my obligations to others as a social animal. Somewhat more formal and less warm than Love, but still rooted in a sense of shared humanity and dignity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worth&lt;/strong&gt;: Excellence, honor, virtue. In many ways, this is the master virtue. If you are familiar with the Greek concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arete_(moral_virtue)&#34;&gt;arete&lt;/a&gt;, that comes close to hitting the mark. The virtue of living and acting well, of doing things the very best you can, because it is worthwhile in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;belly&#34;&gt;Belly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the fiery virtues of primal life. They are the least distinguished from animals, but are still necessary to provide the drive and power to make the other virtues possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunger&lt;/strong&gt;: Ambition, decisiveness, energy. Hunger is the desire to strive and do and achieve. By itself, it can become a vice, but absolutely necessary to make achieving the other virtues possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guts&lt;/strong&gt;: Bravery, courage. Just as you need Hunger to desire to do better, you need Guts to do the right thing even when its hard. Includes physical and moral bravery, which are more closely linked than many suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grit&lt;/strong&gt;: Discipline, industriousness, persistence, toughness. Grit is the virtue of sticking with things and pushing through when it gets hard through sheer stubbornness. Many great things only exist on the other side of pain - Hunger and Guts start you on the path there, but Grit carries you through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you’ve seen an example list of virtues, what might you do to make them real in your life? I was inspired by Benjamin Franklin’s method of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thirteenvirtues.com/&#34;&gt;keeping track of his virtues&lt;/a&gt;, and I have adapted it to my daily journal. At the top of the page on each new day, I draw a little box with my nine virtues in three columns of three rows, each with space next to them for a mark. At the end of the day, I reflect and ask myself how I did. To make it as easy as possible to evaluate, I assume I followed my virtue unless I can think of an example where I failed. If I can think of no examples, I put a happy face next to the virtue. If I failed, I put a sad face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has the advantage of making me think about my virtues at the beginning of the day (when I lay out my page) and at the end (when I ask how I did), and provides me a record of which virtues I might be struggling with the most. Something I’m considering is coming up with more clear criteria for each virtue about what constitutes failing in it, because I don’t want to give myself a pass for things I need to recognize. Even still, I believe there’s value in continuously reinforcing that I am the kind of person who acts in those ways - making it easier to act in accordance with that self-perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last thing: each day, I pick a challenge for one of the virtues. I move through them in sequence, rotating around when I get to the end. Where my default is to look out for failures of each virtue, the point here is to encourage me to actively improve in that virtue. So, for example, a common challenge for days where “Guts” is the focus virtue is “Do something that scares you”, or for Love I might have “Perform an unexpected act of generosity for a stranger.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said many times already, I do not expect my nine virtues will match your values, but I’ve provided a model of how you might incorporate your own virtues into your life. By thinking about what sources you want to inform your approach, selecting qualities from them, and finding links and clumping them together, you can arrive at your own manageable list of virtues. Once you have them, you can keep track of them with an “assumed pass” system plus a challenge to keep you from getting comfortable. Whether you use any of these techniques or not, I encourage you to think about what your values, principles, or virtues are, and to make a conscious effort every day to live up to them.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2018-01-15-my-approach-for-a-virtuous-life/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Artist&#39;s Way</title>
        <link>/reading/the-artists-way/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/reading/the-artists-way/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /reading/the-artists-way/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Julia Cameron&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that if I picked this book up sight unseen and flipped through it, I would likely have put it back on the shelf - it has a lot of markers for being a bit too &amp;ldquo;woo woo&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;touchy feely&amp;rdquo; for my usual tastes. Fortunately, it came highly recommended by a bunch of well-grounded people that I respect, so I decided to give it a shot, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad I did. The basic premise is that everyone can be creative, but most of us have developed the idea that we&amp;rsquo;re not allowed to or have otherwise blocked our access to our creative selves. To counteract this, it provides a twelve week guided program to lead to greater creativity. I&amp;rsquo;m not very far into the program, but already I am seeing the benefit of its two core habits: &lt;a href=&#34;http://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/&#34;&gt;Morning Pages&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/artists-dates/&#34;&gt;Artist Dates&lt;/a&gt;. If you are already convinced that you could be more creative with some help and don&amp;rsquo;t need as much back up, consider going straight to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Artists-Way-Workbook-Julia-Cameron-ebook/dp/B001QL5MQ4/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1515369412&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=artist%27s+way&#34;&gt;workbook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Artists-Way-25th-Anniversary-ebook/dp/B006H19H3M/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1515369412&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=artist%27s+way&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /reading/the-artists-way/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Strategy: A History</title>
        <link>/reading/strategy-a-history/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/reading/strategy-a-history/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /reading/strategy-a-history/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Lawrence Freedman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man oh man am I loving this book. It puts out a comprehensive record of thinking about the concept of strategy in western thought from the Bible and Homer all the way to modern theorists. Along the way, Freedman provides analysis of the strengths and shortcomings of the various formulations and their applications. Despite what might turn into a dry, intellectual subject, the book is quite clear and readable, moving briskly through trends and eras of thought. For me, it&amp;rsquo;s greatest value is highlighting the connections and influences between figures as disparate as Thucydides, Machiavelli, and John Boyd. I suspect that I will be coming back to my notes on this and its bibliography for years to come. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Strategy-History-Sir-Lawrence-Freedman-ebook/dp/B00F3D4IVG/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /reading/strategy-a-history/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>An Expanded Definition of Reading</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/ -&lt;p&gt;We tend to think of “reading” as the time we have a book in front of our face, but when you stop to ask why you are reading, a number of other activities suggest themselves as part of the bigger enterprise. If you are reading to learn, simply passing your eyes over the words will only get you a fraction of what’s there. I’ve been spending a lot of time thinking about how to make reading as effective as possible, and below I share my current thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get some idea of what might fall under this broader umbrella, it’s helpful to ask “what exactly are we trying to get out of reading?” You might read for fun or to kill time. You might read to practice a particular language. You might be looking for inspiration on crafting prose. I have read for all of these reasons and plan to continue to do so, but for today, I want to talk about reading to learn. When I read non-fiction (and some fiction), I am looking to take someone else’s insight and wisdom and incorporate it into my own understanding. This focus makes it clearer what activities support the goal of “reading”: picking the right material, engaging with the text actively, and reflecting on what we’ve read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we ever pick up a book we can make our reading more effective by what we select. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2012/02/book-recommendations-from-nassim-taleb/&#34;&gt;Nasim Taleb&lt;/a&gt; advocates giving heavy preference to older books. He reasons that books that stick around for a long time have shown that they’re worthwhile, whereas the jury is still out on new stuff. I share a lot of sympathy with this approach, especially when it comes to reading about “wisdom”, but if you want to learn about new technologies and scientific discoveries, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_de_Montaigne&#34;&gt;Montaigne&lt;/a&gt; might not be your best bet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how do you make sure you’re reading high quality stuff? That’s a tough question, and one I continually think about. Right now, I’d say that the best filter for high quality is recommendations from a trusted source - preferably someone you know who has enough overlap in tastes and interest to know whether you’d like something or not. I’ve started cultivating these kinds of recommendations by inviting my more readerly friends to an &lt;em&gt;Inverse Book Club&lt;/em&gt;. In a normal book club, everyone reads the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; book. In this one, we all read &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; books and share our thoughts. It does a remarkable job of exposing you to material that is at once interesting to you but not something you would have picked up on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next best qualifier is a source whose tastes and preferences you know pretty well, but you don’t necessarily agree with. Think of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/At_the_Movies_(U.S._TV_series)&#34;&gt;Siskel &amp;amp; Ebert&lt;/a&gt;: you might not have shared their tastes, but they were pretty clear about what they liked, so you can make informed decisions based on what they think. I had a friend in high school with the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; taste in movies from me - if he hated something, it was a good bet I’d like it, and vice versa. This same filter can apply with recommendations from bloggers and podcast hosts and other people that you engage with less actively than your friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there’s the crowd - what’s this book’s Amazon rating? Was it a best seller? Is everybody talking about it? There’s nothing wrong with this approach, but it’s less likely to direct you to &lt;em&gt;exactly what you need&lt;/em&gt;. It also works better when you have some idea what you’re looking for already, like “hmmm, I want to read about physics, what’s the best popular science book on physics?” If you are trying to find wholly new material that you wouldn’t have considered, you’re less likely to get it from looking at what’s popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However we evaluate a book’s worth, we also want to give thought to &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; we want to read about. Do we want to go deep on a topic and read five books in a row on the same subject? Or do we want to introduce some new models into our thinking and read something totally outside of our comfort zone? I think that both are worthwhile, but I have trouble getting the exact right ratio and rhythm down. I mostly go by what I’m interested in, but that introduces the danger of getting bored with something right on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/2016/11/11/neil-gaimans-advice-to-writers-get-bored/&#34;&gt;edge of pushing through to real insight&lt;/a&gt;. It helps to know your own quirks: I tend to enjoy learning about a lot of things, so I probably need to push myself to pursue depth more. If you are an expert on a narrow field, maybe you need to read outside of that field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we’ve selected a book, we’ll get more out of reading by actively engaging with the text. It turns out that simple highlighting doesn’t actually do much to improve recall. Taking notes, on the other hand, &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/2008/05/26/monday-master-class-the-study-hacks-guide-to-note-taking/&#34;&gt;does&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a delicate balance to keep up with the flow of what you’re reading while also stopping to think enough to make connections and help things sink in. My current approach with physical books is to make notes in the margins and to underline quotes or references to other works. With electronic books, I type notes with the date and page number in an Evernote note and highlight anything I want to come back to and record later (like references or good quotes). When I take notes, I try to focus on making connections with concepts I already know, other books I’ve read, and differing points of view. It’s all too easy to fall into the trap of passively nodding along with a book in a way you never would with someone in a conversation. So try to put yourself in the mindset of an intellectually stimulating conversation with your smart friend that you don’t always agree with - be ready to challenge, learn, and find commonalities that aren’t obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading, we can improve recall and strengthen connections through reflection. With some very important books, I’ve gone so far as to go over all my highlights and type them up, cluster references by theme and pull out any exercises or instructions into their own section. Doing this on every single book would probably be overkill. More recently, a friend has turned me onto a very simple approach as a bare minimum per book: when you finish, write a paragraph or so of your thoughts in a journal, either paper or digital. Another technique is to ask Scott Young’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2015/06/22/stop-forgetting/&#34;&gt;retention questions&lt;/a&gt;. However you do it, reflection is really just an extension of the active engagement you cultivated while reading the book and strengthening the ties you’ve made with other material. As you get into it, this reflection and thinking bleeds into the selection we discussed and becomes a cycle. You read a book that makes you think about something else you’ve read, the intersection of those two ideas suggests a new area to explore, and so you ask a friend for a recommendation in that field, and you’re off again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a motivated person that cares about reading, it’s easy to focus on maximizing something like pages read per week, but if that’s your entire definition of reading, you may be missing out on the actual &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt; of the activity. I hope that expanding your definition of reading helps you to apply those same skills to carving out time to pick the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; books, actively &lt;em&gt;engage&lt;/em&gt; with them while you read, and to &lt;em&gt;reflect&lt;/em&gt; on what you’ve read so it sticks.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The 4-Hour Chef</title>
        <link>/reading/the-4-hour-chef/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/reading/the-4-hour-chef/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /reading/the-4-hour-chef/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Tim Ferriss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides being a phenomenal &amp;ldquo;learn to cook from nothing&amp;rdquo; cookbook, this also actually a book on how to learn &lt;em&gt;anything.&lt;/em&gt; Meta-learning is like catnip to me, and I was already a huge Tim Ferriss fan when this came out, so I snapped it right up. Apparently it hasn&amp;rsquo;t done as well as his other books and it was dealing with it&amp;rsquo;s rough release that led him to start his podcast. I was shocked to learn this, because to me it was more of what I had gotten in &lt;em&gt;The 4 Hour Workweek&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The 4 Hour Body&lt;/em&gt;, but better refined and figured out. The frameworks in this book are invaluable companions to other &amp;ldquo;how to learn&amp;rdquo; frameworks like Scott Young and Cal Newport. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re already a master cook, check this book out for it&amp;rsquo;s advice on how to deconstruct a skill and ask experts the right questions to fast track insights and skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/4-Hour-Chef-Cooking-Learning-Anything/dp/0547884591/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1513561238&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=4-hour+chef&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /reading/the-4-hour-chef/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Russell House Rules Core</title>
        <link>/gaming/2017-12-12-russell-house-rules-core/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 21:31:00 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/gaming/2017-12-12-russell-house-rules-core/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /gaming/2017-12-12-russell-house-rules-core/ -&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to put together the core of my personal house rules after years of collecting, tweaking, and trying out various DIY D&amp;amp;D approaches. The notion with these rules was to boil it down to only the things that will be true in just about every campaign I might want to run, rather than trying to capture all of the cool setting-specific rules I might change up. I managed to compress all of that down into six A5 spreads, including character generation, which I&amp;rsquo;m pretty proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s not in here? Campaign-specific stuff including equipment lists, monster lists, detailed treasure lists, sanity rules, that kind of thing. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on all of that being modular as I move forward, which helped drive some of my decision-making in which rules to include.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which gets to the last point: there is shockingly little that is original here. I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly cobbled together the ideas of people cleverer than myself, detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get the pdf of the rules &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/open?id=1LSditu5YRLM6LokM2gJjTGFwUJccMRZl&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or you can read the rules in blog form (no sweet spreads or art deco style, though) below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rules-outlook&#34;&gt;Rules Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put together these rules to have my preferred mishmash of “base” D&amp;amp;D
rules all in one place. The thought is that these are the rules I’ll use
regardless of setting, and I can bolt on specific modules for different
campaigns. There’s nothing very original here, and I tried to document
where I got all this stuff below - if you see a rule that came from your
blog or a G+ discussion and I missed you, let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every rule should encourage the type of play desired&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rules should be modular and avoid interconnectedness except when totally
necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rules should be as simple as possible and no simpler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rules should be as compatible with old school modules and rules as
possible, make it easy to adapt, use, or add on to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use “incomparables” as much as possible rather than straight numeric
modifiers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gain comprehensiveness through accumulation of optional modules, not
through a tightly integrated system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These rules are very much the product of the fantastic DIY D&amp;amp;D/OSR
scene, and just about nothing here is totally original. Especial thanks
to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arnold K and his GLOG for how to approach XP &amp;amp; Leveling, inspiration
on skills, HP and recovery, and general design philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gus L for his take on exploration, encumbrance, exhaustion, light
sources, weapon characteristics, and Fighting Options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brendan S for the original “overloaded encounter die&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delta for the Target 20 approach to combat mechanic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Hogan for the monster profile, calling attack bonus “weapon
skill”, and treasure generation (especially pocket change)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logan Knight for lots of great conversations on fiddly rules stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Young for surprise rules and introducing me to usage dice,
though I can’t remember where he found them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arnold, Gus, Brendan, Logan, and others for lots of different takes
on encumbrance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Raggi for LotFP’s grappling rules and the core of my skill
approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anne Hunter for the idea of “held surprise&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fifth Edition D&amp;amp;D for Advantage and Disadvantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course, the original games and the great hobby they created - this
is my attempt to still have “y’know, basically D&amp;amp;D” but with all the
little tweaks and house rules I prefer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-a-character&#34;&gt;Making a Character&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;roll-attributes&#34;&gt;Roll Attributes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roll 3d6 seven times and assign six of the results as you like. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be hardcore and please both your referee and the dark
gods of heavy metal, or are playing a level 0 funnel, roll 3d6 in order,
no substitutions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;choose-race&#34;&gt;Choose Race&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a race from those available in your campaign and note any
abilities or modifiers granted from it. If you’re stuck or unclear on
options, just go with human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;choose-class&#34;&gt;Choose Class&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a starting class template from those available in your campaign
and note any abilities or modifiers granted. Note that you’re not locked
into this choice forever - you can pick different templates as you level
up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;determine-starting-hp&#34;&gt;Determine Starting HP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roll 1d6 and add your Constitution modifier. Note this as your maximum
HP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;determine-weapon-skill-and-bow-skill&#34;&gt;Determine Weapon Skill and Bow Skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All adventurers start with 1 Weapon Skill and 1 Bow Skill. Some class
templates will add to one or both. If so, add them up and note them on
your sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;determine-unarmored-ac&#34;&gt;Determine Unarmored AC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Default Unarmored AC is 10. Improve it by one point for every point of
positive Dexterity modifier. Your class template may also modify your
AC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;determine-skill-slots-and-starting-skills&#34;&gt;Determine skill slots and starting skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have skill slots equal to half your intelligence, rounded down. By
default, characters begin with three “Just in Time” Skills at rank 1- at
any point during play, you can declare that your background prepared you
for this situation or gave you some knowledge and define a relevant
skill, which is now fixed. Your class template may add further skills.
No skills can have a higher rank than your level. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some campaigns may have fixed skill lists and/or alternate methods of
generating starting skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;money-and-equipment&#34;&gt;Money and Equipment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players begin with 3d6 x 10 base coins and may purchase any equipment on
the available starting equipment list. Equipment lists will vary by
campaign, as will the standard coin. Some campaigns may instead have
gear packages or gear based on careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, all characters begin play with a Blanket (1 slot), a
Waterskin (1 slot), 3 Rations (1 slot), and Flint &amp;amp; Tender (0 Slots).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record equipment in your gear slots, note your “ready” default weapon,
and adjust your AC based on any armor worn. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pick-or-roll-a-name&#34;&gt;Pick or Roll a Name&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select a suitable name for your character, either from your own
imagination or using a random list suitable to the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;characters&#34;&gt;Characters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;attributes&#34;&gt;Attributes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters have six attributes that describe their basic abilities.
Attributes are not as important in these rules as in some versions of
the game, which is intentional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;strength&#34;&gt;Strength&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raw physical ability and athleticism. Add your strength modifier to any
melee damage rolls. Your gear slots are equal to your strength. Test
strength to resist damage that can’t be dodged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;dexterity&#34;&gt;Dexterity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coordination and limberness. Add your dexterity modifier to any ranged
damage rolls. Your modifier also affects your armor class, with a
positive modifier improving AC, and a negative modifier lowering it -
careful not to get mixed up since AC is descending. Test dexterity to
avoid damage that could be dodged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;constitution&#34;&gt;Constitution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health and toughness. Add your constitution modifier to your HP every
time you level up. Test your constitution to resist poison or disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;intelligence&#34;&gt;Intelligence&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleverness and reasoning ability. You have a maximum number of skill
slots equal to half of your intelligence, rounded down. Test
intelligence to advance skills and to save against spells. Depending on
the magic system used, intelligence may affect your ability to cast
spells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;wisdom&#34;&gt;Wisdom&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental fortitude, willpower, and common sense. Add your Wisdom modifier
to your initiative rolls. Test your wisdom to resist horror, illusion,
and mental domination. If you ever have need of mental or spiritual hit
points of some kind, add your Wisdom modifier to the total. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;charisma&#34;&gt;Charisma&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leadership, likability, and social skills. Add your Charisma modifier to
reaction rolls, hireling Guts rolls, and your maximum number of
hirelings, with a minimum of 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;modifiers&#34;&gt;Modifiers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each attribute has an associated modifier, described in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ability&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Modifier&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4-6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7-8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13-15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16-17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;use-as-saving-throws&#34;&gt;Use as Saving Throws&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attributes are used to make any saving throws. If something seems
clearly like a raw test of an ability and not involving any skill, try
to roll equal to or lower than the ability score on a D20. These rolls
are subject to advantage and disadvantage like any other, which may be
determined by racial abilities, class abilities, or circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;movement&#34;&gt;Movement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All human and human sized characters have a movement score of 12, unless
otherwise modified. Wearied characters move at half movement rate. For
things requiring coordination or athleticism, roll a save against
movement as if it were an ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hit-points&#34;&gt;Hit Points&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hit points are really “don’t get hit&amp;rdquo; points, and are an abstract
representation of skill, luck, and toughness, but not always the ability
to take literal wounds. All characters have Hit Points based on a d6 hit
die, which they gain at every level up. New hit dice are rolled at level
up and the new maximum recorded. A character’s constitution modifier is
added to HP at level up, and some class templates add additional hit
points. Hit points are reduced by successful attacks. When a character
reaches zero HP, any additional hits will cause wounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;death-and-dying&#34;&gt;Death and Dying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, taking damage beyond 0 HP causes a wound - this can be
anything horrible in keeping with the nature of the attack. A second
wound will kill a character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that some campaigns will replace wounds with death and
dismemberment tables, death saving throws, or other approaches to tweak the levels of lethality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;recovering-hp&#34;&gt;Recovering HP&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full night’s rest (no watch shifts) with a a cover of some kind (roof, tent, et cetera) and a warm-enough blanket recovers all HP. If you don’t have a comfortable place or have to wake up in the night, only recover 1d6+level HP. Once per day, a good square meal (one ration’s worth per person) recovers 1d6+level HP. Recovered HP cannot go above a character’s maximum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;healing&#34;&gt;Healing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healing from lethal damage is trickier than recovering HP. As a balance between realism and playability, most wounds can be assumed to heal with one week of downtime with appropriate care. If magical healing is available, that may allow faster healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weapon-skill&#34;&gt;Weapon Skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weapon Skill measures a character’s ability to hit opponents in melee combat. When rolling to hit, players add their weapon skill to their attack roll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters start with a weapon skill of 1 and add +1 at every even
level. Some character templates will also increase weapon skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shooting-skill&#34;&gt;Shooting Skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shooting skill is like weapon skill for ranged weapons. Players add it
to their attack roll when making ranged attacks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters start with a shooting skill of 1. Some character templates
increase shooting skill, but it does not otherwise improve. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;character-skills&#34;&gt;Character Skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters have a number of skill slots equal to half their
intelligence. Skills are rated from 0 to 6. A skill cannot rate higher than a character’s current level.  To test a skill, roll 1d6 and add your skill - a total of 6 or more passes. Some skills can be attempted by anyone adventurer and can be rolled even with a skill value of 0.
Every time a character attempts a skill, mark a check next to it. When that character has at least a week of downtime, they may choose to test to advance any one skill that has 3 or more marks next to it. If so, erase all check marks and roll an intelligence save (roll equal to or under Intelligence). If this save is passed, advance the skill to the next rank. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gear-slots&#34;&gt;Gear Slots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A character can carry as many significant items as their strength value before becoming encumbered. You absolutely can’t carry more than your 1.5x your strength items. Especially large items (like two handed weapons or larger) take up two slots or more. Armor takes up one slot for every point of AC better than 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;character-weariness&#34;&gt;Character Weariness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever the exploration die comes up “Tired”, each character marks a tired pip. Encumbered characters mark two pips. When all three pips have been marked, a character becomes wearied and receives disadvantage on all rolls. If a character is both wearied and encumbered, they additionally take a -4 penalty on all rolls (so, roll two, keep the worst, and subtract 4. Good luck with that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;resting&#34;&gt;Resting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters can recover from one tired pip by taking an exploration turn and sharing around a ration (maximum 8 people). To recover from
weariness, a character must take an exploration turn and consume an
entire ration themselves. Note that in both cases, characters must also have water to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hirelings&#34;&gt;Hirelings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters may hire additional help. In most settings, manual labor will
be available, and sometimes hirelings willing to fight. They will need
to be compensated, either by a flat fee or a share of any treasure
recovered. They begin play with a personality and goals determined by
the game master, and have a Guts of 7. Each character can retain the
services of 1 hireling plus a number equal to their charisma modifier,
with a minimum of 1. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;experience&#34;&gt;Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;gaining-experience&#34;&gt;Gaining Experience&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters gain experience by obtaining treasure through adventurous
means - looting dungeons, pulling off heists, getting rewarded for
rescuing royalty, and so forth. One experience point per one standard coin. Characters also gain a small amount of experience from killing enemies (25 XP per HD). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some campaigns may introduce alternate or additional methods of gaining XP as a way to encourage different play styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;leveling-up&#34;&gt;Leveling Up&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every character gains certain things when leveling up, represented in the chart below. For the first four levels, characters gain a class template per level, but none thereafter. Note that HP and Weapon skill can be modified by other sources, such as class templates and attribute modifiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Level&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;HP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Templates&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Max Skill&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Weapon Skill&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;XP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;26000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploration&#34;&gt;Exploration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;turns&#34;&gt;Turns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the players are exploring a dangerous environment like a dungeon, play is broken down into turns. A turn is not a fixed amount of time, but instead represents the amount of time it takes to perform a significant dungeon exploration task such as picking a lock, breaking down a door, or searching a a reasonably sized room. When in doubt, assume it’s roughly ten minutes. Roll the exploration die every turn - I recommend having a different player roll every time to make real the tradeoff between the actions they take and potential costs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploration-movement&#34;&gt;Exploration Movement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During exploration turns, players can move up to their movement x 10 in linear feet, which assumes a careful pace, checking for traps, taking the time to map, and so on. See the combat section for movement in combat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;hoofing-it&#34;&gt;Hoofing It&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player characters can double their exploration speed if they opt to
&lt;em&gt;hoof it&lt;/em&gt;, but this opens them to a 2-in-6 chance of being surprised by foes. While &lt;em&gt;hoofing it&lt;/em&gt; players may not map any new areas and are more likely to be caught unaware by traps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;pursuits&#34;&gt;Pursuits&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If characters are being chased, each group rolls 1d20 and adds their
movement score. The higher score wins the pursuit. The pursued group
uses the lowest movement score available, while the pursuers use the
fastest movement rate available. While in a pursuit, PCs may not map and should be told minimal details by the referee. Absent a clear intention declared at the start of the pursuit (“head back the way we came!”), the referee will determine randomly which directions PCs take at intersections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If desired, pursuits can be resolved on an individual basis, with each character rolling separately and adding their own movement. NPC or monster pursuers should still only make one roll. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the PCs are pursued by NPCs, dropping things that the pursuers find valuable (like treasure for intelligent pursuers or food for beasts) causes the pursuers to make a Guts check. Failure indicates they stop to gather the desired goods. Obstacles like flaming oil or caltrops can also discourage pursuit, causing a Guts check modified by the severity of the obstacle at the referee’s discretion. Players can make their own decisions on how to deal with similar obstacles left by NPCs or monsters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;load&#34;&gt;Load&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;gear-slots-1&#34;&gt;Gear Slots&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters can carry a number of significant items up to their Strength
score before becoming &lt;em&gt;Burdened&lt;/em&gt;. Characters absolutely cannot carry
more items than Str x 1.5. Anything tiny (could fit in your mouth or
closed hand) does not count as a significant item, and bundles of some
items count as a significant item (for example, a number of arrows equal
to one usage die, or 3 torches). Large items, such as two handed
weapons, take up two slots. Armor takes up one slot for each point of AC
it improves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money and gems take up one slot per 1,000 coins or gems - basically it
only matters for giant hoards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;effects-of-burden&#34;&gt;Effects of Burden&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Burdened *characters suffer disadvantage on any physically challenging
roll - combat, pursuits, stealth, and so on. Additionally, when the
Tired result comes up on the exploration die, encumbered characters mark
two Tired pips instead of one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;light&#34;&gt;Light&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since so much of this game takes place in underground places unfriendly
to surface dwellers, light is very important to explorers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;dark&#34;&gt;Dark&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absolute pitch blackness of an underground place with no light
sources, civilized people do not do well. No skill rolls can be
attempted, and players suffer double disadvantage on all other rolls,
including combat, saves, and pursuit rolls. Hirelings must make a Guts
roll at disadvantage to do anything other than panic or collapse, unless
the darkness was intentional (such as dousing all lights to avoid
attention). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player characters in the dark have a 2 in 6 chance of surprising NPCs or
monsters (and vice versa), and no one can be targeted by missile weapons
in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a full turn in the dark, characters gain advantage on any Wisdom
saves to listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;dim&#34;&gt;Dim&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dim light is provided either by inadequate light sources like candles or
from inadequate total illumination. In dim conditions, most characters
suffer disadvantage on all skill checks and attack rolls. The exception
is stealth rolls, which are at an advantage in dim conditions. Some
class and race templates will allow characters to ignore the
disadvantages of dim conditions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player characters have a 2 in 6 chance of surprising NPCs or monsters in
dim conditions (and vice versa), and individuals can only be targeted at
close range by missile weapons. Hirelings take their Guts rolls at a
disadvantage in dim conditions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lit&#34;&gt;Lit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With adequate light, the PCs and their allies receive no penalties, but
it is impossible to surprise NPCs or Monsters unless encountering them
through a newly opened door, on a roll of 1 in 6. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Light Amount&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Effect on Skills&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Effect on Other Rolls&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Surprise Chance&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Missile Targeting&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dark&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None allowed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Double Disadvantage**&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 in 6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dim&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Disadvantage*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Disadvantage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 in 6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Close&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None***&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Any&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Except Stealth, which gains advantage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Except for testing Wisdom to listen, which gains advantage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***Except through closed doors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;light-sources&#34;&gt;Light Sources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the default light sources, but may be changed or supplemented
depending on the campaign’s equipment list. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Candles&lt;/strong&gt;: Provide dim light to one character in a radius of 10 feet. Can
be stuck to helmets, wedged on the top of backpacks, and otherwise
affixed to allow hand’s free use. Six take up one gear slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Torches&lt;/strong&gt;: Allows three characters to be lit, and three more to have dim
light, and shows clearly for 30 feet. May be used as a crude weapon,
doing 1d3 damage with a 1 in 6 chance to set things on fire. Unless
specified, characters are assumed to place torches on the ground in
combat and to recover them after. May be used to light flammable things
on fire as a free action. Three take up one gear slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lanterns&lt;/strong&gt;: Provide enough light for two characters to be fully lit, and
two more to have dim light. Can be attached to belts or harnesses, but
if this is done, they will be hit on a successful attack roll of 15 or
higher. Can be thrown as an improvised firebomb, destroying the lantern
and doing 1d3 damage on the first round, and 1d6 every round thereafter,
extinguishing if a 1 is rolled for damage or if the target or its allies
takes action to put out the fire. A full oil flask provides two pips
worth of Lantern depletion before running out of fuel. Takes up a gear
slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weariness-in-exploration&#34;&gt;Weariness in Exploration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;getting-wearied&#34;&gt;Getting Wearied&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any time the Tired result is rolled on the exploration die, every
character marks a Tired pip (two if the character is encumbered). When
all three Tired pips are filled, the character becomes Wearied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;effects-of-weariness&#34;&gt;Effects of Weariness&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearied characters suffer disadvantage on all rolls and halve their
movement value. This stacks with any other disadvantage affecting the
character, forcing them to roll twice, keep the worst, and subtract four
(most commonly encountered as the combination of overload and
weariness). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;removing-tiredness-and-weariness&#34;&gt;Removing Tiredness and Weariness&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters may erase one Tired pip by spending an exploration turn
sharing around a ration (maximum of eight people per ration) and
drinking water. Wearied characters may erase all Tired pips and remove
their condition by spending an exploration turn eating a full ration
each and drinking water. Waterskins have a usage die of D6 when full.
Sleeping through the night (or at least for several hours), even with a
guard shift, will remove all Tired pips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-exploration-die&#34;&gt;The Exploration Die&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exploration die is rolled every turn in a dangerous environment like
a dungeon. It may also be used for wilderness exploration, although some
modifications would be appropriate, especially regarding light
depletion. I recommend the players roll the exploration die, in the
open, to make real the tradeoffs between courses of action and resource
depletion. It also makes things easier for the referee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;1D6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Exploration Die Result&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Random Encounter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Environmental Encounter or Sign of Random Encounter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Torches/Candles Depleted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lanterns Mark 1 Pip (2 Pips to Depletion)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Magic Dissipates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tired - All Characters Mark One Tired Point, Two if Encumbered&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;random-encounter&#34;&gt;Random Encounter&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The referee rolls on an appropriate encounter table and follows the
rules in the encounters section for determining distance, surprise, and
reaction rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;environmental-encounter&#34;&gt;Environmental Encounter&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something relevant to the area being explored is revealed the
characters, or perhaps just something atmospheric. Where possible, this
should give the players more information and improve their agency. If
appropriate, this may be a sign of a potential random encounter, such as
the tracks of a beast or grafitti left by intelligent monsters, in which
case the players may be able to track the sign to the encounter’s lair. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;torchescandles-depleted&#34;&gt;Torches/Candles Depleted&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any torches or candles being used as light sources go out and are used
up. New ones can be retrieved and re-lit on the next exploration turn
without preventing an action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lanterns-mark-1-pip&#34;&gt;Lanterns Mark 1 Pip&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lantern filled with a full flask of oil takes two pips to go out. Mark
one pip each time this is rolled. Refilling a lantern takes an
exploration turn, as it is significantly fiddlier than lighting a
torch. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;magic-dissipatescountdown&#34;&gt;Magic Dissipates/Countdown&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any ongoing magical effects step down one level or completely dissipate.
This may also be used to keep track of “ticking clock” scenarios, such
as the completion of a ritual in a number of check marks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;tired&#34;&gt;Tired&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each character marks one Tired pip, while encumbered characters mark
two. Please note that this includes hirelings. Once a character has
accumulated three tired marks, they become Wearied and suffer
disadvantage on all rolls and halve their movement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;meetings&#34;&gt;Meetings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;surprise&#34;&gt;Surprise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When characters move at normal exploration speed, they can normally not
be surprised. If they are &lt;em&gt;hoofing it&lt;/em&gt; or if the foe is very sneaky,
they have a 2-in-6 chance of being surprised. NPCs may be surprised by
PCs if they work to be stealthy and are not well-lit in a dungeon. It is
possible for both sides to surprise the other, in which case every one
stands around shocked for a moment but otherwise the surprise is
canceled. Some creatures or skilled NPCs may have a higher chance of
surprise, and players may increase their chance of surprise if they take
particular precautions, such as exceptional concealment, dousing lights,
and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A group that surprises another group has a free round to act in any way
they choose. Monsters and NPCs should make a reaction roll as normal.
After the first round, if the encounter continues, roll initiative as
normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;held-surprise&#34;&gt;Held Surprise&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprise need not mean fighting right away. Any group that surprises the
other “has the drop on them” and can hold surprise: if the meeting turns
to fighting, the group that surprised the other still gets a free round
to do as they please before the other side can act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reaction-rolls&#34;&gt;Reaction Rolls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When NPCs or monsters become aware of the player characters, they should
make a reaction roll. Depending on the circumstances, this may or may
not be modified by a PC’s Charisma - for example, a group of NPCs
surprising the PCs would not be modified, but if both parties warily
approach each other and the PCs shout out something re-assuring, the
Charisma modifier would apply. The modifier of whichever character acts
as spokesman should be used. Reaction rolls may be re-tested when
significant decisions are required, such as accepting or rejecting a
deal, deciding to reveal information, and so on. In these cases the
reaction roll should be modified by the spokesman’s charisma and any
relevant circumstances, such as the quality of the player’s arguments,
bribes offered, what the referee knows about these NPCs, and conditions
in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make a reaction roll, the referee rolls 2d6, adds any relevant
modifiers and consults the table below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2 or Less&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Violent&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Angry&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Threat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Warning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Guarded&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neutral&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neutral&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Positive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Helpful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Amicable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12 or More&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friendly&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rounds&#34;&gt;Rounds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During encounters, time is focused in on rounds, rather than the longer
exploration turns. As with turns, this is an abstract measure of time
that covers roughly doing one thing that matters (such as an attack).
Use rounds even for non-violent (initially) encounters to represent back
and forth and potentially good times to re-check reaction rolls.
Generally assume that an encounter ends up taking a full turn unless it
is exceptionally long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;initiative&#34;&gt;Initiative&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each character rolls 1d6 and adds their Wisdom modifier. Monsters and
NPCs are assumed to have a Wisdom modifier of 0 unless otherwise noted
in their profile. Characters, NPCs, and Monsters act in descending order
of Initiative, which is re-rolled for every round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fighting&#34;&gt;Fighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;movement-in-a-fight&#34;&gt;Movement in a Fight&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, characters can move from one of the below ranges to the next
in combat by spending an action, and may move within their current range
band for free. If you are getting nitty-gritty with a map or miniatures,
assume that characters can move roughly their movement score x2 in feet,
or their movement score divided by 3 in inches/squares if using ~28mm
miniatures (That’s 4 inches/squares with standard “heroic scale”
miniatures or ~24 feet if using a map). Movement can be blocked within
arm’s reach of enemies you wish to move past. For any movement that
requires athletic prowess (leaping over chasms, out-sprinting an
opponent, et cetera) roll a save against movement as if it were an
attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;target-20-to-hit-roll&#34;&gt;Target 20 To Hit Roll&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic to hit mechanic is “Target 20” which means that a player rolls
1d20, adds their character’s Weapon Skill or Bow Skill, their target’s
AC, and if the total is equal to 20 or higher, they hit their target.
Monsters follow the same procedure, assuming 1 WS per HD, unless
otherwise specified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;critical-hits-and-fumbles&#34;&gt;Critical Hits and Fumbles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A roll of a “20” indicates a critical hit, which hits automatically and
allows the player to choose between either double damage or a normal
attack plus some kind of “bonus” like tripping, disarming, knocking
over, and so on. A roll of a “1” indicates a fumble, which automatically
misses, and either results in a free attack by their target, or
something terrible that is situationally appropriate, at the referee’s
discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some class templates, conditions, or other rules may extend the range
for either critical hits or tables to include rolls other than “1” or
“20”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ranged-combat&#34;&gt;Ranged Combat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranged combat is resolved the same as melee, except that Bow Skill
rather than Weapon Skill is added to the attack roll, and targets may be
selected that are farther away. If firing into melee, a miss on an
attack roll of 1-5 will hit a random ally involved in the melee, doing
full damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ranges&#34;&gt;Ranges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Touching&lt;/strong&gt;: Intimately close - grappling or otherwise forced very close
together. Can only use close weapons like daggers or natural weapons.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hand-to-Hand&lt;/strong&gt;: Standard combat range, right at the edge of each other’s weapon
ranges. All melee weapons can be used at this range, but ranged weapons
cannot.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Close&lt;/strong&gt;: Within throwing distance. Ranged weapons can be used on targets
in dim or bright light, and characters can move into melee range and
attack if desired.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Far&lt;/strong&gt;: Beyond throwing distance. Lit targets can be targeted with ranged
weapons, but not targets in dim light. Spend a round moving to get
within Close range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fighting-options&#34;&gt;Fighting Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Charge&lt;/strong&gt;: Move at full speed into combat with any unengaged opponent that
you can reach. Gain advantage to hit, but note that you are at greater
risk from braced weapons. Requires a bit of open space to get moving.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Brace&lt;/strong&gt;: Get a reactive attack against an opponent that comes within melee
range. Most effective with reach weapons where the opponent may not be
able to attack you despite coming into range.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Press&lt;/strong&gt;: Gain advantage on your attack roll but AC is 4 worse.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Defend&lt;/strong&gt;: Improve AC by 2, but cannot attack this round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some class templates may provide additional Fighting Options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fighting-conditions&#34;&gt;Fighting Conditions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Floored&lt;/strong&gt;: Knocked prone on the floor. Can defend yourself only. Enemies
gain advantage to hit you. Takes a full action to stand up.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Stunned&lt;/strong&gt;: Prone, dazed. No actions can be taken. Enemies gain double
advantage to hit you.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Helpless&lt;/strong&gt;: Paralyzed or unconscious. Enemies hit automatically and deal
wounds rather than HP damage.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bleeding Out&lt;/strong&gt;: Player must roll a constitution save every round. After
three failures, the character dies. May be stabilized by an ally rolling
1d6 + Int modifier, with a 6 or higher succeeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bare-handed-fighting&#34;&gt;Bare-Handed Fighting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Punches, kicks, and the like do 1d3 damage unless the character has special training
(such as through a class template) or possesses natural weapons (like
claws or sharp teeth). Unarmed damage beyond 0 HP knocks out the target
(Helpless) and only deals wounds if the attacker so chooses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fighting-stunts&#34;&gt;Fighting Stunts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to do something in a fight other than hurt your foe, like tripping someone,
pushing through a shieldwall, climbing onto a large monster, or the like,
first make an attack against your foe as if they are unarmored. If you
fail, your foe gets a free attack on you. If you succeed, roll 1d6
and add the right attribute modifier (dexterity for something
fiddly like a trip, strength for shoving people around, intelligence for
faking them out, and so forth). A score of 6 or higher succeeds. The referee may impose modifiers or grant advantage or disadvantage to your role depending on the
circumstances. The referee may also tell you risks that may occur if you
fail before you attempt your trick, so be ready for those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some example stunts include tripping, wrestling, shoving backward,
disarming, shoving something in a large mouth, climbing onto a large
opponent, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;guts-rolls&#34;&gt;Guts Rolls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters and NPCs are subject to Guts rolls anytime the referee wants
to check whether they would keep going with what they&amp;rsquo;re doing or quit,
such as danger, extremely unpleasant conditions, or taking casualties,
in or out of combat. Guts is rated from 3 to 12 and is tested by the
referee rolling 2d6, with results equal to or below their Guts
passing. It is the referee’s choice when foes will roll a Guts check,
but some common reasons are taking their first casualty,
being reduced to half strength, losing a leader, or encountering
something that might cause fear. Hirelings may make Guts rolls
(modified by their employer’s Charisma) when asked to do something
dangerous, nasty, or outside of their job description, as well as when
combat may not be going well for the players’ group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;armor-and-armor-class&#34;&gt;Armor and Armor Class&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armor class defines your character’s overall defensive ability. An
unarmored opponent has an Armor Class of 9, while one in full plate with
a shield has an AC of 2. Descending armor class seems a little weird,
but it makes the Target 20 math super easy, so I like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some campaigns may allow piecemeal armor or alternative approaches. The
specifics of what armor maps to Light, Medium, or Heavy will vary
depending on the equipment list for the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;armor-types-and-values&#34;&gt;Armor Types and Values&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Light&lt;/em&gt; (Leather): 7&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt; (Chain): 5&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Heavy&lt;/em&gt; (Plate): 3&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Shield&lt;/em&gt;: 1 Better (so, one lower)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;death-and-dying-1&#34;&gt;Death and Dying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters reduced to 0 HP suffer a wound if they take any further
damage before restoring their HP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;wounds&#34;&gt;Wounds&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters that are damaged after being reduced to 0 HP take a wound and
are immediately Stunned or Helpless depending on the type of wound and
the circumstances. Some wounds may cause the character to begin Bleeding
Out. In any case, a second wound will kill the character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referees who are worried they will be either too soft or too hard
without guidance can use the following chart as a default, but it should
be modified by the nature of the attack and the surrounding
circumstances:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Roll&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Wound&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Severe Head Wound - Helpless, Bleeding Out&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Severe Gut Wound - Helpless, Bleeding Out&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nasty Cut - Stunned, Bleeding Out&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Maimed/Broken Limb - Stunned&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cracked Rips - Stunned&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Light Head Wound - Prone&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this rule may be replaced by some kind of death and
dismemberment chart or other approach in some campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weapon-abilities&#34;&gt;Weapon Abilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since all weapons do the same damage, they are distinguished by certain
characteristics. Some class templates may specify that certain classes
may only use weapons with certain abilities, or that certain abilities
are only usable by classes that specify know how. Also note that
campaigns may add to, subtract from, or modify the list below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heavy&lt;/strong&gt;: Heavy Weapons have advantage on damage, but require two hands to use and
penalize initiative by one, unless the character wielding is inhumanly
strong or enormous. Includes huge swords, axes, and hammers, but
depending on the campaign might also include rifles or others.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Light&lt;/strong&gt;: Weapon has disadvantage on damage. Includes most improvised weapons like
chairs or broken bottles, but also certain thrown weapons like javelins
or knives.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Reach&lt;/strong&gt;: Can be used to attack from the second rank (over the shoulder of someone
in front of you). If Braced, can perform a reactive attack for x2 damage
on the first opponent to charge within range. 
&lt;strong&gt;Close&lt;/strong&gt;: Not only allowed to be used at Near range, which is usually only
achieved by ambush or shenanigans (wrestling), grants advantage on
damage. Most close weapons can be used at melee range for normal damage.
Includes daggers and most natural weapons.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Reactive&lt;/strong&gt;: Allows you to interrupt an incoming attack with an attack that resolves
first. Especially dangerous when combined with reach in the form a
braced spear or similar. Some weapons are only reactive conditionally
(like a braced spear), while others may always be (such as pistols in
appropriate campaigns). Note that a reactive weapon only grants one
attack, unless the campaign rules specify otherwise.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Crushing&lt;/strong&gt;: These weapons are designed to smash through heavy armor. Any armor
granting AC better than 5 counts as 5 against crushing weapons. Note
that this only applies if the AC is derived from physical weight of
armor - plate, scales, carapace or the like. AC derived from nimbleness,
magic, or otherworldly nature is unaffected. In the case of monsters,
the reason for a given armor class (and whether crushing weapons reduce
it) is left to the discretion of the referee.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finesse&lt;/strong&gt;: These weapons allow a much better trade-off between attack and defense.
When pressing with a Finesse weapon, only reduce AC by 2, and when
defending, you may still make an attack, but with disadvantage. Includes
most types of swords that are neither heavy nor cleaving.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cleaving&lt;/strong&gt;: These weapons allow an immediate follow-up attack on a nearby enemy
after landing a killing blow. Includes light axes, falchions, and
scimitars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;doing-stuff&#34;&gt;Doing Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;skills&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;skill-slots&#34;&gt;Skill Slots&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters have a number of skill slots equal to half their
intelligence, rounded down. They may never have more skills than skill
slots. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;skill-rank&#34;&gt;Skill Rank&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every skill is ranked from 0 to 6, and characters may not have a skill
with a higher rank than their level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;using-skills&#34;&gt;Using Skills&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use a skill, roll 1d6 and add your relevant skill - if the result is
six or higher, it succeeds. A roll of 1 always fails. Occasionally
circumstances may be especially favorable or the chances of your skill
being relevant are extremely slim. Your referee may grant you advantage,
disadvantage, or a small modifier to the roll, if so. Some skills can be
attempted when you are untrained (rank 0) but not all, see below. Every
time you use a skill, successful or not, put a check mark next to it on
your character sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;improving-skills&#34;&gt;Improving Skills&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you character has a week of downtime that is not taken up by
healing or other full time action like research, they may practice a
skill and attempt to raise its rank. Remember that rank cannot rise
above your current level. To attempt to raise a skill, erase all marks
and make an intelligence save (roll 1d20 and attempt to get equal to or
lower than your intelligence) - if successful, increase your skill rank
by 1. Some things may improve your chance of learning, such as a
knowledgeable mentor, access to appropriate facilities, or the like. If
so, make the save with advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;untrained-skills&#34;&gt;Untrained Skills&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some skills, but not all, can be attempted without any training at rank
0. This is the referee’s call, but in general it should be limited to
things anyone can try to do without any particular knowledge, like
sneaking around, searching a room, or identifying if a structure looks
dodgy or not. In the case of knowledge based skills, like history or
lore, it is up to the referee how much this field is “common knowledge” - if it’s something almost anyone might have picked up, allow an
untrained attempt, but if it requires specific mastery, do not. For
example, in the modern world, it would probably be fair to allow someone
a check for general knowledge of the Romans, but only an attempt to read
a passage in Latin if they have the skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-skills-are-available&#34;&gt;What Skills are Available?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, skills are left open ended, to be defined as needed in play.
Players and the referee can hash out how specific/general skills can be,
and what advantages they can confer. Some campaigns will include fixed
skill lists, no skills at all, or alternate skill rules. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-not-to-use-skills-for&#34;&gt;What NOT to Use Skills For&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skills should not have a direct use in combat, except occasionally for
stealth, and should not be used for persuasion or social skills. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;advantage--disadvantage&#34;&gt;Advantage &amp;amp; Disadvantage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many things in the game will give your character advantage or
disadvantage on a roll, such as the situation, class abilities, or being
encumbered. Advantage means that you roll two dice and keep the better
result. Disadvantage means you roll two and keep the worse. If you ever
have double advantage, roll two, keep the better, and improve the roll
by 4. If you have double disadvantage, roll two, keep the worse, and
make worse by 4. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;usage-dice&#34;&gt;Usage Dice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anything that gets used up that isn’t otherwise covered (such as by
the exploration die), represent their availability with usage dice. Any
time you use the item, roll on its usage die. A roll of 1 or 2 indicates
that you step down one die size in the following chain. Rolling a 1 or 2
on a D4 means that you are out of that item and have to purchase more.
Items will have a relevant usage die listed next to them. Buying extras
takes up an additional slot but increases the usage die by one step. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out &amp;lt; D4 &amp;lt; D6 &amp;lt; D8 &amp;lt; D10 &amp;lt; D12 &amp;lt; D20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;character-growth&#34;&gt;Character Growth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;experience-points&#34;&gt;Experience Points&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All characters measure their advancement in skill and ability through
experience points (XP), when enough XP are earned, characters advance in
level and gain several perks detailed in the Leveling Up section below.
All characters advance in level at the same rate detailed in the chart
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;standard-level-up-chart&#34;&gt;Standard Level Up Chart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Level&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;HP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Templates&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Max Skill&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Weapon Skill&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;XP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;26000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+1D6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;earning-experience&#34;&gt;Earning Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters can earn experience in a number of ways. The default ways are
listed below, but some campaigns may introduce alternate methods of
earning experience, such as fulfilling quests, meeting objectives, or
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;treasure-looted&#34;&gt;Treasure Looted&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary means of earning experience is through obtaining objects of
material worth through adventurous means. This might mean piles of coins
from a dragon’s hoard or fine art stolen from a rich widow’s house. In
any case, such treasure is worth 1 XP per Standard Coin of value. If it
is ever unclear if treasure has been “recovered”, consider whether it
was physically returned to a relatively civilized area, or if stolen in
a civilized environment, to the character’s lair. Getting ripped off by
unscrupulous fences won’t deny characters XP, but being waylaid by
bandits between the dungeon and town will. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guys from the Thieves’ Guild that Fafhrd and the Gray Mouser ripped
off in Ill Met in Lankhmar did not receive experience for their
treasure, whereas Fafhrd and the Gray Mouser did, despite eventually
losing the treasure, because they got it back home and bought several
rounds of booze with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;killing-enemies&#34;&gt;Killing Enemies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, player characters will receive 25 XP per HD of a dangerous
foe killed. This does not distinguish between “monsters” or “people”,
but some campaigns may wish to do so, if they have a greater or lesser
focus on conflict between “civilized” people. Note that this is
intentionally rather small compared to the potential rewards for
treasure, because XP for treasure tends to encourage more interesting
gameplay than XP for killing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;leveling-up-1&#34;&gt;Leveling Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a character has achieved the required experience for the next level
and has at least a week of downtime, they Level Up to the next level.
Follow the procedure below at each level up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;add-new-hp&#34;&gt;Add New HP&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through level 10, roll a new d6 HD and add the result to your
character’s HP. Add your constitution modifier to the roll. After
level 10, add 2 HP per level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;check-for-weapon-skill-improvement-and-add-if-relevant&#34;&gt;Check for Weapon Skill Improvement and Add if Relevant&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At every even level, add +1 to your character’s Weapon Skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;select-and-apply-class-templates-max-4&#34;&gt;Select and apply class templates (max 4)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For their first four levels, characters select a class template from
those the referee has made available and apply the appropriate
abilities. Each class has templates labeled A, B, C, D. You have to take
the templates in order - you can’t pick ‘B’ without ‘A’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After level 4, characters receive no more class abilities - additional
power will have to come from other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;primary-class-and-multi-classing&#34;&gt;Primary Class and Multi-classing&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each class has a “primary ability”. A character’s primary class is
whichever one they have chosen the most templates from. In the case of a
tie, pick whichever you prefer. Multi-classing is simply having
templates from more than one class, and characters will only possess the
primary ability of their primary class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;up-max-skill-rank&#34;&gt;Up Max Skill Rank&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until level six, note your characters new max Skill Rank to
correspond to your new level. Max Skill Rank Six is the highest for any
character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;referee-stuff&#34;&gt;Referee Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;treasure&#34;&gt;Treasure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most treasure will be in Lairs of some kind, for which the table below
will work, but when in doubt, you may substitute the level of the
dungeon or the average player level for the monster HD to create a basic
hoard:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;HD of Owner&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Two Above Base Coin (1d12 - 6x)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;One Above Base Coin (1d6x)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Base Coin&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4-5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6-7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the following for non-cash treasure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Die Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value Per Item&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Clothing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d6 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fine apparel and hangings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10x5 2 Above Base coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Goods&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d8 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Well-made useful things&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2d10x10 2 Above Base Coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Artwork&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paintings, statues, etc&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10x20 2 Above Base Coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gem/Jewel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d12 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gems&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10x50 2 Above Base Coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Magic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d20 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Magic Items&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Generate as B/X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Rolling maximum results adds an additional re-roll of same potential
value&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;monsters--npcs&#34;&gt;Monsters &amp;amp; NPCs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the many things monsters and NPCs can do is fight the Player
Characters. NPCs might have stats similar to PCs if they are important
enough, but the below monster profile provides the barebones necessary
for combat. NPCs are assumed to be average in every way (attributes =
10) unless otherwise specified, so go with that when you have not
prepared specifics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;monster-profile&#34;&gt;Monster Profile&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following stat line can be used to summarize the relevant combat
statistics for monsters and NPCs. Obviously, good monsters and NPCs will
be more than these stat lines with interests, motivations, special
attacks, weaknesses, and so on - but this is what you need at a moment’s
notice when the dice hit the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mv&lt;/strong&gt;: How far this thing can move. If roughly humanoid, the standard movement
rate is 12, which translates into 120 feet per exploration turn and 24
feet per combat round. Roll this as a save if the monster attempts any
kind of athletics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WS&lt;/strong&gt;: The monster’s weapon skill is added to its D20 rolls to hit opponents.
Usually equal to the Monster’s HD, unless their fighting ability does
not match their toughness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS&lt;/strong&gt;: The monster’s shooting skill is added to its D20 attack rolls for ranged
attacks. Most monsters will either have 0 or 1 Shooting Skill, or it
will be equal to their HD, depending on if they are incapable of
shooting, can give it a shot (hah), or are trained archers/shootists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Att&lt;/strong&gt;: The number of attacks the monster can make in a turn. If more than one,
be on the look out for special attacks, which will hopefully be marked
with an asterisk or the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HD&lt;/strong&gt;: The number of hit dice the monster has (D6s). For full on randomness,
roll a number of D6s equal to this score per opponent to determine hit
points. If you’re in a rush, assume 3.5 per die and round down (if you
are soft) or round up (if you are hard) for every foe of the same time.
If you have to worry about the monster’s “level”, such as for some spell
effects, use HD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AC&lt;/strong&gt;: The monster’s armor class - this may reflect armor worn, naturally thick
hide, great reflexes, or any other number of reasons for being hard to
wound. Have some idea what contributes to this before going into a
fight, as players may try to take advantage of different characteristics
(such as using Crushing weapons against mundane armor or magical weapons
against demonic foes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the equivalent of a player’s Wisdom modifier and is added to the
monster’s initiative roll. The default is ‘0’, but especially quick or
dangerous monsters may have more. Usually it is most convenient to roll
for all monsters with the same stats as one group. Feel free to go more
granular, but it sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sv&lt;/strong&gt;: If the monster is ever called upon to make a saving throw, use this
number. The default is 10. Some monsters may note that they have a
variable save based on the type of danger (such as a very robust but
dumb monster getting a bonus to saves against physical damage but a
penalty to mental manipulation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gts&lt;/strong&gt;: Most frequently, the monster’s Guts measures its willingness to
continue a fight. It is a score from 3 to 12, and to test it, the
referee rolls 2d6 - a score equal to or below Guts indicates a
success. These rules are usually made on behalf of a group of creatures
with the same Guts, which may be influenced by a leader. Occasionally,
Guts will be used as a more generalized “will they/won’t they” stat
for Monsters, at the referee’s discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;monster-hd&#34;&gt;Monster HD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All monsters have a hit dice rating that is the equivalent of character
level. Their HD are all D6s. Some monsters may have HP adjustments to
their HD. HD may be rolled individually per monster or assumed to be an
average of 3.5, rounded down (if you are soft) or rounded up (if you are
hard). With large groups of monsters, it is usually preferable to assume
constant HP for all monsters of identical stats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;monster-ws&#34;&gt;Monster WS&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless otherwise specified, monsters default to +1 WS per HD. Some
monsters will adjust this up or down depending on their inclination to
kill things. This is somewhat more dangerous than most adventurers, but
they need all the help they can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;monster-damage&#34;&gt;Monster Damage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with characters, all monster damage is equal to D6 per attack by
default. Some special attacks may gain advantage, and some very special
attacks may roll multiple dice or larger dice for damage. The referee is
encouraged to design such monsters sparingly, and to be careful when
converting monsters from versions later than OD&amp;amp;D, as D6 HD PCs are
much more fragile than their later edition cousins. It is generally
preferable for monsters to be made more dangerous through multiple
attacks, inflicting special penalties, or affecting an area, rather than
upping the HP output for a single attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;treasure-1&#34;&gt;Treasure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;pocket-change&#34;&gt;Pocket Change&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intelligent monsters can be assumed to carry some small amount of money
about on their persons. Such monsters and characters can be assumed to
carry 1d10 x HD^2 in base coins - on a roll of ’10’, roll again for the
next highest denomination of coin, and if that comes up a ’10’, give
this random schmoe some minor treasure or special item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some especially wealthy characters or creatures may have more on them
than this, but they should be correspondingly more carefully guarded
and/or careful with where they keep their wealth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lairs&#34;&gt;Lairs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters of the treasure hoarding kind will have more treasure in their
lair than on their person. In such cases, you can either place whatever
treasure you like, or you can use the following tables to get some
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;HD of Owner&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Two Above Base Coin (1d12 - 6x)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;One Above Base Coin (1d6x)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Base Coin&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$50.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4-5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6-7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d100 x100xHD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the following for non-cash treasure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Die Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value Per Item&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Clothing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d6 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fine apparel and hangings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10x5 2 Above Base coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Goods&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d8 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Well-made useful things&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2d10x10 2 Above Base Coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Artwork&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paintings, statues, etc&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10x20 2 Above Base Coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gem/Jewel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d12 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gems&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d10x50 2 Above Base Coins*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Magic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1d20 vs W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Magic Items&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Generate as B/X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Rolling maximum results adds an additional re-roll of same potential
value&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;guts-rolls-1&#34;&gt;Guts Rolls&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters will generally test their Guts in a few standard situations,
and also whenever the referee deems it situationally appropriate. Some
standard reasons to roll Guts: ambushed from surprise, take first
casualty, reduced to half strength, lose leader or champion, subject to
infighting. Guts is something of a catch all for determining monster
behavior outside of direct reaction to the player characters (for which
we have the reaction roll). When failed the referee should have the
monsters react according to their base nature, rather than what is best
for them: cowardly ratmen might flee a fight despite seemingly
overwhelming odds, whereas Ogres might stay and try to eat their foes
despite being desperately outclassed and ordered to run away. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;experience-1&#34;&gt;Experience&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters offer 25 XP per HD when killed by the player characters. Some
campaigns may allow that XP for “circumventing” or “solving” those
monsters, but by default, such indirect means are intended to be
captured by the (faster moving) system of gaining XP for treasure. Some
especially dangerous or important monsters may offer more experience, at
the referee’s discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
- /gaming/2017-12-12-russell-house-rules-core/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 