<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Books on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Intuition</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-power-of-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-power-of-intuition/</guid>
      <description>By Gary Klein
The very same things are what excited me and disappointed me the most in this book. It presents intuition as a very no-nonsense ability that is critical for effective decision making, and gives advice on how to train to be better at it. Exactly what I wanted! On the other hand, it describes &amp;ldquo;intuition&amp;rdquo; as simply the ability to learn to detect patterns and apply past experiences to current situations, without consciously realizing you&amp;rsquo;ve made that match - which is rather less romantic than I might hope for something as big and spooky as &amp;ldquo;intuition&amp;rdquo; to be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Consolations of Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-consolations-of-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-consolations-of-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>By Alain de Botton
This book provides a great overview of the tradition of Western philosophy. Besides providing useful summaries of some of the major thinkers and what their philosophy can do for you in your life, it shows the the connecting threads between thinkers that might seem totally unrelated at first glance. Each chapter gives a brief thumbnail of the biography and thinking of a major philosopher, which is great, but what&amp;rsquo;s really useful about this book is that every chapter addresses a specific concern that everyone faces - such as unpopularity, money, and frustration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zen &amp; The Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/zen-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/zen-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</guid>
      <description>By Robert Pirsig
Despite my initially somewhat negative reaction to this book, it has become one of my &amp;ldquo;operating manuals&amp;rdquo; for life. Even when I first read it and disagreed with much of what it said, I found a lot of compelling food for thought. Paradoxically, the very thing that made me uncomfortable initially has become its greatest value to me: the questioning of received ideas of values and building new ones up from scratch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Artist&#39;s Way</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-artists-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-artists-way/</guid>
      <description>By Julia Cameron
I have to admit that if I picked this book up sight unseen and flipped through it, I would likely have put it back on the shelf - it has a lot of markers for being a bit too &amp;ldquo;woo woo&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;touchy feely&amp;rdquo; for my usual tastes. Fortunately, it came highly recommended by a bunch of well-grounded people that I respect, so I decided to give it a shot, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad I did.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategy: A History</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/strategy-a-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/strategy-a-history/</guid>
      <description>By Lawrence Freedman
Man oh man am I loving this book. It puts out a comprehensive record of thinking about the concept of strategy in western thought from the Bible and Homer all the way to modern theorists. Along the way, Freedman provides analysis of the strengths and shortcomings of the various formulations and their applications. Despite what might turn into a dry, intellectual subject, the book is quite clear and readable, moving briskly through trends and eras of thought.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 4-Hour Chef</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-4-hour-chef/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-4-hour-chef/</guid>
      <description>By Tim Ferriss
Besides being a phenomenal &amp;ldquo;learn to cook from nothing&amp;rdquo; cookbook, this also actually a book on how to learn anything. Meta-learning is like catnip to me, and I was already a huge Tim Ferriss fan when this came out, so I snapped it right up. Apparently it hasn&amp;rsquo;t done as well as his other books and it was dealing with it&amp;rsquo;s rough release that led him to start his podcast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Elements of Style</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-elements-of-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-elements-of-style/</guid>
      <description>By William Strunk, Jr. and E.B. White
I mentioned this book in my post on Storytelling Resources, but I thought it deserved its own call out. An incredibly slim book, you can read and understand it in an evening, but will likely return to it again and again. This book clearly lays out the rules of modern American usage and style, favoring concise, vigorous prose. Even if you enjoy waxing more eloquent, this provides a great starting place from which to depart.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leonardo da Vinci</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/leonardo-da-vinci/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/leonardo-da-vinci/</guid>
      <description>By Walter Isaacson
I have long irrationally avoided biographies, despite encountering a few excellent ones like Team of Rivals, so I decided I needed to remedy that to read one about a personal hero of mine. Leonardo stands as the archetypal &amp;ldquo;Renaissance Man&amp;rdquo;, with achievements in art, architecture, science and more all under his belt. His brilliant and beautiful notebooks make any journaler feel inadequate. And yet, one of the most reassuring parts of this book is that it seems unlikely that Leonardo was as set apart intellectually as an Einstein or a Newton, nor as naturally artistically gifted as a Michaelangelo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graphic Storytelling and Visual Narrative</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/graphic-storytelling-and-visual-narrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/graphic-storytelling-and-visual-narrative/</guid>
      <description>By Will Eisner
Written by a giant of the sequential art field, this book covers the insights from decades of creating and teaching about the use of comics to tell stories. Eisner defends and establishes the usefulness and seriousness of the form as a literary medium, capable of addressing themes and issues that matter. The central tenet of the book is that the visuals must be shaped by the needs of the story and not the other way around - otherwise you get lured into meaningless set pieces that serve no purpose but to show off something that looks good.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Save the Cat!</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/save-the-cat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/save-the-cat/</guid>
      <description>By Blake Snyder
Tim Ferriss recommended this book for writers of all kinds, despite its focus on screenwriting. I came to it in order to get a variety of perspectives on storytelling (speaking, writing fiction, writing screenplays, and so forth). Despite the fact that I often watch movies and think &amp;ldquo;I could have written something better than that!&amp;quot;, I have no particular ambition to become a screenwriter, but I have nonetheless found this little book quite helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning Pro</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/turning-pro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/turning-pro/</guid>
      <description>By Steven Pressfield
We&amp;rsquo;ve talked before about War of Art and it&amp;rsquo;s discussion of Resistance, the force within us that stops us from creating and achieving what we might. Well, Turning Pro is Pressfield&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;how to&amp;rdquo; on overcoming that force, and it mostly comes down to doggedly showing up to do the work every day, regardless of how inspired you&amp;rsquo;re feeling. While I find War of Art more inspirational overall, this work is a great companion that gives you concrete steps of what to do when you commit to following the advice in WoA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Show and Tell: How Everybody Can Make Extraordinary Presentation</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/show-and-tell-how-everybody-can-make-extraordinary-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/show-and-tell-how-everybody-can-make-extraordinary-presentation/</guid>
      <description>By Dan Roam
I&amp;rsquo;ve been using the approach outlined in this book for years now, thanks to some fantastic mentors at work, but I only just got around to reading it. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what took me so long to get to it - it was great, and it only took me a little over two hours to read even taking a lot of notes. The basic premise of the book is that you should tell the truth, you should tell it as a story, and you should present the story with pictures as much as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Story Grid</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-story-grid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-story-grid/</guid>
      <description>By Shawn Coyne
This book has been on my list for a long time, but I only just now got around to reading it, and man was I missing out! It breaks down the mysterious art of writing a story that &amp;ldquo;works&amp;rdquo; into comprehensible and testable steps. That&amp;rsquo;s what I think is most remarkable about this book: not that it tells you the components of a story that works (we&amp;rsquo;ve been getting that since Aristotle), but that it gives you tools to tighten up the feedback loop on your stories - you can evaluate your success or failure and make adjustments using these tools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Rules</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/simple-rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/simple-rules/</guid>
      <description>By Donald Sull and Kathleen Eisenhardt
This book identifies six types of &amp;ldquo;simple rules&amp;rdquo; that offer enough guidance to be useful but enough flexibility to respond to complexity. More exciting than that, it walks through how to create your own simple rules for work and life. Unless you&amp;rsquo;re my kind of geek, it&amp;rsquo;s not the sexiest topic in the world, but for one thing, it&amp;rsquo;s shockingly useful, and for another, the authors use a conversational tone that makes for pleasant reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How We Got to Now</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/how-we-got-to-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/how-we-got-to-now/</guid>
      <description>By Steven Johnson
I worry a bit that this is becoming the Steven Johnson fan club, but I am really enjoying his books recently. This one takes a look at history through the lens of what was made possible through the development of some key technologies, like glass and sanitation. Besides providing a plethora of fun trivia, like the fact that in the mid nineteenth century it was more practical to raise the entire city 10 feet than to tunnel under it to install a sewer system, or that chlorinating water reduced infant mortality by ~40%, the book provides a fascinating reframe of how we normally process history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synchronicity</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/synchronicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/synchronicity/</guid>
      <description>By Carl Gustav Jung, trans H.F.C. Hull
If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you probably have a vague idea of Jung from high school English classes, and something about archetypes. Maybe you heard he was an important influence on Lucas when he made Star Wars. If you studied psychology, you may have gotten a brief discussion about how he was important psychologist for a while, but we&amp;rsquo;ve moved past his outdated theories. Well, I&amp;rsquo;m here to tell you that Jung is both weirder and smarter than you probably think, and that makes it worth reading his stuff for yourself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of the Bicameral Mind</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-origin-of-consciousness-in-the-breakdown-of-the-bicameral-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-origin-of-consciousness-in-the-breakdown-of-the-bicameral-mind/</guid>
      <description>By Julian Jaynes
I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist a book about where the voice in your head comes from when today&amp;rsquo;s post is about imagining other people&amp;rsquo;s voices. I have no idea at how well regarded this book is currently as a credible explanation of where consciousness came from, but it makes a fantastic tool for imagining what if the world really were that way? What would it mean? The book argues that &amp;ldquo;consciousness&amp;rdquo; - an almost unending voice in your head that narrates your thoughts and what&amp;rsquo;s going on and is perceived as &amp;ldquo;yourself&amp;rdquo; is actually a rather recent phenomenon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extreme Ownership</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/extreme-ownership/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/extreme-ownership/</guid>
      <description>By Jocko Willink and Leif Babin
This one is not explicitly about creativity, but I think you&amp;rsquo;ll find it more helpful in that respect than you might think at first glance. Written by a pair of Navy SEAL officers who served together in Ramadi, Iraq when it was at its worst, this book lays out deceptively simple principles for effective leadership. I say deceptive because simple does not mean easy. Following the straightforward advice is much harder than understanding it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ego is the Enemy</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/ego-is-the-enemy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/ego-is-the-enemy/</guid>
      <description>By Ryan Holiday
Ryan Holiday has been behind a lot of what I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about here and a lot of the links I&amp;rsquo;ve shared, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t called him out explicitly yet. He&amp;rsquo;s a modern day exponent of an ancient philosophy, and though my interest in stoicism predates my exposure to Holiday, I have found his works useful and engaging. He&amp;rsquo;s best known for The Obstacle is the Way, which has been hugely influential with top performers from the business world to the NFL, but I have found this book more useful personally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Technique for Producing Ideas</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/</guid>
      <description>By James Webb Young
This book might be the best &amp;ldquo;bang for the buck&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen - at 42 pages, you can easily read it in an evening and almost every single page is chock full of useful, actionable tips. It lays out the steps to follow in order to generate new, creative ideas. While it lacks some of the concepts we go through in our creativity series, it easily integrates with them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antifragile</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/antifragile/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/antifragile/</guid>
      <description>By Nassim Taleb
The core concept explored in this book is what is &amp;ldquo;risk&amp;rdquo; and how should we think about it in our lives, but it reaches out and touches so many more areas of interest. Taleb is shockingly smart, enjoyably contrarian, and writes in a very engaging way. This book is one of my top five life and brain changing books - you will be a little bit smarter every time you read it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deskbound</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/deskbound/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/deskbound/</guid>
      <description>By Kelly Starrett and Juliet Starrett
By now, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard about how bad sitting is for you, and maybe you&amp;rsquo;ve even seen or used a standing desk somewhere. Well, this book lays down the case for why sitting is literally killing us in stark, terrifying detail, and proceeds to provide specific, step by step instructions on how to do something about it. It&amp;rsquo;s not as simple as buying a standing desk and burning your chair - you have to re-teach your body appropriate ways of moving after years oflearning the wrong thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/</guid>
      <description>By Scott Adams
The core thesis of this book is that goals are for losers, systems are for winners, and passion is bullshit. When I finally got around to actually reading it, I was pleasantly surprised to find it absolutely jam packed with useful little nuggets. Seriously, this is one of the highest &amp;ldquo;actionable stuff to fluff&amp;rdquo; self-improvement books I&amp;rsquo;ve ever read. While it is full of specific tactics, the real value of this book is how it points out the complex system that leads to your energy, output, and ultimately success.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/influence/</guid>
      <description>By Robert B. Cialdini
This book is a classic for a reason - I&amp;rsquo;ve taken my sweet ass time getting to it, but I am absolutely hooked. Drawing on a combination of scholarly experiments and &amp;ldquo;in the trenches&amp;rdquo; experience with sales training, this book points out thenearly automatic triggers we have evolved to be good, cooperative members ofsociety and how &amp;ldquo;compliance professionals&amp;rdquo; (salesmen, recruiters, and cons) use these techniques to get their way without you even knowing what they&amp;rsquo;re about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lateral Thinking</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/lateral-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/lateral-thinking/</guid>
      <description>By Edward de Bono
I mentioned this book in the previous posts on creativity, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t get its own spotlight yet. It&amp;rsquo;s a classic in the realm of creativity, and a lot of what has been developed since builds on its solid foundation. It takes an extremely practical approach by recommending various exercises a teacher might assign students to encourage and develop lateral thinking, but these are just as easily self-imposed by those of us lacking adult supervision.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Love Yourself Like Your Life Depends on It</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/love-yourself-like-your-life-depends-on-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/love-yourself-like-your-life-depends-on-it/</guid>
      <description>By Kamal Ravikant
This one didn&amp;rsquo;t quite make it on to my list of operating manuals, in part because I just finished it a week or two ago and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how much of an impact it&amp;rsquo;s had on me yet. It might sound hopelessly like positive thinking hippy dippy crap, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting more and more convinced about the power of auto-suggestion, in part because of the Scott Adams persuasion reading list I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Combat</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/on-combat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/on-combat/</guid>
      <description>By Lt. Col. Dave Grossman
This book might seem out of left field for those of you outside of the military or law enforcement, but I think it has several valuable lessons for everybody. First off, it will help you to understand many of the dynamics going on - on both sides - of the deadly force encounters you hear about in the news. Secondly, it&amp;rsquo;s breakdown of the physical, psychological, and environmental factors of the most extreme kind of stress can be reverse-engineered to the more mild kinds of stress most of us are lucky enough to deal with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Checklist Manifesto</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-checklist-manifesto/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-checklist-manifesto/</guid>
      <description>By Atul Gawande
I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to read this book for a long time, but to be perfectly honest, I was worried it was one of those books where if you know the premise you don&amp;rsquo;t need to read it. What I had overlooked is the degree to which making the case for checklists would motivate me to actually change my behavior. The examples given of lives saved and fortunes made through the seemingly simple expedient of using checklists are quite impressive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Design of Everyday Things</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-design-of-everyday-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-design-of-everyday-things/</guid>
      <description>By Don Norman
This book came highly recommended to me by a friend of mine at work and it certainly did not disappoint. It focuses on questions of how objects in our environment can enhance (or detract) from our experience and our lives. Most useful to me was the distinction between affordances and signifiers and the notion of &amp;ldquo;knowledge in the head&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;knowledge in the world.&amp;rdquo; If you&amp;rsquo;re even a little bit interested in how the objects, structures, and organizations around you shape your life in subtle ways, you&amp;rsquo;ll thoroughly enjoy this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The One Minute Workout</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-one-minute-workout/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-one-minute-workout/</guid>
      <description>By Martin Gibala, Christopher Shulgan
Tim Ferriss and Ramit Sethi like to joke about how much their book titles sound like infomercials, but I have to admit that this book has them beat by a mile - One Minute Workout? That&amp;rsquo;s even crazier than six minute abs. What you find when you actually dig in, though, is a thorough discussion of the science and benefits of High Intensity Interval Training. Even better, it presents a variety of HIIT workouts you can try out for your own health.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The People Code: It&#39;s All About Your Innate Motive</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-people-code-its-all-about-your-innate-motive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-people-code-its-all-about-your-innate-motive/</guid>
      <description>By Dr. Taylor Hartman, Ph.D.
I&amp;rsquo;m not gonna lie to you, friends: I was pretty skeptical of this system when I first heard about it at work. One of my business school professors engrained a deep distrust of &amp;ldquo;personality types&amp;rdquo; in general by pointing out that almost all of them except The Big Five lack any rigorous empirical testing. That being said, as I read this book, time and again I saw descriptions that rang extremely true for either myself or my loved ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Full Engagement</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-power-of-full-engagement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-power-of-full-engagement/</guid>
      <description>By Jim Loehr and Tony Schwartz
I started reading this book because I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered the idea of managing &amp;ldquo;energy&amp;rdquo; in several places, and I wanted an adequate description to work with. This book did not disappoint. As I read, I kept thinking &amp;ldquo;this reminds me of Josh Waitzkin&amp;rsquo;s advice in The Art of Learning, so I went back and checked, and sure enough, he trained with the authors. While the physical and emotional energy stuff is useful, I found this work&amp;rsquo;s definition of &amp;ldquo;spiritual&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;caring about something larger than yourself beyond your own self-interest&amp;rdquo; to be the most straightforward and practical definition I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rise and Fall of D.O.D.O.</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-rise-and-fall-of-dodo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/the-rise-and-fall-of-dodo/</guid>
      <description>By Neal Stephenson and Nicole Galland
Neal Stephenson is probably my favorite living author, and so I buy anything with his name on it no questions asked. I tore through this on my recent flight to Beijing and rather enjoyed it. A shadowy government organization discovers that magic used to be real but doesn&amp;rsquo;t work anymore, and then figures out a way to make it work again to send people back in time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools of Titans</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/tools-of-titans/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/tools-of-titans/</guid>
      <description>By Tim Ferriss
I&amp;rsquo;ve been a fan of Ferriss for years, but I think this book is far and away his best yet. It&amp;rsquo;s chock full of great stuff that you can use right now to make your life better - whether to get healthy, make money, or feel more calm in your life. If you only ever read one book of his, make it this one. Hell, if you only read one self-improvement book period, make it this one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waking Up</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/waking-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/waking-up/</guid>
      <description>By Sam Harris
In this book, Harris makes a case for spiritual practice without the scaffolding and foundation of religious beliefs. While he approaches it as an avowed and enthusiastic atheist, I think that the core insight that there are certain practices you can adopt to bring peace, contentment, and compassion into your life without adopting beliefs you are uncomfortable with is useful regardless of your religious convictions. The descriptions of what it feels like to meditate and what it feels like to think you&amp;rsquo;re meditating when you aren&amp;rsquo;t really are worth the price of admission by themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Good Ideas Come From</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/where-good-ideas-come-from/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/where-good-ideas-come-from/</guid>
      <description>By Steven Johnson
I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to read this book ever since listening to James Altucher&amp;rsquo;s interview with the author and it did not disappoint. Wide ranging and diverse in the best possible way, this book draws on examples as diverse as the building of coral reefs and the founding of YouTube to elucidate the components of systems that most reliably produce useful innovation - whether in nature, science, or business.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero to One</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/zero-to-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/zero-to-one/</guid>
      <description>By Peter Thiel with Blake Masters
If you spend as much time as I do listening to podcasts by Silicon Valley types, you&amp;rsquo;ve been hearing about this book for ages. I&amp;rsquo;ve been putting off reading it because I figured &amp;ldquo;well, I&amp;rsquo;m not starting a tech company, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply to me.&amp;rdquo; Turns out that was a silly and limited way to think about the book. I ended up valuing it more for its discussion of the secrets that are the root of real economic value and its concepts of definite versus indefinite optimism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zhuangzi: Basic Writings</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/zhuangzi-basic-writings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/books/zhuangzi-basic-writings/</guid>
      <description>By Zhuang Zi, trans. Burton Watson
This is an excerpt of the complete Zhuangzi, and I&amp;rsquo;m normally a rabid completionist, but there are three facts that lead me to recommend this edition: 1) This is the version I had in my physical library and therefore read, 2) The translator makes a pretty good case that what is excluded is mostly later (less awesome) additions to the work of the original author, and 3) you can get this excerpt for about one third of the price of the complete works.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>