<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wargames on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/wargames/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wargames on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2010 14:40:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/wargames/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Shootin&#39; Stuff</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-10-shootin-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2010 14:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-10-shootin-stuff/</guid>
      <description>So, the first topic I&amp;rsquo;d like to address here with regard to my skirmish rules is of central importance to a modern/sci-fi wargame: shooting stuff. I&amp;rsquo;m going to start out a little theoretical and then move into some practicalities as they relate to those theories.
So, the way I see it, in a skirmish wargame, shooting has two main intentions: to control movement and to remove enemy fighters. The second is fairly obvious, but there are some implications to it I want to discuss, so I&amp;rsquo;ll start with &amp;ldquo;controlling movement&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Necromunda Skirmish Redux</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-10-necromunda-skirmish-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2010 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-10-necromunda-skirmish-redux/</guid>
      <description>So, awhile back I started on the somewhat ambitious project of coming up with some miniature skirmish rules that would be extremely customizable but still balanced for competitive play. I started with the notion of wanting to play &amp;ldquo;Necromunda&amp;rdquo; but with more individuality and perhaps a heavier story focus.
So, a few months back, I went through the Necromunda, Mordheim, and Inquisitor rules and looked for ideas to modify, incorporating ideas from a WWII skirmish game my friend Lance and I developed a few years back (initially based on Games Workshop&amp;rsquo;s Lord of the Rings game, but since modified beyond recognition).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>