<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 13:17:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Deskbound</title>
        <link>/books/deskbound/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/deskbound/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/deskbound/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Kelly Starrett and Juliet Starrett&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard about how bad sitting is for you, and maybe you&amp;rsquo;ve even seen or used a standing desk somewhere. Well, this book lays down the case for why sitting is &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; killing us in stark, terrifying detail, and proceeds to provide specific, step by step instructions on how to do something about it. It&amp;rsquo;s not as simple as buying a standing desk and burning your chair - you have to re-teach your body appropriate ways of moving after years oflearning the wrong thing. Fortunately, the prescriptions in this book are easy to follow and will give you immediate relief as well as long-lasting solutions to problems like stiff backs, joint pain, and chronic stress. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Deskbound-Standing-Up-Sitting-World-ebook/dp/B01E1HDJ64/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1504820657&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=deskbound&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/deskbound/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big</title>
        <link>/books/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Scott Adams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core thesis of this book is that &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage1.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=8e5461f8de&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;goals are for losers, systems are for winners, and passion is bullshit&lt;/a&gt;. When I finally got around to actually reading it, I was pleasantly surprised to find it absolutely &lt;em&gt;jam packed&lt;/em&gt; with useful little nuggets. Seriously, this is one of the highest &amp;ldquo;actionable stuff to fluff&amp;rdquo; self-improvement books I&amp;rsquo;ve ever read. While it is full of specific tactics, the real value of this book is how it points out the complex system that leads to your energy, output, and ultimately success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/How-Fail-Almost-Everything-Still-ebook/dp/B00COOFBA4/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507240924&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=how+to+fail+at+almost+everything+and+still+win+big&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Influence</title>
        <link>/books/influence/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/influence/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/influence/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Robert B. Cialdini&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a classic for a reason - I&amp;rsquo;ve taken my sweet ass time getting to it, but I am absolutely hooked. Drawing on a combination of scholarly experiments and &amp;ldquo;in the trenches&amp;rdquo; experience with sales training, this book points out thenearly automatic triggers we have evolved to be good, cooperative members ofsociety and how &amp;ldquo;compliance professionals&amp;rdquo; (salesmen, recruiters, and cons) use these techniques to get their way without you even knowing what they&amp;rsquo;re about. This book is doubly valuable - you learn how to spot unscrupulous applications of the techniques as well as how to use them in your own (hopefully legitimate) endeavors. For lots of interesting extra context, check out Scott Adams&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=1a94281bd0&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;Persuasion Reading List&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Influence-Psychology-Persuasion-Business-Essentials-ebook/dp/B002BD2UUC/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1504820925&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=influence&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/influence/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Lateral Thinking</title>
        <link>/books/lateral-thinking/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/lateral-thinking/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/lateral-thinking/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Edward de Bono&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this book in the previous posts on creativity, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t get its own spotlight yet. It&amp;rsquo;s a classic in the realm of creativity, and a lot of what has been developed since builds on its solid foundation. It takes an extremely practical approach by recommending various exercises a teacher might assign students to encourage and develop lateral thinking, but these are just as easily self-imposed by those of us lacking adult supervision. My very favorite takeaway from this book is the idea that sometimes to get to a good idea, you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to go through a bad idea first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like this sort of thing, check out my posts on creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Lateral-Thinking-Creativity-Step-ebook/dp/B003V1WTLI/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241682&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=lateral+thinking&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/lateral-thinking/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Love Yourself Like Your Life Depends on It</title>
        <link>/books/love-yourself-like-your-life-depends-on-it/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/love-yourself-like-your-life-depends-on-it/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/love-yourself-like-your-life-depends-on-it/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Kamal Ravikant&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; make it on to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;list of operating manuals&lt;/a&gt;, in part because I just finished it a week or two ago and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how much of an impact it&amp;rsquo;s had on me yet. It might sound hopelessly like positive thinking hippy dippy crap, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting more and more convinced about the power of auto-suggestion, in part because of the Scott Adams &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage1.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=08b4705a3e&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;persuasion reading list&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before. So I&amp;rsquo;m giving the approaches recommended in this book a good, honest try before I either dismiss it or sing its praises. If you do the same, let me know how it works out for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Love-Yourself-Like-Your-Depends-ebook/dp/B0086BX8UE/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241184&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=love+yourself+like+your+life+depends+on+it&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/love-yourself-like-your-life-depends-on-it/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>On Combat</title>
        <link>/books/on-combat/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/on-combat/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/on-combat/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Lt. Col. Dave Grossman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book might seem out of left field for those of you outside of the military or law enforcement, but I think it has several valuable lessons for everybody. First off, it will help you to understand many of the dynamics going on - on both sides - of the deadly force encounters you hear about in the news. Secondly, it&amp;rsquo;s breakdown of the physical, psychological, and environmental factors of the most extreme kind of stress can be reverse-engineered to the more mild kinds of stress most of us are lucky enough to deal with. Finally, it just might help you prepare for unlikely but terrible life-threatening situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Combat-Psychology-Physiology-Deadly-Conflict-ebook/dp/B072HHSZNN/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507240858&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=on+combat&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/on-combat/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Checklist Manifesto</title>
        <link>/books/the-checklist-manifesto/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-checklist-manifesto/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-checklist-manifesto/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Atul Gawande&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to read this book for a long time, but to be perfectly honest, I was worried it was one of those books where if you know the premise you don&amp;rsquo;t need to read it. What I had overlooked is the degree to which making the case for checklists would motivate me to actually change my behavior. The examples given of lives saved and fortunes made through the seemingly simple expedient of using checklists are quite impressive. Plus, there&amp;rsquo;s a neat checklist for creating your own checklist in the back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to up your game to true professionalism in just about any field, check out this book. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right-ebook/dp/B0030V0PEW/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507240882&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=checklist+manifesto&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-checklist-manifesto/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Design of Everyday Things</title>
        <link>/books/the-design-of-everyday-things/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-design-of-everyday-things/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-design-of-everyday-things/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Don Norman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book came highly recommended to me by a friend of mine at work and it certainly did not disappoint. It focuses on questions of how objects in our environment can enhance (or detract) from our experience and our lives. Most useful to me was the distinction between &lt;em&gt;affordances&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;signifiers&lt;/em&gt; and the notion of &amp;ldquo;knowledge in the head&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;knowledge in the world.&amp;rdquo; If you&amp;rsquo;re even a little bit interested in how the objects, structures, and organizations around you shape your life in subtle ways, you&amp;rsquo;ll thoroughly enjoy this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Design-Everyday-Things-Revised-Expanded-ebook/dp/B00E257T6C/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241058&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+design+of+everyday+things&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-design-of-everyday-things/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The One Minute Workout</title>
        <link>/books/the-one-minute-workout/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-one-minute-workout/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-one-minute-workout/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Martin Gibala, Christopher Shulgan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage1.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=93bd7aa625&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;Tim Ferriss&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=e611468584&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;Ramit Sethi&lt;/a&gt; like to joke about how much their book titles sound like infomercials, but I have to admit that this book has them beat by a mile - One Minute Workout? That&amp;rsquo;s even crazier than &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=65db2ca6d1&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;six minute abs&lt;/a&gt;. What you find when you actually dig in, though, is a thorough discussion of the science and benefits of High Intensity Interval Training. Even better, it presents a variety of HIIT workouts you can try out for your own health. Bang-for-buck-wise, HIIT is the king of exercises. Even better, training your heart to speed up and slow down regularly has dramatic effects on your brain&amp;rsquo;s ability to do the same - so following the workouts in this book will help you not only be healthier, but more creative to boot. Not a bad deal for one minute (plus another 9 of warm up, cool down, and rest - but I can&amp;rsquo;t blame them for the catchy title).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/One-Minute-Workout-Science-Smarter-Shorter-ebook/dp/B01IOHQ7RA/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241847&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=one+minute+workout&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-one-minute-workout/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The People Code: It&#39;s All About Your Innate Motive</title>
        <link>/books/the-people-code-its-all-about-your-innate-motive/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-people-code-its-all-about-your-innate-motive/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-people-code-its-all-about-your-innate-motive/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Dr. Taylor Hartman, Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not gonna lie to you, friends: I was pretty skeptical of this system when I first heard about it at work. One of my business school professors engrained a deep distrust of &amp;ldquo;personality types&amp;rdquo; in general by pointing out that almost all of them except &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=86f302a397&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;The Big Five&lt;/a&gt; lack any rigorous empirical testing. That being said, as I read this book, time and again I saw descriptions that rang extremely true for either myself or my loved ones. It&amp;rsquo;s probably easy to take this too far and use it as some kind of universal theory, but it makes an awfully useful heuristic for understanding why you act the way you do, and more importantly, why other people act in such seemingly incomprehensible ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/People-Code-About-Innate-Motive-ebook/dp/B000W5MI7G/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241030&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+people+code&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-people-code-its-all-about-your-innate-motive/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Power of Full Engagement</title>
        <link>/books/the-power-of-full-engagement/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-power-of-full-engagement/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-power-of-full-engagement/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Jim Loehr and Tony Schwartz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started reading this book because I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered the idea of managing &amp;ldquo;energy&amp;rdquo; in several places, and I wanted an adequate description to work with. This book did not disappoint. As I read, I kept thinking &amp;ldquo;this reminds me of Josh Waitzkin&amp;rsquo;s advice in The Art of Learning, so I went back and checked, and sure enough, he trained with the authors. While the physical and emotional energy stuff is useful, I found this work&amp;rsquo;s definition of &amp;ldquo;spiritual&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;caring about something larger than yourself beyond your own self-interest&amp;rdquo; to be the most straightforward and practical definition I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered. A lot of ideas from this book have been incorporated elsewhere, but it&amp;rsquo;s full of specific case studies and examples of how the concepts have been applied in a variety of situations. Great stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Power-Full-Engagement-Managing-Performance-ebook/dp/B000FC0SWS/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241154&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+power+of+full+engagement&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-power-of-full-engagement/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Rise and Fall of D.O.D.O.</title>
        <link>/books/the-rise-and-fall-of-dodo/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-rise-and-fall-of-dodo/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-rise-and-fall-of-dodo/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Neal Stephenson and Nicole Galland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neal Stephenson is probably my favorite living author, and so I buy anything with his name on it no questions asked. I tore through this on my recent flight to Beijing and rather enjoyed it. A shadowy government organization discovers that magic used to be real but doesn&amp;rsquo;t work anymore, and then figures out a way to make it work again to send people back in time. A fun read that touches on all of the exciting possibilities of magic, time travel, and quantum physics. Not as many detailed asides as a pure Stephenson book, but that means that it keeps moving at a brisk pace the whole time. Give it a shot if the idea of mashing up fantasy, sci-fi, and historical fiction gets you all hot and bothered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Rise-Fall-D-D-Novel-ebook/dp/B01M0HPHR6/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241220&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=rise+and+fall+of+dodo&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-rise-and-fall-of-dodo/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Tools of Titans</title>
        <link>/books/tools-of-titans/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/tools-of-titans/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/tools-of-titans/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Tim Ferriss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been a fan of Ferriss for years, but I think this book is far and away his best yet. It&amp;rsquo;s chock full of great stuff that you can use right now to make your life better - whether to get healthy, make money, or feel more calm in your life. If you only ever read one book of his, make it this one. Hell, if you only read one self-improvement book &lt;em&gt;period&lt;/em&gt;, make it this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Tools-Titans-Billionaires-World-Class-Performers-ebook/dp/B01HSMRWNU/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507240811&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=tools+of+titans&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/tools-of-titans/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Waking Up</title>
        <link>/books/waking-up/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/waking-up/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/waking-up/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Sam Harris&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book, Harris makes a case for spiritual practice without the scaffolding and foundation of religious beliefs. While he approaches it as an avowed and enthusiastic atheist, I think that the core insight that there are certain practices you can adopt to bring peace, contentment, and compassion into your life without adopting beliefs you are uncomfortable with is useful regardless of your religious convictions. The descriptions of what it feels like to meditate and what it feels like to &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; you&amp;rsquo;re meditating when you aren&amp;rsquo;t really are worth the price of admission by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Waking-Up-Spirituality-Without-Religion-ebook/dp/B00GEEB9YC/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/waking-up/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Where Good Ideas Come From</title>
        <link>/books/where-good-ideas-come-from/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/where-good-ideas-come-from/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/where-good-ideas-come-from/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Steven Johnson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to read this book ever since listening to James Altucher&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage1.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=7ba3665581&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;interview with the author&lt;/a&gt; and it did not disappoint. Wide ranging and diverse in the best possible way, this book draws on examples as diverse as the building of coral reefs and the founding of YouTube to elucidate the components of systems that most reliably produce useful innovation - whether in nature, science, or business. I would have liked just a hair more advice on how to operationalize the concepts, but as a foundation for thinking about hard problems that matter, this book was invaluable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Steven-Johnson-ebook/dp/B003ZK58TA/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241116&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=where+good+ideas+come+from&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/where-good-ideas-come-from/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Zero to One</title>
        <link>/books/zero-to-one/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/zero-to-one/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/zero-to-one/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Peter Thiel with Blake Masters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you spend as much time as I do listening to podcasts by Silicon Valley types, you&amp;rsquo;ve been hearing about this book for ages. I&amp;rsquo;ve been putting off reading it because I figured &amp;ldquo;well, I&amp;rsquo;m not starting a tech company, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply to me.&amp;rdquo; Turns out that was a silly and limited way to think about the book. I ended up valuing it more for its discussion of the secrets that are the root of real economic value and its concepts of definite versus indefinite optimism. It was also the inspiration for the current series, as it talked about the importance of creativity and implementation in building the future world. It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty quick read and well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Zero-One-Notes-Startups-Future-ebook/dp/B00J6YBOFQ/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241295&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=zero+to+one&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/zero-to-one/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Zhuangzi: Basic Writings</title>
        <link>/books/zhuangzi-basic-writings/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/zhuangzi-basic-writings/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/zhuangzi-basic-writings/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Zhuang Zi, trans. Burton Watson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an excerpt of the complete Zhuangzi, and I&amp;rsquo;m normally a rabid completionist, but there are three facts that lead me to recommend this edition: 1) This is the version I had in my physical library and therefore read, 2) The translator makes a pretty good case that what is excluded is mostly later (less awesome) additions to the work of the original author, and 3) you can get this excerpt for about one third of the price of the complete works. So, with that in mind, let me tell you what&amp;rsquo;s great about this book. It&amp;rsquo;s a lot more lively than most philosophy, featuring poetry, metaphor, and humor. I found it almost as valuable as a demonstration of an alternative way to convey deep, important ideas as I did for the actual ideas it was discussing. It&amp;rsquo;s also interestingly different from the Daoism you may know from the Daodejing. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to get a Yin-Yang symbol tattooed on me anytime soon, but I have found this a worthwhile addition to my mental tool kit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lots more on this book, check out the full post I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/27/the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Zhuangzi-Basic-Writings-Translations-Classics-ebook/dp/B007C5Z3HG/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/zhuangzi-basic-writings/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Practicing Divergent &amp; Convergent Thinking - Creativity Part 3</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/ -&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I had planned on covering all of the exercises in one post, but when I broke them out, I realized I would be delivering a gigantic, hard to digest mess. So I broke it up. Our next few posts will cover all of the exercises associated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/17/the-building-blocks-of-creativity&#34;&gt;building blocks&lt;/a&gt; we covered last time, starting with Divergent and Convergent thinking today. It’s a great place to start, because if you develop your ability to separate these two ways of thinking, everything else will flow naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many people, the skill you will most need to improve is your ability to think up ideas - &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Divergent_thinking&#34;&gt;active divergence&lt;/a&gt;. If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, this seems like a mysterious ability some people are born with, and is totally opaque. Fortunately, whether or not some folks are more naturally inclined to be good at it, you can practice and improve. My favorite practice for this comes from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesaltucher.com/&#34;&gt;James Altucher&lt;/a&gt;. Here it is: write 10 ideas on a prompt, once a day every day. That&amp;rsquo;s it. I first encountered it in his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Choose-Yourself-Guide-Wealth-ebook/dp/B00U7IS4S0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503612736&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=choose+yourself+guide+to+wealth&#34;&gt;The Choose Yourself Guide to Wealth&lt;/a&gt;, which is one of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;mental operating manuals&lt;/a&gt;, but you can also find it explained in this blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2011/02/how-to-be-the-luckiest-guy-on-the-planet-in-4-easy-steps/&#34;&gt;post on how to be &amp;ldquo;lucky&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The lists don&amp;rsquo;t even have to be on anything important - silly stuff works just as well for practicing. You aren’t shooting for good ideas, you just come up with a lot of ideas. This is pure active divergence practice. As you do this regularly enough, you will start finding it much easier to think things up on the spot in any situation, which comes in pretty darn handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you’re jamming on the above practice and you screech to a halt, unable to think of any more ideas. Here’s a few techniques you can use to get the juices flowing again. The first is &amp;ldquo;unclumping&amp;rdquo; - look at one of the ideas you’ve already written and ask yourself what every possible variation of that thing might be. Say your prompt was “things that are round,” and one of your ideas was “balls.&amp;rdquo; You could unclump that by writing baseballs, basketballs, bocce balls, et cetera. If you are wired like I am, this may feel like you are &amp;ldquo;cheating,&amp;rdquo; but actually you are stimulating exactly the muscle we want to exercise here. The next technique is to apply your five senses to the subject you are trying to generate ideas on. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;re locked into things that stimulate sight, or feel, and are ignoring others. In the case of things that are round, &amp;ldquo;smell&amp;rdquo; might make you think of an orange, or &amp;ldquo;taste&amp;rdquo; might prompt you to think of a scoop of ice cream - and then you can go off in a whole new direction. Finally, there&amp;rsquo;s a specific list of modifications you can apply in a handy acronym: T.R.A.N.S.F.O.R.M. - Twist/Turn, Rotate, Add, Novelize, Subtract, Fuse, Omit, Reverse, Minify/Magnify. I tend to default to unclumping when I feel stuck, but all three can really help you expand the number of ideas you generate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve covered how to generate more ideas, but some people find that relatively easy and instead are challenged by what to do with them once you have them. These people need more practice with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convergent_thinking&#34;&gt;active convergence&lt;/a&gt;. Personally, I find this far easier and more intuitive than cranking ideas out, so I&amp;rsquo;ve had to engage in some reflection and discussion with people who think differently from me to figure out what to recommend here. There are two main ways you can come at evaluating the ideas you have previously generated: bottom up or top down. Bottom up approaches focus on evaluating ideas based on their similarity to each other, whereas top down focus on rating ideas with respect to how they fit pre-defined criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal favorite convergence activity is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affinity_diagram&#34;&gt;affinity mapping&lt;/a&gt;. This is a bottom up approach used to organically figure out groupings and categories. To give it a try, first actively diverge as above, but put each idea on its own sticky note. Then, find a big stretch of wall or whiteboard and start putting the ideas up there . As you add ideas, look at the existing ones and ask yourself “do these go together?” If so, place them close to each other. Don’t worry too much about explicitly defining the criteria that makes them go together just yet. As you go through, you&amp;rsquo;ll find that some of your clumps maybe should be split up, and others should be merged - that&amp;rsquo;s okay, the point of the exercise is to discover these relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example top down approach is a model called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.decision-making-confidence.com/pugh-matrix.html&#34;&gt;Pugh Matrix&lt;/a&gt; - a name I only recently learned from an engineer friend for something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing for years. To do this, put each idea on a line in a spreadsheet. Then, label each column with the different criteria you are using. Then go through the matrix you just created and rate each criteria on the same scale (1-5 is a common one, but you can also go for binary or just use whatever makes sense). When you finish, you’ll have a score both for each individual criterion but also an aggregate. If you want to get real fancy, you can apply different weights to different criteria. You can then perform all sorts of manipulations on the data so created (averages, spreads, et cetera). Just be careful to remind yourself that this is still a qualitative and subjective tool, despite its appearance of being a quantitative and objective tool thanks to all those numbers - just remind yourself you made them all up, you didn’t measure them somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By way of an example, my wife and I applied this system when we bought a house. Before we started looking, we came up with a list of features that mattered to us. Once we had identified two houses we liked, we compared them by rating each characteristic. By going through piece by piece and seeing how both houses stacked up, it made it very clear which one we actually favored. So we put in an offer and ended up in a place we love, with the peace of mind that we thought out our decisions thoroughly.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above exercises are merely examples of the deeper principles of divergent and convergent thinking, but extremely useful and illuminating examples. Idea generation especially is a habit you can incorporate into your daily life and start noticing its application in diverse situations. Join us next time as we discuss how to apply and practice the two problem solving frameworks we introduced previously.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Building Blocks of Creativity - Creativity Part 2</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-08-18-the-building-blocks-of-creativity/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-08-18-the-building-blocks-of-creativity/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-08-18-the-building-blocks-of-creativity/ -&lt;p&gt;Last time we came up with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/11/creativity-part-1-defining-creativity&#34;&gt;definition of creativity&lt;/a&gt;, and today we’re going to talk about some of its core building blocks, from deferring judgment to the inputs you take in. These fundamental concepts will give you the raw materials you need to understand and undertake specific exercises to be more creative yourself - some of which we’ll detail in our next installment of the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and most important concept you need for better creativity comes from Edward De Bono’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Lateral-Thinking-Creativity-Step-ebook/dp/B003V1WTLI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1502986629&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=lateral+thinking&#34;&gt;Lateral Thinking&lt;/a&gt;: sometimes to get to a good idea, you have to go through a bad idea. Everything else we’ll talk about grows from this small seed. You can grasp this simple idea in moments, but like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reversi&#34;&gt;Othello&lt;/a&gt;, you can spend a lifetime truly mastering it. For your first challenge, the entire tradition of western thought has focused on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andyeklund.com/is-linear-thinking-bad/&#34;&gt;Linear Thinking&lt;/a&gt;, which de Bono contrasts with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lateral_thinking&#34;&gt;Lateral Thinking&lt;/a&gt; in his book of the same name. Our education and culture reinforce linear thinking relentlessly. It requires every step make sense and build to the next. It’s how you make &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argument#Deductive&#34;&gt;an argument that doesn’t suck&lt;/a&gt;. It’s how you prove things in math or map out a promising theory in science. If one step is wrong, every step after it is wrong, end of story. So when you operate in a linear thinking mode, you carefully check every step of progress to make sure you’re still on firm ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong: linear thinking is extremely important, despite being less sexy than lateral thinking. At some point, you have to figure out if your brilliant idea actually works. The trouble is that linear thinking can hamper you from having the good idea in the first place. Sometimes something silly or wrong gets you to look at a problem in a new way, which produces genuine insight. You give yourself permission to have bad ideas that can get to good ideas later with a habit of thought called &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.basadur.com/2015/02/04/does-deferring-judgment-really-impact-creativity-or-does-immediate-judgement-save-a-lot-of-time-and-provide-the-hard-nosed-focus-that-real-world-innovation-demands/&#34;&gt;Active Deferral of Judgement&lt;/a&gt;.  Simply catch yourself whenever you go “that was silly” or “that will never work” while you are trying to think up ideas. We’ll talk more in the next part of the series about techniques to build this habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deferring judgment lets us properly separate thinking into its two flavors: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cleverism.com/idea-generation-divergent-vs-convergent-thinking/&#34;&gt;divergent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cleverism.com/idea-generation-divergent-vs-convergent-thinking/&#34;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cleverism.com/idea-generation-divergent-vs-convergent-thinking/&#34;&gt;convergent&lt;/a&gt;. Divergent thinking is maximizing the number of ideas on the table - it is often referred to as ideation or idea generation. Convergent thinking is looking at previously created ideas and deciding which ones are relevant - it is often called evaluation. Both kinds of thinking are equally important and equally necessary - remember that my definition of creativity requires things be both new and useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out most of us find it easier to do one or the other, and if we don’t learn about these differences, we get puzzled by other people’s challenges. For example, I have a friend who can fill a page with brand new ideas while I’m still struggling to break 10. On the other hand, ask him to take 100 things and group them based on similarity and he’ll be agonizing while I’m happily clustering sticky notes. The important thing is &lt;a href=&#34;https://melanism.files.wordpress.com/2013/09/cropped-header2013.jpg&#34;&gt;don’t cross the streams&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike chocolate and peanut butter, these two flavors are not better together. Prematurely converging hinders your ability to produce ideas, and coming up with ideas distracts you from evaluating what you already have. Again, we’ll go into some tools next time for how to successfully separate these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I’m sure you will start applying the above concepts all over the place already, there’s another step for maximum effectiveness. If you point a group of people at a problem and say “Diverge then converge and come back to me with something great!” they’re probably going to spend a lot of time spinning their wheels. To get around that, you need a process or framework that gives guidance on what to diverge on, and what criteria to use for convergence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best frameworks for teams is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basadur.com/&#34;&gt;Basadur Applied Creativity&lt;/a&gt;. It consists of an eight part problem solving cycle with divergence and convergence in each phase. It’s remarkably effective for surfacing the best stuff from a group and generating creative solutions to problems with buy in from everyone on the team. I use it at work all the time, and I’m consistently amazed by what we we get when we use the process versus when we don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For individual creative pursuit, though, I find the Basadur approach a bit heavyweight. Instead, I prefer the framework laid out in &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Technique-Producing-Ideas-James-Young-ebook/dp/B00N33OYPI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1502990296&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=a+technique+for+producing+ideas&#34;&gt;A Technique for Producing Ideas&lt;/a&gt;. It is straightforward, actionable, and consistently produces individual insights when followed. Plus, you want to talk about bang for buck? This 42 page book will revolutionize how you work on your own creative projects. We’ll talk through how to apply both of these frameworks next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often overlook the last concept I want to talk about when we are thinking of creativity as an active pursuit: our &lt;a href=&#34;https://danielmiessler.com/blog/creative-output-requires-quality-inputs/#gs.WY=bvIM&#34;&gt;inputs&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to think well, you need things to think about, and those come from what you read, watch, hear, and do. Remember that our definition from last time emphasized the role of finding new connections between existing material in creativity. Your inputs determine both the existing material and the ideas for new connections you have to work with. We live in an age of near unlimited informational options, so next time I’ll discuss some of the ways I like to make decisions about what inputs to seek out and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we talked about, creativity is a much discussed topic, so I’ve left out a number of interesting ideas and focused on the most essential. You could do worse than to check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creativity&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; on creativity if you want to check out some stuff not covered here. I found the discussion of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creativity#Affect&#34;&gt;Affect&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creativity#REM_sleep&#34;&gt;Sleep&lt;/a&gt; especially thought provoking. I was also fascinated by &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Come-Innovation/dp/1594485380/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1502991782&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=where+good+ideas+come+from&#34;&gt;Where Good Ideas Come From&lt;/a&gt;, but it looks more at cultural and strategic ways to foster creativity - how does a society end up creative or what can someone do over the course of their life to cultivate creative insights, rather than “what can I do when I sit down with a specific problem today?” There’s a lot of high quality thinking out there on creativity, and I look forward to revisiting the topic for a long time to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I’ve laid out why Active Deferral of Judgement, Divergence/Convergence, Framework, and Inputs are the basic components of creativity. Next time we’ll go through examples of how to actually apply each of these concepts, but even without that, you now how a powerful toolbox for thinking about and working with creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-08-18-the-building-blocks-of-creativity/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Creativity Part 1 - Defining Creativity</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-08-11-creativity-part-1-defining-creativity/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-08-11-creativity-part-1-defining-creativity/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-08-11-creativity-part-1-defining-creativity/ -&lt;p&gt;When I sat down to write a post about innovation, I quickly realized we had an unwieldy topic on our hands. So, instead of a single post on innovation and the future, I’ve decided to kick off a short series on creativity. To begin with, I’ll provide my favorite definition of creativity and step through each piece of it and what it implies for applications down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about anyone you talk to wants to be “more creative,”  but what does that really mean? There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.copyblogger.com/define-creativity/&#34;&gt;lots&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basadur.com/insightsresearch/OurThoughtsonCreativityandInnovation/tabid/80/Default.aspx&#34;&gt;different&lt;/a&gt; ways to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dictionary.com/browse/creativity&#34;&gt;define&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creativity&#34;&gt;creativity&lt;/a&gt;, and some of them are maddeningly vague or fluffy. Often, we associate creativity only with “artsy” pursuits like painting or poetry and assume that it doesn’t apply to more hard-nosed disciplines. I think that nothing could be farther from the truth. So I’ve cobbled together various definitions in a way that is equally useful whether you are creating art or building a business: the ability to make useful new connections between concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start unpacking that definition, beginning with the core: making connections. We like to idealize creativity as conjuring something out of nothing, but really, to have new ideas, you have to have raw material. That’s one reason why creativity requires voraciously &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g2pre2xnA1M&#34;&gt;reading, watching, and listening to interesting and diverse material&lt;/a&gt;. No one argues that being creative is just knowing about a bunch of different stuff, though. You gotta connect that stuff. That’s one reason games, randomizers, and “oracles” can be so &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.creativethink.com/2007/01/use_a_random_id.html&#34;&gt;useful for spurring creativity&lt;/a&gt; - they force connections where none existed previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so if creativity is about making connections, the thing that makes those connections “creative” is that they are new. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taxonomy_(biology)&#34;&gt;first time&lt;/a&gt; someone noticed that cats and people and elephants have something in common with each other that they don’t with snakes and lizards, that was creative. Noticing it today is not. We are all standing on the shoulders of everyone who has come before us, extending the network of associations further and further into conceptual space.  At first this can seem a bit intimidating, like everything really worthwhile has already been figured out. Here’s the thing, though: because this network of connections that has been made, we have exponentially more raw material to work with than anyone else in the history of humanity. That’s pretty awesome if you ask me. We’re going to dive more into how lucky we really are when we talk about practical ways to be more creative in our own lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, our new connections must also be useful. As we’ll discuss later when we talk about specific techniques, it can actually hinder your ability to come up with stuff if start out too focused on “what’s useful.” That’s just a phase in the process though, and the difference between &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ted.com/40-idioms-that-cant-be-translated-literally/&#34;&gt;brilliant and silly&lt;/a&gt; is how much value people get out of the connection you have made for them. As we’ll see when we dive into more “how to” later in the series, one of the most challenging things to do can be to allow ourselves to be silly at one phase while ruthlessly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/10/18/_kill_your_darlings_writing_advice_what_writer_really_said_to_murder_your.html&#34;&gt;killing our darlings&lt;/a&gt; later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve stepped through why creativity is about connections, how those connections have to be new, and why they need to be useful to qualify as “creative”. With this definition in mind, our future posts will get to the good stuff: practical advice to get you on the path to more creativity in your life and work.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-08-11-creativity-part-1-defining-creativity/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Gleeful Iconoclasm of Zhuangzi</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-07-27-the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-07-27-the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-07-27-the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Note on Spelling Conventions - Skip if you are not a language nerd:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since westerners started studying Chinese, they have tried to get around the inadequacy of the Latin alphabet to render it. For years the most popular way was the “Wade-Giles System,” which uses various letter combinations as kludges to represent tones. It is a clever way to operate within the constraints of existing letters, but if you don’t know the code, you’re gonna say everything wrong.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;More recently, the People’s Republic of China has introduced the pinyin system. The key feature of which is the use of diacritic marks to indicate tones, which is incredibly useful for ignorant westerners like me. With this, you can be much more straightforward in your use of letters, so even if you get the tones wrong, you’re at least getting the rest right. Because of this, I have decided to ditch the Wade-Giles spellings familiar from my youth and use pinyin without the diacritics (because they are a pain in the ass on an English keyboard).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to take advantage of my vacation in China to read some Chinese philosophy in the land that gave it birth. Looking over my bookshelf, I noticed a book I had purchased for a college class - &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://terebess.hu/english/chuangtzu.html&#34;&gt;Zhuangzi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. In the class we only read a tiny excerpt, and ever since it’s been on my “meaning to read” list. So I ended up pulling it out of my bag and digging in while floating through a landscape that looks exactly like a Chinese landscape painting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, let’s provide a bit of context. “Zhuangzi” can refer to both the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zhuang_Zhou&#34;&gt;philosopher&lt;/a&gt; (“Master Zhuang”) or to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zhuangzi_(book)&#34;&gt;the work ascribed to him&lt;/a&gt; (but probably containing material added later by other people as well). Besides the semi-mythical &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laozi&#34;&gt;Laozi&lt;/a&gt; and his &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tao_Te_Ching&#34;&gt;Daodejing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Zhuangzi&lt;/em&gt; is the next most foundational work in Daoism. The philosopher was a rough contemporary of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confucius&#34;&gt;Confucius’s&lt;/a&gt; in the 4th century BCE. Both of these eminent gentlemen helped to define the explosion of thinking known as “&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hundred_Schools_of_Thought&#34;&gt;The Hundred Schools of Thought&lt;/a&gt;”. In terms of influence on later philosophy, this time period is roughly analogous to the early &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellenistic_philosophy&#34;&gt;Hellenisitic age&lt;/a&gt; in the west  - a flowering of different approaches that are still discussed, debated, and even followed today. This author of &lt;em&gt;Zhuangzi&lt;/em&gt; used this context by telling stories featuring members of other schools of thought - sometimes showing them as fellow seekers of wisdom and other times mercilessly parodying them and their hang ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that struck me in the book was the similarity of the core of the philosophy with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism&#34;&gt;Stoicism&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddhism&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;. Zhuangzi essentially argues that the world is constantly changing and the only way to not be perturbed by this is align yourself with that change, which is an expression of the universal Way (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tao&#34;&gt;Dao&lt;/a&gt;). Despite some important differences, the core idea that we can’t control circumstances, but we can control how we react to them, will sound familiar to students of the two schools I mentioned. I will have to reread the Daodejing, but I don’t remember such a clear parallel there. I suppose I shouldn’t be surprised that such a useful and life-changing mental hack was independently discovered in multiple places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is by no means to say that &lt;em&gt;Zhuangzi&lt;/em&gt; is simply a rehash of things you can find elsewhere. It is widely renowned for its imagery, poetry, and imaginative use of metaphor. Some of these struck me as simply bizarre, but many were rather beautiful. One of these poetic sections has become more famous in the west than the book that spawned it: Zhuangzi is the sage who dreamed he was a butterfly and then wondered if he were not a butterfly dreaming of being a man. Besides the imagery, the other ingredient in Zhuangzi’s secret sauce is humor, and there were several times where I would slowly smile or even chuckle as I realized something that I thought was “serious business” was actually the set up for an elaborate joke. When you put these two stylistic traits together, you get a very interesting effect: since you never know exactly where the author stands moment to moment, or even necessarily what he actually means, you have to think for yourself. You can neither buy everything he says uncritically nor dismiss him as someone you disagree with unconditionally. It’s a remarkably effective way to convey something experientially instead of didactically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate this dynamic produced by humor, metaphor, and active engagement, let me share my favorite example. Zhuangzi frequently praises the “useless” and denigrates the “useful.” One image he uses is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://mjglass.ca/metaphor/uselesstree.htm&#34;&gt;gigantic tree&lt;/a&gt; that has only been allowed to get so big because no part of it has any usefulness to humans - which would have gotten it cut down or plucked or such like. He similarly points out that useful people get put to work and sometimes even get killed doing that work, and so argues it’s good to be crippled and deformed. I was finding it hard to swallow the whole “useless is good, useful is bad” line of reasoning until &lt;a href=&#34;https://terebess.hu/english/chuangtzu3.html#26&#34;&gt;one striking metaphor&lt;/a&gt; got me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A man has to understand the useless before you can talk to him about the useful. The earth is certainly vast and broad, though a man uses no more of it than the area he puts his feet on. If, however, you were to dig away all the earth from around his feet until you reached the Yellow Springs, then would the man still be able to make use of it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a koan-like flash of insight reading this about all of the other images I had been reading. If not for that moment, I might have written the whole work off as anti-rational nonsense. For you, the “click” might come somewhere else because of a different interaction of the imagery, humor, and your own thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I still find the &lt;em&gt;Daodejing&lt;/em&gt; more relevant, Zhuangzi’s skepticism and anti-authoriatarianism was a welcome breath of fresh air in the sometimes puzzling field of Daoism, and gave me a wider understanding of the philosophy than I previously had. It also opened my mind to alternative ways to convey philosophical truths. If you have made previous forays into Chinese philosophy and found them dull or staid, perhaps you should give &lt;em&gt;Zhuangzi&lt;/em&gt; a try.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-07-27-the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>On the Usefulness of Fiction</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-07-21-on-the-usefulness-of-fiction/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-07-21-on-the-usefulness-of-fiction/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-07-21-on-the-usefulness-of-fiction/ -&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve talked before about the non-fiction books that have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;shaped my worldview&lt;/a&gt;, but today I want to talk to you about fiction. A lot of my high performing, hard charging friends find it challenging to “waste” time with fiction, but you’re doing yourself a huge disservice if you agree with them. You need fiction in your life. Since I’m wrapping up a vacation where I’ve been able to read some great books, I want to share a few reasons why I think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, let’s get something out of the way: high school English may have left you with the impression that you don’t like fiction. If so, let me propose an alternate interpretation: you don’t like the kind of fiction high school teachers think you should read. I can barely stand most of the literary fiction &lt;a href=&#34;http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=6085&#34;&gt;considered worthwhile by serious English types&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately, pretty early on, I discovered the kind of fiction that gets my motor going. So if you are a self-identified fiction hater, bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so let’s jump into why fiction is good for you. First and most obvious, you can enjoy fiction, and believe it or not, enjoying yourself is important. I’m not even just talking about abstract fulfillment (though there is that) - you need enjoyment for straight-up productivity and maximum achievement. You have to &lt;a href=&#34;http://theartoflearningproject.org/resources/peak-performance/stress-and-recovery/&#34;&gt;recharge sometimes&lt;/a&gt;. Sure, you can do that in a lot of ways, including binge watching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netflix.com/title/80057281&#34;&gt;something great&lt;/a&gt; on Netflix, but reading a good book presents a different cognitive and emotional experience than watching a movie or TV show. I make a point to read at least a few minutes of fiction every night before bed to “turn off.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, great, enjoyment is all well and good you say, but you need something more practical to win you over. Well, fiction exercises your creative and emotional muscles the same way non-fiction exercises your analytical and memory muscles. You get to practice seeing the world from someone else’s viewpoint or imagining it a different way. The former is especially good for empathy and the latter for creativity. Whether you immerse yourself in the emotional experience of someone utterly unlike you, dig into the details of an imaginary world, or slowly piece together whodunnit, fiction lets you stretch your conceptual space. With this wider field of possible thoughts, you free yourself to have more and better ideas. Fiction is like interval training for creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of interesting new thoughts, if you want to have them, you need a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g2pre2xnA1M&#34;&gt;steady diet&lt;/a&gt; of intellectually and emotionally resonant material. You’ll find the biggest boost to creativity with stuff that is seemingly unrelated to any practical concern of yours, because it will present novel juxtapositions instead of tired and well-established relationships. Fiction gives you a smorgasbord of such material. Not only does fiction provide the raw content of people, places, and things that are unfamiliar, it embeds them in stories. Stories are not only easier to remember than raw facts, they are also more emotionally resonant. Emotional resonance is what allows your subconscious mind to engage with topics in a way unaccessible to rational analysis, which is the stuff eureka moments are made of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite benefit of fiction though, is this: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2013/oct/15/neil-gaiman-future-libraries-reading-daydreaming&#34;&gt;just because something is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2013/oct/15/neil-gaiman-future-libraries-reading-daydreaming&#34;&gt;fiction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2013/oct/15/neil-gaiman-future-libraries-reading-daydreaming&#34;&gt; doesn’t mean it isn’t&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2013/oct/15/neil-gaiman-future-libraries-reading-daydreaming&#34;&gt;true&lt;/a&gt;. That may sound like some woo-woo nonsense, so let me unpack it a bit. Sometimes concepts, whether emotional, political, scientific or otherwise, can better find their way into your brain and stick there when they come wrapped up in engaging stories. If you read a book where vastly different alien species &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Ringworld-Larry-Niven-ebook/dp/B01513ZIL6/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644554&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=ringworld&#34;&gt;live and work together with respect&lt;/a&gt; and it makes you realize that the same thing should be much easier when we’re all the same species, you’ve learned something true and good. If &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Silmarillion-J-R-R-Tolkien-ebook/dp/B007978PGI/ref=sr_1_1_ha?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644599&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=silmarillion&#34;&gt;a world of elves and dwarves&lt;/a&gt; ignites a passion for language, culture, and mythology, you will be better equipped to travel the world. If you empathize with &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Citizen-Galaxy-Heinleins-Juveniles-Book-ebook/dp/B005OLRPI0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644719&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=citizen+of+the+galaxy&#34;&gt;the plight of a slave&lt;/a&gt; in a fictional world, you are a better person in the real one. This is the real power and beauty of fiction: it can sneak in under the guise of pure entertainment and plant important truths deep within our psyche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s assume I’ve convinced you that you need more fiction in your life: where should you start? I’ll recommend a few of my favorites, but I’ll warn you, my tastes run pretty nerdy. If you suspect that yours don’t, you may want to look for recommendations elsewhere - maybe ask a friend whose tastes you trust, poke around &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/&#34;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, or if all else finds, pick a movie you like based on a book and go for the original. At any rate, if you’re ready for serious nerdery, here’s some of my favorites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Anathem-Neal-Stephenson-ebook/dp/B0015DPXKI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644816&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=anathem&#34;&gt;Anathem&lt;/a&gt; by Neal Stephenson - If you are at all worried about your attention span, don’t start here, because this book is big. I debated including it in a piece aimed at those new to fiction, but it is one of my very favorite books of all time, and y’all are smart people, so I kept it in. It has deeply influenced how I think about science and physics and pushed me to learn more in those topics than I ever would have otherwise. It’s an adventure story set on a world much like our own that starts out in a monastic retreat dedicated to learning and then sprawls out into the world, exploring philosophy, math, and quantum physics along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/dp/0312863551/ref=sxts_sxwds-tsp_1?pf_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;amp;pf_rd_p=3007296062&amp;amp;pd_rd_wg=XLXu2&amp;amp;pf_rd_r=5DAQMY1BWTD1NCNRS3B1&amp;amp;pf_rd_s=desktop-sx-top-slot&amp;amp;pf_rd_t=301&amp;amp;pd_rd_i=0312863551&amp;amp;pd_rd_w=pnbzu&amp;amp;pf_rd_i=the+moon+is+a+harsh+mistress&amp;amp;pd_rd_r=54DTRV1QBE1YYTRZMYS1&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644861&amp;amp;sr=1&#34;&gt;The Moon is a Harsh Mistress&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Heinlein - The godfather of science fiction, Heinlein wrote several enormously influential books, but this one is my favorite. By telling the story of a prison colony revolution on the moon, it helped to invent Libertarianism here in the real world. Lots of deep political philosophy, but it never gets in the way of an engaging story with men of action, sexy ladies, and a friendly computer named Mike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Good-Omens-Accurate-Prophecies-Nutter-ebook/dp/B0054LJGWS/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644894&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=good+omens&#34;&gt;Good Omens&lt;/a&gt; by Neil Gaiman and Terry Pratchett - My first exposure to either of these authors, I have since gone on to enjoy both quite a bit. The comedic tale of an angel and a demon who team up to make sure the antichrist turns out as average as possible because, well, they both rather like earth and aren’t too keen on the war between heaven and hell actually getting resolved. If you read it and enjoy the humor most, check out more Terry Pratchett, but if you like it more for the otherworldly weirdness, check out more Gaiman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Makers-Cory-Doctorow-ebook/dp/B003VTZU1Q/ref=sr_1_6?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644916&amp;amp;sr=1-6&amp;amp;keywords=makers&#34;&gt;Makers&lt;/a&gt; by Cory Doctorow - Set in the next few years, this book explores many of the exciting possibilities inherent in the burgeoning “maker” culture once high quality 3D printing becomes ubiquitous. It will make you want to head out to your garage to start tinkering as soon as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Coming-Conan-Cimmerian-Barbarian-Book-ebook/dp/B000FBJE24/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500644958&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+coming+of+conan+the+cimmerian&#34;&gt;The Coming of Conan the Cimmerian&lt;/a&gt; by Robert E. Howard - You’ve probably seen the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OBGOQ7SsJrw&#34;&gt;Ahnahld movie&lt;/a&gt;, but did you know Conan started life in the pulp magazines of the 30’s and was created by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_E._Howard&#34;&gt;a brilliant but melancholy Texan&lt;/a&gt;? Howard wrote phenomenal action scenes, and he used the Conan stories as an excuse to write about all the coolest parts of real-world ancient cultures mashed together into one super sweet fictional world. Lots of dark magic, monster fighting, and getting the girl, but with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Styles_and_themes_of_Robert_E._Howard&#34;&gt;surprising depth and quality&lt;/a&gt;. Added bonus: it’s got some rockin’ sweet illustrations by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=mark+schultz+illustrator&amp;amp;safe=off&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjn6fmowprVAhUKySYKHTqFAhsQ_AUICigB&amp;amp;biw=1451&amp;amp;bih=807&#34;&gt;Mark Schultz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Lord-Rings-One-J-R-R-Tolkien-ebook/dp/B007978OY6/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500645294&amp;amp;sr=1-3&amp;amp;keywords=lord+of+the+rings&#34;&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/a&gt; by J.R.R. Tolkien - Okay, since you are reading this in English, I know you&amp;rsquo;ve at least heard about the movies. Many people find the books slow to get going, but I have found them enchanting since I was in junior high, and I re-read the whole trilogy every few years. I may not be able to go toe to toe with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iNScstl1RMw&#34;&gt;Stephen Colbert or James Franco&lt;/a&gt; in a trivia-off these days, but I have maintained my life-long interest in language, linguistics, and mythology that this book implanted in me. For a shorter, faster paced taste, give &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Colour-Illustrated-Hobbit-J-Tolkien-ebook/dp/B00BVT56GC/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500645376&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34;&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/a&gt; a try.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly I’m not saying you should toss out the business or self improvement books, but if you find a way to build regular fiction reading into your life, you will not regret it. If you’re already a fiction reader, I hope you found some new insights here. In any case, let me know what your favorites are!&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-07-21-on-the-usefulness-of-fiction/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>My Operating Manuals for Life</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-07-14-my-operating-manuals-for-life/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-07-14-my-operating-manuals-for-life/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-07-14-my-operating-manuals-for-life/ -&lt;p&gt;If you accept that you have your own &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/7/a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface&#34;&gt;User Interface&lt;/a&gt;, you’re going to need some instructions on how to set it up and maintain it. As you know, my go to source for just about everything is books, and I have found those on the list below especially useful for hacking together my own mental operating system. They currently sit right on my desk where I can see them every day and think about what they mean to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tools-of-titanshttpssmileamazoncomtools-titans-billionaires-world-class-performers-ebookdpb01hsmrwnurefsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498952926sr8-1keywordstoolsoftitans&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Tools-Titans-Billionaires-World-Class-Performers-ebook/dp/B01HSMRWNU/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498952926&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=tools+of+titans&#34;&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most practical book on this list, and I’m most confident it will be immediately useful to you.  I consider it the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;80/20 solution&lt;/a&gt; of self-help books, the one to read if you can only read one.  Chock full of amazing tips, tricks, and strategies for improving your life in every dimension, I have adopted more ideas from here than I can keep track of. While &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Timothy-Ferriss/e/B001ILKBW2/ref=dp_byline_cont_ebooks_1&#34;&gt;all three of Tim Ferriss’s previous books&lt;/a&gt; have had a tremendous positive impact on my life, this is the capstone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;awaken-the-giant-withinhttpssmileamazoncomawaken-giant-within-immediate-emotional-ebookdpb001em101qrefsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498952953sr8-1keywordsawakenthegiantwithin&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Awaken-Giant-Within-Immediate-Emotional-ebook/dp/B001EM101Q/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498952953&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=awaken+the+giant+within&#34;&gt;Awaken the Giant Within&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tonyrobbins.com/&#34;&gt;Tony Robbins’s&lt;/a&gt; main work on personal transformation and behavior change. I have used this book not only to shape my approach to coaching but also to upgrade my own mental Operating System across the board. I have used it to ditch bad habits, take positive action in my life, and otherwise convince myself that my life is what I make of it. If you aren’t sure what you think of Tony Robbins, check out the Netflix documentary &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netflix.com/title/80102204&#34;&gt;I Am Not Your Guru&lt;/a&gt; to get a good taste of what he’s about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-choose-yourself-guide-to-wealthhttpssmileamazoncomchoose-yourself-guide-wealth-ebookdpb00u7is4s0refsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498952987sr8-1keywordschooseyourselfguidetowealth&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Choose-Yourself-Guide-Wealth-ebook/dp/B00U7IS4S0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498952987&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=choose+yourself+guide+to+wealth&#34;&gt;The Choose Yourself Guide to Wealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most recent edition to my collection, a month or two back my friend was like “you need to read this right now,” and he was right. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesaltucher.com/&#34;&gt;James Altucher&lt;/a&gt; argues three main points in the book: secure corporate employment for your entire life is dead and gone, it’s up to you to bring value to the world, and the best way to do that is to follow a daily practice that nourishes and improves yourself mentally, emotionally, spiritually, and physically. He supplements all of this with a number of specific techniques on freelancing, selling, networking, and so forth. Some of the books on this list had already laid the groundwork for believing that financial success comes from no other source than me, but this book gave me the tactical kick in the butt I needed to start acting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;deep-workhttpssmileamazoncomdeep-work-focused-success-distracted-ebookdpb00x47zvxmrefsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498953010sr8-1keywordsdeepwork&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Deep-Work-Focused-Success-Distracted-ebook/dp/B00X47ZVXM/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953010&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=deep+work&#34;&gt;Deep Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equal parts manifesto and field guide, Cal Newport argues that focusing on one thing at a time and choosing important, hard work is a super power in a world of constant distraction. My own experience bears this out - when I most seriously follow the approach explained in this book, not only do I get more work done, I feel more fulfilled and happier about it to boot. This book is essential reading if you want to achieve mastery in anything or even just stand out from your peers at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-art-of-learninghttpssmileamazoncomart-learning-journey-pursuit-excellence-ebookdpb000qcq970refsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498953031sr8-1keywordsartoflearning&#34;&gt;**&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Art-Learning-Journey-Pursuit-Excellence-ebook/dp/B000QCQ970/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953031&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=art+of+learning&#34;&gt;The Art of Learning&lt;/a&gt; **&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more challenging books on this list. I have revisited it multiple times, and every time I find a new insight I didn’t pick up before. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joshwaitzkin.com/&#34;&gt;Waitzkin&lt;/a&gt; has thought deeply and internalized several principles on learning and performance at the highest levels through his experience as a child chess master, world champion Tai Chi Push Hands competitor, top tier Brazilian Jiu Jitsu trainer, and a coach for the most successful hedge fund managers in the world. At times bordering on the mystical and opaque, you have to do your own share of the work with this book. Rather than concrete, actionable strategies, this book deals in fundamental principles that are relevant no matter the strategy you choose: which can be frustrating at times, but is more rewarding and useful in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;antifragilehttpssmileamazoncomantifragile-things-that-disorder-incerto-ebookdpb0083djwgorefsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498953052sr8-1keywordsantifragile&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Antifragile-Things-That-Disorder-Incerto-ebook/dp/B0083DJWGO/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953052&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=antifragile&#34;&gt;Antifragile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another book that doesn’t present easy, pre-digested material. We’ve talked about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/6/9/rethinking-risk-with-antifragile&#34;&gt;somewhat&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/6/16/fragility-robustness-and-antifragility&#34;&gt;extensively&lt;/a&gt; before. While there are a few specific how to’s scattered throughout, such as approaches to diet and exercise, it is far more useful as a foundational text on how to think about uncertainty. It’s another book where I find something new and get smarter every time I revisit it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;zen-and-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenancehttpssmileamazoncomzen-art-motorcycle-maintenance-inquiry-ebookdpb0026772n8refsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498953071sr8-1keywordszenandtheartofmotorcyclemaintenance&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Zen-Art-Motorcycle-Maintenance-Inquiry-ebook/dp/B0026772N8/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953071&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=zen+and+the+art+of+motorcycle+maintenance&#34;&gt;Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only novel on this list, but don’t let that fool you - it’s still loaded to the gills with insight and useful introspective tools. This book was one of the first to seriously shake my arrogant belief that I understood myself deeply or even what “self” means. I agree with more of it every time I come back to it, and it has also been my personal bridge between stoicism and eastern philosophy - a more compatible pairing than you might think. If you’ve always thought Buddhism sounded like crazy woo-woo bullshit, start here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-war-of-arthttpssmileamazoncomwar-art-steven-pressfield-ebookdpb007a4sdcgrefsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498953092sr8-1keywordsthewarofart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/War-Art-Steven-Pressfield-ebook/dp/B007A4SDCG/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953092&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+war+of+art&#34;&gt;The War of Art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shortest book here, it punches way over its weight. I first read it cover to cover on an hour long flight and it lit my mind on fire. If you have anything remotely creative inside you trying to get out, you owe it to yourself to read this book. It is uncomfortable and galvanizing at the same time - like a cold shower, you will flinch from it at first, but emerge ready to take on the world. It is medicine I take whenever I find myself getting lazy and complacent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;letters-from-a-stoichttpssmileamazoncomletters-stoic-epistulae-morales-lucilium-ebookdpb005nc0mgwrefsr_1_1ieutf8qid1498953114sr8-1keywordslettersfromastoic&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Letters-Stoic-Epistulae-Morales-Lucilium-ebook/dp/B005NC0MGW/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953114&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=letters+from+a+stoic&#34;&gt;Letters from a Stoic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick note on translations: these last two books were obviously not written in English, and the translation you select will have a big impact on what you think of it - generally stay away from the free Kindle editions, as these tend to be old, public domain translations of mediocre quality. If you want to get into the nitty gritty of why I chose these translations, shoot me an email and we can geek out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal favorite work of stoic philosophy, it barely edged out &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Meditations-New-Translation-Modern-Library-ebook/dp/B000FC1JAI/ref=sr_1_12?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498954701&amp;amp;sr=8-12&amp;amp;keywords=meditations+marcus+aurelius&#34;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt; for my token Stoic book. Stoicism is such a central part of my personal philosophy that I could have easily chosen nothing but stoic books. Here’s a good &lt;a href=&#34;http://tim.blog/2009/04/13/stoicism-101-a-practical-guide-for-entrepreneurs/&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/a&gt; of stoicism generally, but at the core of it are three men, each impressive in his own way: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus_Aurelius&#34;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epictetus&#34;&gt;Epictetus&lt;/a&gt;.  While I appreciate all of them, turns out I’m a Seneca guy. It is shocking how modern and relevant his 2,000 year old letters feel. Writing to a young friend and protege, Seneca’s advice has the wisdom and clarity of an older mentor who has been there, wishes he had done better, and now advises his young friend to learn from his experience. Friendly, worldly, but with an unceasing dedication to living a good life, these letters are good for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-poetic-eddahttpssmileamazoncompoetic-edda-lee-m-hollander-ebookdpb00ceigz3mrefsr_1_3ieutf8qid1498953134sr8-3keywordspoeticedda&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Poetic-Edda-Lee-M-Hollander-ebook/dp/B00CEIGZ3M/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498953134&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=poetic+edda&#34;&gt;The Poetic Edda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the rest of the list, this may come as something of a surprise entry, but I find the myths in it both beautiful and meaningful. The Germanic myths lack the &lt;a href=&#34;http://classics.oxfordre.com/&#34;&gt;neat and tidy systemization&lt;/a&gt; imposed on Greek myth, leaving them with a raw vitality and tantalizingly missing pieces. With all my focus on rational stoicism and conscious improvement, I find it useful to remember the murkier subconscious parts of my mind that can only be accessed through stories of gods, monsters, and magic. Plus they’re viking myths so they’re super metal. If you’re still not convinced and insist on directly useful, you’ll find fewer collections of wisdom poetry more straightforward than the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/havamal.html&#34;&gt;Havamal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that there’s quite a lot to read here, but these are special and well worth the time. I encourage you to pick just one new book and give it a go today. It just might change your life.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-07-14-my-operating-manuals-for-life/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Using the Dunning-Kruger Effect for Fun and Profit</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/ -&lt;p&gt;We all labor under a whole pile of cognitive biases day to day, but let’s talk about an especially pernicious one: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect&#34;&gt;the Dunning-Kruger effect&lt;/a&gt;. This extremely subtle bias afflicts us all, affecting our very ability to assess whether we are suffering from a bias or not. So it’s super important to be aware of it and take appropriate counter measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Dunning&#34;&gt;David Dunning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin_Kruger&#34;&gt;Justin Kruger&lt;/a&gt; have experimentally documented the long recognized tendency of people to suffer from “&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illusory_superiority&#34;&gt;illusory superiority&lt;/a&gt;,” and so have had the effect named after them. Basically, if you want to assess how good you are at a task, you have to understand that task well enough to be good at it. Which means that if you don’t understand it that well, you will overestimate your competence. While everyone can suffer from this bias in domain-specific areas, it especially afflicts people with lower general intelligence, who lack the metacognitive ability to recognize that their fundamental reasoning is flawed - such as the bank robber McArthur Wheeler, who &lt;a href=&#34;http://awesci.com/the-astonishingly-funny-story-of-mr-mcarthur-wheeler/&#34;&gt;applied lemon juice to his face in the belief that it would make him invisible to security cameras&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bias has an interesting corollary: competent people tend to assume that what is easy for them is easy for everyone else, and so under-estimate their relative competence compared to a group. We’ve all seen our math whiz friend surprised that we count on our fingers, or that one guy at work who can come up with exactly the right phrasing for a concept that we’ve been struggling to express for hours. If you’re actively seeking ways to better yourself, chances are there are certain fields where you have a high degree of competence. You can use this corollary to motivate yourself to action. Say you want to start a business, but you’re crippled by doubt that you know enough to charge anything - well, seek some external validation from sources you trust, and with their go ahead, move forward knowing that things that seem easy to you are hugely valuable to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use the Dunning-Kruger effect in an even more interesting and useful way, though: actively cultivate the belief that I am dumber than I think. I got this idea from &lt;a href=&#34;https://sivers.org/2015-12-ferriss2&#34;&gt;Derek Sivers&lt;/a&gt; and have found it tremendously useful. Since I recognize that I am predisposed to think I’m above average, I systematically tell myself that I below average. Not in a way that is abusive or self-flagellating, just outcomes based. Now, perhaps I end up with an overall inaccurate view of my competence (maybe I really am a special snowflake), but odds are I was going to get it wrong no matter what, and getting it wrong this way is more productive and useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it useful to cultivate a disregard for your own intelligence? Lots of reasons. First off, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Epictetus&#34;&gt;it is impossible for anyone to begin to learn that which he thinks he already knows&lt;/a&gt;. Zen practitioners cultivate &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin&#34;&gt;beginners mind,&lt;/a&gt;” where you actively open yourself to possibilities and new connections. The certainty that you already understand everything you need to about a situation is poisonous to this mindset. The preconceived approaches of a self-identified expert to a problem are more likely to be conventional and generic rather than tailored to the situation at hand. Most importantly, a belief in your own competence is exactly the kind of food your Ego craves, and starving it will make you more pleasant to be around, less susceptible to making massive mistakes, and otherwise less likely to &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Ego-Enemy-Ryan-Holiday-ebook/dp/B015NTIXWE/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498764085&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=ego+is+the+enemy&#34;&gt;crash the burning wreckage of your life straight into the ground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t make a regular practice to actively cultivate your self-perception of your competence, familiarity with this bias will serve you well. Any time you want to jump into an argument and give some advice - pause and ask yourself how much you really know about the topic. When you get frustrated with someone for screwing up something easy, ask yourself how much work you had to put into making it easy. Most importantly, I hope that knowledge of this bias will convince you to never ever stop learning.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Analysis is Only the Beginning - An Introduction to Systems Thinking</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/ -&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about systems. We’ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/4/10/designing-your-own-productivity-framework&#34;&gt;touched&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/5/11/super-combinations-from-tools-of-titans&#34;&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; them in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/5/11/super-combinations-from-tools-of-titans&#34;&gt;several&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/6/9/rethinking-risk-with-antifragile&#34;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;, and they provide an incredibly valuable tool for understanding a complex world. When we stop thinking about things as independent objects and start thinking about them as elements in a greater whole of interdependent parts, we recognize that they are systems. Today we’re going to talk about a method of inquiry custom designed for such highly complex entities: Systems Thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional analysis is just that - analytical - a word that comes from Greek roots meaning &amp;ldquo;to break apart&amp;rdquo;. We &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oOS00ttAblQ&#34;&gt;break down big problems&lt;/a&gt; into smaller components to better understand them. You and I have both used this technique to solve hundreds, if not thousands, of problems in our lives, which pales in comparison to what this technique has given the world through the scientific revolution. We use analysis to figure out what matters and focus on it. Analysis allows us to deeply understand things by reducing cutting out the unnecessary and leaving only the essential. Analysis is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble with the analytical approach is that almost everything that matters happens within an interdependent context. We pretend a piece of a problem is isolated from its surroundings. This &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heuristic&#34;&gt;useful fiction&lt;/a&gt; becomes less so as the complexity and importance of the interactions we’re ignoring increases. While there have always been complex systems that are better understood holistically than broken apart, in today’s connected world, there are more and more. Almost every challenge that matters today arises in a world of dependence, interdependence, and emergence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a supplementary method of problem solving developed especially for our complex world called &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systems_thinking&#34;&gt;Systems Thinking&lt;/a&gt;. Like many concepts we talk about here, it’s easy to explain but difficult to apply. Systems thinking supplements traditional analysis with synthesis and inquiry. Synthesis is the opposite of analysis: once you better understand the parts, you put them back together and see how your knowledge of the parts has informed your understanding of the whole. Inquiry is the commitment to investigate systems as integrated wholes and to repeat the analysis and synthesis steps as needed to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more you can train yourself to think this way, the better you will be able to navigate complex, ambiguous, and chaotic situations. As you can see from the Wikipedia link, “system” is such a generic and useful word that it is difficult to define the approach simply and cleanly. &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Learning-Organization-ebook/dp/B000SEIFKK/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1498177025&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+fifth+discipline&#34;&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Senge introduced much of the business world to systems thinking. In this work, Senge pioneered the concept of a “learning organization,” which will revisit another time. For now, if you want a quick, free guide to the fundamentals of how to get started, I recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anser.org/docs/systems_thinking_applied.pdf&#34;&gt;Systems Thinking Applied: a Primer.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems thinking can be applied to complex systems of any kind.. Some people split up “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perflensburg.se/Privatsida/cp-web/capchsyt.htm&#34;&gt;hard&lt;/a&gt;” systems thinking (like computer networks) and “&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soft_systems_methodology&#34;&gt;soft&lt;/a&gt;” systems thinking (like organizations or ecological regions). Dedicated professionals use these distinctions to formulate practical tools to understand and fix complex systems in their fields. For most of us, though, the commonalities are more useful: understanding that the behavior of every constituent element affects the whole, that those elements are interdependent, and that you cannot meaningful subdivide them into subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we’ve taken a very brief look at one of the most important mental models you can put into your toolbox. Systems thinking is a flexible tool that is used in many fields, so if you have an interest in a particular field, you can almost certainly find a dedicated resource for applying Systems Thinking within it. For now, just pause for a moment whenever you notice that something in your life is interdependent on other elements and think about the system that it - and you - are a part of.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 