<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Colonies on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/colonies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Colonies on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 10:57:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/colonies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joint Stock Corporation</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-30-the-joint-stock-corporation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 10:57:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-30-the-joint-stock-corporation/</guid>
      <description>http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gNw4kY9sMeU/U7GjyFcF5hI/AAAAAAAAAzI/Sju6JkOUh-M/s1600/20130420_FNP001_0.jpg
Once again this text is rules. This text is commentary for the blog. ** ** To avoid confusion with the companies sent out from colonies on expeditions, the organization which owns the colony and employs all of its inhabitants is referred to as a corporation. The default assumption is that it literally is a joint stock corporation formed by wealthy investors who elect a board of directors who hire officers to make them profits, but the rules will work just as well for representing a department of government, a thieves guild, or any other sort of organization that might dispatch adventurers to far off places in search of wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Company Voyages</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-26-adventuring-company-voyages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 09:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-26-adventuring-company-voyages/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Companies: Colonies</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-25-adventuring-companies-colonies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 11:07:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-25-adventuring-companies-colonies/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-d5m35f9TnuM/U6sMmvc7JJI/AAAAAAAAAx4/BzNZqlkwGLc/s1600/presidio1351833927828.png
Colonies (All money is in LotFP’s “Silver Standard”) Current version of rules text looks like this. Commentary for this blog entry looks like this. ** ** Resources General Description Food (~5sp) - one unit feeds one person for one week Building Materials (~5sp) - Wood, stone, et cetera used to construct buildings Treasure (~40sp) - Gold, loot, art, spices, furs, other trade goods - sent home as profit ** ** The way I’ve worked out the resource values is a crazy scaffolding of assumptions and handwaving.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>