<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adventure Companies on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/adventure-companies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Adventure Companies on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 22:20:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/adventure-companies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Companies Expeditions and Sites of Interest</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-08-17-adventuring-companies-expeditions-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 22:20:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-08-17-adventuring-companies-expeditions-and/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-abIA7iiktSA/U_GGLQOqi6I/AAAAAAAAA-I/_lQwcr-Xfsg/s1600/Mayan-Ruins-by-DoktorRengen-on-deviantART-Google-Chrome_2012-12-12_13-06-03.png
So, I know I&amp;rsquo;ve been slow the last couple of months, and I apologize. Currently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been extremely lucky to be working on a layout project that should turn out to be something pretty cool, but I don&amp;rsquo;t want to advertise it loudly until it&amp;rsquo;s closer to completion. The downside to this very exciting news is that my own personal hobby projects, like the Adventure Companies one, is going on the back-burner (still thinking about it and working on it, but I can&amp;rsquo;t make it a priority of my gaming hobby time).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Purchases and Acquisitions</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-07-01-purchases-and-acquisitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 13:16:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-07-01-purchases-and-acquisitions/</guid>
      <description>http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-FGyLQSyOen0/U7MVTFmk70I/AAAAAAAAAzY/gRe9CioqSv4/s1600/city-scape.jpg
These are rules. These are commentary for the blog. ** ** So, a few responses to previous posts have made me realize that not everyone finding these posts realizes they are part of a series. That link will take you to all the posts in this project so far, and will continue to take you to any more that come up. By way of a general introduction, I should point out that the structure of these rules owe a lot to Fantasy Flight’s Rogue Trader game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joint Stock Corporation</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-30-the-joint-stock-corporation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 10:57:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-30-the-joint-stock-corporation/</guid>
      <description>http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gNw4kY9sMeU/U7GjyFcF5hI/AAAAAAAAAzI/Sju6JkOUh-M/s1600/20130420_FNP001_0.jpg
Once again this text is rules. This text is commentary for the blog. ** ** To avoid confusion with the companies sent out from colonies on expeditions, the organization which owns the colony and employs all of its inhabitants is referred to as a corporation. The default assumption is that it literally is a joint stock corporation formed by wealthy investors who elect a board of directors who hire officers to make them profits, but the rules will work just as well for representing a department of government, a thieves guild, or any other sort of organization that might dispatch adventurers to far off places in search of wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Company Voyages</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-26-adventuring-company-voyages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 09:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-26-adventuring-company-voyages/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Companies: Colonies</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-25-adventuring-companies-colonies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 11:07:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-06-25-adventuring-companies-colonies/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-d5m35f9TnuM/U6sMmvc7JJI/AAAAAAAAAx4/BzNZqlkwGLc/s1600/presidio1351833927828.png
Colonies (All money is in LotFP’s “Silver Standard”) Current version of rules text looks like this. Commentary for this blog entry looks like this. ** ** Resources General Description Food (~5sp) - one unit feeds one person for one week Building Materials (~5sp) - Wood, stone, et cetera used to construct buildings Treasure (~40sp) - Gold, loot, art, spices, furs, other trade goods - sent home as profit ** ** The way I’ve worked out the resource values is a crazy scaffolding of assumptions and handwaving.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Companies Characteristics</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-05-27-adventuring-companies-characteristics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 18:36:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-05-27-adventuring-companies-characteristics/</guid>
      <description>http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-KV-M1U_Ulo8/U4U9ia-03aI/AAAAAAAAAu8/OauBtCT2uZ8/s1600/the-explorer-tom-wooldridge.jpg
So, I know I&amp;rsquo;ve been pretty quiet on this project, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been continuing to noodle with it in the background. After I posted that table of contents last time, I did an analysis of what sections depended on other sections and realized that the main core that would affect how just about everything else played out was statting up the &amp;ldquo;adventure company&amp;rdquo; itself. I think that this, plus the colony rules, will be the main contributions of this project (assuming I do a half decent job, anyway).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Companies Working Table of Contents</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-05-05-adventuring-companies-working-table-of/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 16:28:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-05-05-adventuring-companies-working-table-of/</guid>
      <description>http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ltuY-yMnYgA/U2gebTzQl3I/AAAAAAAAAug/Tod9G7vpKT0/s1600/conquistadors_ii_by_shutupandwhisper-d6ro3z5.jpg
Following up my general thrust post on the adventuring company setting/game thing I’m working on, here’s the working table of contents for what I’m planning to write, with some initial indication of organization. I have a few questions about this that would be helpful to get answers for: ** ** 1. Does this look like something cool? Would anyone besides me get any use out of this? 2. Has too much of this already been done too well to be worth repeating?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventuring Company Expeditions and Modularity</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-05-04-adventuring-company-expeditions-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 14:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-05-04-adventuring-company-expeditions-and/</guid>
      <description>http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Uc7mqZHjc5k/U2a4PfqtB2I/AAAAAAAAAuQ/H_v9uMz0Kbw/s1600/hudson-east-india-company-granger.jpg
So, now that I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten Middenheim out the door and received a gratifyingly positive reaction, I&amp;rsquo;ve started thinking about another project idea I had a while back. It was spurred by a blog post I read somewhere (maybe Monsters &amp;amp; Manuals or Hack &amp;amp; Slash?) that talked about the lack of quality OSR innovation in the Campaign Setting arena. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if that&amp;rsquo;s still the case, but that thought mixed with some other ideas resulted in the outlines of a thing I want to make.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>