<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Communication on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/communication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Communication on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Culture is a Story that Isn&#39;t Over Yet</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/</guid>
      <description>Stories are essential for building and maintaining strong cultures. They help everyone learn the group&amp;rsquo;s way of doing things, create belonging, and make meaning out of what they do every day. In fact, you can define culture as an ongoing story that a group tells together.
Cultures share a way of thinking about things. All of us shape our thinking with mental models, which help us to see blind spots, work better, and understand what we learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Connections with Oral Storytelling</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>Humans have been telling stories face to face since forever, and doing it well gives you a leg up personally and professionally. Compelling business presentations are critical for success, and natural storytelling techniques can take them to the next level. Even outside of business, stories help you build relationships and entertain your friends. You can improve your oral storytelling today by paying attention to structure, shortening your stories, using your voice well, and supporting what you say with your face and hands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 4 - Delivery</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/</guid>
      <description>Now that your story has a great structure and you know what good practice looks like, let’s focus on what you’re actually trying to improve with your practice: the delivery of your story. I’ve gotta tell you, this was the hardest post for me to write in this series because delivery is so dependent on your medium - public speakers care very much about maintaining their posture and projecting their voice, comic book artists not so much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 3 - Practice, Practice, Practice</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/</guid>
      <description>However you choose to share your stories with the world, you’ll have to practice to make them look effortless and beautiful. You’ll need to tell more stories and tell each of your stories more times to improve your craft and your tales. To make those repetitions useful, you’ll need feedback as fast as possible, and the best feedback comes from a caring but objective partner. After I dig into each of these topics, I’ll give you a specific playbook for preparing for a speech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 1 - Introduction</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Anyone who wants to communicate with other humans needs storytelling, but most folks have no idea what it really is, much less how to improve it. Some people even have the misguided notion that storytelling is worthless fluff. With this series, we’ll clear up that misconception and then cover the best techniques for improving your storytelling.
As we did with creativity, let’s begin by defining “storytelling”. You’ve probably heard it used in a number of contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 2 - Structure</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-11-3-storytelling-part-2-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-11-3-storytelling-part-2-structure/</guid>
      <description>Every good story has a structure, and if you make it explicit ahead of time, you can spot gaps and make improvements. Below we’ll go through a simple tool to make your structure clear, how to use it, the elements of the classic story, some variant story structure options depending on intent, and finally some alternatives to consider.
You can craft stories with a lot of different structures, but for all of them, you need a tool to make the structure explicit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>