<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fellhold on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/fellhold/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fellhold on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/fellhold/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Sages Say&#34; Monster Generator</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</guid>
      <description>I made a thing that makes monsters. I&amp;rsquo;m terribly pleased with it right now, but let me know what you think. If the embed below is giving you weird formatting (on a phone or tablet, say), or if you just want to mess with it, check out the sheet here.
I used Brendan&amp;rsquo;s excellent methodology to build it in Google Sheets. Every time you refresh this page, you should get a new result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OSR Classes: The Mastermind and the Rook</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 08:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</guid>
      <description>After my last post on Flexible Reaction Rolls, I found myself thinking about how to build Character Classes that fit with the schemey, urban style of play I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for with Fellhold. The trouble for me until now was that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t think of ways to get that stuff without impinging on the Old School playstyle I enjoy. What cracked it for me was turning the Reaction Roll into a mechanic with more knobs to play with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Reaction Rolls</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 11:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</guid>
      <description>Reaction rolls are one of my very favorite set of rules. They&amp;rsquo;re quick, easy, and help me to come up with more interesting stuff than I might on my own. I use them as a general purpose social sub-system, though not nearly to the same extent as Courtney Campbell in his excellent On the Non-Player Character. Instead, I use them more as an oracle when I&amp;rsquo;m unsure of how the NPCs would react.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Money &amp; Equipment in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 12:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but I find coming up with equipment lists a huge pain in the ass. Coming up with starting equipment packages? Even harder. So why don&amp;rsquo;t I just use one of the perfectly serviceable equipment lists already out there? Because I definitely buy into the thought that equipment lists are a great way to convey implicit setting and approaches to the game. So I bit the bullet and cranked the below out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Soul Economy in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:07:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>So, back when I first started rebooting my home campaign setting from a Tentpole Megadungeon generic D&amp;amp;D world that owed a lot to Dwimmermount and into something a little funkier, one of the ideas I hit upon was that the economy would be based on souls. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really know what that meant, but it seemed cool, so I ran with it. Well, after lots of reading and thinking and coming up with other parts of the world, it finally clicked together into something that makes some (warped, D&amp;amp;D, in-game) sense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>By Our Powers Combined: Fellhold has an Artist!</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-09-19-by-our-powers-combined-fellhold-has/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-09-19-by-our-powers-combined-fellhold-has/</guid>
      <description>I am very excited to announce that the Fellhold project now has an official artist! The talented and gracious Eric Koch has signed on as the better half of this DIY monstrosity. You can check out his stuff here at his tumblr. So far he has been a joy to work with, and while I plan on greedily hogging all of his RPG-related art time for the next year or so, if after that you&amp;rsquo;re in need of pictures, I highly recommend him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Fellhold Artist to Conquer the DIY D&amp;D World</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-08-11-call-for-fellhold-artist-to-conquer-diy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 06:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-08-11-call-for-fellhold-artist-to-conquer-diy/</guid>
      <description>https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/564x/00/b6/f9/00b6f94294560fd38fefa36b3d6de0fe.jpg
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restaurant and Coffee House Generators</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-26-restaurant-and-coffee-house-generators/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 08:55:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-26-restaurant-and-coffee-house-generators/</guid>
      <description>https://cdn1.artstation.com/p/assets/images/images/002/316/001/large/tim-lochner-rpg-grp.jpg?1460166029
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fine Dining Carousing Table</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-11-fine-dining-carousing-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-11-fine-dining-carousing-table/</guid>
      <description>http://i2.cdn.turner.com/cnnnext/dam/assets/151104103018-asia-instagram-chefs-lennardy3-super-169.jpeg
One of the things I enjoy the most about living in a big city, and look forward to the most when visiting another city, is the food. Honestly, I&amp;rsquo;d say most of my enjoyment of a vacation comes down to how good the food I get to eat on it is. What&amp;rsquo;s the point of going somewhere beautiful or culturally important if you&amp;rsquo;re eating bland crap while you&amp;rsquo;re there?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conspiracy Generator for Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-08-conspiracy-generator-for-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 09:36:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-08-conspiracy-generator-for-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2782/5805833979_8c7b781b53_o.jpg
I was pretty skeptical of myself when I set out to write this section. Initially, I just planned on including some guidance that basically said &amp;ldquo;go read the section of Night&amp;rsquo;s Black Agents about conspiracies and make something up for your city. But with all of the other generators I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing, it just seemed to go against the ethos I&amp;rsquo;ve been following of &amp;ldquo;make tools that people can use or ignore as they like&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vendors and Merchants of Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-05-vendors-and-merchants-of-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 13:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-07-05-vendors-and-merchants-of-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>http://img02.deviantart.net/e961/i/2013/326/d/a/the_enchanted_trinkets_shop_by_shutupandwhisper-d6v841n.jpg
Today we have another of the specialist NPC types in Fellhold, like the Sages previously presented. Also like the sages, a big, big inspiration for them was Noism/David McGrogan&amp;rsquo;s treatment of fences here. The goal with merchants is twofold: first off, I want to make the people who sell PCs the stuff they frequently buy potentially interesting, and secondly to be contacts in the world of business, providing their own jobs and intrigue and social connections with a different flavor than sages, patrons, or fences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books and Libraries in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-28-books-and-libraries-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-28-books-and-libraries-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sages and Their Petty Rivalries in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-27-sages-and-their-petty-rivalries-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-27-sages-and-their-petty-rivalries-in/</guid>
      <description>http://www.alchemydiscussion.com/attachment.php?id=334
Noisms/David McGrogan has done some really fantastic stuff with generating player characters&amp;rsquo; social circles in more urban games - most notably in Yoon-Suin, and in development for his new setting/game &amp;ldquo;There is Therefore a Strange Land&amp;rdquo;, as shown in this post. In that post, he provides a table for generating a fence (not a physical barrier around a yard, but a person who buys dubiously acquired merchandise), and I have found it tremendously inspirational for Fellhold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Do you Do in the City? Default Urbancrawl Actions</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-22-what-do-you-do-in-city-default/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 06:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-22-what-do-you-do-in-city-default/</guid>
      <description>http://digitalcollections.lib.washington.edu/utils/ajaxhelper/?CISOROOT=boydBraas&amp;amp;CISOPTR=83&amp;amp;action=2&amp;amp;DMSCALE=90&amp;amp;DMWIDTH=369&amp;amp;DMHEIGHT=460&amp;amp;DMX=0&amp;amp;DMY=0&amp;amp;DMTEXT=&amp;amp;DMROTATE=0
Ever since I decided that the rebooted Fellhold is a massive dungeon-city/city-dungeon, I have been giving a lot of thought to Urbancrawling rules. This series of posts at the Alexandrian covered the topic in a lot of detail, and helped me to organize my thinking, including the core idea of having a &amp;ldquo;default action&amp;rdquo;. And Paolo&amp;rsquo;s discussion of his game Gangs &amp;amp; Bullshit introduced the idea of structuring how you &amp;ldquo;zoom in&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;zoom out&amp;rdquo;, and when I smashed the two ideas together, I felt a tremendous &amp;ldquo;A-ha!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifestyles of the Poor and Adventurous</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-20-lifestyles-of-poor-and-adventurous/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 11:19:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-20-lifestyles-of-poor-and-adventurous/</guid>
      <description>https://ajcarlisle.files.wordpress.com/2014/02/hobbit-chroniclesdosartdesigng4.jpg
One of the major &amp;ldquo;themes&amp;rdquo; of my Fellhold reboot (if that&amp;rsquo;s not too grand a word) is the idea of place being important. Factions have turf, demons have loci they are tied to, and some powers only work in certain places. A frequent hole in the sense of place in D&amp;amp;D games is a place for the characters to live - hence all the murderhoboery. I contend that one contributing reason for this is that most cost of living or lifestyle rules suck and are boring.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Fellhold Random Encounter Tables</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-16-some-fellhold-random-encounter-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 07:28:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-16-some-fellhold-random-encounter-tables/</guid>
      <description>http://uo-planescape.wdfiles.com/local--files/quartiere-gilde/Bazaar_by_Tony_Diterlizzi-02620_(1996)_TSR_AD&amp;amp;D_2ed_Planescape-The_Planewalker&#39;s_Handbook.jpg
Today we continue with some more Fellhold Reboot content - in this case a couple of random encounter tables. There&amp;rsquo;s reference to some district and faction encounters - those are still under developed. The first here is a list of situations you could find your contacts in when you go to find them or bump into them on the street. It&amp;rsquo;s part of a series of rules I&amp;rsquo;m putting together to try to enhance the role contacts play for players in the game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Places of Interest in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-13-places-of-interest-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 07:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-06-13-places-of-interest-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/236x/2c/ab/5b/2cab5b15d229d430e5a56741489829d0.jpg
As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in a few previous posts, I am in the process of pretty extensively overhauling my homebrew setting Fellhold. As a part of that, I&amp;rsquo;ve been drafting some tables to help with stocking the place, which is an enormous, largely ruined city where the dungeon and the urban run together pretty fluidly. Below are the tables for &amp;ldquo;Places of Interest&amp;rdquo;, which are the handful of places within a district likely worth looking into in more detail, also usable to detail out something that catches the players&amp;rsquo; attention in play.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make Anything Gameable: Ask What Three Times</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-01-31-how-to-make-anything-gameable-ask-what/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 11:41:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2016-01-31-how-to-make-anything-gameable-ask-what/</guid>
      <description>So, I like to get into procedures, techniques, and tactics in a lot of aspects of my life: the nitty gritty, detailed ways to exactly do a particular thing. For some gaming related examples, check out these previous posts: creating d100 tables from media, and various procedures in the megadungeon. What I want to talk about today is how to get the most out of mining a book, comic, picture, or whatever for gameable stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Reboot in 25 Words</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-11-14-fellhold-reboot-in-25-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 15:35:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-11-14-fellhold-reboot-in-25-words/</guid>
      <description>http://cdn.obsidianportal.com/assets/8680/Seattle_Underground.jpg So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on rebooting my homebrew campaign setting for a while now, just letting thoughts percolate, challenging myself to get creative, and I think something clicked when I went on the Seattle Underground tour.
As a sneak peak, here&amp;rsquo;s the new Fellhold in 25 words or less:
Endless forest, Germanic dwarves, falling lich empire, Pacific Northwest, pioneers, crapsack, city, demons, witches, brick, dynamite, warrior lodges, feuds, ratmen, wendigos, tides, totem poles, gods’ bones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Militant Random Encounter Pop-o-Matic Chart</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-02-03-militant-random-encounter-pop-o-matic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 22:23:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-02-03-militant-random-encounter-pop-o-matic/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-hAS9364Y86o/UvCHcALbpgI/AAAAAAAAAqI/iWvi1gmHzA8/s1600/2-10.jpg
So, as inspired by some of the random encounters over at Playing D&amp;amp;D with Pornstars, here is a random encounter generator for patrols from the more militant sort of opponents. Specifically, in Fellhold, I&amp;rsquo;m using this for random encounters with hobgoblin and human gang member patrols. My party still tore through one of these with a well-timed sleep spell and judicious application of axes. Now they&amp;rsquo;re trying to decide whether to charm or murder the sleeping hobgoblins and where to go from there, so I&amp;rsquo;d say mission = success.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dwarves as Germanic Sumerians</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-29-dwarves-as-germanic-sumerians/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2014 22:05:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-29-dwarves-as-germanic-sumerians/</guid>
      <description>http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-AjvpI67tAjs/Uunrn4yN3KI/AAAAAAAAAns/Kx0PfAq_boQ/s1600/012_max.jpg
So, a combination of a Google+ post about Dwarves being like the Sumerians (that unfortunately I cannot find to properly attribute) and Ben L.&amp;lsquo;s post on Textual Corruptions has me thinking about dwarves in Fellhold. Specifically, it has come up a lot that the Dwarf character&amp;rsquo;s loosely defined familiarity with Dwarven culture has given him all sorts of benefits in the part of the dungeon built by the dwarves. Well, I&amp;rsquo;ve thought of a great way to get around that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Pretty Picture Friday</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-24-pretty-pretty-picture-friday_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2014 21:56:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-24-pretty-pretty-picture-friday_24/</guid>
      <description>As has become something of a tradition, I am posting a bunch of pictures on Friday in a mad dash to keep up with my weekdaily posting. The second part of the Vornheiming Middenheim epilogue is under construction, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably get a lot done on that on an airplane ride Sunday evening, so I hope to have it to post on Monday or Tuesday. In the meantime, here are some cool pictures I found for my Fellhold campaign from cghub.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Pretty Picture Friday</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-17-pretty-pretty-picture-friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 22:14:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-17-pretty-pretty-picture-friday/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve found lots of good stuff for slums while looking for stuff relating to my Middenheim posts. So, here&amp;rsquo;s a pretty pictures post for Friday.
http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-NDqY8EaKkgg/UtobACjcBRI/AAAAAAAAAj8/ZnruLWnAoLo/s1600/2iuxmyu.jpg
http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-SqZgUq8beH4/UtobHW6YWvI/AAAAAAAAAkE/VCm8fACQL2g/s1600/19.jpg
http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Mbrnd-9S6-s/UtobNUK8RVI/AAAAAAAAAkM/y12J3GHWX80/s1600/87b9b3496b0b32027bc88cf1eaadcb3b.jpg
http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-jwCfgz16dAU/UtobULC4w3I/AAAAAAAAAkU/vw4X_K6yXug/s1600/1100x793_19201_Town_2d_medieval_architecture_picture_image_digital_art.jpg
http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-LbD--hDKY1I/UtobZeifkAI/AAAAAAAAAkc/NEvTQIOJ40k/s1600/BPnfc-oCIAAnU-e.jpg
http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-lQ3dD4CXOk0/UtobhHz_flI/AAAAAAAAAkk/mVzy_HNUP_I/s1600/medieval_town_by_gaciu000-d5ld4x9.jpg</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping the Habit</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-01-keeping-habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 22:24:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2014-01-01-keeping-habit/</guid>
      <description>I spent most of the day recovering from New Years Eve festivities, and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to get to the Middenheim project before my self-imposed midnight deadline. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m going to post a few pictures and a link to the Pinterest board I&amp;rsquo;ve created for the Fellhold campaign. Most of the board comes from Thomas Fitzgerald&amp;rsquo;s excellent Middenmurk tumblr, but I&amp;rsquo;ve supplemented it with stuff I&amp;rsquo;ve found recently and over the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vornheiming Middenheim Part I</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-19-vornheiming-middenheim-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2013 08:35:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-19-vornheiming-middenheim-part-i/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summoning Up the Courage</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-18-summoning-up-courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 07:24:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-18-summoning-up-courage/</guid>
      <description>So, I really really like LotFP&amp;rsquo;s summon spell (not exactly an original sentiment, there). I like it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;enough rope to hang yourself&amp;rdquo; approach that makes a potentially super powerful spell available at level 1 with the caveat that it&amp;rsquo;s highly random and unstable. And for LotFP&amp;rsquo;s weird fantasy milieu, I even like the bizarre otherworldly results. But for Fellhold, I wanted something a little more thematically coherent, so I reworked it to work for my game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off Screen Factions Part II: Combat</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-17-off-screen-factions-part-ii-combat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 08:33:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-17-off-screen-factions-part-ii-combat/</guid>
      <description>In yesterday&amp;rsquo;s post I gave a brief outline of factional goings on off-screen using Courtney Campbell&amp;rsquo;s rules from &amp;ldquo;On the NPC&amp;rdquo; as a starting point. Today I&amp;rsquo;m going to lay out one way to handle combat between factions, though it&amp;rsquo;s abstract enough that you could use it to handle non-combat rivalry as well. I&amp;rsquo;m also going to touch briefly on an idea about taking and losing territory. Yesterday&amp;rsquo;s post was about getting an idea of what the factions think of each other so that when players run into them, there will be rivalries and alliances to learn and manipulate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Procedure for Off-Screen Faction Interaction</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-16-a-procedure-for-off-screen-faction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 06:58:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-16-a-procedure-for-off-screen-faction/</guid>
      <description>So, I wanted to try a little experiment. I got &amp;ldquo;On the Non-Player Character&amp;rdquo; back when it first came out, skimmed it, read some reviews, but then didn&amp;rsquo;t read it fully until the last few days. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how I feel about using it for regular encounters and the like, but I was struck with the idea to use it to do off-screen faction interactions, like in a mega-dungeon. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to do the experiment here (I&amp;rsquo;m also trying out the &amp;ldquo;After the Break&amp;rdquo; feature, which I just learned how to use).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Spells</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-13-some-spells/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2013 13:34:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-13-some-spells/</guid>
      <description>So, I&amp;rsquo;m going through the spell lists to try to make them more appropriate for the shape that wizards are starting to take in Fellhold. My good friend (Yllgrad&amp;rsquo;s player, if you follow the play report posts at all) sent me some spell ideas (Troll Form, Create Familiar, Orb of Many Colors, Volsungr&amp;rsquo;s Anvil, and Summon Spiders are all based on his stuff), and that got me started working on the spell descriptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Granularity of Megadungeons</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-12-the-granularity-of-megadungeons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 07:45:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-12-the-granularity-of-megadungeons/</guid>
      <description>Because I ought to be working on the spell list for the updated magic rules so that the new wizard character can actually do his thing, so of course I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about megadungeons instead.
 Derinkuyu: Real Dungeon. Google it!
So, we&amp;rsquo;ve got node-based megadungeon design and we&amp;rsquo;ve got various dungeon map generators, dating back to the 1st Edition DMG. I think these two extremes of granularity (very little and very much respectively) are missing a sweet spot in a methodology for designing a megadungeon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Level Fighters, What&#39;s Going On?</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-11-high-level-fighters-whats-going-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 12:01:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-11-high-level-fighters-whats-going-on/</guid>
      <description>So, after being shamed by the accurate description at Charles Akin&amp;rsquo;s Great Blog Roll Call of my posting habits (ridiculously infrequent), I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to put up a quick post with some thoughts from a recent Google+ conversation, and to work on my concision to boot.
I solicited some ideas about how much damage higher-level fighters should do in older types of D&amp;amp;D. In OD&amp;amp;D and the various flavors of Basic-derived D&amp;amp;D, fighters don&amp;rsquo;t really get a bunch of attacks or damage bonuses beyond whatever they start with (okay, except against 1HD foes).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[UPDATE] Occult Magic for Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-05-occult-magic-for-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 22:34:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-05-occult-magic-for-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>http://images19.fotki.com/v27/photos/4/41638/2024361/13066wizardvan-vi.jpg
[edit: In my excitement, I was pretty lazy about attributing sources or making explicit how much stuff I got directly from other folks, so I&amp;rsquo;ve edited the post to reflect that. In adding the proper attributions, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty embarrassing how little of this stuff is my own. ] * *This seemed to warrant a blog post. Here are the (mostly) complete rules for Wizard (magic user) magic in the new Fellhold house rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 36 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 19:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night we wrapped up “Season 1” of Fellhold. Not Season 1 in some pre-planned plot arc sense, heavens no! Rather, starting next week we’re switching to the new game I mentioned last time, and it just so happened that a lot of shit hit the fan this session and we ended at a good cliffhanger. Serendipitous! 
So, shit and fan hitting: we returned to Gurgu smashing pillars in his summoning area, most of the party hiding, and Bryni leading Bjergmund and a few priests and initiates down to see the “miracle” of Gurgu summoned, with the hopes of gently guiding them to the worship of Volsungr or some other proper god (but they figured Volsungr would be the best fit).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 35 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-02-fellhold-session-35-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 20:09:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-02-fellhold-session-35-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session was fairly short on game play, but what did happen seemed to go pretty well. The reason gameplay was short was because we spent the first hour or so discussing what game to add to the rotation. Fellhold will continue, but two weeks from today it will go on a hiatus while we play a new game for a while. The thought is to keep anybody (myself included) from getting burned out or losing interest, and to enjoy other roleplaying games, cos why have just one?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 34 Recap and Supplemental Optional Library Rules</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-26-fellhold-session-34-recap-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 19:45:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-26-fellhold-session-34-recap-and/</guid>
      <description>Research, research, research. This session was pretty much entirely the players using the library in the Fyrberg temple to try to find out more about the history of Gurgu, Gurguism, and the complex in the mountain. It dragged a little, as everyone was researching different stuff, and I had to narrate results of their researches to each person individually. Also, describing what you’ve read in ancient texts isn’t always the most interesting experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 31 Recap (and rules for clerics of Hrokr)</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 15:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</guid>
      <description>This will be a fairly bare bones recap, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been busier than anticipated this week.
Yllgrad managed to escape the temple, and he even did so without murdering the initiates that he held hostage. Of course, shortly after leaving, they told the high priest what had happened, and the priesthood of Gurgu decided to pursue the crazed dwarf. When the characters who had undergone the initiation into the belief of Gurgu reached the shrine again, they found the priests and initiates looking agitated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runic Magic in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 17:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>*Nota Bene: Pretty much this entire post is rules, but I&amp;rsquo;ve maintained the convention of bold italic type so that it will stand out if you&amp;rsquo;re scrolling up or down the page only looking for the useful stuff. * 
I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to come add magic runes to the Fellhold campaign for a while now, to get that delicious Viking flavor. I contemplated a cool combinatory system with very modular runes, kinda inspired by sygalldry in Patrick Rothfuss&amp;rsquo;s Kingkiller Chronicle books, but I decided that a) that would be a whole lot of work, and b) it would clash with the overall Vancian magical flavor of D&amp;amp;D the campaign has mostly relied on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 30 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 21:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 29 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 20:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session saw us with about half the usual group due to a confluence of work and finals for three of the players. So, that left us with Caleb, Earn, and Yllgrad in the big city of Mickleheim. Their players were pretty pumped about getting stuff sold and getting to the Volcano, but a) I wanted to flesh out Mickleheim some, b) I wanted to give some of the Vornheim city kit rules and others that I’ve compiled a test drive, and c) I needed some more time to properly prep the volcano adventure, so we ended up zooming in on their errands in the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 28 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 19:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Problem</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 16:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</guid>
      <description>So, in my ongoing Fellhold campaign, we’ve been using Akratic Wizardry’s rather good “weapon damage by class” rule as a compromise between “all weapons do d6” and “all weapons have their own unique damage”. I think if we weren’t already 6 months into using these rules, I’d probably tweak some of the damage a little bit, and maybe recategorize a few weapons (having short bows, long bows, and crossbows all do “medium weapon” damage, and treating hired swords as level 1 fighting men means that players have access to cheap and plentiful d8 damage – I gotta remember to play up the hirelings as people more).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventurer as a Meta-Class</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 21:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</guid>
      <description>So, I’m reading through the excellent analysis of skills in D&amp;amp;D over at Hack &amp;amp; Slash. It touches on what the functions of a resolution mechanic are at all, and especially digs into what 3.x/Pathfinder style skills bring to D&amp;amp;D (and don’t). Considering some of my recent forays away from a pure lack of skill systems at all (using the “Good at” and “Bad at” cues, considering the use of roll under stat checks more often, et cetera), this is striking me as very useful analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part I: Introduction</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 21:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</guid>
      <description>So, for some blog fodder, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided I&amp;rsquo;m going to take on the rather ambitious project of going through every version of D&amp;amp;D and comment on the rules. To keep myself sane, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking to core books only. I&amp;rsquo;m up in the air on OD&amp;amp;D if it will include the supplements or only the the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s. The idea is to hit up White Box, Holmes, Moldvay, Mentzer, Rules Cyclopedia, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, AD&amp;amp;D 2E, D&amp;amp;D 3/3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Interlude on Rule Systems</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 16:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</guid>
      <description>Not exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swords &amp; Wizardry Appreciation Day!</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 10:48:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the first official Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Appreciation day! Considering Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox is the ruleset we&amp;rsquo;re using for the Fellhold campaign, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d like to jump in on this. I&amp;rsquo;ve expounded earlier why we went with Whitebox, but basically I found the simplicity attractive as a foundation to add house rules to, rather than trying to cut out pieces of other versions. As play has gone on, it has both taught me to value and enjoy the lack of some rules but also it has pointed out exactly how other rules came to be by experiencing the desire to have them in game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humanoids of Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 01:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Long Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 22:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/</guid>
      <description>Grasping, Avaricious PCs - the best kind
So, long time no recap. As mentioned in my little apology for non-blogging/calling myself to action post, I’m going to completely change up my style for recaps. The whole ‘pulp adventure narrator’ tone was dumb, and I was dumb, but now I’m better, and I’m going to actually talk about player decisions and my decisions and how the session went down and so forth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-10-so-again-with-absence-of-blogging-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 22:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-10-so-again-with-absence-of-blogging-thing/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Sessions 13 &amp; 14 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</guid>
      <description>After fleeing from the seemingly endless hordes of large and aggressive trollkin, our adventurers spiked a door behind them and listened with baited breath. Not hearing any sounds of further pursuit, they decided against fleeing blindly, and continued to explore and map carefully. After discovering a secret door and defeating a hideous ooze that dissolved a few weapons, they secured a small clutch of gems, spiked another two doors behind them and decided to rest inside the dungeon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 12 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 17:40:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</guid>
      <description>We left off with our adventurers deep within the Ashfell, and as we joined them this week, they continued to explore . They returned to the relief mural depiction of the founding of Fellhold and followed the carvings around a large hall, reading a story of dwarves comes to Ashfell, delving into the mountain, and ending with a scene of trade, craft, and fellowship between dwarves and men. Having satisfied themselves that this mural did not contain any further clues about how to proceed, they set off to continue down a wide passageway leading from the imposing statue of a sorceror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 11 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 22:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our brave adventurers consolidated after cutting down wave after wave of goblin fighters, and decided that the best course of action was to camp outside of the goblin lair they had extensively mapped out. Spending the night in quiet, they proceeded to thoroughly map out every nook and cranny of the goblin delving, and then turned their eyes to the previously explored excavated stairs deeper into the mountain. Following these stairs down, they found a brief encounter with vicious giant rats, a long since abandoned market place, many empty store rooms, and a painful but ultimately unremarkable needle trap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Fellhold Rules Post</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 15:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</guid>
      <description>Howdy folks. The bulk of this post will be the first actual rules I have written for Fellhold coming out of my reading &amp;ldquo;An Echo, Resounding&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Dungeon World&amp;rdquo;. I was initially afraid I would simply be using pieces from each with no original material whatsoever, but in the process of figuring out what I really wanted to do, I ended up coming up with something more different than I expected, though the influences are obvious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules, Part 4</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 22:05:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</guid>
      <description>So, for this post I&amp;rsquo;m taking a bit of a departure from the campaign and domain play rules that I&amp;rsquo;ve been kitbashing from Dungeon World and An Echo, Resounding. This is mostly because it&amp;rsquo;s been awhile, and I&amp;rsquo;m having to reconstruct all the stuff I had figured out from what are now opaque notes, and instead of figuring all that out tonight, I went instead for a simpler problem and decided to tackle some planning/layout issues, and then to address equipment tags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 10 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 22:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid adventurers, after having destroyed a wolf pack, venture through a secret door into hewn underground passages. Joined this time by Yllgrad and Earn and their cohorts (though still not by Blum) the strengthened party takes a few moments to regroup and take advantage of magical healing before venturing into the underground passages. Finding no sign of the goblins they heard exclaim earlier, they push into to the passages and find a room full of rubble with stairs leading steeply downward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 9 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 10:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</guid>
      <description>Due to various obligations in Silverdelf, Yllgrad, Blum, and Earn remained behind, but along with their hirelings and henchmen, Bryni, Caleb, and Varian set off to explore the heretofore unknown eastern path up the spur to Fellhold. They found that the path petered out in a heavily wooded and gently sloping portion of mountain, with crags and boulders suggesting caves. On further exploration, they found a large cave opening, and an initial scan of the cave revealed a heavy bed of pine needles as well as the grisly remains of creatures large and small, accompanied by a horrible smell.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 8 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 08:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</guid>
      <description>After last week&amp;rsquo;s harrowing encounter with arm-hungry statues and pit traps, our daring band of adventurers decided it was time to attend to some matters outside of Fellhold&amp;rsquo;s dark halls. Acca, the hireling who lost his arm, survived his grievous injury, and his family was so grateful for the pension his employer offered him that his son Weorc took service in his place. The party set out on a quiet trip to Mickleheim where they once again strengthened their ties to Clan Dagaeca through the steward Cnud, selling them the splendid necklace of fire opals lifted from Earn the bandit chief and discovering that an exotic beast brought in alive for the midwinter festival would make a fine offering to Hrokr, fine enough that a bounty might be offered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 7 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 10:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid band of adventurers finished up their business in Mickleheim, recruiting even more hirelings for renewed expeditions. They returned to Silverdelf without incident and discovered that the captured bandits had been sent off to whatever rough justice awaited them in Mickleheim along with the rescued shipment of whiskey. They also caught wind of an armed group buying supplies and setting off in the direction of Fellhold, but for what purpose?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 6 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 08:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night, our intrepid band set out on the road to Mickleheim. The first two days of the three day journey passed quietly, but on the third day just after sun up they were set upon by a pack of vicious wolves! Though the only serious injury was to one of Earn&amp;rsquo;s retainers, who was viciously mauled, Earn leapt to his aid and stemmed the bleeding. After the players dispatched one of the wolves, the rest turned tail and ran, losing three more to parting blows and crossbow quarrels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, Part 3</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 10:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Though the title of this post shortchanges the role An Echo, Resounding is playing in my development of the referee rules in my campaign, I figured it was best to stay consistent.
As an example of the role AER is playing, though I&amp;rsquo;m working my way up to the domain rules, rather than down, I am broadly using the categories and concepts from AER&amp;rsquo;s domain play, so that most of the framework for reconciling Dungeon World style GMing tools with the AER domain play should already be there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Wilderness (Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, part 2)</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</guid>
      <description>As the party is about to venture forth to Mickleheim, I&amp;rsquo;ve started giving some thought to wilderness/sandbox adventure, which I&amp;rsquo;ve intended from the start to be a facet of the Fellhold campaign. I cheated a little bit up front by asking my players to do me the courtesy of agreeing that their characters had come together with the intent to explore Fellhold, at least initially, and we&amp;rsquo;d go from there. This let me devote my initial focus to having mapped and stocked dungeon locations (as it turns out, far more than I&amp;rsquo;ve needed so far - before play, I overestimated the speed with which the party would explore).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Challenges in Judgement</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</guid>
      <description>So, I wanted to separate these thoughts from the recap post, as I intend to keep those almost entirely descriptive of the fiction that works out in the game, rather than the rules and inter-player interactions, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see what works!
After accepting a player&amp;rsquo;s more reasonable interpretation of how Sleep affected a group with mixed hit dice, I was faced with the situation where the party got the drop on a lone, as yet unarmed, surprised 3rd level fighting man with a boat load of hit points (here&amp;rsquo;s me realizing some of the dangers of incorporating unmodified AD&amp;amp;D module encounters into my OD&amp;amp;D game).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 5 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night proved to be one of the most successful outings of our brave adventurers yet. Once again venturing under the mountain and into Fellhold, the judicious question of &amp;ldquo;just how many people does the spell Sleep affect?&amp;rdquo; proved to be the defining moment of the session. Finding the remaining bandits at their midday meal, the magic user Blum cast Sleep on the unsuspecting bandits, and immediately placed all but their leader into a magical slumber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bit of Fellhold Flavor</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-28-a-bit-of-fellhold-flavor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 13:26:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-28-a-bit-of-fellhold-flavor/</guid>
      <description>So, I was inspired by Mr. Maliszewski&amp;rsquo;s post over at Grognardia about homebrew campaign settings to talk a little bit about what&amp;rsquo;s been established regarding Fellhold so far. There isn&amp;rsquo;t a whole lot, because I&amp;rsquo;m trying really hard not to indulge my world building bug and detail out a hugely elaborate setting before things occur in play. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to fix a firm aesthetic in my mind, so that as questions/situations come up in play, I can incorporate recent events and player actions, but still maintain an editorial voice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to Swords &amp; Wizardry WhiteBox Part 2</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 18:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</guid>
      <description>So, the title of this post is more for the sake of continuity than for accuracy. You see, as my referee rule hacking has continued, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using not just Dungeon World, but also An Echo, Resounding and to a lesser extent the Red Tide Campaign Sourcebook. The sandbox material in Red Tide is, as mentioned before, quite excellent, but a good deal of it is superseded by what is included in *An Echo, Resounding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 3 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 21:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</guid>
      <description>After leaving last session with our explorers holding a bandit sergeant hostage, we rejoined the action this evening. A brief parley established that the bandit leader, Gren, didn&amp;rsquo;t value the contributions of his sergeant Dag, and some quick bargaining brought Dag over to the side of the adventurers. They managed to flee, trigger the pressure plate trap to drop a net, and then picked up the net and threw it onto the advancing bandits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;You Have to Put in the Work&#34;</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-20-have-to-put-in-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 11:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-20-have-to-put-in-work/</guid>
      <description>Let me tell you a little story about the path that led to my starting up an Old School D&amp;amp;D Campaign. While having far too much time on my hands courtesy of the United States Government, I stumbled onto the indie RPG scene online. Amongst other things, I discovered Vincent Baker&amp;rsquo;s games and blog, and started reading and being inspired by both. One post that didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly register at the time, but has since stuck with me was I &amp;lt;3 the OSR, and especially comment number 8.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 2 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 22:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</guid>
      <description>In tonight&amp;rsquo;s expedition, our daring adventurers took their first steps into the dank underground of Fellhold. After some accurate mapping and cleverly avoiding a pressure plate trap, the party got the drop on a group of bandits going through their loot. They failed to take full advantage of the surprise and entered into a grinding battle with them. With only the bandits&amp;rsquo; leader and one bandit still standing, a group of bandit reinforcements was spotted about to join the fray, and in a last ditch desperate effort, our adventurers managed to subdue the leader and hope to use his life to parley a way out of this dangerous situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to White Box, Part 1</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 16:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</guid>
      <description>So, as mentioned in my previous post, I think that the GMing rules from Dungeon World/AW are those which can most profitably be ported into an Old School D&amp;amp;D game (Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox in my case). With that in mind, I&amp;rsquo;m going to start by going through the Dungeon World Agendas, Principles and Moves, as well as the Always Say guidelines, and discuss/tweak to the &amp;lsquo;Old School&amp;rsquo; refing style I am using in my game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeon World, An Echo, Resounding, Refereeing and You</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-16-dungeon-world-echo-resounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2012 18:36:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-16-dungeon-world-echo-resounding/</guid>
      <description>(ed: in my original post, I said that Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox was shared under a Creative Commons License, but this was incorrect. It is, in fact, shared under the Open Game License. I&amp;rsquo;ve edited the text below to reflect this)
So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through the ever-excellent Kevin Crawford&amp;rsquo;s An Echo, Resounding, as well as Sage LaTorra&amp;rsquo;s totally sweet Dungeon World, switching back and forth between the two of them, and I think there&amp;rsquo;s something really powerful to be made between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Point of Similarity</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 22:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</guid>
      <description>So, all of my recent posts have been about the Old School Renaissance, and my old school D&amp;amp;D game. If you look to the posts that started this blog, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that I was quite enamored of indie RPGs and forge theory and the like. At first glance this seems like something of a flip-flop, but it was actually from the indie &amp;ldquo;scene&amp;rdquo; that I discovered the OSR and became fired up to run a D&amp;amp;D game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Random</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-11-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 13:16:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-11-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love/</guid>
      <description>One of the many things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to embrace in preparing my Old School campaign has been what Mr. Maliszewski over at Grognardia refers to as &amp;ldquo;The Oracular Power of Dice&amp;rdquo;. I also got the name for my blog from a post by Ben Robbins at Ars Ludi on a similar topic. Basically, the idea is to accept what the dice give you and then craft your plans around them, rather than to have a master plan and only accept results that fit with that plan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Note about Rules</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-11-a-note-about-rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 11:04:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-11-a-note-about-rules/</guid>
      <description>So, one of the things I took to heart while reading through James Malieszewski&amp;rsquo;s Dwimmermount campaign over at Grognardia was the notion that it is easier to start with sparse rules and then add more subsystems than it is to cut back an existing bigger system. I originally intended to go real-hard core old school and use the original three Little Brown Books as the rules, and add from there. Alas, during character generation I found myself not comfortable enough with them to quickly and efficiently use them as in-game reference material.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 1</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 22:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</guid>
      <description>So, our brave expedition&amp;rsquo;s first venture up the mountain led to a ruined outpost guarding a gate into the underworld. Blum and Varian were unable to make it on this first expedition, but Yllgrad, Caleb, Bryni, and Earn set their sights on adventure and followed the path out of Silverdelf up the spur of the mountain. While exploring the ruined outpost, Earn and Caleb ventured into a ruined tower and were set upon by a giant spider!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prep is Fun!</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-06-prep-is-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2012 12:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-06-prep-is-fun/</guid>
      <description>So, we had to put off our first game session until next week due to a number of scheduling difficulties, but that&amp;rsquo;s probably good, as I will be far more prepared this way. I&amp;rsquo;m having a grand old time swiping stuff from modules and supplements new and old, gleefully combing OD&amp;amp;D, S&amp;amp;W, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, LL, and whatever else comes in handy, while checking facts about ecology online. I haven&amp;rsquo;t designed a dungeon in about 15 years, and back then I was completely focused on providing just the right challenge that players would have a tough time of it, but would win, and they were all &amp;ldquo;lair&amp;rdquo; type dungeons, very much of the &amp;ldquo;something bad is outside of our village, please go deal with it!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Wild Campaign Appears!</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-08-29-a-wild-campaign-appears/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 15:11:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-08-29-a-wild-campaign-appears/</guid>
      <description>Last night saw the character generation session for my new old school campaign, Fellhold. Fellhold is a dungeon built into the living rock of Ashfell made up of ancient dwarven ruins, later additions by a foul cabal of sorcerors and their minions, and who knows what else that has burrowed its way in. The general feel is Germanic swords and sorcery (think if Robert E. Howard wrote Beowulf. Or, you know, the Frost Giant&amp;rsquo;s Daughter works too).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>