<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Happiness on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/happiness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Happiness on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Habits for a Happier Life</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I found myself in a funk for a month or two. I don’t want to go all James Altucher and turn this blog into a parade of failures and fears, but I think it’s important to take a look behind the curtain of the generally positive tone I keep here. So, as you read the tips below, keep in mind that they’re coming from someone who needs them.
As you know, I like to have clear definitions before talking about fuzzy topics, so let’s define happiness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned at Forefront 2017</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-10-6-what-i-learned-at-forefront-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/coaching/2017-10-6-what-i-learned-at-forefront-2017/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I attended a conference called Forefront in Chicago, and I had a great time. I met a ton of great people and learned a lot. So, I wanted to record what I learned here, both so that I could keep it fresh, and also to share some of the great material with a wider audience. I learned how great it is to connect with people that are weird the same way you are, how to be happier, how better to hold myself and my clients accountable, and the value of belonging to a supportive community when trying to accomplish anything challenging.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>