<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dungeon World on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/dungeon-world/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dungeon World on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/dungeon-world/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Wilderness (Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, part 2)</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</guid>
      <description>As the party is about to venture forth to Mickleheim, I&amp;rsquo;ve started giving some thought to wilderness/sandbox adventure, which I&amp;rsquo;ve intended from the start to be a facet of the Fellhold campaign. I cheated a little bit up front by asking my players to do me the courtesy of agreeing that their characters had come together with the intent to explore Fellhold, at least initially, and we&amp;rsquo;d go from there. This let me devote my initial focus to having mapped and stocked dungeon locations (as it turns out, far more than I&amp;rsquo;ve needed so far - before play, I overestimated the speed with which the party would explore).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to Swords &amp; Wizardry WhiteBox Part 2</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 18:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</guid>
      <description>So, the title of this post is more for the sake of continuity than for accuracy. You see, as my referee rule hacking has continued, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using not just Dungeon World, but also An Echo, Resounding and to a lesser extent the Red Tide Campaign Sourcebook. The sandbox material in Red Tide is, as mentioned before, quite excellent, but a good deal of it is superseded by what is included in *An Echo, Resounding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to White Box, Part 1</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 16:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</guid>
      <description>So, as mentioned in my previous post, I think that the GMing rules from Dungeon World/AW are those which can most profitably be ported into an Old School D&amp;amp;D game (Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox in my case). With that in mind, I&amp;rsquo;m going to start by going through the Dungeon World Agendas, Principles and Moves, as well as the Always Say guidelines, and discuss/tweak to the &amp;lsquo;Old School&amp;rsquo; refing style I am using in my game.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>