<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recap on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/tags/recap/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recap on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2014 08:26:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/recap/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Crapsack Goblins Home Game Report</title>
      <link>/gaming/2014-06-24-crapsack-goblins-home-game-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2014 08:26:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2014-06-24-crapsack-goblins-home-game-report/</guid>
      <description>http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L8hPWdfkCPs/U6mZWjje4zI/AAAAAAAAAxo/1Zmomz1THZA/s1600/The_Great_Goblin_3.jpg
Commentary So last night I was able to run for the first time the game concept I outlined here. Since writing that, I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on the set up a little bit and I was able to subject my regular weekly group to the game rather than trying it out on strangers first. The summary version is that it was hilarious and fun and the combination of setting and rules created exactly the kind of mad-cap goblin shennanigans I was hoping for!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planet of the Lost</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-07-25-planet-of-lost/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 19:14:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-07-25-planet-of-lost/</guid>
      <description>So, this is just a quick post on the alternate game we&amp;rsquo;ve now played for our last two sessions: Planet of the Lost. The basic idea is that our characters were all on a flight from Nairobi to London and it crashed under mysterious circumstances in the desert. We all figured we were in the Sahara at first, but it&amp;rsquo;s quickly becoming clear that something much weirder is going on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 36 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 19:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night we wrapped up “Season 1” of Fellhold. Not Season 1 in some pre-planned plot arc sense, heavens no! Rather, starting next week we’re switching to the new game I mentioned last time, and it just so happened that a lot of shit hit the fan this session and we ended at a good cliffhanger. Serendipitous! 
So, shit and fan hitting: we returned to Gurgu smashing pillars in his summoning area, most of the party hiding, and Bryni leading Bjergmund and a few priests and initiates down to see the “miracle” of Gurgu summoned, with the hopes of gently guiding them to the worship of Volsungr or some other proper god (but they figured Volsungr would be the best fit).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 35 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-07-02-fellhold-session-35-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 20:09:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-07-02-fellhold-session-35-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session was fairly short on game play, but what did happen seemed to go pretty well. The reason gameplay was short was because we spent the first hour or so discussing what game to add to the rotation. Fellhold will continue, but two weeks from today it will go on a hiatus while we play a new game for a while. The thought is to keep anybody (myself included) from getting burned out or losing interest, and to enjoy other roleplaying games, cos why have just one?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 34 Recap and Supplemental Optional Library Rules</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-06-26-fellhold-session-34-recap-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 19:45:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-06-26-fellhold-session-34-recap-and/</guid>
      <description>Research, research, research. This session was pretty much entirely the players using the library in the Fyrberg temple to try to find out more about the history of Gurgu, Gurguism, and the complex in the mountain. It dragged a little, as everyone was researching different stuff, and I had to narrate results of their researches to each person individually. Also, describing what you’ve read in ancient texts isn’t always the most interesting experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 31 Recap (and rules for clerics of Hrokr)</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 15:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</guid>
      <description>This will be a fairly bare bones recap, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been busier than anticipated this week.
Yllgrad managed to escape the temple, and he even did so without murdering the initiates that he held hostage. Of course, shortly after leaving, they told the high priest what had happened, and the priesthood of Gurgu decided to pursue the crazed dwarf. When the characters who had undergone the initiation into the belief of Gurgu reached the shrine again, they found the priests and initiates looking agitated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 30 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 21:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 28 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 19:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Long Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 22:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2013-04-10-the-long-recap/</guid>
      <description>Grasping, Avaricious PCs - the best kind
So, long time no recap. As mentioned in my little apology for non-blogging/calling myself to action post, I’m going to completely change up my style for recaps. The whole ‘pulp adventure narrator’ tone was dumb, and I was dumb, but now I’m better, and I’m going to actually talk about player decisions and my decisions and how the session went down and so forth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Sessions 13 &amp; 14 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</guid>
      <description>After fleeing from the seemingly endless hordes of large and aggressive trollkin, our adventurers spiked a door behind them and listened with baited breath. Not hearing any sounds of further pursuit, they decided against fleeing blindly, and continued to explore and map carefully. After discovering a secret door and defeating a hideous ooze that dissolved a few weapons, they secured a small clutch of gems, spiked another two doors behind them and decided to rest inside the dungeon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 12 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 17:40:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</guid>
      <description>We left off with our adventurers deep within the Ashfell, and as we joined them this week, they continued to explore . They returned to the relief mural depiction of the founding of Fellhold and followed the carvings around a large hall, reading a story of dwarves comes to Ashfell, delving into the mountain, and ending with a scene of trade, craft, and fellowship between dwarves and men. Having satisfied themselves that this mural did not contain any further clues about how to proceed, they set off to continue down a wide passageway leading from the imposing statue of a sorceror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 11 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 22:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our brave adventurers consolidated after cutting down wave after wave of goblin fighters, and decided that the best course of action was to camp outside of the goblin lair they had extensively mapped out. Spending the night in quiet, they proceeded to thoroughly map out every nook and cranny of the goblin delving, and then turned their eyes to the previously explored excavated stairs deeper into the mountain. Following these stairs down, they found a brief encounter with vicious giant rats, a long since abandoned market place, many empty store rooms, and a painful but ultimately unremarkable needle trap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 10 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 22:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid adventurers, after having destroyed a wolf pack, venture through a secret door into hewn underground passages. Joined this time by Yllgrad and Earn and their cohorts (though still not by Blum) the strengthened party takes a few moments to regroup and take advantage of magical healing before venturing into the underground passages. Finding no sign of the goblins they heard exclaim earlier, they push into to the passages and find a room full of rubble with stairs leading steeply downward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 9 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 10:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</guid>
      <description>Due to various obligations in Silverdelf, Yllgrad, Blum, and Earn remained behind, but along with their hirelings and henchmen, Bryni, Caleb, and Varian set off to explore the heretofore unknown eastern path up the spur to Fellhold. They found that the path petered out in a heavily wooded and gently sloping portion of mountain, with crags and boulders suggesting caves. On further exploration, they found a large cave opening, and an initial scan of the cave revealed a heavy bed of pine needles as well as the grisly remains of creatures large and small, accompanied by a horrible smell.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 8 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 08:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</guid>
      <description>After last week&amp;rsquo;s harrowing encounter with arm-hungry statues and pit traps, our daring band of adventurers decided it was time to attend to some matters outside of Fellhold&amp;rsquo;s dark halls. Acca, the hireling who lost his arm, survived his grievous injury, and his family was so grateful for the pension his employer offered him that his son Weorc took service in his place. The party set out on a quiet trip to Mickleheim where they once again strengthened their ties to Clan Dagaeca through the steward Cnud, selling them the splendid necklace of fire opals lifted from Earn the bandit chief and discovering that an exotic beast brought in alive for the midwinter festival would make a fine offering to Hrokr, fine enough that a bounty might be offered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 7 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 10:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid band of adventurers finished up their business in Mickleheim, recruiting even more hirelings for renewed expeditions. They returned to Silverdelf without incident and discovered that the captured bandits had been sent off to whatever rough justice awaited them in Mickleheim along with the rescued shipment of whiskey. They also caught wind of an armed group buying supplies and setting off in the direction of Fellhold, but for what purpose?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 6 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 08:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night, our intrepid band set out on the road to Mickleheim. The first two days of the three day journey passed quietly, but on the third day just after sun up they were set upon by a pack of vicious wolves! Though the only serious injury was to one of Earn&amp;rsquo;s retainers, who was viciously mauled, Earn leapt to his aid and stemmed the bleeding. After the players dispatched one of the wolves, the rest turned tail and ran, losing three more to parting blows and crossbow quarrels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 5 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night proved to be one of the most successful outings of our brave adventurers yet. Once again venturing under the mountain and into Fellhold, the judicious question of &amp;ldquo;just how many people does the spell Sleep affect?&amp;rdquo; proved to be the defining moment of the session. Finding the remaining bandits at their midday meal, the magic user Blum cast Sleep on the unsuspecting bandits, and immediately placed all but their leader into a magical slumber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 3 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 21:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</guid>
      <description>After leaving last session with our explorers holding a bandit sergeant hostage, we rejoined the action this evening. A brief parley established that the bandit leader, Gren, didn&amp;rsquo;t value the contributions of his sergeant Dag, and some quick bargaining brought Dag over to the side of the adventurers. They managed to flee, trigger the pressure plate trap to drop a net, and then picked up the net and threw it onto the advancing bandits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 2 Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 22:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</guid>
      <description>In tonight&amp;rsquo;s expedition, our daring adventurers took their first steps into the dank underground of Fellhold. After some accurate mapping and cleverly avoiding a pressure plate trap, the party got the drop on a group of bandits going through their loot. They failed to take full advantage of the surprise and entered into a grinding battle with them. With only the bandits&amp;rsquo; leader and one bandit still standing, a group of bandit reinforcements was spotted about to join the fray, and in a last ditch desperate effort, our adventurers managed to subdue the leader and hope to use his life to parley a way out of this dangerous situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 1</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 22:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</guid>
      <description>So, our brave expedition&amp;rsquo;s first venture up the mountain led to a ruined outpost guarding a gate into the underworld. Blum and Varian were unable to make it on this first expedition, but Yllgrad, Caleb, Bryni, and Earn set their sights on adventure and followed the path out of Silverdelf up the spur of the mountain. While exploring the ruined outpost, Earn and Caleb ventured into a ruined tower and were set upon by a giant spider!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>