<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Systems on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/tags/systems/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Systems on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Practicing Divergent &amp; Convergent Thinking - Creativity Part 3</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Okay, so I had planned on covering all of the exercises in one post, but when I broke them out, I realized I would be delivering a gigantic, hard to digest mess. So I broke it up. Our next few posts will cover all of the exercises associated with the building blocks we covered last time, starting with Divergent and Convergent thinking today. It’s a great place to start, because if you develop your ability to separate these two ways of thinking, everything else will flow naturally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis is Only the Beginning - An Introduction to Systems Thinking</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</guid>
      <description>Let’s talk about systems. We’ve touched on them in several posts, and they provide an incredibly valuable tool for understanding a complex world. When we stop thinking about things as independent objects and start thinking about them as elements in a greater whole of interdependent parts, we recognize that they are systems. Today we’re going to talk about a method of inquiry custom designed for such highly complex entities: Systems Thinking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Start Guide for Your Brain’s User Interface</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</guid>
      <description>Note: This post might get your hackles up a bit. You might find it especially surprising in a space dedicated to agency and self improvement - but stick with me and you might learn something extremely useful.
We overestimate our control over what we think, how we feel, and even what we do. We assume that every moment of every day we are rationally picking and choosing what to do. It turns out this is an extremely inadequate view of how we operate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bliss of a Bizarro Book Club</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-02-5-the-bliss-of-a-bizarro-book-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-02-5-the-bliss-of-a-bizarro-book-club/</guid>
      <description>While book clubs are great for getting everybody on the same page (har har), a Bizarro Book Club is a way to inject more diversity into your intellectual life. I’ve talked before about the importance of high quality inputs to your creativity, and this is my favorite new method for finding stuff that I would never have on my own. It combines the traditional social benefits of a book club with a much more exciting way of engaging with books, and it’s just as easy to do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Creativity Frameworks - Creativity Part 4</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-1-two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-1-two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4/</guid>
      <description>In our last installment in this series, we talked about divergent and convergent thinking. Keep that in mind, as it will be central to everything we discuss below. Today, we’re going to talk about frameworks you can use to structure your creative efforts - one for teams and one for individuals. You can use either framework in the other situation, but I find them better suited to different applications.
When we discussed creativity frameworks previously, I mentioned the Basadur Applied Creativity method.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>