<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dungeon Dozen on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/dungeon-dozen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dungeon Dozen on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 16:22:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/dungeon-dozen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello Dungeon Dozen Fans</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-04-04-hello-dungeon-dozen-fans/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 16:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-04-04-hello-dungeon-dozen-fans/</guid>
      <description>Howdy folks. If you&amp;rsquo;ve stopped by the front page here from my Dungeon Dozen Fan Index, then you&amp;rsquo;ll notice it&amp;rsquo;s been a bit since I&amp;rsquo;ve updated the blog here. Rest assured the index has taken a higher priority as a matter of community service than my own blatherings. That being said, I&amp;rsquo;m starting to ramp up a bit again in thinking and writing about RPGs, and if you have seen the Middenheim posts here, I&amp;rsquo;m working on the final .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeon Dozen Mix-Tape Contest</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-01-10-dungeon-dozen-mix-tape-contest/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 15:23:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-01-10-dungeon-dozen-mix-tape-contest/</guid>
      <description>http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-W01-ViuCl8Y/Us75pu7EsTI/AAAAAAAAAgI/Norj7uGQrSU/s1600/designmonsters.jpg
Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve caught up to the present day on the Dungeon Dozen Fan Index, I&amp;rsquo;m all fired up about how awesome all of these d12 tables are. Each one was my new favorite as I read it. I got to thinking about how there&amp;rsquo;s practically a whole game there (aided and abetted in this notion by Patrick Stuart, who really concretized that idea). Certainly I think there&amp;rsquo;s a lot there in very small packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeon Dozen Fan Index Finished</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-01-10-dungeon-dozen-fan-index-finished/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 00:29:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-01-10-dungeon-dozen-fan-index-finished/</guid>
      <description>. . . for now. I have completed getting the fan index up to date and categorized as far as I am capable of right now. In case you aren&amp;rsquo;t happy with how I&amp;rsquo;ve gone about it, I&amp;rsquo;ve alphabetized all of the links here, but otherwise left them unformatted. I can&amp;rsquo;t guarantee that I&amp;rsquo;ll update that non-organized list as often as I update the index here on the blog, but it should be one hell of a head start for anyone who wants to go about putting the links together differently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeon Dozen Fan Index</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-01-06-dungeon-dozen-fan-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 11:43:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2014-01-06-dungeon-dozen-fan-index/</guid>
      <description>http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6mCru7ZTpxI/UssFQiSoTOI/AAAAAAAAAfY/yIS7Li2NzTM/s1600/solids5.jpg
Dungeon Dozen Fan Index
Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, folks, we&amp;rsquo;ll be getting back to Middenheim soon (possibly even later today, depending on what I can get done). But I wanted to take a minute to talk about a mini-project I&amp;rsquo;m maybe one third to half way through: the Dungeon Dozen Fan Index. First off, if you aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar with the Dungeon Dozen, you&amp;rsquo;re missing out. Jason Sholtis creates totally amazing D12 tables of just about anything you can imagine: dungeon building, encounters, monster abilities, character backgrounds, and more.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>