<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Damp;D on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/dampd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Damp;D on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 22:34:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/dampd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[UPDATE] Occult Magic for Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-05-occult-magic-for-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 22:34:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-12-05-occult-magic-for-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>http://images19.fotki.com/v27/photos/4/41638/2024361/13066wizardvan-vi.jpg
[edit: In my excitement, I was pretty lazy about attributing sources or making explicit how much stuff I got directly from other folks, so I&amp;rsquo;ve edited the post to reflect that. In adding the proper attributions, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty embarrassing how little of this stuff is my own. ] * *This seemed to warrant a blog post. Here are the (mostly) complete rules for Wizard (magic user) magic in the new Fellhold house rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seclusium Construction Worksheets</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-28-seclusium-construction-worksheets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 20:16:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-28-seclusium-construction-worksheets/</guid>
      <description>Delightfully Vancian * * [UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 36 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 19:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night we wrapped up “Season 1” of Fellhold. Not Season 1 in some pre-planned plot arc sense, heavens no! Rather, starting next week we’re switching to the new game I mentioned last time, and it just so happened that a lot of shit hit the fan this session and we ended at a good cliffhanger. Serendipitous! 
So, shit and fan hitting: we returned to Gurgu smashing pillars in his summoning area, most of the party hiding, and Bryni leading Bjergmund and a few priests and initiates down to see the “miracle” of Gurgu summoned, with the hopes of gently guiding them to the worship of Volsungr or some other proper god (but they figured Volsungr would be the best fit).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part IV: The Underworld &amp; Wilderness Adventures</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-03-every-version-of-d-part-iv-underworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-03-every-version-of-d-part-iv-underworld/</guid>
      <description>So, as I come to the last of the original Little Brown Books, I have to give a bit of background. When I was getting into D&amp;amp;D as an impatient and overconfident adolescent, I initially gave the DMG something of a pass. It was actually the last of the core rulebooks I bought, and if I remember correctly, I ran my first campaign for quite a while without it. I basically figured I knew what was up, and the Player’s Handbook had “the real rules” (a.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 35 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-02-fellhold-session-35-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 20:09:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-07-02-fellhold-session-35-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session was fairly short on game play, but what did happen seemed to go pretty well. The reason gameplay was short was because we spent the first hour or so discussing what game to add to the rotation. Fellhold will continue, but two weeks from today it will go on a hiatus while we play a new game for a while. The thought is to keep anybody (myself included) from getting burned out or losing interest, and to enjoy other roleplaying games, cos why have just one?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part III: Monsters and Treasure</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-28-every-version-of-d-part-iii-monsters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2013 19:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-28-every-version-of-d-part-iii-monsters/</guid>
      <description>Monsters and Treasures  Okay, so I’ve been writing other stuff for awhile now, and I’ve been neglectful of this little series of naked hubris. So back to it with Monsters and Treasure, Volume 2 of OD&amp;amp;D.
The table that opens the book displays its wargame roots to me. Monsters are presented here as a list, rather than as encyclopedia type entries that you see in the Monster Manual and onwards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 34 Recap and Supplemental Optional Library Rules</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-26-fellhold-session-34-recap-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 19:45:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-26-fellhold-session-34-recap-and/</guid>
      <description>Research, research, research. This session was pretty much entirely the players using the library in the Fyrberg temple to try to find out more about the history of Gurgu, Gurguism, and the complex in the mountain. It dragged a little, as everyone was researching different stuff, and I had to narrate results of their researches to each person individually. Also, describing what you’ve read in ancient texts isn’t always the most interesting experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of &#34;Better than Any Man&#34; and Mercenary Group Recruitment</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-19-review-of-than-any-man-and-mercenary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 16:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-06-19-review-of-than-any-man-and-mercenary/</guid>
      <description>So, after my enthusiastic blurb the other day, I figured “Better than Any Man” warranted a full review after I finished reading it last night. So, here that review is.

First off, for those that might not know, what is “Better than Any Man” (hereafter referred to as BTAM)? BTAM is a meaty adventure/mini-sandbox written by James Raggi for his Lamentations of the Flame Princess Adventures line and specifically for “Free RPG Day 2013”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RPG May Blog Carnival: Campaigns I&#39;d Like to Run</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-28-rpg-may-blog-carnival-campaigns-i-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 16:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-28-rpg-may-blog-carnival-campaigns-i-like/</guid>
      <description>First Time Blog Carnival Participation!
By way of participating in the RPG Blog Carnival for May, I thought I’d jump in with talking about campaigns I’d like to run, and man, are there a lot. Unfortunately, probably a lot more than I’ll ever get to, but that’s just the way of things. So, to impose some structure on my excessive campaign desires, I am going to give an example for each suggested facet of the topic from the introductory post to this Month’s carnival.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 31 Recap (and rules for clerics of Hrokr)</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 15:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</guid>
      <description>This will be a fairly bare bones recap, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been busier than anticipated this week.
Yllgrad managed to escape the temple, and he even did so without murdering the initiates that he held hostage. Of course, shortly after leaving, they told the high priest what had happened, and the priesthood of Gurgu decided to pursue the crazed dwarf. When the characters who had undergone the initiation into the belief of Gurgu reached the shrine again, they found the priests and initiates looking agitated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runic Magic in Fellhold</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 17:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>*Nota Bene: Pretty much this entire post is rules, but I&amp;rsquo;ve maintained the convention of bold italic type so that it will stand out if you&amp;rsquo;re scrolling up or down the page only looking for the useful stuff. * 
I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to come add magic runes to the Fellhold campaign for a while now, to get that delicious Viking flavor. I contemplated a cool combinatory system with very modular runes, kinda inspired by sygalldry in Patrick Rothfuss&amp;rsquo;s Kingkiller Chronicle books, but I decided that a) that would be a whole lot of work, and b) it would clash with the overall Vancian magical flavor of D&amp;amp;D the campaign has mostly relied on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make Sweet D100 Tables for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-16-how-to-make-sweet-d100-tables-for-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 03:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-16-how-to-make-sweet-d100-tables-for-fun/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 30 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 21:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 29 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 20:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session saw us with about half the usual group due to a confluence of work and finals for three of the players. So, that left us with Caleb, Earn, and Yllgrad in the big city of Mickleheim. Their players were pretty pumped about getting stuff sold and getting to the Volcano, but a) I wanted to flesh out Mickleheim some, b) I wanted to give some of the Vornheim city kit rules and others that I’ve compiled a test drive, and c) I needed some more time to properly prep the volcano adventure, so we ended up zooming in on their errands in the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 28 Recap</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 19:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part II: Men &amp; Magic</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 21:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Problem</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 16:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</guid>
      <description>So, in my ongoing Fellhold campaign, we’ve been using Akratic Wizardry’s rather good “weapon damage by class” rule as a compromise between “all weapons do d6” and “all weapons have their own unique damage”. I think if we weren’t already 6 months into using these rules, I’d probably tweak some of the damage a little bit, and maybe recategorize a few weapons (having short bows, long bows, and crossbows all do “medium weapon” damage, and treating hired swords as level 1 fighting men means that players have access to cheap and plentiful d8 damage – I gotta remember to play up the hirelings as people more).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventurer as a Meta-Class</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 21:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</guid>
      <description>So, I’m reading through the excellent analysis of skills in D&amp;amp;D over at Hack &amp;amp; Slash. It touches on what the functions of a resolution mechanic are at all, and especially digs into what 3.x/Pathfinder style skills bring to D&amp;amp;D (and don’t). Considering some of my recent forays away from a pure lack of skill systems at all (using the “Good at” and “Bad at” cues, considering the use of roll under stat checks more often, et cetera), this is striking me as very useful analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part I: Introduction</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 21:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</guid>
      <description>So, for some blog fodder, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided I&amp;rsquo;m going to take on the rather ambitious project of going through every version of D&amp;amp;D and comment on the rules. To keep myself sane, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking to core books only. I&amp;rsquo;m up in the air on OD&amp;amp;D if it will include the supplements or only the the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s. The idea is to hit up White Box, Holmes, Moldvay, Mentzer, Rules Cyclopedia, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, AD&amp;amp;D 2E, D&amp;amp;D 3/3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Interlude on Rule Systems</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 16:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</guid>
      <description>Not exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>