<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RPGs on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/rpgs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RPGs on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/rpgs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Sages Say&#34; Monster Generator</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</guid>
      <description>I made a thing that makes monsters. I&amp;rsquo;m terribly pleased with it right now, but let me know what you think. If the embed below is giving you weird formatting (on a phone or tablet, say), or if you just want to mess with it, check out the sheet here.
I used Brendan&amp;rsquo;s excellent methodology to build it in Google Sheets. Every time you refresh this page, you should get a new result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OSR Classes: The Mastermind and the Rook</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 08:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</guid>
      <description>After my last post on Flexible Reaction Rolls, I found myself thinking about how to build Character Classes that fit with the schemey, urban style of play I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for with Fellhold. The trouble for me until now was that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t think of ways to get that stuff without impinging on the Old School playstyle I enjoy. What cracked it for me was turning the Reaction Roll into a mechanic with more knobs to play with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Reaction Rolls</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 11:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</guid>
      <description>Reaction rolls are one of my very favorite set of rules. They&amp;rsquo;re quick, easy, and help me to come up with more interesting stuff than I might on my own. I use them as a general purpose social sub-system, though not nearly to the same extent as Courtney Campbell in his excellent On the Non-Player Character. Instead, I use them more as an oracle when I&amp;rsquo;m unsure of how the NPCs would react.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Money &amp; Equipment in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 12:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but I find coming up with equipment lists a huge pain in the ass. Coming up with starting equipment packages? Even harder. So why don&amp;rsquo;t I just use one of the perfectly serviceable equipment lists already out there? Because I definitely buy into the thought that equipment lists are a great way to convey implicit setting and approaches to the game. So I bit the bullet and cranked the below out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Soul Economy in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:07:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>So, back when I first started rebooting my home campaign setting from a Tentpole Megadungeon generic D&amp;amp;D world that owed a lot to Dwimmermount and into something a little funkier, one of the ideas I hit upon was that the economy would be based on souls. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really know what that meant, but it seemed cool, so I ran with it. Well, after lots of reading and thinking and coming up with other parts of the world, it finally clicked together into something that makes some (warped, D&amp;amp;D, in-game) sense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of &#34;Better than Any Man&#34; and Mercenary Group Recruitment</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-19-review-of-than-any-man-and-mercenary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 16:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-19-review-of-than-any-man-and-mercenary/</guid>
      <description>So, after my enthusiastic blurb the other day, I figured “Better than Any Man” warranted a full review after I finished reading it last night. So, here that review is.

First off, for those that might not know, what is “Better than Any Man” (hereafter referred to as BTAM)? BTAM is a meaty adventure/mini-sandbox written by James Raggi for his Lamentations of the Flame Princess Adventures line and specifically for “Free RPG Day 2013”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free RPG Day</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-16-free-rpg-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2013 13:47:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-16-free-rpg-day/</guid>
      <description>So, yesterday was &amp;ldquo;Free RPG Day&amp;rdquo;. For those of you who don&amp;rsquo;t know, participating game stores buy boxes from the Free RPG Day organizers which are chock full of free game material. Usually this consists of one-off adventures, quick start versions of rules, that kind of thing. And for Castles &amp;amp; Crusades, Dungeon Crawl Classics, and Star Wars: Edge of the Empire, that is precisely what I got (there were some others, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to grab stuff just for the sake of grabbing stuff when other people might get more use out of it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 32 and 33 Recap and Quick and Dirty Mass Combat Rules</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-11-fellhold-session-32-and-33-recap-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2013 16:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-11-fellhold-session-32-and-33-recap-and/</guid>
      <description>Session 32 started out with a lot of technical issues for everyone participating. I suspect it had to do with the changes Google had just made to the hangouts/video chat format. Speaking of which, I miss my posts about hangouts displaying the name of the video chat, because that was the primary way I reminded myself what session number we were on for the blog. Oh well, being able to count should be good enough for the most part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RPG May Blog Carnival: Campaigns I&#39;d Like to Run</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-28-rpg-may-blog-carnival-campaigns-i-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 16:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-28-rpg-may-blog-carnival-campaigns-i-like/</guid>
      <description>First Time Blog Carnival Participation!
By way of participating in the RPG Blog Carnival for May, I thought I’d jump in with talking about campaigns I’d like to run, and man, are there a lot. Unfortunately, probably a lot more than I’ll ever get to, but that’s just the way of things. So, to impose some structure on my excessive campaign desires, I am going to give an example for each suggested facet of the topic from the introductory post to this Month’s carnival.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 31 Recap (and rules for clerics of Hrokr)</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 15:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</guid>
      <description>This will be a fairly bare bones recap, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been busier than anticipated this week.
Yllgrad managed to escape the temple, and he even did so without murdering the initiates that he held hostage. Of course, shortly after leaving, they told the high priest what had happened, and the priesthood of Gurgu decided to pursue the crazed dwarf. When the characters who had undergone the initiation into the belief of Gurgu reached the shrine again, they found the priests and initiates looking agitated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runic Magic in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 17:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>*Nota Bene: Pretty much this entire post is rules, but I&amp;rsquo;ve maintained the convention of bold italic type so that it will stand out if you&amp;rsquo;re scrolling up or down the page only looking for the useful stuff. * 
I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to come add magic runes to the Fellhold campaign for a while now, to get that delicious Viking flavor. I contemplated a cool combinatory system with very modular runes, kinda inspired by sygalldry in Patrick Rothfuss&amp;rsquo;s Kingkiller Chronicle books, but I decided that a) that would be a whole lot of work, and b) it would clash with the overall Vancian magical flavor of D&amp;amp;D the campaign has mostly relied on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make Sweet D100 Tables for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-how-to-make-sweet-d100-tables-for-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 03:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-how-to-make-sweet-d100-tables-for-fun/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 30 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 21:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Harryhausen Tribute</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-09-ray-harryhausen-tribute/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 22:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-09-ray-harryhausen-tribute/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 29 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 20:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session saw us with about half the usual group due to a confluence of work and finals for three of the players. So, that left us with Caleb, Earn, and Yllgrad in the big city of Mickleheim. Their players were pretty pumped about getting stuff sold and getting to the Volcano, but a) I wanted to flesh out Mickleheim some, b) I wanted to give some of the Vornheim city kit rules and others that I’ve compiled a test drive, and c) I needed some more time to properly prep the volcano adventure, so we ended up zooming in on their errands in the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 28 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 19:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part II: Men &amp; Magic</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 21:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Problem</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 16:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</guid>
      <description>So, in my ongoing Fellhold campaign, we’ve been using Akratic Wizardry’s rather good “weapon damage by class” rule as a compromise between “all weapons do d6” and “all weapons have their own unique damage”. I think if we weren’t already 6 months into using these rules, I’d probably tweak some of the damage a little bit, and maybe recategorize a few weapons (having short bows, long bows, and crossbows all do “medium weapon” damage, and treating hired swords as level 1 fighting men means that players have access to cheap and plentiful d8 damage – I gotta remember to play up the hirelings as people more).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventurer as a Meta-Class</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 21:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</guid>
      <description>So, I’m reading through the excellent analysis of skills in D&amp;amp;D over at Hack &amp;amp; Slash. It touches on what the functions of a resolution mechanic are at all, and especially digs into what 3.x/Pathfinder style skills bring to D&amp;amp;D (and don’t). Considering some of my recent forays away from a pure lack of skill systems at all (using the “Good at” and “Bad at” cues, considering the use of roll under stat checks more often, et cetera), this is striking me as very useful analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part I: Introduction</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 21:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</guid>
      <description>So, for some blog fodder, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided I&amp;rsquo;m going to take on the rather ambitious project of going through every version of D&amp;amp;D and comment on the rules. To keep myself sane, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking to core books only. I&amp;rsquo;m up in the air on OD&amp;amp;D if it will include the supplements or only the the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s. The idea is to hit up White Box, Holmes, Moldvay, Mentzer, Rules Cyclopedia, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, AD&amp;amp;D 2E, D&amp;amp;D 3/3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Interlude on Rule Systems</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 16:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</guid>
      <description>Not exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swords &amp; Wizardry Appreciation Day!</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 10:48:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the first official Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Appreciation day! Considering Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox is the ruleset we&amp;rsquo;re using for the Fellhold campaign, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d like to jump in on this. I&amp;rsquo;ve expounded earlier why we went with Whitebox, but basically I found the simplicity attractive as a foundation to add house rules to, rather than trying to cut out pieces of other versions. As play has gone on, it has both taught me to value and enjoy the lack of some rules but also it has pointed out exactly how other rules came to be by experiencing the desire to have them in game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humanoids of Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 01:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Sessions 13 &amp; 14 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</guid>
      <description>After fleeing from the seemingly endless hordes of large and aggressive trollkin, our adventurers spiked a door behind them and listened with baited breath. Not hearing any sounds of further pursuit, they decided against fleeing blindly, and continued to explore and map carefully. After discovering a secret door and defeating a hideous ooze that dissolved a few weapons, they secured a small clutch of gems, spiked another two doors behind them and decided to rest inside the dungeon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 12 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 17:40:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</guid>
      <description>We left off with our adventurers deep within the Ashfell, and as we joined them this week, they continued to explore . They returned to the relief mural depiction of the founding of Fellhold and followed the carvings around a large hall, reading a story of dwarves comes to Ashfell, delving into the mountain, and ending with a scene of trade, craft, and fellowship between dwarves and men. Having satisfied themselves that this mural did not contain any further clues about how to proceed, they set off to continue down a wide passageway leading from the imposing statue of a sorceror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 11 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 22:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our brave adventurers consolidated after cutting down wave after wave of goblin fighters, and decided that the best course of action was to camp outside of the goblin lair they had extensively mapped out. Spending the night in quiet, they proceeded to thoroughly map out every nook and cranny of the goblin delving, and then turned their eyes to the previously explored excavated stairs deeper into the mountain. Following these stairs down, they found a brief encounter with vicious giant rats, a long since abandoned market place, many empty store rooms, and a painful but ultimately unremarkable needle trap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Fellhold Rules Post</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 15:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</guid>
      <description>Howdy folks. The bulk of this post will be the first actual rules I have written for Fellhold coming out of my reading &amp;ldquo;An Echo, Resounding&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Dungeon World&amp;rdquo;. I was initially afraid I would simply be using pieces from each with no original material whatsoever, but in the process of figuring out what I really wanted to do, I ended up coming up with something more different than I expected, though the influences are obvious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules, Part 4</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 22:05:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</guid>
      <description>So, for this post I&amp;rsquo;m taking a bit of a departure from the campaign and domain play rules that I&amp;rsquo;ve been kitbashing from Dungeon World and An Echo, Resounding. This is mostly because it&amp;rsquo;s been awhile, and I&amp;rsquo;m having to reconstruct all the stuff I had figured out from what are now opaque notes, and instead of figuring all that out tonight, I went instead for a simpler problem and decided to tackle some planning/layout issues, and then to address equipment tags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 10 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 22:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid adventurers, after having destroyed a wolf pack, venture through a secret door into hewn underground passages. Joined this time by Yllgrad and Earn and their cohorts (though still not by Blum) the strengthened party takes a few moments to regroup and take advantage of magical healing before venturing into the underground passages. Finding no sign of the goblins they heard exclaim earlier, they push into to the passages and find a room full of rubble with stairs leading steeply downward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 9 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 10:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</guid>
      <description>Due to various obligations in Silverdelf, Yllgrad, Blum, and Earn remained behind, but along with their hirelings and henchmen, Bryni, Caleb, and Varian set off to explore the heretofore unknown eastern path up the spur to Fellhold. They found that the path petered out in a heavily wooded and gently sloping portion of mountain, with crags and boulders suggesting caves. On further exploration, they found a large cave opening, and an initial scan of the cave revealed a heavy bed of pine needles as well as the grisly remains of creatures large and small, accompanied by a horrible smell.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 8 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 08:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</guid>
      <description>After last week&amp;rsquo;s harrowing encounter with arm-hungry statues and pit traps, our daring band of adventurers decided it was time to attend to some matters outside of Fellhold&amp;rsquo;s dark halls. Acca, the hireling who lost his arm, survived his grievous injury, and his family was so grateful for the pension his employer offered him that his son Weorc took service in his place. The party set out on a quiet trip to Mickleheim where they once again strengthened their ties to Clan Dagaeca through the steward Cnud, selling them the splendid necklace of fire opals lifted from Earn the bandit chief and discovering that an exotic beast brought in alive for the midwinter festival would make a fine offering to Hrokr, fine enough that a bounty might be offered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 7 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 10:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid band of adventurers finished up their business in Mickleheim, recruiting even more hirelings for renewed expeditions. They returned to Silverdelf without incident and discovered that the captured bandits had been sent off to whatever rough justice awaited them in Mickleheim along with the rescued shipment of whiskey. They also caught wind of an armed group buying supplies and setting off in the direction of Fellhold, but for what purpose?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 6 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 08:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night, our intrepid band set out on the road to Mickleheim. The first two days of the three day journey passed quietly, but on the third day just after sun up they were set upon by a pack of vicious wolves! Though the only serious injury was to one of Earn&amp;rsquo;s retainers, who was viciously mauled, Earn leapt to his aid and stemmed the bleeding. After the players dispatched one of the wolves, the rest turned tail and ran, losing three more to parting blows and crossbow quarrels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, Part 3</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 10:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Though the title of this post shortchanges the role An Echo, Resounding is playing in my development of the referee rules in my campaign, I figured it was best to stay consistent.
As an example of the role AER is playing, though I&amp;rsquo;m working my way up to the domain rules, rather than down, I am broadly using the categories and concepts from AER&amp;rsquo;s domain play, so that most of the framework for reconciling Dungeon World style GMing tools with the AER domain play should already be there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Wilderness (Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, part 2)</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</guid>
      <description>As the party is about to venture forth to Mickleheim, I&amp;rsquo;ve started giving some thought to wilderness/sandbox adventure, which I&amp;rsquo;ve intended from the start to be a facet of the Fellhold campaign. I cheated a little bit up front by asking my players to do me the courtesy of agreeing that their characters had come together with the intent to explore Fellhold, at least initially, and we&amp;rsquo;d go from there. This let me devote my initial focus to having mapped and stocked dungeon locations (as it turns out, far more than I&amp;rsquo;ve needed so far - before play, I overestimated the speed with which the party would explore).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Challenges in Judgement</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</guid>
      <description>So, I wanted to separate these thoughts from the recap post, as I intend to keep those almost entirely descriptive of the fiction that works out in the game, rather than the rules and inter-player interactions, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see what works!
After accepting a player&amp;rsquo;s more reasonable interpretation of how Sleep affected a group with mixed hit dice, I was faced with the situation where the party got the drop on a lone, as yet unarmed, surprised 3rd level fighting man with a boat load of hit points (here&amp;rsquo;s me realizing some of the dangers of incorporating unmodified AD&amp;amp;D module encounters into my OD&amp;amp;D game).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 5 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night proved to be one of the most successful outings of our brave adventurers yet. Once again venturing under the mountain and into Fellhold, the judicious question of &amp;ldquo;just how many people does the spell Sleep affect?&amp;rdquo; proved to be the defining moment of the session. Finding the remaining bandits at their midday meal, the magic user Blum cast Sleep on the unsuspecting bandits, and immediately placed all but their leader into a magical slumber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bit of Fellhold Flavor</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-28-a-bit-of-fellhold-flavor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 13:26:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-28-a-bit-of-fellhold-flavor/</guid>
      <description>So, I was inspired by Mr. Maliszewski&amp;rsquo;s post over at Grognardia about homebrew campaign settings to talk a little bit about what&amp;rsquo;s been established regarding Fellhold so far. There isn&amp;rsquo;t a whole lot, because I&amp;rsquo;m trying really hard not to indulge my world building bug and detail out a hugely elaborate setting before things occur in play. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to fix a firm aesthetic in my mind, so that as questions/situations come up in play, I can incorporate recent events and player actions, but still maintain an editorial voice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to Swords &amp; Wizardry WhiteBox Part 2</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 18:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</guid>
      <description>So, the title of this post is more for the sake of continuity than for accuracy. You see, as my referee rule hacking has continued, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using not just Dungeon World, but also An Echo, Resounding and to a lesser extent the Red Tide Campaign Sourcebook. The sandbox material in Red Tide is, as mentioned before, quite excellent, but a good deal of it is superseded by what is included in *An Echo, Resounding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 3 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 21:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</guid>
      <description>After leaving last session with our explorers holding a bandit sergeant hostage, we rejoined the action this evening. A brief parley established that the bandit leader, Gren, didn&amp;rsquo;t value the contributions of his sergeant Dag, and some quick bargaining brought Dag over to the side of the adventurers. They managed to flee, trigger the pressure plate trap to drop a net, and then picked up the net and threw it onto the advancing bandits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;You Have to Put in the Work&#34;</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-20-have-to-put-in-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 11:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-20-have-to-put-in-work/</guid>
      <description>Let me tell you a little story about the path that led to my starting up an Old School D&amp;amp;D Campaign. While having far too much time on my hands courtesy of the United States Government, I stumbled onto the indie RPG scene online. Amongst other things, I discovered Vincent Baker&amp;rsquo;s games and blog, and started reading and being inspired by both. One post that didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly register at the time, but has since stuck with me was I &amp;lt;3 the OSR, and especially comment number 8.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 2 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 22:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</guid>
      <description>In tonight&amp;rsquo;s expedition, our daring adventurers took their first steps into the dank underground of Fellhold. After some accurate mapping and cleverly avoiding a pressure plate trap, the party got the drop on a group of bandits going through their loot. They failed to take full advantage of the surprise and entered into a grinding battle with them. With only the bandits&amp;rsquo; leader and one bandit still standing, a group of bandit reinforcements was spotted about to join the fray, and in a last ditch desperate effort, our adventurers managed to subdue the leader and hope to use his life to parley a way out of this dangerous situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to White Box, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 16:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</guid>
      <description>So, as mentioned in my previous post, I think that the GMing rules from Dungeon World/AW are those which can most profitably be ported into an Old School D&amp;amp;D game (Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox in my case). With that in mind, I&amp;rsquo;m going to start by going through the Dungeon World Agendas, Principles and Moves, as well as the Always Say guidelines, and discuss/tweak to the &amp;lsquo;Old School&amp;rsquo; refing style I am using in my game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeon World, An Echo, Resounding, Refereeing and You</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-16-dungeon-world-echo-resounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2012 18:36:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-16-dungeon-world-echo-resounding/</guid>
      <description>(ed: in my original post, I said that Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox was shared under a Creative Commons License, but this was incorrect. It is, in fact, shared under the Open Game License. I&amp;rsquo;ve edited the text below to reflect this)
So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through the ever-excellent Kevin Crawford&amp;rsquo;s An Echo, Resounding, as well as Sage LaTorra&amp;rsquo;s totally sweet Dungeon World, switching back and forth between the two of them, and I think there&amp;rsquo;s something really powerful to be made between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Point of Similarity</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 22:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</guid>
      <description>So, all of my recent posts have been about the Old School Renaissance, and my old school D&amp;amp;D game. If you look to the posts that started this blog, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that I was quite enamored of indie RPGs and forge theory and the like. At first glance this seems like something of a flip-flop, but it was actually from the indie &amp;ldquo;scene&amp;rdquo; that I discovered the OSR and became fired up to run a D&amp;amp;D game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 1</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 22:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</guid>
      <description>So, our brave expedition&amp;rsquo;s first venture up the mountain led to a ruined outpost guarding a gate into the underworld. Blum and Varian were unable to make it on this first expedition, but Yllgrad, Caleb, Bryni, and Earn set their sights on adventure and followed the path out of Silverdelf up the spur of the mountain. While exploring the ruined outpost, Earn and Caleb ventured into a ruined tower and were set upon by a giant spider!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s a Paradigm? And why is it shifting?</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-10-22-what-paradigm-and-why-is-it-shifting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2010 20:41:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-10-22-what-paradigm-and-why-is-it-shifting/</guid>
      <description>Okay, so, despite the continuing blog silence, I have been thinking very hard about The Book of Threes for the past couple weeks, and doing lots of &amp;ldquo;research&amp;rdquo; (in other words, reading RPGs that I&amp;rsquo;d love to get to play, and actually getting some gaming in for once!).
I can tell you right now that the rules as they currently exist are not long for this world. Well, that&amp;rsquo;s not true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book of Threes Revision Sneak Preview</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-09-02-book-of-threes-revision-sneak-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2010 08:47:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-09-02-book-of-threes-revision-sneak-preview/</guid>
      <description>Well, it&amp;rsquo;s amazing how much having a real, face-to-face conversation can do for a design. Despite my lack of discernible activity here on the bloog, the gears they are a-churnin, I&amp;rsquo;m doing thinking and reading and what not that are all informing where I&amp;rsquo;m going.
But! To keep this from being a totally content free &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t go away!&amp;rdquo; sort of post, here&amp;rsquo;s a sneak preview of what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about right now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book of Threes Best Interests</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-08-18-book-of-threes-best-interests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2010 14:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-08-18-book-of-threes-best-interests/</guid>
      <description>So, I had a brainwave on how to make &amp;ldquo;Best Interests&amp;rdquo; have a little more teeth (and only after writing it down did I realize it&amp;rsquo;s a solution pretty close to the Burning Wheel system I&amp;rsquo;m finally getting around to reading).
Not only will it give the best interests more mechanical weight, it will (hopefully) increase the tension of choosing between differing interests. Here&amp;rsquo;s my thought: you&amp;rsquo;ve got three best interests (individual, family, and clan) and three resources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book of Threes Alpha Test Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-07-11-book-of-threes-alpha-test-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2010 13:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-07-11-book-of-threes-alpha-test-recap/</guid>
      <description>Okay, sorry this was a bit later than forecasted, but I wanted to collect some thoughts from the first playtest of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; done on Google Wave.
First off, it taught me a lot about Google Wave, and while I think it&amp;rsquo;s far superior to a standard forum for RPGs, it still has some shortcomings compared to &amp;lsquo;the real thing&amp;rsquo; of sitting at a table with your friends and talking it out in person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nINjaSpectres</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-05-ninjaspectres/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2010 12:28:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-05-ninjaspectres/</guid>
      <description>So, as previously mentioned, I got excited about making a Ninja Burger + InSpectres hack, and after noodling around with it, discovered it didn&amp;rsquo;t take much to do at all!
So here it is.
Let me know what you think (this is as yet unplaytested, but considering it comes from two games that work fine and are playtested, I assume it&amp;rsquo;ll be fine. I may make changes once I get the chance to play it some).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smash it up, Smash it up!</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 03:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/</guid>
      <description>So, a recent trend I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading about at the cool kid forums is a sort of game where you say &amp;ldquo;need book X to play&amp;rdquo;. Basically people put out more or less detailed conversion notes for using one set of rules with material from another game (whether just the fluff or some of the actual rules). Shadowrun is a popular target, as it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty universally loved world, with a pretty poorly regarded system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Playtest Update</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 11:41:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/</guid>
      <description>So, the online playtest has kicked off and been going strong for a little over a week, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d give a progress report. We&amp;rsquo;re still in the clan creation phase, but it&amp;rsquo;s working out well. I was afraid that the online format might kill some of the collaborative goodness of the group setting crafting, but so far we&amp;rsquo;ve had lots of that nonetheless, which is really encouraging. Everybody&amp;rsquo;s different ideas are inspiring and spinning off everybody else&amp;rsquo;s, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be happier so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Update</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-19-a-quick-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2010 03:38:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-19-a-quick-update/</guid>
      <description>So, the &amp;ldquo;Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; playtest is getting rolling, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty excited about the opportunities Google Wave is offering for online pencil and paper roleplaying. But since it hasn&amp;rsquo;t gotten very far yet, no commentary so far on the game, and my energies towards it are more focused on getting this game running than on doing more tweaking until I see where it&amp;rsquo;s going.
That being said, I have still been thinking about this whole starter RPG concept, and right now I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards a core resolution that looks a lot like the &amp;ldquo;Otherkind Dice&amp;rdquo; I talked about a few posts back, with the inclusion of something similar to the &amp;ldquo;Secrets&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Keys&amp;rdquo; seen in Lady Blackbird and The Shadow of Yesterday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Playtest</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2010 08:38:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/</guid>
      <description>So, with the revised conflict resolution rules settled as a starting point, I think it&amp;rsquo;s time to take the leap and start playtesting. But my current environment is barren not only in water, but also gamers.
So I&amp;rsquo;m going to give Google Wave a try for an online playtest of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in participating, comment here or email me, and I&amp;rsquo;ll set you up with a Wave account invite.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revised Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2010 08:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>Well, after thinking about the issues raised in Conflict Resolution Conflict, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to what I think is a workable starting point for moving forward with the core resolution rules for &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;.
I decided to go with letting both sides put forward a set number of dice, and for that number to be equal to the leader&amp;rsquo;s current Wealth score. This gives wealth something to do as a static value, and ties it directly into conflict resolution, so now all three resources have something to do in conflict.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ragonarok!</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-12-ragonarok/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2010 03:55:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-12-ragonarok/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s done! I wrote a quick little hack for &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; to play in a Norse flavor called &amp;ldquo;Ragonarok&amp;rdquo; (see what I did there?). The rules changes are available as text here on the blog or as part of a PDF that includes custom character and reference sheets, and a pretty neat little picture of Odin I whipped up. Let me know what you think! Even if you haven&amp;rsquo;t played Agon, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear what you think of the layout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Return of Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 10:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>So, in an earlier post I talked about some sticking points with conflict resolution as it currently stands in &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m having some more fundamental questions about the system than just the number of dice that should be put forward by participants in a round. I&amp;rsquo;m wondering how much the current conflict resolution rules contribute to what I want the game to be and how players will actually, you know, play the game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2010 09:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>Okay, so, I&amp;rsquo;ve been posting some stuff about the game over at this thread on the Forge, both to try to target some hard-core design oriented folks and to draw traffic towards the blog and game :) At any rate, a commenter over there pointed out a glaring deficiency with the conflict resolution rules as written, and then proposed a great solution for one part of it, and some potential solutions for the other, that I wanted to hash out here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Name Day</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 04:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s decided!
I&amp;rsquo;m going to go ahead and go with Tyler&amp;rsquo;s suggestion of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; until it dies or I find a better one. So feel free to throw down with any suggestions or to tell me that&amp;rsquo;s crap, but &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; is the new working title. Beats the Annuvin out of &amp;ldquo;Celto-Germania&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insert Title Here</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 11:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/</guid>
      <description>No really, this post is about titles :)
So, as mentioned before, I have no idea what to name this bad boy as yet. I&amp;rsquo;ve been engaging in some correspondence with my friend Tyler who&amp;rsquo;s pointed me in some good directions, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share the stuff that&amp;rsquo;s working for me, and see if anyone else can take it in a better direction than I can.
So, my goals for the title are for it to be simple and evocative of the milieu, without locking in any really specific flavor elements (so, while &amp;ldquo;The Crow Father&amp;rsquo;s Children&amp;rdquo; has a cool ring to it, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to lock in the Crow Father as one of the gods your group has to use or assume is real).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial Design Thoughts</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 04:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>So, I wanted to keep these thoughts separate from the announcement post so that it didn&amp;rsquo;t get overwhelmed with the information here. I just wanted to lay out a few of the thoughts I had while designing the rules, with the hope that this will open up more avenues of approach for improving the rules (like &amp;ldquo;you wanted this rule to do what? You&amp;rsquo;re way off base!).
First off, the ideas that got me going on this game were notions of conflicting loyalties, and the idea of loyalty impairing your ability to act independently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That Will Remain Nameless at this Time</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 03:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s here! Well, actually it&amp;rsquo;s right here, but I mean it&amp;rsquo;s done. And by done, I mean ready to start the process of becoming a real game.
Why the vague &amp;ldquo;its&amp;rdquo; all over the place? Because I still don&amp;rsquo;t have a good name! I&amp;rsquo;m totally stumped. I keep trying to think of one, trying to put it out of my head hoping an answer will pop up unexpected, trying to steal other people&amp;rsquo;s good names, but none are working so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tale that Grows in the Telling</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 12:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/</guid>
      <description>So, that first draft of the game rules I promised? It&amp;rsquo;s progressing nicely. A little too nicely. What I intended to be a barebones mechanics document is quickly turning into the first draft of the complete rules. I just can&amp;rsquo;t stop writing! So, new ETA for the first draft is May 1st (T minus 5 days).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Excitement!</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2010 11:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/</guid>
      <description>Exciting News!
That last game project that I mentioned, with the reading list? I&amp;rsquo;ve been scribbling away notes on the rules, and I&amp;rsquo;m ready to begin typing up the very rough, totally beta, untested at all draft. I would prefer to do some personal playtesting before releasing it into the wilds of the internet, but I&amp;rsquo;m not going to be in a position to do that for awhile, so I will post it for review and solicit recommendations once it&amp;rsquo;s typed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Direction for Now</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2010 03:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m going to be taking a bit of a break from my starter RPG project for two main reasons. First off, I&amp;rsquo;ve found a wealth of games I&amp;rsquo;d really enjoy to run, some of which I think would make good introductions to what roleplaying is for adult, non-gamer type people. But secondly, I still take the starter RPG notion seriously, but I realized that paradoxically, an RPG designed for beginning players should not be my first full-fledged RPG design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magic and Obligations</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-29-magic-and-obligations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 10:53:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-29-magic-and-obligations/</guid>
      <description>Okay, as I said last time, I&amp;rsquo;m now going to take a break from reviews for a while (I&amp;rsquo;m out of games to read, for one) and start talking about my own game. It is still fragmentary and hazy, but I&amp;rsquo;ve come to a few decisions that will help guide the process from here. First off, I think I have decided that the genre will be &amp;ldquo;sword and sorcery&amp;rdquo; in a setting of my own devising.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spirit of the Century</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-29-spirit-of-century/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 10:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-29-spirit-of-century/</guid>
      <description>For my last Indie game review for a while, I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about &amp;ldquo;Spirit of the Century&amp;rdquo; from Evil Hat Productions. I&amp;rsquo;ve saved this one for last for a couple of reasons. For one, despite some creative and innovative mechanics and approaches, of the games I&amp;rsquo;ve reviewed, I&amp;rsquo;d say it&amp;rsquo;s the most traditional: PCs each have a character, they all cooperate in an adventure the GM comes up with and controls, and their characters have skills and stunts and gadgets that work much like any other RPG.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In a Wicked Age</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-29-in-wicked-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 04:45:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-29-in-wicked-age/</guid>
      <description>Tonight I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about the game that got me excited about this whole Indie RPG business: In a Wicked Age. This is the second game in my survey by D. Vincent Baker, author of &amp;ldquo;Dogs in the Vineyard&amp;rdquo; of a couple posts back. First off, some generalities: IaWA is a wonderfully fluid and story driven game, with an emphasis on low to no preparation for play. It does this in a few innovative ways that I want to discuss as inspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agon</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-18-agon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 12:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-18-agon/</guid>
      <description>In this installment, I will continue my reviews of &amp;ldquo;Indie RPGs&amp;rdquo; that have recently made an impression on me. Today I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;quot;, a game of mythical Greek heroes. First off, &amp;ldquo;Agon&amp;rdquo; is awesome. I absolutely love it, and if I had like minded players around me, I would run a game tomorrow. It is simple but rich, and it captures the feel of Greek mythology and the whole Greek ethos masterfully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dogs in the Vineyard</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-18-dogs-in-vineyard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 12:16:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-03-18-dogs-in-vineyard/</guid>
      <description>Okay, long time, no post. I apologize, and will try to make with the regular updates!
For the moment, I&amp;rsquo;m going to set aside my more general and theoretical speculation about RPGs and discuss some concrete examples. Of course, I plan to sneak general applicability into my discussion, but I&amp;rsquo;ve recently become acquainted with some games that get me very excited, and I want to talk about why. This is still going to be a part of my &amp;lsquo;starter RPG&amp;rsquo; series, because I approached these rules not only as potentially fun games in and of themselves, but with a critical eye towards innovations and techniques worth steeling, with ease of use by new players as the lens through which I viewed these innovations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Matter of Taste</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:58:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/</guid>
      <description>So, before we go into how to encourage a particular genre with the rules, there is the question of what genre to shoot for. If my whole contention is that the real draw of RPGs is the non-mechanical aspects, then a good starter RPG needs to have a genre with wide appeal and plenty of material to fire the imagination. I&amp;rsquo;ll run through a brief list of some popular settings/genres and my thoughts on them, but this is an area where personal taste could cloud my judgement extraordinarily easily, so I would very much appreciate comments on what flavors are good choices for players new to roleplaying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting vs Genre</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:52:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/</guid>
      <description>Right now I want to talk about a distinction I recently came up with between setting and genre. Both get used pretty interchangeably with respect to RPGs, with setting usually having a slightly narrower focus. And either one is usually considered fairly separate from rules issues. But in a discussion of whether it was better to have specific rules for every game setting, or to have a great set of generic rules to use in whatever setting, I realized something about the interaction of the game rules and the game world that I think warrants a distinction in terms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rules and Roleplaying</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:51:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/</guid>
      <description>Well, last time I talked about how I want to focus more on roleplay than on game mechanics in my starter RPG. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: I&amp;rsquo;m a huge game mechanics nut. Sometimes I enjoy designing game rules more than I do actually playing them. As a kid, I once stayed up all night designing a wargame for little green army men that we never got to play because we were so excited about coming up with rules for each weapon, each vehicle, and every situation we could imagine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The RP in RPG</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:42:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/</guid>
      <description>In my last post I talked about my own introduction to RPGs through D&amp;amp;D and it&amp;rsquo;s possible shortcomings as a game for new players, and then a game I found particularly suited to the task, Teenagers From Outer Space.
So why set out to create a set of rules specifically for the purpose of introducing players to the hobby? Well, for one I have pragmatic reasons. I&amp;rsquo;m living and working in a place where I don&amp;rsquo;t know any other roleplayers, and so I don&amp;rsquo;t have the opportunity to indulge in my hobby of choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeons and Teenagers from Outer Space</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/</guid>
      <description>I have a few ideas on what elements a good &amp;lsquo;starter&amp;rsquo; RPG needs, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through a number of games in order to find more ideas to add to that list. But I&amp;rsquo;ll start with some of my actual play experience with starting new players on RPGs.
To start with the start, my own (and I suspect many others&amp;rsquo;) first RPG was the venerable Dungeons and Dragons. I myself started out with Advanced Dungeons and Dragons Second Edition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starter RPG Project</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-01-31-starter-rpg-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2010 01:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2010-01-31-starter-rpg-project/</guid>
      <description>Well, the first project I&amp;rsquo;m going to share progress on is my attempt to create a roleplaying game custom built to introduce new players, with a strong emphasis on quick character creation, one-off or pick up game playability, and ease of learning the rules.
Here, I&amp;rsquo;m going to layout some of my general philosophy behind what I&amp;rsquo;m doing, and in later posts I&amp;rsquo;ll get into more specifics and make references to games that have influenced me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>