<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fellhold Campaign on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/fellhold-campaign/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fellhold Campaign on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2013 16:12:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/fellhold-campaign/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 32 and 33 Recap and Quick and Dirty Mass Combat Rules</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-11-fellhold-session-32-and-33-recap-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2013 16:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-11-fellhold-session-32-and-33-recap-and/</guid>
      <description>Session 32 started out with a lot of technical issues for everyone participating. I suspect it had to do with the changes Google had just made to the hangouts/video chat format. Speaking of which, I miss my posts about hangouts displaying the name of the video chat, because that was the primary way I reminded myself what session number we were on for the blog. Oh well, being able to count should be good enough for the most part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 31 Recap (and rules for clerics of Hrokr)</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 15:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-22-fellhold-session-31-recap-and-rules-for/</guid>
      <description>This will be a fairly bare bones recap, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been busier than anticipated this week.
Yllgrad managed to escape the temple, and he even did so without murdering the initiates that he held hostage. Of course, shortly after leaving, they told the high priest what had happened, and the priesthood of Gurgu decided to pursue the crazed dwarf. When the characters who had undergone the initiation into the belief of Gurgu reached the shrine again, they found the priests and initiates looking agitated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runic Magic in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 17:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>*Nota Bene: Pretty much this entire post is rules, but I&amp;rsquo;ve maintained the convention of bold italic type so that it will stand out if you&amp;rsquo;re scrolling up or down the page only looking for the useful stuff. * 
I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to come add magic runes to the Fellhold campaign for a while now, to get that delicious Viking flavor. I contemplated a cool combinatory system with very modular runes, kinda inspired by sygalldry in Patrick Rothfuss&amp;rsquo;s Kingkiller Chronicle books, but I decided that a) that would be a whole lot of work, and b) it would clash with the overall Vancian magical flavor of D&amp;amp;D the campaign has mostly relied on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 30 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 21:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-15-fellhold-session-30-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Harryhausen Tribute</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-09-ray-harryhausen-tribute/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 22:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-09-ray-harryhausen-tribute/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 29 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 20:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-08-fellhold-session-29-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night’s session saw us with about half the usual group due to a confluence of work and finals for three of the players. So, that left us with Caleb, Earn, and Yllgrad in the big city of Mickleheim. Their players were pretty pumped about getting stuff sold and getting to the Volcano, but a) I wanted to flesh out Mickleheim some, b) I wanted to give some of the Vornheim city kit rules and others that I’ve compiled a test drive, and c) I needed some more time to properly prep the volcano adventure, so we ended up zooming in on their errands in the city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 28 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 19:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-01-fellhold-session-28-recap/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Problem</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 16:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-25-a-problem/</guid>
      <description>So, in my ongoing Fellhold campaign, we’ve been using Akratic Wizardry’s rather good “weapon damage by class” rule as a compromise between “all weapons do d6” and “all weapons have their own unique damage”. I think if we weren’t already 6 months into using these rules, I’d probably tweak some of the damage a little bit, and maybe recategorize a few weapons (having short bows, long bows, and crossbows all do “medium weapon” damage, and treating hired swords as level 1 fighting men means that players have access to cheap and plentiful d8 damage – I gotta remember to play up the hirelings as people more).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventurer as a Meta-Class</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 21:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-24-adventurer-as-meta-class/</guid>
      <description>So, I’m reading through the excellent analysis of skills in D&amp;amp;D over at Hack &amp;amp; Slash. It touches on what the functions of a resolution mechanic are at all, and especially digs into what 3.x/Pathfinder style skills bring to D&amp;amp;D (and don’t). Considering some of my recent forays away from a pure lack of skill systems at all (using the “Good at” and “Bad at” cues, considering the use of roll under stat checks more often, et cetera), this is striking me as very useful analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part I: Introduction</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 21:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</guid>
      <description>So, for some blog fodder, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided I&amp;rsquo;m going to take on the rather ambitious project of going through every version of D&amp;amp;D and comment on the rules. To keep myself sane, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking to core books only. I&amp;rsquo;m up in the air on OD&amp;amp;D if it will include the supplements or only the the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s. The idea is to hit up White Box, Holmes, Moldvay, Mentzer, Rules Cyclopedia, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, AD&amp;amp;D 2E, D&amp;amp;D 3/3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Interlude on Rule Systems</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 16:39:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-a-brief-interlude-on-rule-systems/</guid>
      <description>Not exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swords &amp; Wizardry Appreciation Day!</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 10:48:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-swords-wizardry-appreciation-day/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the first official Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Appreciation day! Considering Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox is the ruleset we&amp;rsquo;re using for the Fellhold campaign, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d like to jump in on this. I&amp;rsquo;ve expounded earlier why we went with Whitebox, but basically I found the simplicity attractive as a foundation to add house rules to, rather than trying to cut out pieces of other versions. As play has gone on, it has both taught me to value and enjoy the lack of some rules but also it has pointed out exactly how other rules came to be by experiencing the desire to have them in game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humanoids of Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 01:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-17-humanoids-of-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Sessions 13 &amp; 14 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 07:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-12-12-fellhold-sessions-13-14-recap/</guid>
      <description>After fleeing from the seemingly endless hordes of large and aggressive trollkin, our adventurers spiked a door behind them and listened with baited breath. Not hearing any sounds of further pursuit, they decided against fleeing blindly, and continued to explore and map carefully. After discovering a secret door and defeating a hideous ooze that dissolved a few weapons, they secured a small clutch of gems, spiked another two doors behind them and decided to rest inside the dungeon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 12 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 17:40:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-27-fellhold-session-12-recap/</guid>
      <description>We left off with our adventurers deep within the Ashfell, and as we joined them this week, they continued to explore . They returned to the relief mural depiction of the founding of Fellhold and followed the carvings around a large hall, reading a story of dwarves comes to Ashfell, delving into the mountain, and ending with a scene of trade, craft, and fellowship between dwarves and men. Having satisfied themselves that this mural did not contain any further clues about how to proceed, they set off to continue down a wide passageway leading from the imposing statue of a sorceror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 11 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 22:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-fellhold-session-11-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our brave adventurers consolidated after cutting down wave after wave of goblin fighters, and decided that the best course of action was to camp outside of the goblin lair they had extensively mapped out. Spending the night in quiet, they proceeded to thoroughly map out every nook and cranny of the goblin delving, and then turned their eyes to the previously explored excavated stairs deeper into the mountain. Following these stairs down, they found a brief encounter with vicious giant rats, a long since abandoned market place, many empty store rooms, and a painful but ultimately unremarkable needle trap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Fellhold Rules Post</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 15:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-19-first-fellhold-rules-post/</guid>
      <description>Howdy folks. The bulk of this post will be the first actual rules I have written for Fellhold coming out of my reading &amp;ldquo;An Echo, Resounding&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Dungeon World&amp;rdquo;. I was initially afraid I would simply be using pieces from each with no original material whatsoever, but in the process of figuring out what I really wanted to do, I ended up coming up with something more different than I expected, though the influences are obvious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules, Part 4</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 22:05:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</guid>
      <description>So, for this post I&amp;rsquo;m taking a bit of a departure from the campaign and domain play rules that I&amp;rsquo;ve been kitbashing from Dungeon World and An Echo, Resounding. This is mostly because it&amp;rsquo;s been awhile, and I&amp;rsquo;m having to reconstruct all the stuff I had figured out from what are now opaque notes, and instead of figuring all that out tonight, I went instead for a simpler problem and decided to tackle some planning/layout issues, and then to address equipment tags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 10 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 22:57:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-12-fellhold-session-10-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid adventurers, after having destroyed a wolf pack, venture through a secret door into hewn underground passages. Joined this time by Yllgrad and Earn and their cohorts (though still not by Blum) the strengthened party takes a few moments to regroup and take advantage of magical healing before venturing into the underground passages. Finding no sign of the goblins they heard exclaim earlier, they push into to the passages and find a room full of rubble with stairs leading steeply downward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 9 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 10:06:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-11-06-fellhold-session-9-recap/</guid>
      <description>Due to various obligations in Silverdelf, Yllgrad, Blum, and Earn remained behind, but along with their hirelings and henchmen, Bryni, Caleb, and Varian set off to explore the heretofore unknown eastern path up the spur to Fellhold. They found that the path petered out in a heavily wooded and gently sloping portion of mountain, with crags and boulders suggesting caves. On further exploration, they found a large cave opening, and an initial scan of the cave revealed a heavy bed of pine needles as well as the grisly remains of creatures large and small, accompanied by a horrible smell.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 8 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 08:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-30-fellhold-session-8-recap/</guid>
      <description>After last week&amp;rsquo;s harrowing encounter with arm-hungry statues and pit traps, our daring band of adventurers decided it was time to attend to some matters outside of Fellhold&amp;rsquo;s dark halls. Acca, the hireling who lost his arm, survived his grievous injury, and his family was so grateful for the pension his employer offered him that his son Weorc took service in his place. The party set out on a quiet trip to Mickleheim where they once again strengthened their ties to Clan Dagaeca through the steward Cnud, selling them the splendid necklace of fire opals lifted from Earn the bandit chief and discovering that an exotic beast brought in alive for the midwinter festival would make a fine offering to Hrokr, fine enough that a bounty might be offered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 7 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 10:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-23-fellhold-session-7-recap/</guid>
      <description>Our intrepid band of adventurers finished up their business in Mickleheim, recruiting even more hirelings for renewed expeditions. They returned to Silverdelf without incident and discovered that the captured bandits had been sent off to whatever rough justice awaited them in Mickleheim along with the rescued shipment of whiskey. They also caught wind of an armed group buying supplies and setting off in the direction of Fellhold, but for what purpose?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 6 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 08:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-16-fellhold-session-6-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night, our intrepid band set out on the road to Mickleheim. The first two days of the three day journey passed quietly, but on the third day just after sun up they were set upon by a pack of vicious wolves! Though the only serious injury was to one of Earn&amp;rsquo;s retainers, who was viciously mauled, Earn leapt to his aid and stemmed the bleeding. After the players dispatched one of the wolves, the rest turned tail and ran, losing three more to parting blows and crossbow quarrels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, Part 3</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 10:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Though the title of this post shortchanges the role An Echo, Resounding is playing in my development of the referee rules in my campaign, I figured it was best to stay consistent.
As an example of the role AER is playing, though I&amp;rsquo;m working my way up to the domain rules, rather than down, I am broadly using the categories and concepts from AER&amp;rsquo;s domain play, so that most of the framework for reconciling Dungeon World style GMing tools with the AER domain play should already be there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Wilderness (Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, part 2)</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</guid>
      <description>As the party is about to venture forth to Mickleheim, I&amp;rsquo;ve started giving some thought to wilderness/sandbox adventure, which I&amp;rsquo;ve intended from the start to be a facet of the Fellhold campaign. I cheated a little bit up front by asking my players to do me the courtesy of agreeing that their characters had come together with the intent to explore Fellhold, at least initially, and we&amp;rsquo;d go from there. This let me devote my initial focus to having mapped and stocked dungeon locations (as it turns out, far more than I&amp;rsquo;ve needed so far - before play, I overestimated the speed with which the party would explore).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Challenges in Judgement</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-some-challenges-in-judgement/</guid>
      <description>So, I wanted to separate these thoughts from the recap post, as I intend to keep those almost entirely descriptive of the fiction that works out in the game, rather than the rules and inter-player interactions, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see what works!
After accepting a player&amp;rsquo;s more reasonable interpretation of how Sleep affected a group with mixed hit dice, I was faced with the situation where the party got the drop on a lone, as yet unarmed, surprised 3rd level fighting man with a boat load of hit points (here&amp;rsquo;s me realizing some of the dangers of incorporating unmodified AD&amp;amp;D module encounters into my OD&amp;amp;D game).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 5 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 06:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-10-09-fellhold-session-5-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night proved to be one of the most successful outings of our brave adventurers yet. Once again venturing under the mountain and into Fellhold, the judicious question of &amp;ldquo;just how many people does the spell Sleep affect?&amp;rdquo; proved to be the defining moment of the session. Finding the remaining bandits at their midday meal, the magic user Blum cast Sleep on the unsuspecting bandits, and immediately placed all but their leader into a magical slumber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bit of Fellhold Flavor</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-28-a-bit-of-fellhold-flavor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 13:26:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-28-a-bit-of-fellhold-flavor/</guid>
      <description>So, I was inspired by Mr. Maliszewski&amp;rsquo;s post over at Grognardia about homebrew campaign settings to talk a little bit about what&amp;rsquo;s been established regarding Fellhold so far. There isn&amp;rsquo;t a whole lot, because I&amp;rsquo;m trying really hard not to indulge my world building bug and detail out a hugely elaborate setting before things occur in play. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to fix a firm aesthetic in my mind, so that as questions/situations come up in play, I can incorporate recent events and player actions, but still maintain an editorial voice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to Swords &amp; Wizardry WhiteBox Part 2</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 18:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-26-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to_26/</guid>
      <description>So, the title of this post is more for the sake of continuity than for accuracy. You see, as my referee rule hacking has continued, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using not just Dungeon World, but also An Echo, Resounding and to a lesser extent the Red Tide Campaign Sourcebook. The sandbox material in Red Tide is, as mentioned before, quite excellent, but a good deal of it is superseded by what is included in *An Echo, Resounding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 3 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 21:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-24-fellhold-session-3-recap/</guid>
      <description>After leaving last session with our explorers holding a bandit sergeant hostage, we rejoined the action this evening. A brief parley established that the bandit leader, Gren, didn&amp;rsquo;t value the contributions of his sergeant Dag, and some quick bargaining brought Dag over to the side of the adventurers. They managed to flee, trigger the pressure plate trap to drop a net, and then picked up the net and threw it onto the advancing bandits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;You Have to Put in the Work&#34;</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-20-have-to-put-in-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 11:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-20-have-to-put-in-work/</guid>
      <description>Let me tell you a little story about the path that led to my starting up an Old School D&amp;amp;D Campaign. While having far too much time on my hands courtesy of the United States Government, I stumbled onto the indie RPG scene online. Amongst other things, I discovered Vincent Baker&amp;rsquo;s games and blog, and started reading and being inspired by both. One post that didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly register at the time, but has since stuck with me was I &amp;lt;3 the OSR, and especially comment number 8.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 2 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 22:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-18-fellhold-session-2-recap/</guid>
      <description>In tonight&amp;rsquo;s expedition, our daring adventurers took their first steps into the dank underground of Fellhold. After some accurate mapping and cleverly avoiding a pressure plate trap, the party got the drop on a group of bandits going through their loot. They failed to take full advantage of the surprise and entered into a grinding battle with them. With only the bandits&amp;rsquo; leader and one bandit still standing, a group of bandit reinforcements was spotted about to join the fray, and in a last ditch desperate effort, our adventurers managed to subdue the leader and hope to use his life to parley a way out of this dangerous situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules to White Box, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 16:46:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-17-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-to/</guid>
      <description>So, as mentioned in my previous post, I think that the GMing rules from Dungeon World/AW are those which can most profitably be ported into an Old School D&amp;amp;D game (Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox in my case). With that in mind, I&amp;rsquo;m going to start by going through the Dungeon World Agendas, Principles and Moves, as well as the Always Say guidelines, and discuss/tweak to the &amp;lsquo;Old School&amp;rsquo; refing style I am using in my game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeon World, An Echo, Resounding, Refereeing and You</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-16-dungeon-world-echo-resounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2012 18:36:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-16-dungeon-world-echo-resounding/</guid>
      <description>(ed: in my original post, I said that Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry WhiteBox was shared under a Creative Commons License, but this was incorrect. It is, in fact, shared under the Open Game License. I&amp;rsquo;ve edited the text below to reflect this)
So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through the ever-excellent Kevin Crawford&amp;rsquo;s An Echo, Resounding, as well as Sage LaTorra&amp;rsquo;s totally sweet Dungeon World, switching back and forth between the two of them, and I think there&amp;rsquo;s something really powerful to be made between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Point of Similarity</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 22:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</guid>
      <description>So, all of my recent posts have been about the Old School Renaissance, and my old school D&amp;amp;D game. If you look to the posts that started this blog, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that I was quite enamored of indie RPGs and forge theory and the like. At first glance this seems like something of a flip-flop, but it was actually from the indie &amp;ldquo;scene&amp;rdquo; that I discovered the OSR and became fired up to run a D&amp;amp;D game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Random</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-11-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 13:16:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-11-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love/</guid>
      <description>One of the many things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to embrace in preparing my Old School campaign has been what Mr. Maliszewski over at Grognardia refers to as &amp;ldquo;The Oracular Power of Dice&amp;rdquo;. I also got the name for my blog from a post by Ben Robbins at Ars Ludi on a similar topic. Basically, the idea is to accept what the dice give you and then craft your plans around them, rather than to have a master plan and only accept results that fit with that plan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Note about Rules</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-11-a-note-about-rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 11:04:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-11-a-note-about-rules/</guid>
      <description>So, one of the things I took to heart while reading through James Malieszewski&amp;rsquo;s Dwimmermount campaign over at Grognardia was the notion that it is easier to start with sparse rules and then add more subsystems than it is to cut back an existing bigger system. I originally intended to go real-hard core old school and use the original three Little Brown Books as the rules, and add from there. Alas, during character generation I found myself not comfortable enough with them to quickly and efficiently use them as in-game reference material.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 1</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 22:06:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2012-09-10-fellhold-session-1/</guid>
      <description>So, our brave expedition&amp;rsquo;s first venture up the mountain led to a ruined outpost guarding a gate into the underworld. Blum and Varian were unable to make it on this first expedition, but Yllgrad, Caleb, Bryni, and Earn set their sights on adventure and followed the path out of Silverdelf up the spur of the mountain. While exploring the ruined outpost, Earn and Caleb ventured into a ruined tower and were set upon by a giant spider!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>