<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>New Rules on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/new-rules/</link>
    <description>Recent content in New Rules on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/new-rules/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Sages Say&#34; Monster Generator</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</guid>
      <description>I made a thing that makes monsters. I&amp;rsquo;m terribly pleased with it right now, but let me know what you think. If the embed below is giving you weird formatting (on a phone or tablet, say), or if you just want to mess with it, check out the sheet here.
I used Brendan&amp;rsquo;s excellent methodology to build it in Google Sheets. Every time you refresh this page, you should get a new result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OSR Classes: The Mastermind and the Rook</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 08:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</guid>
      <description>After my last post on Flexible Reaction Rolls, I found myself thinking about how to build Character Classes that fit with the schemey, urban style of play I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for with Fellhold. The trouble for me until now was that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t think of ways to get that stuff without impinging on the Old School playstyle I enjoy. What cracked it for me was turning the Reaction Roll into a mechanic with more knobs to play with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Reaction Rolls</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 11:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</guid>
      <description>Reaction rolls are one of my very favorite set of rules. They&amp;rsquo;re quick, easy, and help me to come up with more interesting stuff than I might on my own. I use them as a general purpose social sub-system, though not nearly to the same extent as Courtney Campbell in his excellent On the Non-Player Character. Instead, I use them more as an oracle when I&amp;rsquo;m unsure of how the NPCs would react.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Spells</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-12-13-some-spells/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2013 13:34:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-12-13-some-spells/</guid>
      <description>So, I&amp;rsquo;m going through the spell lists to try to make them more appropriate for the shape that wizards are starting to take in Fellhold. My good friend (Yllgrad&amp;rsquo;s player, if you follow the play report posts at all) sent me some spell ideas (Troll Form, Create Familiar, Orb of Many Colors, Volsungr&amp;rsquo;s Anvil, and Summon Spiders are all based on his stuff), and that got me started working on the spell descriptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 36 Recap</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 19:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-07-09-fellhold-session-36-recap/</guid>
      <description>Last night we wrapped up “Season 1” of Fellhold. Not Season 1 in some pre-planned plot arc sense, heavens no! Rather, starting next week we’re switching to the new game I mentioned last time, and it just so happened that a lot of shit hit the fan this session and we ended at a good cliffhanger. Serendipitous! 
So, shit and fan hitting: we returned to Gurgu smashing pillars in his summoning area, most of the party hiding, and Bryni leading Bjergmund and a few priests and initiates down to see the “miracle” of Gurgu summoned, with the hopes of gently guiding them to the worship of Volsungr or some other proper god (but they figured Volsungr would be the best fit).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Session 32 and 33 Recap and Quick and Dirty Mass Combat Rules</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-11-fellhold-session-32-and-33-recap-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2013 16:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-11-fellhold-session-32-and-33-recap-and/</guid>
      <description>Session 32 started out with a lot of technical issues for everyone participating. I suspect it had to do with the changes Google had just made to the hangouts/video chat format. Speaking of which, I miss my posts about hangouts displaying the name of the video chat, because that was the primary way I reminded myself what session number we were on for the blog. Oh well, being able to count should be good enough for the most part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runic Magic in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 17:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-runic-magic-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>*Nota Bene: Pretty much this entire post is rules, but I&amp;rsquo;ve maintained the convention of bold italic type so that it will stand out if you&amp;rsquo;re scrolling up or down the page only looking for the useful stuff. * 
I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to come add magic runes to the Fellhold campaign for a while now, to get that delicious Viking flavor. I contemplated a cool combinatory system with very modular runes, kinda inspired by sygalldry in Patrick Rothfuss&amp;rsquo;s Kingkiller Chronicle books, but I decided that a) that would be a whole lot of work, and b) it would clash with the overall Vancian magical flavor of D&amp;amp;D the campaign has mostly relied on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make Sweet D100 Tables for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-how-to-make-sweet-d100-tables-for-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 03:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-05-16-how-to-make-sweet-d100-tables-for-fun/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>