<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coaching on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/categories/coaching/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coaching on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/coaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Level Up Your Process to Learn Better, Faster (Learning Overview Part 1)</title>
      <link>/coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2019-03-15-level-up-your-process-to-learn-better-faster-learning-overview-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few months, I’ve put some time into improving how I learn, and I’d like to share some of that in a series on “metalearning” (learning how to learn). While there are many things I want to cover, from mental models to specific tools, the underlying logic will be to look at learning as a process. Taking a process focus has several benefits - let’s walk through some of the biggest to kick off this series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Culture is a Story that Isn&#39;t Over Yet</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-03-27-culture-is-a-story-that-isnt-over-yet/</guid>
      <description>Stories are essential for building and maintaining strong cultures. They help everyone learn the group&amp;rsquo;s way of doing things, create belonging, and make meaning out of what they do every day. In fact, you can define culture as an ongoing story that a group tells together.
Cultures share a way of thinking about things. All of us shape our thinking with mental models, which help us to see blind spots, work better, and understand what we learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Connections with Oral Storytelling</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>Humans have been telling stories face to face since forever, and doing it well gives you a leg up personally and professionally. Compelling business presentations are critical for success, and natural storytelling techniques can take them to the next level. Even outside of business, stories help you build relationships and entertain your friends. You can improve your oral storytelling today by paying attention to structure, shortening your stories, using your voice well, and supporting what you say with your face and hands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jeff Russell Storytime</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-22-jeff-russell-storytime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-22-jeff-russell-storytime/</guid>
      <description>One of my favorite memories from the Army is “Jeff Russell Storytime”. It seemed like a silly way to pass the time, but ended up teaching me a lot that I still use today. Out of way too much free time, it evolved into a regular occurrence that we all enjoyed a lot. I got to share some of my favorite gems from history and mythology, and over time I learned a thing or two about storytelling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Approach for a Virtuous Life</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-15-my-approach-for-a-virtuous-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-15-my-approach-for-a-virtuous-life/</guid>
      <description>Today I run the risk of sounding a bit preachy. Let me state for the first (but not last) time that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to tell you how to live your life or what “being good” means. We all want to be good people, but many of us have different perspectives on what that means. Even worse, almost every terrible ethical lapse you read about in the news began years ago with a gradual slip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Expanded Definition of Reading</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-12-18-an-expanded-definition-of-reading/</guid>
      <description>We tend to think of “reading” as the time we have a book in front of our face, but when you stop to ask why you are reading, a number of other activities suggest themselves as part of the bigger enterprise. If you are reading to learn, simply passing your eyes over the words will only get you a fraction of what’s there. I’ve been spending a lot of time thinking about how to make reading as effective as possible, and below I share my current thinking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Through Storytelling</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>Stories are not only a great way to communicate information, they are also a powerful tool for learning it. People remember information better when it comes in the form of a story. In fact, we are so good at putting stuff together into stories that we often get things wrong with it. Fortunately, you can take advantage of our natural tendencies to learn better. Besides making your process more fun, there are three main ways stories can help you learn: forcing careful thought, assisting recall, and providing deliberate practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 5 - Resources for Digging Deeper</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-11-27-storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-11-27-storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper/</guid>
      <description>I’ve done my best to share a fantastic beginner’s guide to storytelling with this series, but there is a lot of depth to all of the topics that I’ve touched on. Below, I provide my recommendations on resources for digging into Story Structure, Effective Practice, Public Speaking, Oral Storytelling, Writing, and Visual Storytelling. In each section, I’ve provided a handful of my favorite “how to” resources, whether books, blogs, videos, or courses along with a section of illustrative examples applying the lessons you’ll learn from the how to books.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 4 - Delivery</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/</guid>
      <description>Now that your story has a great structure and you know what good practice looks like, let’s focus on what you’re actually trying to improve with your practice: the delivery of your story. I’ve gotta tell you, this was the hardest post for me to write in this series because delivery is so dependent on your medium - public speakers care very much about maintaining their posture and projecting their voice, comic book artists not so much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 3 - Practice, Practice, Practice</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/</guid>
      <description>However you choose to share your stories with the world, you’ll have to practice to make them look effortless and beautiful. You’ll need to tell more stories and tell each of your stories more times to improve your craft and your tales. To make those repetitions useful, you’ll need feedback as fast as possible, and the best feedback comes from a caring but objective partner. After I dig into each of these topics, I’ll give you a specific playbook for preparing for a speech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 1 - Introduction</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Anyone who wants to communicate with other humans needs storytelling, but most folks have no idea what it really is, much less how to improve it. Some people even have the misguided notion that storytelling is worthless fluff. With this series, we’ll clear up that misconception and then cover the best techniques for improving your storytelling.
As we did with creativity, let’s begin by defining “storytelling”. You’ve probably heard it used in a number of contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make Decisions Like a Boss</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/</guid>
      <description>Making good decisions is an essential life skill, and you can improve it with practice. We have some fundamental handicaps to overcome, but if we make it a habit to practice decisiveness in low-impact environments and avoid worthless decisions when it matters, we can dramatically improve our ability to make high quality decisions. By committing to better decision making, recognizing when to make decisions and when not to, improving our ability to do one thing at a time, and clarifying what we are deciding, we can improve not only the quantity but the quality of the decisions we make.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habits for a Happier Life</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I found myself in a funk for a month or two. I don’t want to go all James Altucher and turn this blog into a parade of failures and fears, but I think it’s important to take a look behind the curtain of the generally positive tone I keep here. So, as you read the tips below, keep in mind that they’re coming from someone who needs them.
As you know, I like to have clear definitions before talking about fuzzy topics, so let’s define happiness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Depth Before Breadth - Why You Should Learn One Thing at a Time</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</guid>
      <description>Many of us have a hard time limiting our effort to one field at a time - there’s so much interesting stuff out there and it’s more available than ever. All of this stuff can lure us into paying hidden costs when we try to learn everything all at once - costs that prevent us from getting the benefits breadth is supposed to bring. On the other hand, if you pursue depth, while you will only focus on one field at a time before moving onto the next, you will get much more out of each field, with a more robust breadth down the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Mentors</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-22-virtual-mentors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-22-virtual-mentors/</guid>
      <description>High performers frequently emphasize the importance of quality mentors, and we’ve all experienced the value of learning from people who have been there and done that. Finding a great mentor can be a big challenge, though. Luckily, you can benefit from the wisdom of impressive people with “virtual mentors”.
Let’s talk about why to bother with this technique: finding and building a relationship with a top notch mentor is a big challenge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources for Digging Deeper - Creativity Part 6</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-15-resources-for-digging-deeper-creativity-part-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-15-resources-for-digging-deeper-creativity-part-6/</guid>
      <description>This is our last installment in the current series on creativity, but don’t expect it to be the last you hear about creativity in this space. Now that we’ve gone through definitions, building blocks, divergence and convergence exercises, frameworks, and inputs, I want to provide a list of resources you can use to continue to explore on your own.
Books As will surprise no one, I read a lot of books, so today’s list is heavy on books.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practicing Divergent &amp; Convergent Thinking - Creativity Part 3</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-08-25-practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Okay, so I had planned on covering all of the exercises in one post, but when I broke them out, I realized I would be delivering a gigantic, hard to digest mess. So I broke it up. Our next few posts will cover all of the exercises associated with the building blocks we covered last time, starting with Divergent and Convergent thinking today. It’s a great place to start, because if you develop your ability to separate these two ways of thinking, everything else will flow naturally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Building Blocks of Creativity - Creativity Part 2</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-08-18-the-building-blocks-of-creativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-08-18-the-building-blocks-of-creativity/</guid>
      <description>Last time we came up with a definition of creativity, and today we’re going to talk about some of its core building blocks, from deferring judgment to the inputs you take in. These fundamental concepts will give you the raw materials you need to understand and undertake specific exercises to be more creative yourself - some of which we’ll detail in our next installment of the series.
The first and most important concept you need for better creativity comes from Edward De Bono’s Lateral Thinking: sometimes to get to a good idea, you have to go through a bad idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creativity Part 1 - Defining Creativity</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-08-11-creativity-part-1-defining-creativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-08-11-creativity-part-1-defining-creativity/</guid>
      <description>When I sat down to write a post about innovation, I quickly realized we had an unwieldy topic on our hands. So, instead of a single post on innovation and the future, I’ve decided to kick off a short series on creativity. To begin with, I’ll provide my favorite definition of creativity and step through each piece of it and what it implies for applications down the road.
Just about anyone you talk to wants to be “more creative,” but what does that really mean?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gleeful Iconoclasm of Zhuangzi</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-07-27-the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-07-27-the-gleeful-iconoclasm-of-zhuangzi/</guid>
      <description>A Note on Spelling Conventions - Skip if you are not a language nerd:
Since westerners started studying Chinese, they have tried to get around the inadequacy of the Latin alphabet to render it. For years the most popular way was the “Wade-Giles System,” which uses various letter combinations as kludges to represent tones. It is a clever way to operate within the constraints of existing letters, but if you don’t know the code, you’re gonna say everything wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Usefulness of Fiction</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-07-21-on-the-usefulness-of-fiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-07-21-on-the-usefulness-of-fiction/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve talked before about the non-fiction books that have shaped my worldview, but today I want to talk to you about fiction. A lot of my high performing, hard charging friends find it challenging to “waste” time with fiction, but you’re doing yourself a huge disservice if you agree with them. You need fiction in your life. Since I’m wrapping up a vacation where I’ve been able to read some great books, I want to share a few reasons why I think so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Operating Manuals for Life</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-07-14-my-operating-manuals-for-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-07-14-my-operating-manuals-for-life/</guid>
      <description>If you accept that you have your own User Interface, you’re going to need some instructions on how to set it up and maintain it. As you know, my go to source for just about everything is books, and I have found those on the list below especially useful for hacking together my own mental operating system. They currently sit right on my desk where I can see them every day and think about what they mean to me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Dunning-Kruger Effect for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</guid>
      <description>We all labor under a whole pile of cognitive biases day to day, but let’s talk about an especially pernicious one: the Dunning-Kruger effect. This extremely subtle bias afflicts us all, affecting our very ability to assess whether we are suffering from a bias or not. So it’s super important to be aware of it and take appropriate counter measures.
David Dunning and Justin Kruger have experimentally documented the long recognized tendency of people to suffer from “illusory superiority,” and so have had the effect named after them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis is Only the Beginning - An Introduction to Systems Thinking</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</guid>
      <description>Let’s talk about systems. We’ve touched on them in several posts, and they provide an incredibly valuable tool for understanding a complex world. When we stop thinking about things as independent objects and start thinking about them as elements in a greater whole of interdependent parts, we recognize that they are systems. Today we’re going to talk about a method of inquiry custom designed for such highly complex entities: Systems Thinking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fragility, Robustness, and Antifragility</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-16-fragility-robustness-and-antifragility/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-16-fragility-robustness-and-antifragility/</guid>
      <description>Last time, we discussed a new way of looking at the concept of “risk” and our inability to scientifically define it. Today, we go a little deeper and break systems into three categories based on their exposure to volatility: fragile, robust, and antifragile.
First we need to realize that volatility, time, and risk are really the same thing. This sounds bizarre, right? But let’s return to our least-worst definition of risk: “exposure to negative outcomes brought about by volatility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preventative Maintenance - Self Care Part 2</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-05-26-preventative-maintenance-self-care-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-05-26-preventative-maintenance-self-care-part-2/</guid>
      <description>We talked last time about a theoretical model of stress, now I want to talk about a few of the best methods for preparing yourself to handle and dissipate stress over the long term. We’ll cover how exercise, diet, sleep, and mental tools can all insulate you against stress and deal with it once it’s there.
As we talked about before, and as you’re no doubt sick of hearing, exercise is the single best thing you can do to improve your ability to deal with stress across the board.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bathtub Model of Stress - Self Care Part 1</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-05-19-the-bathtub-model-of-stress-self-care-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-05-19-the-bathtub-model-of-stress-self-care-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Stress is something that we all probably experience more often that we’d like and near constantly hear about in books, online, and on popular TV shows, but most of us have a pretty nebulous understanding of just what stress really is. So, today I want to introduce a more specific definition of stress than we usually use, talk about a useful model for thinking about it, break that model down its component parts, and then take a look at how that breakdown can help us more effectively manage and use stress in our lives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Super” Combinations from Tools of Titans</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-05-12-super-combinations-from-tools-of-titans/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-05-12-super-combinations-from-tools-of-titans/</guid>
      <description>I’ve talked a lot about Tools of Titans here, but today I want to share my favorite trick for using the book. While every “tool&amp;rdquo; in the book is useful individually, I believe some of the material is even more useful when synthesized into a coherent whole. Below, I’m going to share the one that’s been on my mind the most recently, with a concrete example of the super tool in action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lazy Man&#39;s Guide to Exercise</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-27-the-lazy-mans-guide-to-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-27-the-lazy-mans-guide-to-exercise/</guid>
      <description>As I’m sure you’re sick of hearing, exercise is the single best thing you can do to make every other area of your life better and easier. We all know this, but damn if getting started doesn&amp;rsquo;t suck. Especially if you didn’t take to exercise early in life, it’s hard to motivate yourself to endure such unpleasantness. You end up with the same vague feeling of guilt you feel when you realize you haven’t flossed since right after your last dentist appointment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Float On - My First Experience with a Flotation Tank</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-21-float-on-my-first-experience-with-a-flotation-tank/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-21-float-on-my-first-experience-with-a-flotation-tank/</guid>
      <description>Today I want to talk about something a little different - my first experience with a float tank session. Also known as flotation tanks or sensory deprivation tanks, I first heard about them via Tim Ferriss, and he discusses them in his latest book Tools of Titans, but apparently Joe Rogan is also a huge proponent of them, and has some great stuff to say about using them in a regular practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get Outta My Head and Into My. . .</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-14-get-outta-my-head-and-into-my-/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-14-get-outta-my-head-and-into-my-/</guid>
      <description>To paraphrase Billy Ocean a bit, today’s post is all about getting material out of your head and into your task capture system (not as catchy, I know). Writing down what you need to do is the most fundamental building block in a comprehensive productivity framework. It’s a seemingly simple tool, but it really is the 80/20 tool in the framework. Simply keeping everything you need to do in one place that you check regularly will do more for your productivity and peace of mind than any other single behavior change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jeff&#39;s Recommended Self-Improvement Reading</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-11-jeffs-recommended-self-improvement-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-11-jeffs-recommended-self-improvement-reading/</guid>
      <description>Below is an annotated list of some of my favorite books related to self-improvement and the general pursuit of excellence. It’s a pretty long list, so feel free to skip around to the areas that most grab your interest and come back to revisit when you’re looking for something new. It’s by no means comprehensive, and I’ve always got a whole stack of books waiting to be read, so expect updates and additions down the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning is Indispensable</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-11-planning-is-indispensable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-11-planning-is-indispensable/</guid>
      <description>“In preparing for battle, I have always found that plans are useless but planning is indispensable”
 — Dwight D. Eisenhower
Planning is something that I resisted for a long time. I thought it would be stifling and a pain in the ass, with no real benefit. Oh how wrong I was. Now that I have made planning a major part of how I work, I find myself far less stressed, I rarely feel overwhelmed, and I have made significant progress on personal and professional goals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing Your Own Productivity Framework</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-10-designing-your-own-productivity-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-10-designing-your-own-productivity-framework/</guid>
      <description>There is an unimaginably huge amount of material out there on productivity, self-improvement, and achievement. Books, blogs, podcasts, online courses: the works. Some of it is amazing, some of it is crap, but most of it is specific and narrowly focused - which is awesome when you are tackling a particular challenge that it addresses. The material that goes broader tends to be presented as a total, self-contained package. The trouble with the former is that you need a way to organize your ever-widening array of tools, and the problem with the latter is that the only person any productivity system works perfectly for is the one who invented it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome and Hello</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-04-10-welcome-and-hello/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-04-10-welcome-and-hello/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my blog! I use this space to share the very best self-improvement material I come across and my own thoughts and insights based on my experiences coaching highly driven top performers. I believe we’d all be better off if more people adopted the kinds of habits, practices, and ways of thought that are featured here - happier, more accomplished, and tackling bigger and harder problems.
The material on this blog will help you to get more work done, feel less stressed, and to take conscious control of where you’re headed with your career.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-8-groundwork-for-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-8-groundwork-for-strategy/</guid>
      <description>Strategy gets used so much and for so many things that it has become almost meaningless. Playing wargames as a kid kindled my fascination with strategy, joining the Army stoked that fire, and going to business school and into management consulting has worked it into a raging blaze. As much as I love strategy, I am painfully aware of its status as a cringe-inducing buzzword. So today I want to lay out my own definition of strategy, a bit of history where it came from, why it has gotten its sorry reputation, and how you might apply it to your own life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Start Guide for Your Brain’s User Interface</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</guid>
      <description>Note: This post might get your hackles up a bit. You might find it especially surprising in a space dedicated to agency and self improvement - but stick with me and you might learn something extremely useful.
We overestimate our control over what we think, how we feel, and even what we do. We assume that every moment of every day we are rationally picking and choosing what to do. It turns out this is an extremely inadequate view of how we operate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Aid for Stress - Self Care Part 3</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-2-first-aid-for-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-2-first-aid-for-stress/</guid>
      <description>We’ve discussed what stress is and how to think of it, as well as ways to improve your ability to handle it in a systematic way, but sometimes even the best prepared feel more than the usual amount of stress. Today we’re going to talk about what you can do immediately when you find yourself feeling stressed out.
The very first thing you should do is stop and breathe. Breathing is one of the few interfaces your conscious mind has with your autonomic processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling as Thinking</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-12-4-journaling-as-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-12-4-journaling-as-thinking/</guid>
      <description>Journaling doesn’t just mean recording your life for when you become super famous, you can accomplish a lot of different things by journaling. Sure, you absolutely can create a record for yourself and your family (and future biographers). You might instead want to get the neurotic and depressed thoughts out of your head and onto paper so that you can get on with business. Or perhaps you want to reinforce habits, like being grateful or generating ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximize the Value of Your Creative Inputs - Creativity Part 5</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-8-maximize-the-value-of-your-creative-inputs-creativity-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-8-maximize-the-value-of-your-creative-inputs-creativity-part-4/</guid>
      <description>In the previous posts on creativity, I’ve mentioned “inputs” pretty frequently, but I haven’t gone into much detail about them. Today, I’ll talk about what I mean by inputs, why they’re important, and share some rules for maximizing their usefulness. I’m very excited to be sharing this with you, because I think it’s an often overlooked aspect of creativity that can have huge effects on your work with very little effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Risk with Antifragile</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-06-9-rethinking-risk-with-antifragile/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-06-9-rethinking-risk-with-antifragile/</guid>
      <description>Risk fundamentally shapes some of our most critical decisions, but most of us don’t think very deeply or clearly about it. Nassim Taleb is not like most of us. he has thought long, hard, and with great rigor about risk and randomness, and he presents that thinking most usefully and straightforwardly in Antifragile. That being said, while his writing and storytelling are superb, it’s not exactly light beach reading. Below we’re going to talk about just one of the many useful concepts presented in the book, which is a fundamentally different way to think about and evaluate risk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some of the Things I Learned in 2017</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-2-some-of-the-things-i-learned-in-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-2-some-of-the-things-i-learned-in-2017/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important habits I have been building over the past couple years has been to be more deliberate in my reflection. So I wanted to close out this year with an inventory of what I’ve learned, both to solidify it and to figure out where I might spend my efforts next year. To figure out how to structure such a list, I turned to my daily practice modeled on the one suggested by James Altucher, but with a few additions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Storytelling Part 2 - Structure</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-11-3-storytelling-part-2-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-11-3-storytelling-part-2-structure/</guid>
      <description>Every good story has a structure, and if you make it explicit ahead of time, you can spot gaps and make improvements. Below we’ll go through a simple tool to make your structure clear, how to use it, the elements of the classic story, some variant story structure options depending on intent, and finally some alternatives to consider.
You can craft stories with a lot of different structures, but for all of them, you need a tool to make the structure explicit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 70/20/10 Model for Skill Development</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-05-5-the-702010-model-for-skill-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-05-5-the-702010-model-for-skill-development/</guid>
      <description>If you spend any time around corporate learning and development types, you will likely run into the “70/20/10 Rule”. Today we’re going to talk about what it is and what it isn’t, some important cautions in making use of it, why it can be a useful heuristic, and what each component of the ratio is and how it applies to learning valuable skills. If you’re not familiar, I hope you find it a new and useful tool, and if you are, I hope to shed some new light on the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bliss of a Bizarro Book Club</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-02-5-the-bliss-of-a-bizarro-book-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-02-5-the-bliss-of-a-bizarro-book-club/</guid>
      <description>While book clubs are great for getting everybody on the same page (har har), a Bizarro Book Club is a way to inject more diversity into your intellectual life. I’ve talked before about the importance of high quality inputs to your creativity, and this is my favorite new method for finding stuff that I would never have on my own. It combines the traditional social benefits of a book club with a much more exciting way of engaging with books, and it’s just as easy to do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Creativity Frameworks - Creativity Part 4</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-09-1-two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-09-1-two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4/</guid>
      <description>In our last installment in this series, we talked about divergent and convergent thinking. Keep that in mind, as it will be central to everything we discuss below. Today, we’re going to talk about frameworks you can use to structure your creative efforts - one for teams and one for individuals. You can use either framework in the other situation, but I find them better suited to different applications.
When we discussed creativity frameworks previously, I mentioned the Basadur Applied Creativity method.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned at Forefront 2017</title>
      <link>/coaching/2017-10-6-what-i-learned-at-forefront-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2017-10-6-what-i-learned-at-forefront-2017/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I attended a conference called Forefront in Chicago, and I had a great time. I met a ton of great people and learned a lot. So, I wanted to record what I learned here, both so that I could keep it fresh, and also to share some of the great material with a wider audience. I learned how great it is to connect with people that are weird the same way you are, how to be happier, how better to hold myself and my clients accountable, and the value of belonging to a supportive community when trying to accomplish anything challenging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s the Point of Your Story?</title>
      <link>/coaching/2019-03-1-whats-the-point-of-your-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2019-03-1-whats-the-point-of-your-story/</guid>
      <description>When we think of storytelling, we tend to focus on delivery, or maybe even structure, but the first thing we need to nail is why you’re telling the story in the first place. I’ve mentioned Dan Roam’s excellent book Show and Tell before, and I’ve shared a tool for using his four PUMA templates, but today I want to talk through what these four different approaches to storytelling are and what differentiates them: what are you trying to change about your audience?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>