<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 13:17:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Learning Through Storytelling</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/ -&lt;p&gt;Stories are not only a great way to communicate information, they are also a powerful tool for learning it. People &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quantifiedcommunications.com/blog/storytelling-22-times-more-memorable&#34;&gt;remember information better&lt;/a&gt; when it comes in the form of a story. In fact, we are so good at putting stuff together into stories that we often &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2016/04/narrative-fallacy/&#34;&gt;get things wrong with it&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately, you can take advantage of our natural tendencies to learn better. Besides making your process more fun, there are three main ways stories can help you learn: forcing careful thought, assisting recall, and providing deliberate practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;composition-requires-understanding&#34;&gt;Composition Requires Understanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, figuring out a story forces you to think deeply about your material and how to organize it. Sometimes this is relatively straightforward, like choosing which parts of a famous person’s life to focus on and how to sequence them. On the other hand, if you are trying to tell a story about how covalent bonds work, you don’t have the usual raw story material to work with: human characters, actions, and consequences. Applying the lens of “how do I make this a story?” forces you to think about what parts of your topic will be the characters, how you will represent the information as actions  in a satisfying sequence, and what will be the stakes and consequences. You can’t make these decisions unless you’ve engaged with the material deeply, so the simple act of composing the story does a lot of heavy lifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;structure-aids-recall&#34;&gt;Structure Aids Recall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, story structure gives you cues to remember details. If you can remember the ending, when you get stuck in the middle, you can ask yourself “wait, what has to happen to get there?” By creating a story, you build logical cause and effect relationships that are easier to follow and remember than a simple sequence. In “The Three Little Pigs”, if I can’t remember what the second brother built his house from, it’s easy to go “what’s sturdier than straw but flimsier than bricks?” and bam, sticks. That is much easier than “What is the second item in a list of potential building materials?” The really cool thing is that you can use this approach to back into memorizing a sequence. If you need to remember things in a particular order (like a list of Kings or the periodic table), you can create a story where every event follows logically and is matched to one of the things in your list. Then when you get through the story, you just so happened to have gone through the list in order, without ever stopping to think “what is item number 37?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;telling-reveals-issues&#34;&gt;Telling Reveals Issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the act of producing the story will reveal gaps in your understanding and your memory. When you get to a crucial part and go “aw, crud, what was supposed to happen here?”, you’ve just identified part of the material you don’t understand or remember very well yet. Remember &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/10/storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice&#34;&gt;effective practice&lt;/a&gt;? Telling the story creates an immediate form of feedback that can speed up your learning. This works well on your own, but it works even better with an audience. Does your story make them feel like they understand the concept you have represented? Do they have questions? Can you answer them? If you find any especially big issues, go back to composition and structure to revisit the basics of your story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tips-and-tricks&#34;&gt;Tips and Tricks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are few small things you can do to get the most out of your learning stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be vivid and concrete&lt;/strong&gt;: We remember tangible things best. So instead of “the limbic system”, Tim Urban talks about “&lt;a href=&#34;https://waitbutwhy.com/2013/10/why-procrastinators-procrastinate.html&#34;&gt;The Instant Gratification Monkey&lt;/a&gt;”. The more something can stand out in your mind, the better, so don’t be afraid to exaggerate and use visually clear stereotypes, like a cartoonist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anthropomorphize&lt;/strong&gt;: As social animals, a lot of our brain is wired to care about people. So turn as much stuff into people as possible. Want to craft a story explaining the international power politics that led to WWI? Personify each nation as a kid on a play ground and describe their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make things emotional&lt;/strong&gt;: Just like we are wired to care more about people, we have a preference for remembering emotionally vivid things. This is really just a specific tweak on being vivid - characters in your story don’t mildly dislike one another, they HATE each other. Warm regard? Nope, UNDYING FRIENDSHIP AND LOYALTY. Not only will it be more vivid, it will be simpler to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make things crude&lt;/strong&gt;: Things that are shocking, gross, or sexy are much easier to remember (for obvious reasons). So wherever possible, put these elements into your stories. Two characters get into a fight? Make it a fight in a barnyard and they end up covered in filth. Need to explain a concept that involves two things coming together? Make it sex (and vivid, and concrete).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the structure simple&lt;/strong&gt;: Don’t try to come up with some overly complicated plot. The goal is not to tell a story that will win a Nobel Laureate, it’s to help you learn something. So stick as close to some variation of “situation, challenge, complications, resolution”, preferably with a clear protagonist. These types of stories easily accommodate and encourage the other tips above, and are the most familiar and easiest stories to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously some fields take more easily to storytelling than others, but you’ll be surprised by how flexible a learning tool it can be. The next time you find yourself grappling with some difficult material, try composing a story to figure it out, structure it in a way easy to remember, and tell it to figure out where you still have work to do.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-12-11-learning-through-storytelling/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Elements of Style</title>
        <link>/books/the-elements-of-style/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-elements-of-style/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-elements-of-style/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By William Strunk, Jr. and E.B. White&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this book in my post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/27/storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper&#34;&gt;Storytelling Resources&lt;/a&gt;, but I thought it deserved its own call out. An incredibly slim book, you can read and understand it in an evening, but will likely return to it again and again. This book clearly lays out the rules of modern American usage and style, favoring concise, vigorous prose. Even if you enjoy waxing more eloquent, this provides a great starting place from which to depart. It&amp;rsquo;s also admirably organized, with a detailed table of contents and clear headings for the rules it propounds, making it ideal as a reference work (which it will be for the vast majority of its usefulness, since it will only take an hour or two to read it the first time). If you write at all for your living or for pleasure, you should have this book in easy reach at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Elements-Style-Fourth-William-Strunk/dp/020530902X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1512954090&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+elements+of+style&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-elements-of-style/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Leonardo da Vinci</title>
        <link>/books/leonardo-da-vinci/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/leonardo-da-vinci/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/leonardo-da-vinci/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Walter Isaacson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have long irrationally avoided biographies, despite encountering a few excellent ones like &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Team-Rivals-Political-Abraham-Lincoln-ebook/dp/B000N2HBSO/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1512342434&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=team+of+rivals&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team of Rivals&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided I needed to remedy that to read one about a personal hero of mine. Leonardo stands as the archetypal &amp;ldquo;Renaissance Man&amp;rdquo;, with achievements in art, architecture, science and more all under his belt. His brilliant and beautiful notebooks make any journaler feel inadequate. And yet, one of the most reassuring parts of this book is that it seems unlikely that Leonardo was as set apart intellectually as an Einstein or a Newton, nor as naturally artistically gifted as a Michaelangelo. Instead, Leonardo learned everything through a combination of insatiable curiosity and determined attention and focus. He was also able to turn his varied interests and propensity for abandoning projects into a firm set of multidisciplinary knowledge that spurred creative insight across fields. So he&amp;rsquo;s something of a role model for those of us who worry we didn&amp;rsquo;t win the genetic lottery or feel a lack of focus. This book is fantastic and humanizing while still highlighting the key takeaways from his life that we can enjoy in our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Leonardo-Vinci-Walter-Isaacson-ebook/dp/B071Y385Q1/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1512342983&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=leonardo+da+vinci+walter+isaacson&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/leonardo-da-vinci/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Graphic Storytelling and Visual Narrative</title>
        <link>/books/graphic-storytelling-and-visual-narrative/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/graphic-storytelling-and-visual-narrative/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/graphic-storytelling-and-visual-narrative/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Will Eisner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written by a giant of the sequential art field, this book covers the insights from decades of creating and teaching about the use of comics to tell stories. Eisner defends and establishes the usefulness and seriousness of the form as a literary medium, capable of addressing themes and issues that matter. The central tenet of the book is that the visuals must be shaped by the needs of the story and not the other way around - otherwise you get lured into meaningless set pieces that serve no purpose but to show off something that looks good. It covers a lot of the same ground as the other works we&amp;rsquo;ve discussed on Storytelling, but does so with beautiful illustrations (duh) and a very different focus than works addressed primarily to crafters of prose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Graphic-Storytelling-Visual-Narrative-Instructional/dp/039333127X/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1512954142&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/graphic-storytelling-and-visual-narrative/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Storytelling Part 5 - Resources for Digging Deeper</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-11-27-storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-11-27-storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-11-27-storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper/ -&lt;p&gt;I’ve done my best to share a fantastic beginner’s guide to storytelling with this series, but there is a lot of depth to all of the topics that I’ve touched on. Below, I provide my recommendations on resources for digging into Story Structure, Effective Practice, Public Speaking, Oral Storytelling, Writing, and Visual Storytelling. In each section, I’ve provided a handful of my favorite “how to” resources, whether books, blogs, videos, or courses along with a section of illustrative examples applying the lessons you’ll learn from the how to books. These lists are by no means exhaustive, and if I’ve missed any of your favorite works on storytelling, please let me know, as I am always hungry for new insights on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;story-structure&#34;&gt;Story Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-yourself&#34;&gt;How To Do It Yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Story-Grid-What-Good-Editors-ebook/dp/B00WT7TP8A/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&#34;&gt;The Story Grid&lt;/a&gt; by Shawn Coyne&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to dive deep into structure and how to put together a story that works, you could do a lot worse than to read The Story Grid. Shawn Coyne takes an editor’s approach to figuring out the nuts and bolts of what “works” in a story or not. The book focuses mostly on fiction, but he has regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/articles/&#34;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; and further material at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/articles/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; that apply it to all sorts of other examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Thousand-Faces-Collected-Joseph-Campbell/dp/1577315936/ref=tmm_hrd_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720139&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34;&gt;The Hero with a Thousand Faces&lt;/a&gt; by Joseph Campbell&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dare you to time how long you can read about story structure without &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Campbell&#34;&gt;Joseph Campbell&lt;/a&gt; coming up. This book is where he lays out the fundamental structure shared by almost every enduring mythological tale across the world. Something about this sort of story speaks to the fundamental human experience, and has been for at least thousands of years. If you’ve ever heard of a “hero’s journey” or the “monomyth”, this book is where that comes from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Save-Cat-Blake-Snyder-ebook/dp/B00340ESIS/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720178&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=save+the+cat&#34;&gt;Save the Cat&lt;/a&gt; by Blake Snyder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blake Snyder devotes his book to the end-to-end process of writing a screenplay, and so contains a lot of material not directly related to structure, but it has a rock-solid basic approach to thinking about structure, and even better, hands-on details about how to actually do that. My personal favorite thing from the book is “The Board” - a board you put up on the wall that shows the breakdown into acts, on which you place index cards for each scene, and for each scene you track the change in emotional charge and what the conflict is. The Story Grid covers a lot of the same ground, but they are useful to compare and cherry pick from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oP3c1h8v2ZQ&#34;&gt;On the Shapes of Stories&lt;/a&gt; by Kurt Vonnegut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This delightful (and short) video shares both Vonnegut’s clear understanding of story structure as well as his wit. I recommend watching it a few times: the first time to enjoy it as an entertaining presentation, and then again to realize “oh wait, there’s actually something there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-others-do-it-well&#34;&gt;See Others Do It Well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Mythology-Timeless-Heroes-Anniversary-Illustrated-ebook/dp/B071LDBDTM/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720202&amp;amp;sr=1-3&amp;amp;keywords=mythology&#34;&gt;Mythology&lt;/a&gt; by Edith Hamilton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see the basic myths that Campbell was talking about, there are fewer better presentations than Edith Hamilton’s collection of Greek myths. Academically rigorous but easy to read, this is the “one book” on classical mythology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0084805/?ref_=fn_al_tt_1&#34;&gt;Tootsie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Screenwriting classes love to use Tootsie as an example, because it’s just a good, solid story with a structure that works. Every scene moves the story forward, every scene has a shift in emotional charge, every scene has conflict, and the character grows exactly the way we want to see him do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0085334/?ref_=fn_al_tt_1&#34;&gt;A Christmas Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am especially tickled to point to this example because it is framed as a narrator telling a story - aren’t we all so meta. Every anecdote in the seemingly scattered remembrances of the narrator actually contributes to the overall story, following that Red Rider BB gun. It’s extremely tight and on point the whole time, which helps to explain why people happily re-watch every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0110912/?ref_=nv_sr_1&#34;&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another favorite of film nerds, Pulp Fiction serves as a great example of how structure does not equal chronology. Tartantino chooses to show us scenes based on what he wants us to know about the character at the time, which means that he can’t rely on normal causality to carry the plot along if he gets the sequencing wrong. We’re left with a movie where we buy into the plight of a lot of pretty bad dudes and enjoy struggling along with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_2?url=search-alias%3Dstripbooks&amp;amp;field-keywords=the+dresden+files&#34;&gt;The Dresden Files&lt;/a&gt; by Jim Butcher&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, this one is by the far the nerdiest thing I’m recommending, but hear me out. Each one of these novels works as a tightly structured hard boiled detective story - all the obligatory scenes and genre conventions are there in ways that are both satisfyingly familiar and intriguingly new. At the same time, each book builds the overall character arc of its titular protagonist, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry_Dresden&#34;&gt;Harry Dresden&lt;/a&gt; (spoiler alert) and calls back to previous novels in both expected and unexpected ways. The quality certainly improves over the course of the series, but even the first few books are enjoyable stand alone detective stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;effective-practice&#34;&gt;Effective Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-yourself-1&#34;&gt;How To Do It Yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/4-Hour-Chef-Cooking-Learning-Anything/dp/0547884591/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720290&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=4-hour+chef&#34;&gt;The 4-Hour Chef&lt;/a&gt; by Tim Ferriss&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does cooking have to do with Storytelling? Not much, but the first section of this book breaks down Tim’s recipe for deconstructing a new skill to learn and how to maximize the value of your practice. I like to think I’ve done a lot of the deconstructing and sequencing work for you on Storytelling with this series, but it’s a meta-skill worth learning. As an added bonus, if you don’t already know how to cook, this is the best learn-to-cook cookbook ever written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Little-Book-Talent-Improving-Skills-ebook/dp/B007JC1RM2/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720315&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=little+book+of+talent&#34;&gt;The Little Book of Talent&lt;/a&gt; by Daniel Coyle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short and to the point, Coyle distills the lessons he has learned from neuroscientists, coaches, and performers for building world-class talent into short tips. The book is helpfully organized into sections focused on getting started, building skills effectively, and maintaining motivation when it gets hard. Intended as a quick reference to be carried around and looked at again and again, this book won’t convince you that deliberate practice is the way to get great if you don’t already believe it, but it will help you immensely in actually doing the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Art-Learning-Journey-Pursuit-Excellence-ebook/dp/B000QCQ970/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720343&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+art+of+learning&#34;&gt;The Art of Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Josh Waitzkin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Josh Waitzkin is terrifyingly brilliant and has an amazing ability to learn new fields to highest levels of mastery. His book is one of my personal &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;operating manuals&lt;/a&gt;, and every time I return to it, I realize that I didn’t understand it as well as I thought before. His section on “Making Smaller Circles” is especially relevant for how to approach practice once you’ve already identified the skill or had the basic insight you need to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/&#34;&gt;Scott Young’s Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott is a fantastic resource on all things learning related, and he relentlessly looks for ways to make his learning more effective. You’ll see him come up again below in the examples section, but there’s an absolute wealth of free material on his blog. I especially recommend his advice on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2016/07/28/ultralearn-diy-1/&#34;&gt;setting up your own ultralearning project&lt;/a&gt; if you want to really improve your storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rapid-learner-course.com/&#34;&gt;Rapid Learner Course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Scott Young, he has very thoughtfully put together all of his best material and experience on effectively learning things as quickly as possible into this online course. I have found it extremely effective in learning challenging material quickly on everything from languages through improving my coaching skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-others-do-it-well-1&#34;&gt;See Others Do It Well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Moonwalking-Einstein-Science-Remembering-Everything-ebook/dp/B004H4XI5O/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720375&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=moonwalking+with+einstein&#34;&gt;Moonwalking with Einstein&lt;/a&gt; by Joshua Foer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are lots of works on improving your memory and even on memory competition, I chose to highlight Joshua Foer’s because it focuses on his own journey going from having no idea such as a thing as “mental athletics” existed to himself competing and succeeding as one. It provides a really impressive example of what you can achieve by learning the right way to practice and following through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/my-projects/&#34;&gt;Scott Young’s Ultralearning Projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t sure that Scott Young knows what he’s talking about when it comes to learning things well quickly, check out his ultralearning projects. This dude completed the equivalent of an MIT undergrad in Computer Science in one year. For the most visually impressive example, check out his drawing project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1504320/?ref_=nv_sr_1&#34;&gt;The King’s Speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dramatized, of course, but the true story of someone with some pretty serious challenges to telling stories working his butt off to get it right. Most of us don’t have quite as high stakes as King George VI &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AHY2UzOonig&#34;&gt;declaring war on Germany&lt;/a&gt;, but we all have challenges to overcome and opportunities to tell an important story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;presentations-and-public-speaking&#34;&gt;Presentations and Public Speaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-yourself-2&#34;&gt;How To Do It Yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Show-Tell-Everybody-Extraordinary-Presentations-ebook/dp/B00IDD8WHE/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720407&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=show+and+tell+dan+roam&#34;&gt;Show and Tell&lt;/a&gt; by Dan Roam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked about this book before, but it is the best “one stop shop” on how to go from zero to giving great presentations I’ve seen. It discusses, structure, practice, and delivery in ways that will be familiar to you from this series, and has a great recommended reading list at the end, with some of the same titles you’ll see here. I especially appreciate its emphasis on tying together the spoken message and whatever visuals you are presenting, and how they can reinforce each other to create a stronger whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dalecarnegie.com/events/dale_carnegie_course/&#34;&gt;Dale Carnegie Course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of different courses offered by Dale Carnegie Training these days, some focused more specifically on public speaking than others, but the underlying principle for all of them is to better understand and empathize with other people as human beings. I have not taken one of their courses yet, but I’ve heard nothing but good things and its on my list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.toastmasters.org/&#34;&gt;Toastmasters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another recommendation that I have to provide on the strength of what I’ve heard, this is the best known way to make sure you get a lot more chances to speak in public and learn by doing. They have clubs all over the world and create a supportive environment for people to build their skills as a speaker and get meaningful feedback. If you don’t have a job that requires a lot of presentations (or if you do and are hungry for even more), this is a great way to get your reps in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtools.com/CommSkll/PublicSpeaking.htm&#34;&gt;Mindtools Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article provides a nice overview of how to approach improving your public speaking, and goes into more specifics than we’ve covered in this general series on storytelling. The thing I like the most about it are the links - each section provides a basic overview, but there are a lot of links to dive deeper on specific topics as needed. That’s not all - the article linked is part of a series on giving presentations, which itself is part of a series on Communication skills. Mindtools has a pretty smart nesting and linking of related skills and makes a great resource for a motivated learner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_shapes_who_you_are&#34;&gt;Your body language may shape who you are&lt;/a&gt; - Amy Cuddy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise known as “Fake it ’til you become it”, this is one of my favorite TED talks of all time, and is applicable to much more than just public speaking. It talks about the feedback loop created by our body language, the mental states they create, and what we believe about ourselves. Does public speaking terrify you? If so, the cure is to adopt the posture and body language of someone triumphant and powerful to counteract your natural scared body language. It sounds nuts, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-others-do-it-well-2&#34;&gt;See Others Do It Well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/tony_robbins_asks_why_we_do_what_we_do&#34;&gt;Why we do what we do&lt;/a&gt;” by Tony Robbins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tony Robbins is one of the most dynamic and engaging public speakers I’ve ever seen. If you want to see even more of him doing his thing, check out his outstanding Netflix documentary &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tonyrobbins.com/documentary/&#34;&gt;I Am Not Your Guru&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_gilbert_on_genius&#34;&gt;Your elusive creative genius&lt;/a&gt;” by Elizabeth Gilbert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I snuck this one in for some bonus storytelling advice along with watching someone deliver an effective speech. Gilbert talks about the psychology necessary to do the actual work of writing (or anything else creative). Pairs extremely well with &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/War-Art-Steven-Pressfield-ebook/dp/B007A4SDCG/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511728452&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+war+of+art&#34;&gt;The War of Art&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8CrOL-ydFMI&#34;&gt;This is Water&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by David Foster Wallace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not quite as energetic or dynamic as the previous two, pay attention as you listen to this one to the more writerly approach Wallace takes with his structure, self-referential commentary, and asking the audience to get a bit meta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1Okt_YrKPdw&#34;&gt;We Shall Fight Them on the Beaches&lt;/a&gt;” by Winston Churchill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most famous speeches of all time. Notice how different the cadence and emphasis were than a modern politician would use. This guy knew he had your attention for the next 12 minutes, and he made sure to convey the gravitas the occasion demanded. I wouldn’t recommend that you try to copy Churchill’s style today, but take a look at the differences in assumptions about delivery and style between then and now, and ask yourself if you really want to stick with yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;oral-storytelling&#34;&gt;Oral Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-yourself-3&#34;&gt;How To Do It Yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegreatcourses.com/courses/the-art-of-storytelling-from-parents-to-professionals.html&#34;&gt;The Art of Storytelling: From Parents to Professionals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course focuses on the art of standing in front of people and telling them a story with your voice and goes into a lot of great nuts and bolts details. It also includes material on things like structure and characterization and so on, but what it is has that you can’t get from other sources is a lot of specific advice that doesn’t apply to writing or movie making or drawing comics and may or may not apply to large audience public speaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/talktoanybody/&#34;&gt;How to Talk to Anybody&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another course on general communication and social skills, this includes some very practical and easy to follow advice on telling stories, because stories are an essential part of good interpersonal skills. My favorite piece of advice: keep a story “toolbox” of ready-to-go stories you’ve practiced and tweaked and pull them out whenever it’s appropriate. Sounds obvious, but have you actually done it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Storytelling-Art-Technique-Ellin-Greene/dp/1591586003/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720443&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=storytelling+art+and+technique&#34;&gt;Storytelling: Art and Technique&lt;/a&gt; by Ellin Greene and Janice M. Del Negro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A classic textbook on oral storytelling as practiced in America. I have not read this yet, but it seems to be the definitive reference work on the subject and is cited all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.secondcity.com/courses/hollywood/improv-program/&#34;&gt;Second City Improv Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The famous Chicago-based group invented comedy improv as we know it, and has codified how to succeed when improvising. If you don’t happen to live in Chicago, there are improv groups just about everywhere. What does improv have to do with storytelling? It gets you used to finding relevant connections with other people and spinning them into a story, and also teaches you to read what’s working for your audience and what’s not. Plus, you’ll bomb a few times, which feels terrible, but then you keep going and you realize it’s not a big deal, which is crucial to build the confidence to tell entertaining stories with enough verve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-others-do-it-well-3&#34;&gt;See Others Do It Well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LmhZKN58otE&#34;&gt;Mike Birbiglia - What I Should Have Said Was Nothing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend recently pointed me in Birbiglia’s direction as a great example of a comedian who builds his humor through storytelling rather than relying as much on specific jokes. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pattonoswalt.com/&#34;&gt;Patton Oswalt&lt;/a&gt; is another favorite of mine. I especially like to pay attention to what stand up comedians do because the most common reason we’re telling a story in our personal lives is to entertain people and make them laugh - so who better to check out than people that get paid to do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dancarlin.com/product-category/hardcore-history/&#34;&gt;Hardcore History&lt;/a&gt; by Dan Carlin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts are another favorite form of verbal storytelling for me, because they have to be good enough to work without visuals of any kind. Carlin does a remarkable job of calling up vivid images in your mind of the events he describes and invites you to empathize with the actual lived experience of the human beings that were there. Really good stuff, but be forewarned: most episodes are better named “audiobooks” and run several hours long. Perfect for long drives, not so great for bite sized enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lorepodcast.com/&#34;&gt;Lore&lt;/a&gt; by Aaron Mahnke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife turned me on to this one, where Mahnke recounts historically attested tales of weird and creepy stuff. Most of the stories are not (and cannot be) verified as actually happening, but all of them are things that people at least said actually happened - you know, folklore. Even though Mahnke’s cadence includes the occasional hilariously inexplicable pause, he effectively holds your interest and builds tension to creepy climax of each episode. Unlike Hardcore History, these are usually just the right length for listening while doing chores or making a commute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing&#34;&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-yourself-4&#34;&gt;How To Do It Yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Elements-Style-Fourth-William-Strunk/dp/020530902X/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;sr=&#34;&gt;The Elements of Style&lt;/a&gt; by William Strunk and E.B. White&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is the definitive guide to what American authors mean when they say “good writing”. It’s quite brief at a whole 85 pages, and contains advice on everything from comma usage to word choice. Anyone who has ever told you to get rid of unnecessary words, use the active voice, and to prefer the plainest way of saying something possible was speaking in the tradition of Strunk. It’s usefully organized as topical chapters subdivided into brief discussion of pithy principles - as an information architecture nerd, I find that delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Writing-Memoir-Craft-Stephen-King-ebook/dp/B000FC0SIM/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720522&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=on+writing+stephen+king&#34;&gt;On Writing&lt;/a&gt; by Stephen King&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classic work by one of the most popular and successful authors of all time, King knows a thing or two about telling stories via the printed word. Like his fiction, the prose is direct, clear, and keeps up a good clip. My one complaint is that it’s structure as a collection of disconnected memories leaves something to be desired in the referencing things later department - but perhaps that’s the point, you have to digest it to get the good stuff out of it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Words-That-Work-What-People-ebook/dp/B000Q9J0K6/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720595&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=words+that+work&#34;&gt;Words that Work&lt;/a&gt; by Frank Luntz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wonderfully pragmatic book that focuses on the importance of how you say it when most of are laser focused on what it is we want to say. While the thrust of the book is on persuasion, as Luntz has worked as a marketer and political speechwriter, the advice to choose your words based on the impact they will have on your audience applies to anything that relies on words. I find it especially useful to compare and contrast with The Elements of Style, which is predominantly focused on aesthetics rather than persuasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Nobody-Wants-Read-Your-Sh-ebook/dp/B01GZ1TJBI/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720485&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=nobody+wants+to+read+your+shit&#34;&gt;Nobody Wants to Read Your Sh*t&lt;/a&gt; by Steven Pressfield&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this brief work, Pressfield takes the lessons he’s learned writing in different fields - advertising, screenplays, fiction, non-fiction, and self help - and how he applies them across the board. The title reveals the most important lesson: people are busy and don’t want to read anything unless there’s a reason it is compellingly interesting to them - which means you need to develop some serious empathy to get anywhere as a writer. Funny how that keeps popping up about storytelling, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stevenpressfield.com/&#34;&gt;Steven Pressfield’s Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve referenced Pressfield several times in this series, because I so much enjoy his writing on writing. His blog provides more frequent and bite size doses of what you get in his books. If you aren’t sold on War of Art or Nobody Wants to Read Your Sh*t from my description, pop over to his blog for “Writing Wednesdays” to get a good feel for tone, style, and content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-others-do-it-well-4&#34;&gt;See Others Do It Well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Invisible-Cities-Italo-Calvino-ebook/dp/B00ALJH62U/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720682&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=invisible+cities&#34;&gt;Invisible Cities&lt;/a&gt; by Italo Calvino&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a much more “literary” book than I usually read and enjoy, but it’s dream-like descriptions of bizarre cities are extremely vivid and compelling. There’s a “twist” at the end that most people know before they come to the book, but honestly, I just enjoyed it for imagining the impossible cities as real fantastic places, and enjoying the near-poetic language used to bring them to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Steven-Johnson-ebook/dp/B003ZK58TA/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&#34;&gt;Where Good Ideas Come From&lt;/a&gt; by Steven Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my examples here of good writing are fiction, because most non-fiction writers must split their effort between getting good at writing and getting good at whatever they’re writing about, whereas fiction authors can focus almost entirely on the craft of making good prose. Steven Johnson’s early works show the signs of that division of labor - Emergence covers absolutely fascinating material and makes extremely valuable connections, but it gets a big clunky to follow at times. His more recent works, however, expertly weave together the disparate facts and insights he shares with you. Honestly, I could have picked from several books, but I like Where Good Ideas Come From the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Gates-Fire-Steven-Pressfield-ebook/dp/B000NJL7QO/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720696&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=gates+of+fire&#34;&gt;Gates of Fire&lt;/a&gt; by Steven Pressfield&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven Pressfield may not be a Proust or a Hemingway, but I enjoy his books a lot more. Gates of Fire does a great job of describing action in an exciting way while simultaneously exploring the nature of fear, bravery, and loyalty. Required reading at most American military academies and incredibly popular in the special operations community, this is one of the best written books on leadership you can pick up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Reamde-Novel-Neal-Stephenson-ebook/dp/B004XVN0WW/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720655&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=reamde&#34;&gt;Reamde&lt;/a&gt; by Neal Stephenson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, most folks would not point to Neal Stephenson as a prose stylist, but this book is the perfect example of nailing  the execution of a techno-political thriller. As I’ve mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/21/on-the-usefulness-of-fiction&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, Stephenson is one of my favorite authors, and I’ve read all of his books, so this one especially stood out by being different in style to his others. The long, information-rich digressions that I so love from &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Snow-Crash-Novel-Neal-Stephenson-ebook/dp/B000FBJCJE/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511735883&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=snow+crash&#34;&gt;Snow Crash&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Baroque-Cycle-Quicksilver-Confusion-System-ebook/dp/B00KVIBWPI/ref=sr_1_5?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511735898&amp;amp;sr=1-5&amp;amp;keywords=the+baroque+cycle&#34;&gt;The Baroque Cycle&lt;/a&gt; are completely missing here, because this book is all about creating tension and then ratcheting it up relentlessly. Other than Breaking Bad, I have never seen such an expert display of continually increasing stakes: imagine an infinite sequence of falling out of frying pans into fires into frying pans and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;visual-storytelling&#34;&gt;Visual Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-yourself-5&#34;&gt;How To Do It Yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Graphic-Storytelling-Visual-Narrative-Instructional-ebook/dp/B00ID584B6/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720720&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=visual+storytelling+and+narrative&#34;&gt;Visual Storytelling and Narrative&lt;/a&gt; by Will Eisner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you not familiar with comics, Will Eisner is the guy after whom their biggest award is named - he started writing comics in New York in the 30’s when his high school buddy Bob Kane (creator of Batman) suggested he give it a go, coined the term “graphic novel”, and worked hard to argue and prove that comics could tell  serious stories and were a legitimate literary form. This book takes what he learned from his decades of experience creating and teaching sequential art and distills it into a guide to make sure the visuals are always in service to the story - and not the other way around. Beautifully illustrated (duh) and cogently written, this book is useful for anyone who needs to convey messages with a combination of words and images, not just artists and flimmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Understanding-Comics-Invisible-Scott-McCloud/dp/006097625X/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720759&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=understanding+comics&#34;&gt;Understanding Comics&lt;/a&gt; by Scott McCloud&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another meta-work: a comic book about comic books. Why am I harping on comics so much here? Well besides being a big nerd and enjoying them quite a lot, they provide an excellent comparison point to writing (nothing but words) and movies (moving pictures combined with spoken words) that allows examination of what is the same and what is different - and McCloud does exactly that. The central conceptual point of the work is that comic readers are active participants in the creation of the story, because they have to fill in the gaps between every frame. Writers and filmmakers can pull off that trick if they try, but with comics it is absolutely essential and pervasive. That creates a medium with a unique form of engagement worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iZAcRJafmD4&#34;&gt;Genndy Tartakovsky - Reading the Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this video when I was looking for examples of composition and pacing done well for the post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/20/storytelling-part-4-delivery&#34;&gt;Delivery&lt;/a&gt; and was immediately hooked. As my previous posts have made no effort to hide, I’m a big fan of everything Genndy Tartakovsky does, and this explained how he does it with remarkable clarity and great examples. I’ve since watched several episodes of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0278238/&#34;&gt;Samurai Jack&lt;/a&gt; and keep noticing the three techniques identified here. As with comics, I like analyses of animation as a way of learning about film, because the lack of human actors and overt stylization allows you to focus on form and composition and such like very purely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Doodle-Revolution-Unlock-Power-Differently/dp/1591847036/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511720787&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+doodle+revolution&#34;&gt;The Doodle Revolution&lt;/a&gt; by Sunni Brown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this book is not about storytelling exactly, it is about learning to understand and use “visual language”, which can greatly improve communication and understanding, particularly of abstract concepts. This book addresses many of the challenges with learning and using visual language, from people not even stopping to consider it all the way to insecurity over artistic or creative ability hindering visual output. It provides a lot of very concrete guidance on how and when to use visual language in business and personal settings, all without being good at art. Pairs extremely well with Show and Tell above and &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Gamestorming-Playbook-Innovators-Rulebreakers-Changemakers-ebook/dp/B003XDUCLS/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511738084&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=gamestorming&#34;&gt;Gamestorming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-others-do-it-well-5&#34;&gt;See Others Do It Well&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u6XAPnuFjJc&#34;&gt;Drive: The Surprising Truth about What Motivates Us&lt;/a&gt; by Dan Pink&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quick little video does an excellent job of teaching you something important in a way that is far more memorable and effective than a simple lecture or written chapter. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thersa.org/discover/videos/rsa-animate?id=51787&#34;&gt;RSA Animate&lt;/a&gt; provides the live-drawn whiteboard style graphics to Dan Pink’s narration, and the overall combination of diagrammatic pictures and voice over creates something that will stick with you for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cpXrz2Sfv8Y&#34;&gt;Clone Wars Animated Shorts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love Samurai Jack, but these shorts combine Tartakovsky’s stylistic elements described in the video linked above with my lifelong love of Star Wars. Taken as a whole, I “joke” that these are my favorite prequel. Originally aired as 3 minute (later expanded to 15 minute) shorts between programs on Cartoon Network, these are incredibly tight little self contained stories that nonetheless build into an overall picture of the Clone War, seamlessly linking the end of Attack of the Clones with the beginning of The Revenge of the Sith. Even if you are not a fan of Star Wars, check out the expert use of environments, composition, and carefully choreographed fight scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/300-Frank-Miller-ebook/dp/B00A7H2MG6/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511721758&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=frank+miller+300&#34;&gt;300&lt;/a&gt; by Frank Miller&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the only Zack Snyder film I completely enjoy, I give full credit to Frank Miller for the original, which Snyder very directly adapted. Yes, this is the second time Thermopylae has come up in the examples here, but that is to be expected from a classicist infantryman. The graphic novel showcases Miller’s high-contrast style and impressive composition, but also uses size and placement of frames/panels to expertly pull you through the story. It is also just as much a story about storytelling as less gory titles like &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Sandman-Vol-Preludes-Nocturnes-New-ebook/dp/B0064W67IM/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511739016&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+sandman&#34;&gt;The Sandman&lt;/a&gt; - about the story Western Europe tells itself about its past, the stories a culture tells itself about its values, and the stories we tell ourselves to link our past with our present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0058279/&#34;&gt;Kwaidan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This movie is visually stunning. It came out in 1964 and I first saw it in 2017, and more than 50 years later, it still looks fantastic.  Not “good for its time” but “good for all movies ever made” in a way that is unfortunately rare. It treats us to not one, but four separate expertly told traditional Japanese ghost stories. It’s not an especially scary movie, but it is riveting and beautiful. I recommend it as an example of visual storytelling because for those of us who are American, it removes familiar cultural and artistic conventions and stands on the strength of its craft as a film alone.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-11-27-storytelling-part-5-resources-for-digging-deeper/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Save the Cat!</title>
        <link>/books/save-the-cat/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/save-the-cat/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/save-the-cat/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Blake Snyder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Ferriss recommended this book for writers of all kinds, despite its focus on screenwriting. I came to it in order to get a variety of perspectives on storytelling (speaking, writing fiction, writing screenplays, and so forth). Despite the fact that I often watch movies and think &amp;ldquo;I could have written something better than that!&amp;quot;, I have no particular ambition to become a screenwriter, but I have nonetheless found this little book quite helpful. It&amp;rsquo;s advice to get &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; clear about what your story is about applies across the board, and I appreciate its brass tacks focus on the fact that for anybody to ever experience your fantastic art, you have to sell it, which means people have to want to buy it. Definitely check it out if you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a quick, fun read on how to write punchy things that get people&amp;rsquo;s attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Save-Cat-Blake-Snyder-ebook/dp/B00340ESIS/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1511023642&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=save+the+cat&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/save-the-cat/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Storytelling Part 4 - Delivery</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/ -&lt;p&gt;Now that your story has a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/3/storytelling-part-2-structure&#34;&gt;structure&lt;/a&gt; and you know what good &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/10/storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice&#34;&gt;practice&lt;/a&gt; looks like, let’s focus on what you’re actually trying to improve with your practice: the delivery of your story. I’ve gotta tell you, this was the hardest post for me to write in this series because delivery is so dependent on your medium - public speakers care very much about maintaining their posture and projecting their voice, comic book artists not so much. As I reflected, though, I realized that there are three principles underlying good execution in storytelling regardless of medium: clarity, pacing, and emotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clarity&#34;&gt;Clarity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first principle of effective story delivery is Clarity. You might have interesting content, solid structure, and dedicated practice, but if you do not convey your story clearly, it will be wasted. Clarity means boiling down what you have to share to its essence. I especially struggle here, because I tend to be pretty verbose, as you’ve probably gathered. In writing, especially persuasive writing, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.dilbert.com/2015/08/22/the-day-you-became-a-better-writer-2nd-look/&#34;&gt;few easy rules&lt;/a&gt; will greatly enhance your clarity: stick to active voice, use short sentences, and keep your words &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Thing-Explainer-Complicated-Stuff-Simple/dp/0544668251/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1510935423&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=thing+explainer&amp;amp;dpID=51Uv99xOnIL&amp;amp;preST=_SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_&amp;amp;dpSrc=srch&#34;&gt;simple&lt;/a&gt;. For visual storytelling, you want strong forms in a clear &lt;a href=&#34;https://designschool.canva.com/blog/visual-design-composition/&#34;&gt;composition&lt;/a&gt;. When telling a story in person, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lisabmarshall.com/2015/07/23/how-to-project-your-voice/&#34;&gt;speak up&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtco.com/enunciation-exercises-for-drama-teachers-2712994&#34;&gt;enunciate&lt;/a&gt;. In all cases, make your medium as transparent as possible -  you want your audience too caught up in the story to notice how it’s being told to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pacing&#34;&gt;Pacing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closely related to clarity is the principle of Pacing. Your &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/3/storytelling-part-2-structure&#34;&gt;structure&lt;/a&gt; builds the macro level pacing of your story, but to really nail it you need micro pacing within it. Stand up comics &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dLECCmKnrys&#34;&gt;master&lt;/a&gt; the art of pacing because jokes require &lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/scienceofus/2017/05/the-art-and-science-of-comedic-timing.html&#34;&gt;tiny manipulations of timing&lt;/a&gt; for comedic effect. Not just jokes, but all storytelling relies on pacing to build anticipation, excite the audience, and hold attention. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mj07qh51zPI&#34;&gt;just&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tokBFnNGAU&#34;&gt;about&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Axru07JeBig&#34;&gt;any&lt;/a&gt; cartoon ever made by Genndy Tartakovsky for visual pacing par excellence. In writing, you can tweak pacing at a few different levels - at the most micro, you can vary &lt;a href=&#34;http://study.com/academy/lesson/narrative-techniques-dialogue-pacing-description-reflection.html&#34;&gt;sentence length to affect pacing&lt;/a&gt; (I know I just told you to keep sentences short, but some variation is good), and at a more macro level, you can build anticipation and excitement between &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/414/&#34;&gt;scenes and acts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;emotion&#34;&gt;Emotion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final element of quality delivery is Emotion. You want to skillfully vary emotional ups and downs to create a rich experience for your audience. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/&#34;&gt;The Story Grid&lt;/a&gt; provides a method for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/tracking-the-scene/&#34;&gt;tracking the charge of emotionally resonant values&lt;/a&gt; scene to scene that is just fantastic. Basically, every scene needs a change in the value that’s at stake in the story - either between positive and negative, or from positive to extra positive (or negative to extra negative). For example, in action movies, the value at stake is Life vs Death, so let’s take a look at one of my favorites: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldfinger_(film)&#34;&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/a&gt;. A famous scene opens with Bond tied up and about to get lasered by the eponymous baddy. The scene begins negative on the value of Life/Death (Bond is about to die!), builds suspense by convincing you that the villain really means to kill Bond and that he really is helpless, but then surprisingly ends positive (Bond survives!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To convey these emotional shifts, first figure out what your emotional value is, and then whether the shift is positive or negative. Once you have that figured out, make the emotional shift intense by using clarity and pacing. Think of a horror movie: the storyteller wants to scare you by taking a scene from Life to Death. Every shot focuses on the soon-to-be victim or on an environment that could hide a lurking threat. They use pacing to draw out the apprehension and build up a sense of dread. Check out this fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cs0PrI3ylso&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; from one of my favorite horror films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;putting-it-into-practice-public-speaking&#34;&gt;Putting it Into Practice: Public Speaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s put these principles together with a concrete example: public speaking. First off, I can apply all three principles equally well to the preparation of my materials as to the actual speaking. Once I have my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/3/storytelling-part-2-structure&#34;&gt;structure&lt;/a&gt; down, I’ll go through the content with an eye toward clarity - eliminating any &lt;a href=&#34;http://catb.org/jargon/html/C/cruft.html&#34;&gt;cruft&lt;/a&gt;, checking that my supporting points help my main idea, and making sure the sequence has a clear progression. Next, I’ll take a look at each section to get an idea if my pacing is on the right track, and I’ll review my overall presentation to see what emotional shifts I’m looking to bring to my audience. With that in mind, I think about how I’ll do it in the moment - when will I tell a joke, pause for effect, get quieter, and so on. All of that tells me what elements of in-the-moment delivery to focus on during my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/10/storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice&#34;&gt;practice&lt;/a&gt;. I will make sure to speak loudly and distinctly (clarity), slowly (pacing), and to emphasize the right words with tone of voice, gesture, and facial expression (emotion). Also, I’ll maintain a strong posture without moving too much (clarity and emotion) and when I do move, it will be deliberately and at a speed that reinforces the energy I want to convey to the audience (emotion and pacing). With these elements in mind, I can target the feedback I get specifically, which makes the practice much more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any given medium, we could get into pages and pages of material on good delivery. There are books written on the subject for every field, and with this post we’ve barely dipped our toes in the water. What I hope you take away, though, are the strong principles underlying the tactics and techniques of different mediums. With these delivery tips, you now have a complete, if basic, toolbox for telling quality stories. Next time I’ll share some of my favorite resources for diving deeper and building out that toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-11-20-storytelling-part-4-delivery/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Turning Pro</title>
        <link>/books/turning-pro/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/turning-pro/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/turning-pro/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Steven Pressfield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve talked before about &lt;em&gt;War of Art&lt;/em&gt; and it&amp;rsquo;s discussion of Resistance, the force within us that stops us from creating and achieving what we might. Well, Turning Pro is Pressfield&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;how to&amp;rdquo; on overcoming that force, and it mostly comes down to doggedly showing up to do the work every day, regardless of how inspired you&amp;rsquo;re feeling. While I find &lt;em&gt;War of Art&lt;/em&gt; more inspirational overall, this work is a great companion that gives you concrete steps of what to do when you commit to following the advice in WoA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Turning-Pro-Steven-Pressfield-ebook/dp/B0087TUM54/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/turning-pro/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Storytelling Part 3 - Practice, Practice, Practice</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/ -&lt;p&gt;However you choose to share your stories with the world, you’ll have to practice to make them look effortless and beautiful. You’ll need to tell more stories and tell each of your stories more times to improve your craft and your tales. To make those repetitions useful, you’ll need feedback as fast as possible, and the best feedback comes from a caring but objective partner. After I dig into each of these topics, I’ll give you a specific playbook for preparing for a speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all seen storytelling naturals that just toss off something amazing without trying. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/steve_jobs_how_to_live_before_you_die&#34;&gt;Steve Jobs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iZAcRJafmD4&#34;&gt;Genndy Tartakovsky&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6YDTfEhChgw&#34;&gt;Jim Gaffigan&lt;/a&gt;. We sit enthralled by their effortless execution and marvel at their inborn talent. Anybody who has ever gotten worse after practicing a presentation a few times knows how this goes - obviously those people must be uniquely gifted. These naturals, though? Turns out they’re not. Every single gifted storyteller has practiced a ton to craft the right story and perfect their delivery. This is fantastic news - it means that any of us can become “naturals&amp;rdquo; if we just put in the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need practice to achieve mastery in any field, but paradoxically, it is especially important for achieving “effortless” poise. Pretty early on I noticed the effect I just mentioned: I would practice a formal presentation, get more stilted, and conclude I was better off winging it. What a shame! I wasted years telling mediocre stories when I could have been improving dramatically. My “aha!” moment hit me in business school, when I had to prepare a final presentation for my marketing class. It was for a big chunk of my grade, I had teammates relying on me, and the teacher had coached us on presentations, which included lots of dry runs. So I followed his advice, and you know what? My presentation kicked ass. Random classmates told me how compelling I had been - which, frankly, shocked me, because I thought it was just another presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I reflected on it, though, I remembered something from my drama geek days in high school: when learning a new play, actors begin by acting out the scenes with script in hand, reading the lines as they go. Once they memorize their lines and put down the scripts, at first they get less emotive, less convincing. They get worse. But when was the last time you saw a movie full of scripts? After this initial dip, the actors got way, way better - they internalized the lines until remembering them was easy and they could focus on the hard work of being someone else. Business presentations are the same way - your baseline comfort is likely better than the cognitively demanding task of trying to reproduce something you prepared a little. On the other hand, if you prepare a lot, remembering becomes easy, and you can focus on all the stuff that contributes to doing a great job in the moment. There’s an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncanny_valley&#34;&gt;uncanny valley&lt;/a&gt; of story preparation that can only be spanned with practice, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDfqwHck2Qg&#34;&gt;and lots of it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to storytelling, there are two levels of preparation, one strategic and the other tactical - practicing your craft and practicing your story. At the strategic level, you need to tell a lot of stories to raise your baseline level of skill. Tactically, practicing each story you tell before you let it into the wild ensures you tell the best story you can right now. As an example, think about a writer - they not only need to write a lot of pieces before their best seller, but that work will also require a lot of drafts. Both rely on repetition, but at different scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the scale of your practice, it requires feedback to be effective. The tighter you can make your feedback loops, the better your results. This is true for two reasons: first off, with immediate feedback, you more accurately associate the behavior with the feedback.  It’s the same principle as when you’re training a dog - &lt;a href=&#34;https://clickertraining.com/15tips&#34;&gt;the more closely you associate the event with the reinforcement, the faster the learning&lt;/a&gt;. Faster feedback loops also give you more meaningful repetitions within the same timeframe. I say meaningful because a repetition only matters if you learn something from it. A short repetition with quality feedback will improve your story infinitely more than a thorough repetition with no feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not saying that there’s no place for longer form repetitions (I like reading novels as well as short stories!). Instead, you should use your longer practices more intentionally. Such full-length repetitions help you to understand how the pieces come together as a whole, so I recommend you put them at the beginning and at the end of your total practice time. For the bulk of your practice, though, zoom in to relevant chunks and evaluate just that chunk for more immediate feedback. In a presentation, that would mean talking through a single section as if you were presenting it live. For writing, this would mean editing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/the-scene/&#34;&gt;scene&lt;/a&gt;, and for a comic it would mean sketching out different compositions and forms to see which works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A live human being that cares about you and also willing to tell hard truths sets the gold standard for feedback. It’s well worth cultivating these kinds of relationships in any field where you want to excel, but essential for storytelling. Writers need editors, public speakers need coaches, and artists need critics with a discerning eye. As much as possible, do your short form practice in front of these kinds of people. If you do not have access to someone like this at the moment, the next best thing is to find a way to step outside of your normal perception. This is easiest with public speaking: just film yourself and then watch it. You’ll get a completely different perspective (literally!) on what’s working or not. For art, you can do things like turn your work upside down, look only at silhouettes, try negative space exercises and so forth. Writing’s trickier, but you can practice adopting different mindsets - you have your “writer hat” and your “editor hat”, and depending on which one you’re wearing, you think differently. This is a hard skill, but very useful. In all of these cases, time will help you get some distance and objectivity, but it will slow down your feedback process, which is what makes a trusted partner so valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s apply these principles to my favorite kind of storytelling: public speaking. First, we have strategic practice, and for this I recommend you seek out more opportunities to speak in public - you could try &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.toastmasters.org/&#34;&gt;Toastmasters&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dalecarnegie.com/events/dale_carnegie_course/&#34;&gt;Dale Carnegie Public Speaking class&lt;/a&gt;, or just let your boss know that you’d like to give more presentations. Now we get into the tactical level: for any one of those presentations, try your hardest to find a partner - this is usually  easy for school or work projects, but harder for working solo. Next, you want to practice enough to get past the uncanny valley of inadequate preparation. Start out with one or two complete run throughs so that you know how it fits together. If you can, give these presentations in front of your partner, but at least record yourself. Review each presentation after you’re done and identify the most critical and/or challenging areas as your focus for practice. When I say “chunk” I mean a section in your table of contents - think back to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/11/3/storytelling-part-2-structure&#34;&gt;spine of your PUMA&lt;/a&gt;. For each chunk, deliver just that section and get feedback. Repeat until you’re happy with the section. You can even zoom your repetitions in tighter and tighter as you figure out what concept, phrase, or transition specifically is tripping you up. For each repetition, get feedback from your partner or the recording. Once you’ve run through all of your chunks, do one more end-to-end presentation to weld everything together. Ideally, you want to give these final run throughs in the actual space you’ll be presenting. Once you go through this process, you’ll feel incredibly confident and relaxed on stage, because you know you’re ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice is the unsexy reality behind any slick presentation, gorgeous movie, or gripping novel you’ve ever encountered. It is the hidden difference between amateurs and masters. Using practice to improve your craft turns out to be very easy: you make sure you have both strategic and tactical practice, you do it enough to push through the uncanny valley, you incorporate quality feedback, and you tighten up your feedback loops as much as possible. Get a trusted partner to help you prepare and you’re really cooking with gas. In the next post, we’ll cover just what that feedback should be focused on: storytelling delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-11-10-storytelling-part-3-practice-practice-practice/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Show and Tell: How Everybody Can Make Extraordinary Presentation</title>
        <link>/books/show-and-tell-how-everybody-can-make-extraordinary-presentation/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/show-and-tell-how-everybody-can-make-extraordinary-presentation/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/show-and-tell-how-everybody-can-make-extraordinary-presentation/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Dan Roam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been using the approach outlined in this book for years now, thanks to some fantastic mentors at work, but I only just got around to reading it. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what took me so long to get to it - it was great, and it only took me a little over two hours to read even taking a lot of notes. The basic premise of the book is that you should tell the truth, you should tell it as a story, and you should present the story with pictures as much as possible. It goes into more detail on how to make all of that happen of course, but if you&amp;rsquo;re only ever going to read one book on how tell a story that people will care about, read this one. The four presentation Storylines (Presentation Underlying Message Architectures, or PUMAs) are worth the price of admission alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Show-Tell-Everybody-Extraordinary-Presentations-ebook/dp/B00IDD8WHE/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1509759382&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=show+and+tell&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/show-and-tell-how-everybody-can-make-extraordinary-presentation/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Story Grid</title>
        <link>/books/the-story-grid/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-story-grid/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-story-grid/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Shawn Coyne&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book has been on my list for a long time, but I only just now got around to reading it, and man was I missing out! It breaks down the mysterious art of writing a story that &amp;ldquo;works&amp;rdquo; into comprehensible and testable steps. That&amp;rsquo;s what I think is most remarkable about this book: not that it tells you the components of a story that works (we&amp;rsquo;ve been getting that since Aristotle), but that it gives you tools to tighten up the feedback loop on your stories - you can evaluate your success or failure and make adjustments using these tools. You still have to put in the work and get inspired by the Muse, but all of the guesswork is removed. It has a really strong emphasis on writing fiction, but the lessons are applicable to any sort of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Story-Grid-What-Good-Editors-ebook/dp/B00WT7TP8A/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1509759425&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=story+grid&amp;amp;dpID=41zjXULn5kL&amp;amp;preST=_SX342_QL70_&amp;amp;dpSrc=srch&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-story-grid/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Storytelling Part 1 - Introduction</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/ -&lt;p&gt;Anyone who wants to communicate with other humans needs storytelling, but most folks have no idea what it really is, much less how to improve it. Some people even have the misguided notion that storytelling is worthless fluff. With this series, we’ll clear up that misconception and then cover the best techniques for improving your storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we did with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/11/creativity-part-1-defining-creativity&#34;&gt;creativity&lt;/a&gt;, let’s begin by defining “storytelling”. You’ve probably heard it used in a number of contexts. Some folks use it to mean the ancient tradition of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.houstonstorytellers.org/&#34;&gt;oral storytelling&lt;/a&gt; - like you do around a campfire. Others use it to refer to the craft of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storygrid.com/&#34;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; or making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.indiewire.com/2013/09/pixars-22-rules-of-storytelling-presented-with-film-stills-from-pixar-films-34932/&#34;&gt;movies&lt;/a&gt; or even &lt;a href=&#34;http://scottmccloud.com/2-print/1-uc/&#34;&gt;comics&lt;/a&gt;. Personally, I define storytelling in a way common to all of these media: the synthesis of structure, content, and delivery used to convey meaning. Now let’s break that down into its component parts. Structure is how you organize the elements of your story, content is the information and impressions  conveyed, and delivery is the combination of methods relevant to your medium. When you bring all of these things together, you get a story, whatever your vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we know what storytelling is, why do we care? Most of us don’t get paid to make movies or write novels, so what do we need with hoity-toity storytelling? It turns out, anyone who ever needs to get other humans to understand or remember something needs storytelling. People are more likely to &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2014/10/why-your-brain-loves-good-storytelling&#34;&gt;pay attention&lt;/a&gt; to stories and more likely to &lt;a href=&#34;https://womensleadership.stanford.edu/stories&#34;&gt;remember&lt;/a&gt; them, even on the scale of &lt;a href=&#34;http://longnow.org/seminars/02015/jun/09/how-stories-last/&#34;&gt;generations&lt;/a&gt;. Our brains love narratives so much that we even &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Narrative_fallacy&#34;&gt;invent them where they don’t exist&lt;/a&gt;. Heck, forget about other people - you can even use storytelling to help yourself &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtools.com/pages/article/newTIM_01.htm&#34;&gt;remember things better&lt;/a&gt;. The good news is that you can secure these benefits in any field that requires communicating with other people by improving your storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people see storytelling as a nice extra at best, and at worst as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/What-are-good-storytelling-techniques-for-startup-pitches&#34;&gt;useless embellishment&lt;/a&gt; that distracts from what matters. Even if you accept that storytelling is useful, you might see it as a mysterious knack that some people just have. Fortunately, when you take a look at storytelling, you discover that it can get results and can be practiced. Notice that above we included content as one of the building blocks of storytelling: you can’t tell a good story without material suited to its purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount and kind of content required by a story will vary based on what you’re doing with it. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/pirate-riddles-for-sophisticates&#34;&gt;joke&lt;/a&gt; can be pretty light on content, because the humor comes from the structure and delivery. On the other hand, if you try to ask for a huge investment with nothing but pretty slides well-ordered buzzwords, you’re gonna have a bad time. Since content is going to be specific to what stories you decide to tell, we’re not going to talk about it so much here. I’m assuming that you’re good on the content you want to share, but looking at storytelling’s other two components points the way to improving: master the structures and delivery techniques relevant to your chosen field of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll focus on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;80/20&lt;/a&gt; of storytelling by covering three foundational skills: structure, practice, and delivery. On each topic I’ll detail the efforts that will have &lt;a href=&#34;https://breakingmuscle.com/fitness/what-is-the-minimum-effective-dose-my-tim-ferriss-obsession-confession&#34;&gt;the biggest impact for the least effort necessary&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll go over techniques relevant to written, spoken, and visual storytelling. Even though this series will only present foundational approaches, we’ll close with a list of resources that you can dive into if you really catch the storytelling bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve arrived at a better understanding of what storytelling is and why it matters, I hope you’re as excited as I am to jump into ways to get better. Improving my storytelling has had unexpected and exciting ripple effects throughout my life, and I can’t wait to hear about how you experience the same.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-10-27-storytelling-part-1-introduction/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Make Decisions Like a Boss</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/ -&lt;p&gt;Making good decisions is an essential life skill, and you can improve it with practice. We have some fundamental handicaps to overcome, but if we make it a habit to practice decisiveness in low-impact environments and avoid worthless decisions when it matters, we can dramatically improve our ability to make high quality decisions. By committing to better decision making, recognizing when to make decisions and when not to, improving our ability to do one thing at a time, and clarifying what we are deciding, we can improve not only the quantity but the quality of the decisions we make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself pulling junk food out of the pantry late at night in the middle of a diet? Let’s just say that pasta doesn’t have a long life expectancy in my house. The culprit here is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_fatigue&#34;&gt;decision fatigue&lt;/a&gt;. Making decisions, even trivial ones, uses up some finite resource in your brain. The more decisions you make in a row, the more you &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/files/attachments/584/decision200602-15vohs.pdf&#34;&gt;impair your ability to self-regulate&lt;/a&gt;, making you more likely to take the lazy or easy option. This can be pretty trivial, like the box full of crackers you pound while trying not to wake up your wife with the crunching, but it can also be more serious. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/108/17/6889&#34;&gt;seminal study&lt;/a&gt; of this phenomenon followed judges making parole decisions. They discovered that the judges were more likely to grant parole first thing in the morning or immediately after lunch. Apparently, when they had been working all morning, they depleted their ability to carefully consider the case and instead defaulted to the safer option - keeping the prisoner confined for another month. Some CEOs, like Facebook’s Mark Zuckerberg, take this information to its logical conclusion and eliminate as many decisions from their life as possible, &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/startup-grind/choice-minimalism-why-mark-zuckerberg-wears-the-same-thing-every-day-2f132f1b5706&#34;&gt;all the way down to wearing the same “uniform” every day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding decision fatigue is super important, but I don’t think it’s the full story. Based on personal experience, I happen to agree with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/danschawbel/2017/01/23/jocko-willink-career-advice-from-a-former-navy-seal/#48da2c194845&#34;&gt;Jocko Willink&lt;/a&gt; that decision making is like a muscle and it needs exercise. Decision fatigue is like muscle failure: if you try to do 1000 pushups in a row, your form will probably start suffering, and making too many decisions in a row will similarly suffer. On the other hand, if you never do any pushups, when you drop down to prove you’re still in fighting shape, you might not be too happy with the result. If you never make any decisions, your brain will literally lose the ability to do it well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decisiveness is also linked to willpower and focus - improving your ability to do one thing at a time will let you get better results for the same amount of mental effort. It’s not a 100% one-to-one correlation, but whatever gets depleted by decision making seems to be linked to what lets us use our willpower (usually measured by psychologists with such fun activities as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gizmodo.com.au/2016/05/how-to-make-your-willpower-stronger-according-to-science/&#34;&gt;holding your hand in ice water&lt;/a&gt;). We get &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/the-mission/multitasking-is-killing-your-brain-79104e62e930&#34;&gt;addicted to distractions&lt;/a&gt;, and they screw up our ability both to do one kind of work at a time as well as make decisions. We are all &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_miser&#34;&gt;cognitive misers&lt;/a&gt;, and when we build our ability to avoid distraction, we have more mental resources left for making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve talked about internal factors that affect your decision making, but there is an important external element: the clarity of your criteria. If you take a second and think about it, this makes intuitive sense: if you have to waste time and energy on figuring out why your decision matters, or how to make it, you’re not spending that time or energy actually making the decision itself. You can take some steps to affect this external factor, which we’ll detail below, but for now, let’s just recognize that decisions with vague criteria will eat up more effort than those with a lot of clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you put this all together, you get a surprisingly simple prescription to improve your decision making: treat it like exercise. Like a muscle, decisiveness will atrophy if you don’t use it but will also give out if you do too much in a row. So, like an athlete, you need to distinguish between training and performance. When you need to be on and your decision-making counts, when it’s game time, avoid trivial decisions. For example, you might create a morning routine to remove decision-making and have a fixed system for selecting clothes to wear so that when you get to work, you can focus on your most important task for the day while you’re fresh. For especially important events, like a big pitch or quarterly planning, you might plan out your day ahead of time and stay away from email and texts, to really minimize decisions to what counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to training for better decision making. When you don’t need to be at your best, actively search out decisions to make to be your mental gym. Here’s my favorite example: always have an answer when someone asks “what would you like to/for _____?” Friends trying to decide where to get dinner? Name a restaurant. Husband asking what you want to watch on TV? Mention a show you’d like. Your new kryptonite is “I dunno, what do you think?” For frequently made decisions, improve the criteria you apply by developing some &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Simple-Rules-Thrive-Complex-World-ebook/dp/B00LZ7GTSY/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1508452048&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=simple+rules&#34;&gt;simple rules&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, you can also cultivate your ability to focus by &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/2016/11/11/neil-gaimans-advice-to-writers-get-bored/&#34;&gt;practicing being bored&lt;/a&gt; and taking the &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/2016/09/14/on-deep-breaks/&#34;&gt;right kind of breaks&lt;/a&gt;.  If you can practice decisiveness in low stakes environments and remove constraints from the more significant decisions in your life, you’ll be making better decisions in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important decision you can make is paradoxically the one to be more decisive. Once you have, you can use the techniques we’ve covered here to gradually improve. I again echo Jock Willink when I tell you that the way to better decisions is to simply decide to make more of them and follow through. Hopefully this has given you some insight on how to follow through, but the core is very simple: decide to be decisive and you will be.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Simple Rules</title>
        <link>/books/simple-rules/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/simple-rules/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/simple-rules/ -&lt;p&gt;By Donald Sull and Kathleen Eisenhardt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book identifies six types of &amp;ldquo;simple rules&amp;rdquo; that offer enough guidance to be useful but enough flexibility to respond to complexity. More exciting than that, it walks through how to create your own simple rules for work and life. Unless you&amp;rsquo;re my kind of geek, it&amp;rsquo;s not the sexiest topic in the world, but for one thing, it&amp;rsquo;s shockingly useful, and for another, the authors use a conversational tone that makes for pleasant reading. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re looking to make better decisions about investing, dating, or your company&amp;rsquo;s strategy, this book has you covered.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/simple-rules/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Habits for a Happier Life</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/ -&lt;p&gt;Recently, I found myself in a funk for a month or two. I don’t want to go all &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamesaltucher.com/&#34;&gt;James Altucher&lt;/a&gt; and turn this blog into a parade of failures and fears, but I think it’s important to take a look behind the curtain of the generally positive tone I keep here. So, as you read the tips below, keep in mind that they’re coming from someone who needs them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, I like to have clear definitions before talking about fuzzy topics, so let’s define happiness. I like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shawnachor.com/&#34;&gt;Shawn Achor&lt;/a&gt;’s approach: a happy person believes their actions can impact the world around them, they are a “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-happiness-advantage/201103/are-you-irrational-optimist&#34;&gt;rational optimist&lt;/a&gt;”. &lt;a href=&#34;https://markmanson.net/stop-trying-to-be-happy&#34;&gt;Happiness is not the same as pleasure&lt;/a&gt; and it’s not something anybody feels constantly. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.killingbuddha.co/blog/2016/2/10/chief-executive-philosopher-naval-on-happiness-as-peace-and-choosing-your-desires-carefully&#34;&gt;It’s a choice and it takes work&lt;/a&gt;. Some people appear to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychology24.org/the-psychology-of-pessimism-and-optimism/&#34;&gt;predisposed to be happier&lt;/a&gt; and most people appear to have &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedonic_treadmill&#34;&gt;a baseline level of happiness&lt;/a&gt; that they return to after major events like winning the lottery or suffering an accident. So, that means that happiness is a state of belief that your actions can change the world around you, which you can tweak from a likely starting level, and we can count on it to be interrupted by sadness, fear, anger, and everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness research brings us two pieces of good news. First off, it turns out that being a rational optimist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/bul-1316803.pdf&#34;&gt;improves outcomes&lt;/a&gt; on just about every external and internal success metric we have. Secondly, while you may be predisposed to certain default amounts of optimism, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/shawn_achor_the_happy_secret_to_better_work&#34;&gt;certain behaviors can move the needle&lt;/a&gt; and change your default level of happiness. Taken together, we’re not stuck based on shitty genes or a bad upbringing: we can be happier with the right habits, and that will make us more successful, creating a virtuous cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick aside: none of this is medical or psychiatric advice, as I am not a doctor of any sort - please do not stop or alter any treatment plans you’re following based on reading this - bloggers are a bad choice for medical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do these happiness boosting behaviors look like? First, we have to deal with unhappiness. As the old saying goes “if you find yourself in a hole, stop digging.” So, before you can start working on being happy, remove or mitigate any clear and present sources of distress you can, like shitty relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next most obvious things to deal with are the foundational physical things we talked about back in the series on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/5/26/preventative-maintenance-self-care-part-2&#34;&gt;stress&lt;/a&gt;. So, take another look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/6/2/first-aid-for-stress&#34;&gt;Stress First Aid questions&lt;/a&gt; and ask if any of them are ongoing problems.  If they are, consider working backwards to root causes. For example, maybe you’re consistently sleeping poorly. Is it because you don’t care about sleeping well? Probably not. Maybe you’re drinking a bit too much and it’s messing up your sleep cycle. Why the drinking? Work&amp;rsquo;s a bit more stressful than usual. Understanding these second and third order questions can point you to the real problem to treat rather than the symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you’ve removed any obvious reasons for being bummed out and you’re taking care of yourself physically, but you’re still challenged by weird, formless anxiety. I deal with this pretty frequently, myself. For this kind of pervasive negativity, I use a variation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/&#34;&gt;morning pages&lt;/a&gt; to stop myself wallowing in inaction and self pity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I do: I take a few minutes in the morning and write a stream of consciousness of what’s bothering me today. I don’t worry particularly about solving anything or even understanding why I feel that way - the goal is just to write it down. I very rarely arrive at a solution or even come to a better understanding of where the anxiety is coming from, but for some weird reason, getting that negativity out where I can see it and realize how arbitrary it is gives me just enough strength to go focus on something useful that will have a greater positive effect - like eating something healthy or working out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, “don’t be unhappy” is necessary but not sufficient, so what can you do more proactively? My favorite habit is this: write down three things you’re grateful for every day. I’ve been doing this pretty consistently since I started using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.intelligentchange.com/products/the-five-minute-journal&#34;&gt;Five Minute Journal&lt;/a&gt; prompts several months back, but Shawn Achor’s talk at &lt;a href=&#34;http://forefrontevent.com/&#34;&gt;Forefront&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to a crucial new component: why. When you force yourself to reflect on why you’re grateful for something, you think about it harder and create stronger connections - which is the entire point of the exercise. You are literally retraining your brain to go to happy places more easily than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid using the same answers every day, I recommend two tweaks: 1) only write down things that happened in the last 24 hours, and 2) use the following prompts: something big, something small, and something transient. For example, if you had a delicious dinner right before your journal, you could be grateful for the big fact that you have plenty of money to enjoy a luxurious meal, or the little detail that they had your favorite dessert, or the transient taste lingering in your mouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’re consistently taking care of your baseline physical needs and writing down what you’re grateful for, there are some other &lt;a href=&#34;http://alifeofproductivity.com/5-habits-lead-happiness/&#34;&gt;great habits&lt;/a&gt; from Shawn Achor. “The Doubler” involves writing down a pleasant experience in the past 24 hours and at least three bullet points describing it in detail. “The Fun Fifteen” is fifteen minutes of mindful cardio exercise that you enjoy. Mindfulness meditation is paying close attention to your breath for at least two minutes a day. Daily Intentional Kindness involves calling, texting, or emailing one new person a day to thank or compliment them genuinely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of options from other folks, of course. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/2015/08/18/the-evolutionary-angel-naval-ravikant/&#34;&gt;Naval Ravikant on the Tim Ferriss show&lt;/a&gt; recommends getting more sunlight on a daily basis (~30 minutes, but don’t burn yourself). Another person featured in &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Tools-Titans-Billionaires-World-Class-Performers-ebook/dp/B01HSMRWNU/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507834431&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=tools+of+titans&#34;&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chade-Meng_Tan&#34;&gt;Chade-Meng Tan&lt;/a&gt;, suggests &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifehacker.com/googles-three-step-formula-for-happiness-1733803164&#34;&gt;wishing for three random strangers to be happy&lt;/a&gt; a day. Kamal Ravikant (Naval’s brother) wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Love-Yourself-Like-Your-Depends-ebook/dp/B0086BX8UE/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507834455&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=love+yourself+like+your+life+depends+on+it&#34;&gt;short book&lt;/a&gt; about the power of truly loving yourself. Some of the common links in all of these is being &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindful.org/meditation/mindfulness-getting-started/&#34;&gt;more present in the current moment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common thread I’ve come across in all of this is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.positivityblog.com/make-someone-happy/&#34;&gt;focus on others instead of yourself&lt;/a&gt; - a selfish orientation seems to lock us in to survival mode. Survival mode means stress and focusing on what we don’t have, and unfortunately it’s the easy default because our brain was built to keep us alive, not happy. Everything we experience as happiness was simply &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2017/04/05/the-problem-of-happiness/&#34;&gt;the evolutionary carrot to encourage certain behaviors&lt;/a&gt;. Humanity’s killer app has always been cooperation, so it makes sense that the most fool proof ways to get happier all revolve around doing things that will make other people happy, and therefore make you a valued member of a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know that happiness is not a foregone conclusion, and some of us struggle with it more than others. What I hope you’ve learned here is that neither is it impossible to attain. In fact, with some simple interventions, just about anyone can improve their default happiness and see positive results throughout their life.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>How We Got to Now</title>
        <link>/books/how-we-got-to-now/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/how-we-got-to-now/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/how-we-got-to-now/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Steven Johnson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worry a bit that this is becoming the Steven Johnson fan club, but I am really enjoying his books recently. This one takes a look at history through the lens of what was made possible through the development of some key technologies, like glass and sanitation. Besides providing a plethora of fun trivia, like the fact that in the mid nineteenth century it was more practical to raise the entire city 10 feet than to tunnel under it to install a sewer system, or that chlorinating water reduced infant mortality by ~40%, the book provides a fascinating reframe of how we normally process history. Instead of looking at decisions made by individuals or trends embodied in governments and cultures, it asks &amp;ldquo;what couldn&amp;rsquo;t have happened without this technology that did happen after it was invented?&amp;rdquo; Maybe not as immediately useful as &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Steven-Johnson-ebook/dp/B003ZK58TA/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507915701&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=where+good+ideas+come+from&#34;&gt;Where Good Ideas Come From&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, but it&amp;rsquo;s possibly a more approachable and enjoyable introduction to Johnson&amp;rsquo;s style. Definitely check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/how-we-got-to-now/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Synchronicity</title>
        <link>/books/synchronicity/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/synchronicity/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/synchronicity/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Carl Gustav Jung, trans H.F.C. Hull&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you probably have a vague idea of Jung from high school English classes, and something about archetypes. Maybe you heard he was an important influence on Lucas when he made &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;. If you studied psychology, you may have gotten a brief discussion about how he was important psychologist for a while, but we&amp;rsquo;ve moved past his outdated theories. Well, I&amp;rsquo;m here to tell you that Jung is both &lt;em&gt;weirder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;smarter&lt;/em&gt; than you probably think, and that makes it worth reading his stuff for yourself. &lt;em&gt;Synchronicity&lt;/em&gt; is a perfect introduction because it is short and enjoyably mind-bending. Jung basically argues that disparate events can be meaningfully linked in ways besides causality. If nothing else, it is an enjoyable mental exercise to wrestle with such an alien concept, and who knows, you might gain a richer understanding of your own experience of the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Synchronicity-Connecting-Principle-Collected-Extracts-ebook/dp/B0073X0GCE/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507242093&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=synchronicity&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/synchronicity/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Depth Before Breadth - Why You Should Learn One Thing at a Time</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/ -&lt;p&gt;Many of us have a hard time limiting our effort to one field at a time - there’s so much interesting stuff out there and it’s more available than ever. All of this stuff can lure us into paying hidden costs when we try to learn everything all at once - costs that prevent us from getting the benefits breadth is supposed to bring. On the other hand, if you pursue depth, while you will only focus on one field at a time before moving onto the next, you will get much more out of each field, with a more robust breadth down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, I have to admit that I find this approach really really hard. I want to learn how to do everything and I want to learn it now. In high school, I tried to build a furnace in my backyard to make bronze. For two semesters in college, I took Latin, Greek, and Arabic simultaneously - oh, and after hours, one of my professors was giving a free class on Hittite. In the Army, I took up woodworking, leatherworking, mixed martial arts, and kayaking. In other words, I am a poster child for what you might call a &amp;ldquo;generalist” on a good day and a “dilettante” on a bad one. So, if you feel any objections as we go through this, believe me that I’m right there with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you’ve probably guessed by now, I never got any good at those things, and I certainly didn’t master any of them. If you try to learn everything, you never get good at anything. If only there were some saying that could have steered me in the right direction, something about jacks and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netflix.com/title/80049714&#34;&gt;masters&lt;/a&gt; - hmmmm. I have finally started to figure out that a lot of interests without any depth is just a protracted form of ADD. Jumping to some new skill gives you a virtuous justification to drop something as soon as it gets hard - “oh, I’m not quitting, I’m just also doing this other thing.” The trouble is, you learn precisely by &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/2011/12/23/flow-is-the-opiate-of-the-medicore-advice-on-getting-better-from-an-accomplished-piano-player/&#34;&gt;pushing through when you want to quit&lt;/a&gt;. Initial enthusiasm can jumpstart you in a new field, but if you only listen to excitement, you’ll quit as soon as you start to make any real progress. I know, because I’ve done it countless times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve become fascinated by an alternative to my serial dabbling that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joshwaitzkin.com/&#34;&gt;Josh Waitzkin&lt;/a&gt; recommends. We’ve talked about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/4/11/jeffs-recommended-self-improvement-reading&#34;&gt;him&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/9/22/virtual-mentors&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;. Josh stresses the importance of achieving real depth before you even try for breadth. He bases this on his own experience: he became a world champion chess player as a child, then moved on to world championships in Tai Chi Chuan Push Hands, and now co-runs a world class Jujitsu dojo with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Garcia_(grappler)&#34;&gt;Marcelo Garcia&lt;/a&gt;. He didn’t learn all three things at once, instead he spent years obsessively focused on one at a time. He was able to take what he learned from each pursuit and apply it to his next one precisely because he took the time and effort to get that good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets even better, though: you can apply this lesson within your current field of study. Instead of learning a gajillion opening moves in Chess, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kphr-8GLD_8&#34;&gt;learn the endgame&lt;/a&gt;. Rather than learning an entire Tai Chi sequence poorly, learn the first stance really well before moving on to the next. To get good at Jujitsu, find the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xRc1pjZW5Bo&#34;&gt;one move that forces you to learn the right fundamentals&lt;/a&gt;. As Bruce Lee said, “I fear not the man who has practiced ten thousand kicks once, but I fear the man who has practiced one kick ten thousand times.” Even though all of the above examples are from sports, you can apply this technique elsewhere just as effectively. For example, if studying history, rather than reading a big picture survey, you might choose a single figure and learn about him deeply, coming to understand his context through his life. Or if you are studying a literary genre, instead of trying to read all of the books you can find from that genre, you could choose one work and dig in on plot points, themes, allusions, linguistic choices and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why this insistence on depth? Well, for one thing, focusing on one topic will &lt;a href=&#34;https://sivers.org/book/ArtOfLearning&#34;&gt;reduce the complexity&lt;/a&gt; while retaining important principles. Instead of worrying about punches and kicks and blocks all at once, you just learn all of the body mechanics to throw a punch in great detail. Having done this, you will internalize the core principles. Studying this way is highly organic - you branch out into adjacent areas to inform your narrow field of focus almost without realizing it. These natural connections form a strong latticework for real learning. Going so hard at one topic also ingrains this stuff deep down in your subconscious, which allows you to apply it intuitively rather than consciously. Without that internalization, the only insights you will have from between fields will be shallow - things like “gee, Chess is a bit like moving ancient armies on the field” or “huh, turns out every martial art with punches has kind of the same body mechanics.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I still value being well-rounded - but it turns out the best way to become well rounded is sequential mastery rather than simultaneous dabbling. Dabbling is certainly stimulating, but it won&amp;rsquo;t produce any impressive insights. Now, do all of us need to monofocus to the intense degree that Mr. Waitzkin does? Probably not. You could take a Tim Ferriss approach and treat life as a series of intense &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@suprada/2-week-experiments-and-6-week-projects-8c29a5fbb310&#34;&gt;two week experiments&lt;/a&gt;. Or take the Warren Buffet “&lt;a href=&#34;http://jamesclear.com/buffett-focus&#34;&gt;Two Lists&lt;/a&gt;” approach to at least limit your long term projects. Or divide your work and learning into &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/2012/11/21/knowledge-workers-are-bad-at-working-and-heres-what-to-do-about-it/&#34;&gt;deep and shallow&lt;/a&gt; and make sure you only have one topic for deep work, but do what you want with shallow. You can always be more focused without being perfectly focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to close with one more hidden bonus lesson from adopting a depth first approach - you &lt;a href=&#34;https://sivers.org/donkey&#34;&gt;don’t have to do everything&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://sivers.org/donkey&#34;&gt;right now&lt;/a&gt;. While a bit of &lt;a href=&#34;http://observer.com/2017/06/why-you-should-pretend-today-is-the-end-memento-mori-stoicism-philosophy/&#34;&gt;memento mori&lt;/a&gt; can help you to focus on what’s most important, it can sometimes drive us to extremes. I personally find it hard to strike the right balance between “get your ass in gear, your time is your most precious resource!” and “you can let that go for now, it’ll still be there later.” I try to resolve that conflict by focusing not on quantity of time, but quality. It’s certainly not an original thought, but it helps. I remind myself I will never be able to do everything, so maximizing the number of things I do is a waste of time, whereas I can control how intensely I focus on what I’m doing right now - and the better the focus, the better my time. If I get hit by a bus tomorrow, it might mean I never get to study &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_European_martial_arts&#34;&gt;western martial arts&lt;/a&gt; like I’ve wanted to for years, but it can’t take away the quality of my time today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, I know better than most how hard this advice can be to follow, but when I’ve forced myself to do so, it’s been well worth it. Dabbling is a sneaky form of laziness, and learning one subject at a time turns out to be the better path to what you were trying to accomplish by studying a lot of things. I’ve only just begun applying this concept seriously, soI’d love to hear your thoughts and experiences as we figure this out together.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Virtual Mentors</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-09-22-virtual-mentors/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-09-22-virtual-mentors/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-09-22-virtual-mentors/ -&lt;p&gt;High performers frequently emphasize the importance of quality mentors, and we’ve all experienced the value of learning from people who have been there and done that. Finding a great mentor can be a big challenge, though. Luckily, you can benefit from the wisdom of impressive people with  “virtual mentors”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about why to bother with this technique: finding and building a relationship with a top notch mentor is a big challenge. For one thing, there aren’t that many people at the top of their field to go around- that’s what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8gXCCBmTvBI&#34;&gt;special means&lt;/a&gt;. Secondly, top performers tend to be pretty darn busy, so even if they &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tonyrobbins.com/events/date-with-destiny/&#34;&gt;industrialize&lt;/a&gt; helping people, they can only reach so many. Finally, talented people are gifted in different ways - you might want to ask &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woody_Allen&#34;&gt;Woody Allen&lt;/a&gt; for advice on filmmaking, but not so much for parenting. The good news is that we can bypass these limitations by learning a simple technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start by taking advantage of a quirk in our neurology. It turns out that consciousness might work by &lt;a href=&#34;http://slatestarcodex.com/2017/09/05/book-review-surfing-uncertainty/&#34;&gt;simulating the world around us and constantly testing our simulation against sensory inputs&lt;/a&gt;. As social animals, a ridiculous amount of that simulation bandwidth is dedicated to &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/folkpsych-simulation/&#34;&gt;what other people are thinking, feeling, and will do&lt;/a&gt;. Unless you are on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autism_spectrum&#34;&gt;autism spectrum&lt;/a&gt;, by virtue of being a neurotypical human, you are already stupendously good at imagining what other people might say or do, and how they would look and sound doing it. Here’s the upshot: if you want advice from someone, you probably know enough about them to imagine a darn good model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I recommend: select a handful of people you admire to be your personal board of directors. Stick with no more than three to five keep things manageable. Find experts in the areas of your life that are most challenging. Most folks will choose areas of interest like personal finance, exercise, and career. For a particularly important field, consider picking two people with differing viewpoints so you can compare them. You know the best part? Your virtual mentors don’t have to be alive. They don’t even have to be real. Go right ahead and ask yourself “what would Gandalf do?” if that’s how you roll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, let me share my own virtual mentors. A lot of these names will sound familiar from my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;Operating Manuals&lt;/a&gt; and books of the week. When I need to get tougher, I turn to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jockopodcast.com/&#34;&gt;Jocko Willink&lt;/a&gt;. If I’m dealing with emotional turmoil, I wonder what &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt; would write to me. For a question of focus, learning, or quality, I imagine &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joshwaitzkin.com/&#34;&gt;Josh Waitzkin&lt;/a&gt;. When thinking about investment and risk, I imagine &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fooledbyrandomness.com/&#34;&gt;Nasim Taleb’s&lt;/a&gt; no-doubt snarky advice. Your list will differ, of course, but I want to point to a common thread uniting these figures - each of them is incredibly distinctive. Their strong personalities and clear styles make them easier to imagine vividly, which enhances the accuracy of your simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, now that you’ve got your mentors lined up, let’s talk about how you use them. The quickest version is just a quick “what would ______ do?” With this approach, you aren’t taking much advantage of your brain’s ability to simulate, but you can get guidance in moments. If you have a bit more time, take a  step in the concrete direction and ask yourself “what advice would ______ give me here?” Framing your question this way helps you to imagine an actual conversation, which will likely draw more on your subconscious knowledge of your mentor. For maximum effect, you want to really rev up the virtual reality generator you carry around in your head. First, close your eyes and visualize your mentor as clearly as you can. Focus not only on their face, but also on other details - what is their posture? What does their voice sound like? Are they close or far? Sitting or standing? Keeping your eyes closed, tell them about your situation and ask them what they think you should do. If you’re by yourself, you can say this out loud if it helps, but probably not if there are people around. As you imagine their response, really try to hear and see them giving it to you - the stronger the visualization, the more you will perceive your mentor as “someone else” and less just the usual voice in your head doing impressions. Hash it out as much as you need to until you’re happy with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, sure, there are limitations here, but it has some real value. This technique is most effective when you already know what you need to do but you just can’t find the motivation, or when choosing between multiple attractive options. There are mornings where I have only gotten out of bed and worked out because I imagined Jocko Willink telling me to “be tougher”. In instances like this, the main power comes in reminding yourself how someone you admire thinks and acts. Even in less straightforward situations, though, this technique can help you to dredge things up from your subconscious. There isn’t anything spooky or magic about this, so clearly you’re not going to get anything that isn’t already in your head somewhere, but you might be surprised at what you didn’t know you knew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that all of this sounds a bit silly - I mean, I basically just recommended you get some imaginary friends. If you’re willing to give it a go, though, you might be surprised at how useful it can be. If nothing else, motivating yourself past resistance with a well placed “what would ______  do here?” can be a game changer for habit formation. I hope that you find wonderful live mentors, but even with them, virtual mentors make a great supplement.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-09-22-virtual-mentors/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of the Bicameral Mind</title>
        <link>/books/the-origin-of-consciousness-in-the-breakdown-of-the-bicameral-mind/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/the-origin-of-consciousness-in-the-breakdown-of-the-bicameral-mind/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/the-origin-of-consciousness-in-the-breakdown-of-the-bicameral-mind/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Julian Jaynes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist a book about where the voice in your head comes from when today&amp;rsquo;s post is about imagining other people&amp;rsquo;s voices. I have no idea at how well regarded this book is currently as a credible explanation of where consciousness came from, but it makes a fantastic tool for imagining &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=4893&#34;&gt;what if the world really were that way? What would it mean?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; The book argues that &amp;ldquo;consciousness&amp;rdquo; - an almost unending voice in your head that narrates your thoughts and what&amp;rsquo;s going on and is perceived as &amp;ldquo;yourself&amp;rdquo; is actually a rather recent phenomenon. Jaynes says that the Old Testament documents a culture going through the transition, and that you see similar evidence in Mesopotamian history as well. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing immediately practical here, but it&amp;rsquo;s enjoyably mind-blowing. Plus, season one of Westworld will make a lot more sense, so there&amp;rsquo;s also that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Origin-Consciousness-Breakdown-Bicameral-Mind-ebook/dp/B009MBTRHA/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507242057&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+origin+of+consciousness+in+the+breakdown+of+the+bicameral+mind&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/the-origin-of-consciousness-in-the-breakdown-of-the-bicameral-mind/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Extreme Ownership</title>
        <link>/books/extreme-ownership/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/extreme-ownership/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/extreme-ownership/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Jocko Willink and Leif Babin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is not explicitly about creativity, but I think you&amp;rsquo;ll find it more helpful in that respect than you might think at first glance. Written by a pair of Navy SEAL officers who served together in Ramadi, Iraq when it was at its worst, this book lays out deceptively simple principles for effective leadership. I say deceptive because simple does not mean easy. Following the straightforward advice is much harder than understanding it. Which brings us to creativity: this book&amp;rsquo;s advice on building discipline will help you immensely in building the habits you need for quality creativity. If you want to get a taste, or if you read the book and can&amp;rsquo;t get enough, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=d5e1e97557&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;Jocko Podcast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Extreme-Ownership-U-S-Navy-SEALs-ebook/dp/B00VE4Y0Z2/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241993&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=extreme+ownership&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/extreme-ownership/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Resources for Digging Deeper - Creativity Part 6</title>
        <link>/coaching/2017-09-15-resources-for-digging-deeper-creativity-part-6/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/coaching/2017-09-15-resources-for-digging-deeper-creativity-part-6/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /coaching/2017-09-15-resources-for-digging-deeper-creativity-part-6/ -&lt;p&gt;This is our last installment in the current series on creativity, but don’t expect it to be the last you hear about creativity in this space. Now that we’ve gone through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/11/creativity-part-1-defining-creativity&#34;&gt;definitions&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/17/the-building-blocks-of-creativity&#34;&gt;building blocks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/25/practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3&#34;&gt;divergence and convergence exercises&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/9/1/two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4&#34;&gt;frameworks&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/9/8/maximize-the-value-of-your-creative-inputs-creativity-part-4&#34;&gt;inputs&lt;/a&gt;, I want to provide a list of resources you can use to continue to explore on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;books&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As will surprise no one, I read a lot of books, so today’s list is heavy on books. Here are some of my favorites and my thoughts on them. I’ve divided them up into categories based on what part of the creative process they’ll help out the most with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;strategic-creativity&#34;&gt;Strategic Creativity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These books focus on the higher level questions associated with creativity: what problems do you apply your creative process to? what habits do you cultivate for improved creativity in the long term? what conceptual models do you bring to your efforts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Art-Learning-Journey-Pursuit-Excellence-ebook/dp/B000QCQ970/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505443400&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+art+of+learning&#34;&gt;The Art of Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve mentioned this book before as one of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;Operating Manuals&lt;/a&gt;, but today I want to emphasize its advice on cultivating a commitment to quality and building in structures of ebb and flow, stress and relaxation, into your life. On first read through, this book comes off as a bit esoteric and hard to apply, but that is because it provides principles important enough to span multiple disciplines, and you will have to figure out how to apply them to your areas of concern. When you do, though, the payoff is pretty great. Read this book if you are especially interested in deeply mastering a field or if you want to improve your ability both to “turn it on” and “turn it off”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Technique-Producing-Ideas-James-Young-ebook/dp/B00N33OYPI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445424&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=a+technique+for+producing+ideas&#34;&gt;A Technique for Producing Ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We covered this in detail in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/9/1/two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; in this series, but it really is worth including again. Of all the books in this section, this one is the most straightforwardly actionable - it provides a step by step framework to use. The scope of the framework, though, is broad enough that I think it appropriately fits into the realm of the strategic. Read this book if you need advice on how to structure your work when presented with a problem that calls for creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Steven-Johnson-ebook/dp/B003ZK58TA/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445448&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=where+good+ideas+come+from&#34;&gt;Where Good Ideas Come From&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have wanted to talk about this book in this series so many times, but all I’ve been able to swing is a mention here and there. It is a fascinating and entertaining look at the commonalities between innovators in fields as diverse as biology, literature, and air conditioning invention. From a practical standpoint, it gives guidance on how to cultivate those commonalities in your life - such as living and interacting with “liquid networks”, taking notes in a way that lets you develop “slow hunches”, and allowing “fuzzy connection making”. Read this book if you want structure your life in a way that maximizes your potential to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Zero-One-Notes-Startups-Future-ebook/dp/B00J6YBOFQ/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445474&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=zero+to+one&#34;&gt;Zero to One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it focuses on building a start up, the core thesis of this book is that start ups are near perfect vehicles for world-changing innovation, but to make that happen, you have to think about the world in certain ways. The most provocative way this book recommends is to seek out “secrets” - things that you know or suspect and the rest of the world either doesn’t know or thinks is ridiculous - and then use those secrets to build a monopoly in a field.  To find such secrets, Thiel suggests that you ask yourself “what are things that I believe that everyone else thinks are ridiculous?” Read this book if you are trying to figure out why creativity matters or how you can change the world with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;active-divergence&#34;&gt;Active Divergence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core habit for active divergence - practicing idea generation - is extremely simple and will take you far, but if you are looking for more resources on how to stretch your brain to have more and different ideas, these books will help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Become-Idea-Machine-Because-Currency/dp/B00UG9DWKK/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445505&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=become+an+idea+machine&#34;&gt;Become an Idea Machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This small book takes the idea generation practice I encountered in &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Choose-Yourself-Guide-Wealth-ebook/dp/B00U7IS4S0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505441181&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=choose+yourself+guide+to+wealth&#34;&gt;The Choose Yourself Guide to Wealth&lt;/a&gt; and recommended in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/8/25/practicing-divergent-convergent-thinking-creativity-part-3&#34;&gt;my post&lt;/a&gt; and provides you with a bunch of prompts to get you going. In addition to specific prompts it also provides some advice on how to make sure you’re still stretching yourself with your practice and what to do when you want to start moving from having a lot of ideas to having good ideas with techniques like “idea sex” and “10 things I learned from _____”. Read this book if you feel intimidated by getting started in active divergence or you feel like you’ve hit a plateau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Lateral-Thinking-Creativity-Step-ebook/dp/B003V1WTLI/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445608&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=lateral+thinking&#34;&gt;Lateral Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A classic in the creativity field for a reason, in addition to a wonderful definition of what lateral thinking is and how it complements linear reasoning, it contains dozens of exercises designed for teachers to use with their students. The good news is that the activities are not particularly age-specific, so you can use them yourself, no teacher required! Read this book if you want more of the theoretical underpinning of why divergence is important, or if you need more diverse exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Whack-Side-Head-More-Creative-ebook/dp/B005DO9TW8/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445626&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=a+whack+on+the+side+of+the+head&#34;&gt;A Whack on the Side of the Head&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This delightfully irreverent book focuses on using playfulness and the unexpected to generate novel solutions. My favorite suggestion from the book is its recommendation to use “oracles” - something that provides arbitrary responses which you have to apply to your current situation. Read this book if you are looking for ways to get unstuck in your divergence process or if you want to inject some fun into your creative process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;active-convergence&#34;&gt;Active Convergence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Gamestorming-Playbook-Innovators-Rulebreakers-Changemakers-ebook/dp/B003XDUCLS/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445647&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=gamestorming&#34;&gt;Gamestorming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book contains a number of group facilitation tips and tricks that will be familiar to most consultants but might be totally new in other fields. While it includes exercises that facilitate divergence as well, I have found it most useful for its suggestions on different ways to converge - from affinity mapping to dot voting, this book has a ton of interactive group activities that can help you sift through your ideas and find the good ones. Read this book if you are looking for ways to help your team identify what’s valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;focus-concentration-and-mindset&#34;&gt;Focus, Concentration, and Mindset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Deep-Work-Focused-Success-Distracted-ebook/dp/B00X47ZVXM/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445663&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=deep+work&#34;&gt;Deep Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/7/14/my-operating-manuals-for-life&#34;&gt;Operating Manuals&lt;/a&gt;, in this book Cal Newport lays out how to focus on work that really matters and build a career based on quality and insight. It includes advice on how to structure your time dedicated to deep work based on the requirements of your career, how to negotiate a shallow work budget with your boss, and a method for weighing the pros and cons of digital tools for your life and work. My single favorite technique from the book is to practice being bored, so that you can learn to work through roadblocks in your creative process. Read this book if you want to tune out distractions and think hard about things to improve the quality of your insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/War-Art-Steven-Pressfield-ebook/dp/B007A4SDCG/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445678&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=war+of+art&#34;&gt;The War of Art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be sensing a theme, here, but creativity is a critical aspect of how I try to run my life, so we have yet another Operating Manual. This short book is a dose of strong, bracing medicine - Steven Pressfield takes the hardass logic of a Marine and applies it to creative endeavors. Not feeling inspired? Tough, do the work. How do you guarantee creative output? Sit your ass down and work every day. Read this book if you need a dose of equal parts tough love and inspiration to work on that important project you keep putting off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous-tips-and-tricks&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous Tips and Tricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Mind-Performance-Hacks-Tools-Overclocking-ebook/dp/B0043D2EN6/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445702&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=mind+performance+hacks&#34;&gt;Mind Performance Hacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first read this book years ago in college, and I absolutely love it. The author’s stated intent is to help you be more like a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mentat&#34;&gt;mentat&lt;/a&gt;, which is just fine with me. It covers a diversity of topics from improving memory to mental clarity to, yes, creativity. This book served as my exposure to topics that would later become deeply important to me like meditation, breathing exercises, and the link between physical and mental fitness. Published by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/&#34;&gt;O’Reilly&lt;/a&gt; it has the easy referenceability of a well-executed technical manual. I also discovered while working on this post that the author has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Mindhacker-Tips-Tricks-Games-Level-ebook/dp/B005LGUMKQ/ref=sr_1_2?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445702&amp;amp;sr=1-2&amp;amp;keywords=mind+performance+hacks&#34;&gt;new book&lt;/a&gt; out on similar topics that I am eager to check out. Read this book if you want to get excited about all of the ways you can improve your brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Tools-Titans-Billionaires-World-Class-Performers-ebook/dp/B01HSMRWNU/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505445877&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=tools+of+titans&#34;&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, last Operating Manual, I promise. This book has so much high quality stuff, but most of what will be directly relevant to creativity will be in the Wealthy and Wise sections. Robert Rodriguez’s chapter in particular was an unexpected gem on the subject. Josh Waitzkin’s chapter also presents a lot of what is in &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Art-Learning-Journey-Pursuit-Excellence-ebook/dp/B000QCQ970/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505443400&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+art+of+learning&#34;&gt;The Art of Learning&lt;/a&gt; in a compressed way if you want to get a taste. “Testing the ‘Impossible’: 17 Questions that Changed My Life” is available as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/2016/12/07/testing-the-impossible-17-questions-that-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; and presents a useful set of lenses by which to re-assess a situation, which can lead to some great creative insights. Read this book if you want a relentless focus on practical advice that incorporates creativity into a wider goal of achievement and fulfillment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos-and-podcasts&#34;&gt;Videos and Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everybody shares my predilection for books, and many process information better by &lt;a href=&#34;http://academic.udayton.edu/lawrenceulrich/LeaderArticles/Drucker%20Managing%20Oneself.pdf&#34;&gt;listening rather than reading&lt;/a&gt;. If you are one of these people, I think you’ll enjoy the some of these videos, talks, and podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://unmistakablecreative.com/&#34;&gt;Unmistakable Creative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This delightful podcast interviews high performers in a variety of fields and focuses on the creative aspects of what they do. While the episodes stop short of digging in as much as the Tim Ferriss Show, they are also much shorter. I tend to use this as a way to be exposed to people and fields I wouldn’t otherwise have looked into. Listen to this podcast if you want to get inside the heads of a diverse group of high performing creative people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/podcast/&#34;&gt;Tim Ferriss Show&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owe this show a huge debt for introducing me to a lot of the best stuff that has contributed to my thinking on creativity, including Josh Waitzkin and James Altucher. Tim gets an unbelievably diverse set of people from &lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/2015/02/02/arnold-schwarzenegger/&#34;&gt;governators&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/2015/05/30/chris-sacca/&#34;&gt;billionaires&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/2015/09/07/the-iceman-wim-hof/&#34;&gt;crazy dutchmen&lt;/a&gt;. I am always pleasantly surprised by how much I get out of episodes that initially sound uninteresting to me - like most of the diet and exercise focused ones, for example. Listen to this podcast if you want to go way deep with some amazing people or if &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Tools-Titans-Billionaires-World-Class-Performers-ebook/dp/B01HSMRWNU/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505443713&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=tools+of+titans&#34;&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/a&gt; sounds great, but you’re not much of a reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks&#34;&gt;TED Talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of great TED talks out there, and big surprise, several of them are about creativity. This &lt;a href=&#34;http://motto.time.com/4256296/ted-talks-creativity/&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; breaks down some of the best. I can vouch for Eilzabeth Gilbert’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_gilbert_on_genius&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;. She talks about how useful it is for writers (and other creatives) to view inspiration as an external force coming from a muse outside of their control - because it removes the pressure of trying to be great. Instead, you just have to show up and do the work, and when the muse wants to visit, she does. It does a lot of the same work as War of Art above. Watch this talk if you keep putting off starting that creative pursuit because you’re afraid it won’t be good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thejohncleese.com/&#34;&gt;John Cleese&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years back, I went down a rabbit hole of googling “John Cleese on creativity” and discovered that after his illustrious career in comedy following founding &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Python%27s_Flying_Circus&#34;&gt;Monty Python’s Flying Circus&lt;/a&gt;, he has spent the last several years as a creativity consultant of sorts, and he has given a number of talks and appeared on shows and the like. My favorite concept is where he talks about giving yourself &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pb5oIIPO62g&#34;&gt;time and an appropriate environment to be creative&lt;/a&gt; (oh, and humor helps too) - which will sound familiar to readers of &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Deep-Work-Focused-Success-Distracted-ebook/dp/B00X47ZVXM/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1505444434&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=deep+work&#34;&gt;Deep Work&lt;/a&gt;. Some other good choices are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DMpdPrm6Ul4&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L6Mqw1aY0cs&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Watch these videos if you want good, solid advice on creativity from someone who has been there and done that delivered in a charming English accent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;courses&#34;&gt;Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, creativity is all about practice and one of the best investments you can make is in a course. We’ve covered a chunk of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basadur.com/&#34;&gt;Basadur Applied Creativity process&lt;/a&gt;, but a day long course will be literally life-changing. Unless you practice, you can’t really internalize a rigorous step-by-step approach to problem solving, and we all make mistakes when learning. A course solves that problem by including a skilled facilitator who knows where people are most likely to fall back on old habits and how to step in and address them. Also, you’ll get to explore your &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.basadurprofile.com/default.aspx&#34;&gt;problem solving profile&lt;/a&gt;, which will blow you away when you start seeing how relevant it is in the workplace. I’m sure there are lots of valuable creativity classes and events to attend, but I can whole heartedly endorse this one from experience, and I hope you get the chance to do so as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the end of our current series on creativity, but we’ll continue to explore creativity here in the future. Creativity is vitally important in our fast changing world, and can’t be safely relegated to scruffy “creatives” in some other building - we all need it. I hope that this series has already helped you be more creative and given you some great areas to look more deeply into.&lt;/p&gt;
- /coaching/2017-09-15-resources-for-digging-deeper-creativity-part-6/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Ego is the Enemy</title>
        <link>/books/ego-is-the-enemy/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/ego-is-the-enemy/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/ego-is-the-enemy/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Ryan Holiday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan Holiday has been behind a lot of what I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about here and a lot of the links I&amp;rsquo;ve shared, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t called him out explicitly yet. He&amp;rsquo;s a modern day exponent of an ancient philosophy, and though my interest in stoicism predates my exposure to Holiday, I have found his works useful and engaging. He&amp;rsquo;s best known for &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffrussellcoaching.us15.list-manage1.com/track/click?u=df2d4a2d24de687c5851d6fb7&amp;amp;id=958eeb71ed&amp;amp;e=a21731beeb&#34;&gt;The Obstacle is the Way&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which has been hugely influential with top performers from the business world to the NFL, but I have found this book more useful personally. It is a systematic analysis of how prone we all are to excessive self regard and the ways that destroys you - whether you are aspiring, achieving, or failing. Ego also hinders true creativity because it stops you from the real work you need to push limits and discover new frontiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Ego-Enemy-Ryan-Holiday-ebook/dp/B015NTIXWE/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241941&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=ego+is+the+enemy&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/ego-is-the-enemy/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A Technique for Producing Ideas</title>
        <link>/books/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By James Webb Young&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book might be the best &amp;ldquo;bang for the buck&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen - at 42 pages, you can easily read it in an evening and almost every single page is chock full of useful, actionable tips. It lays out the steps to follow in order to generate new, creative ideas. While it lacks some of the concepts we go through in our creativity series, it easily integrates with them. Do yourself a favor and check this out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like this sort of thing, check out my &lt;a href=&#34;jpowellrussell.com/tags/creativity/&#34;&gt;posts on creativity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Technique-Producing-Ideas-James-Young-ebook/dp/B00N33OYPI/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507241480&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=a+technique+for+producing+ideas&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/a-technique-for-producing-ideas/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Antifragile</title>
        <link>/books/antifragile/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/books/antifragile/</guid>
        <description>Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead /books/antifragile/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Nassim Taleb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core concept explored in this book is what is &amp;ldquo;risk&amp;rdquo; and how should we think about it in our lives, but it reaches out and touches so many more areas of interest. Taleb is shockingly smart, enjoyably contrarian, and writes in a very engaging way. This book is one of my top five life and brain changing books - you will be a little bit smarter every time you read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the posts I wrote about this book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/6/9/rethinking-risk-with-antifragile&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeffrussellcoaching.com/coaching-blog/2017/6/16/fragility-robustness-and-antifragility&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Antifragile-Things-That-Disorder-Incerto-ebook/dp/B0083DJWGO/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1507240948&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=antifragile&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- /books/antifragile/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 