<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Every Version of Damp;D on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/every-version-of-dampd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Every Version of Damp;D on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 12:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/every-version-of-dampd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part IV: The Underworld &amp; Wilderness Adventures</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-07-03-every-version-of-d-part-iv-underworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-07-03-every-version-of-d-part-iv-underworld/</guid>
      <description>So, as I come to the last of the original Little Brown Books, I have to give a bit of background. When I was getting into D&amp;amp;D as an impatient and overconfident adolescent, I initially gave the DMG something of a pass. It was actually the last of the core rulebooks I bought, and if I remember correctly, I ran my first campaign for quite a while without it. I basically figured I knew what was up, and the Player’s Handbook had “the real rules” (a.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part III: Monsters and Treasure</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-28-every-version-of-d-part-iii-monsters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2013 19:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-06-28-every-version-of-d-part-iii-monsters/</guid>
      <description>Monsters and Treasures  Okay, so I’ve been writing other stuff for awhile now, and I’ve been neglectful of this little series of naked hubris. So back to it with Monsters and Treasure, Volume 2 of OD&amp;amp;D.
The table that opens the book displays its wargame roots to me. Monsters are presented here as a list, rather than as encyclopedia type entries that you see in the Monster Manual and onwards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part II: Men &amp; Magic</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 21:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-30-every-version-of-d-part-ii-men-magic/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Version of D&amp;D Part I: Introduction</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 21:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2013-04-23-every-version-of-d-part-i-introduction/</guid>
      <description>So, for some blog fodder, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided I&amp;rsquo;m going to take on the rather ambitious project of going through every version of D&amp;amp;D and comment on the rules. To keep myself sane, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking to core books only. I&amp;rsquo;m up in the air on OD&amp;amp;D if it will include the supplements or only the the original three LBB&amp;rsquo;s. The idea is to hit up White Box, Holmes, Moldvay, Mentzer, Rules Cyclopedia, AD&amp;amp;D 1E, AD&amp;amp;D 2E, D&amp;amp;D 3/3.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>