<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deep Thinking on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/deep-thinking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deep Thinking on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/deep-thinking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fragility, Robustness, and Antifragility</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-16-fragility-robustness-and-antifragility/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-16-fragility-robustness-and-antifragility/</guid>
      <description>Last time, we discussed a new way of looking at the concept of “risk” and our inability to scientifically define it. Today, we go a little deeper and break systems into three categories based on their exposure to volatility: fragile, robust, and antifragile.
First we need to realize that volatility, time, and risk are really the same thing. This sounds bizarre, right? But let’s return to our least-worst definition of risk: “exposure to negative outcomes brought about by volatility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Risk with Antifragile</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-9-rethinking-risk-with-antifragile/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-9-rethinking-risk-with-antifragile/</guid>
      <description>Risk fundamentally shapes some of our most critical decisions, but most of us don’t think very deeply or clearly about it. Nassim Taleb is not like most of us. he has thought long, hard, and with great rigor about risk and randomness, and he presents that thinking most usefully and straightforwardly in Antifragile. That being said, while his writing and storytelling are superb, it’s not exactly light beach reading. Below we’re going to talk about just one of the many useful concepts presented in the book, which is a fundamentally different way to think about and evaluate risk.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>