<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Book of Threes on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/tags/the-book-of-threes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Book of Threes on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2010 20:41:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/the-book-of-threes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s a Paradigm? And why is it shifting?</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-10-22-what-paradigm-and-why-is-it-shifting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2010 20:41:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-10-22-what-paradigm-and-why-is-it-shifting/</guid>
      <description>Okay, so, despite the continuing blog silence, I have been thinking very hard about The Book of Threes for the past couple weeks, and doing lots of &amp;ldquo;research&amp;rdquo; (in other words, reading RPGs that I&amp;rsquo;d love to get to play, and actually getting some gaming in for once!).
I can tell you right now that the rules as they currently exist are not long for this world. Well, that&amp;rsquo;s not true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book of Threes Revision Sneak Preview</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-09-02-book-of-threes-revision-sneak-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2010 08:47:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-09-02-book-of-threes-revision-sneak-preview/</guid>
      <description>Well, it&amp;rsquo;s amazing how much having a real, face-to-face conversation can do for a design. Despite my lack of discernible activity here on the bloog, the gears they are a-churnin, I&amp;rsquo;m doing thinking and reading and what not that are all informing where I&amp;rsquo;m going.
But! To keep this from being a totally content free &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t go away!&amp;rdquo; sort of post, here&amp;rsquo;s a sneak preview of what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about right now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book of Threes Best Interests</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-08-18-book-of-threes-best-interests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2010 14:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-08-18-book-of-threes-best-interests/</guid>
      <description>So, I had a brainwave on how to make &amp;ldquo;Best Interests&amp;rdquo; have a little more teeth (and only after writing it down did I realize it&amp;rsquo;s a solution pretty close to the Burning Wheel system I&amp;rsquo;m finally getting around to reading).
Not only will it give the best interests more mechanical weight, it will (hopefully) increase the tension of choosing between differing interests. Here&amp;rsquo;s my thought: you&amp;rsquo;ve got three best interests (individual, family, and clan) and three resources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book of Threes Alpha Test Recap</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-07-11-book-of-threes-alpha-test-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2010 13:56:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-07-11-book-of-threes-alpha-test-recap/</guid>
      <description>Okay, sorry this was a bit later than forecasted, but I wanted to collect some thoughts from the first playtest of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; done on Google Wave.
First off, it taught me a lot about Google Wave, and while I think it&amp;rsquo;s far superior to a standard forum for RPGs, it still has some shortcomings compared to &amp;lsquo;the real thing&amp;rsquo; of sitting at a table with your friends and talking it out in person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Playtest Update</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 11:41:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-24-a-quick-playtest-update/</guid>
      <description>So, the online playtest has kicked off and been going strong for a little over a week, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d give a progress report. We&amp;rsquo;re still in the clan creation phase, but it&amp;rsquo;s working out well. I was afraid that the online format might kill some of the collaborative goodness of the group setting crafting, but so far we&amp;rsquo;ve had lots of that nonetheless, which is really encouraging. Everybody&amp;rsquo;s different ideas are inspiring and spinning off everybody else&amp;rsquo;s, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be happier so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Playtest</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2010 08:38:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-15-online-playtest/</guid>
      <description>So, with the revised conflict resolution rules settled as a starting point, I think it&amp;rsquo;s time to take the leap and start playtesting. But my current environment is barren not only in water, but also gamers.
So I&amp;rsquo;m going to give Google Wave a try for an online playtest of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in participating, comment here or email me, and I&amp;rsquo;ll set you up with a Wave account invite.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revised Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2010 08:22:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-15-revised-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>Well, after thinking about the issues raised in Conflict Resolution Conflict, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to what I think is a workable starting point for moving forward with the core resolution rules for &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;.
I decided to go with letting both sides put forward a set number of dice, and for that number to be equal to the leader&amp;rsquo;s current Wealth score. This gives wealth something to do as a static value, and ties it directly into conflict resolution, so now all three resources have something to do in conflict.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Return of Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 10:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>So, in an earlier post I talked about some sticking points with conflict resolution as it currently stands in &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m having some more fundamental questions about the system than just the number of dice that should be put forward by participants in a round. I&amp;rsquo;m wondering how much the current conflict resolution rules contribute to what I want the game to be and how players will actually, you know, play the game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2010 09:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-08-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>Okay, so, I&amp;rsquo;ve been posting some stuff about the game over at this thread on the Forge, both to try to target some hard-core design oriented folks and to draw traffic towards the blog and game :) At any rate, a commenter over there pointed out a glaring deficiency with the conflict resolution rules as written, and then proposed a great solution for one part of it, and some potential solutions for the other, that I wanted to hash out here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Name Day</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 04:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-06-name-day/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s decided!
I&amp;rsquo;m going to go ahead and go with Tyler&amp;rsquo;s suggestion of &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; until it dies or I find a better one. So feel free to throw down with any suggestions or to tell me that&amp;rsquo;s crap, but &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo; is the new working title. Beats the Annuvin out of &amp;ldquo;Celto-Germania&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insert Title Here</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 11:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-04-insert-title-here/</guid>
      <description>No really, this post is about titles :)
So, as mentioned before, I have no idea what to name this bad boy as yet. I&amp;rsquo;ve been engaging in some correspondence with my friend Tyler who&amp;rsquo;s pointed me in some good directions, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share the stuff that&amp;rsquo;s working for me, and see if anyone else can take it in a better direction than I can.
So, my goals for the title are for it to be simple and evocative of the milieu, without locking in any really specific flavor elements (so, while &amp;ldquo;The Crow Father&amp;rsquo;s Children&amp;rdquo; has a cool ring to it, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to lock in the Crow Father as one of the gods your group has to use or assume is real).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial Design Thoughts</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 04:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-01-initial-design-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>So, I wanted to keep these thoughts separate from the announcement post so that it didn&amp;rsquo;t get overwhelmed with the information here. I just wanted to lay out a few of the thoughts I had while designing the rules, with the hope that this will open up more avenues of approach for improving the rules (like &amp;ldquo;you wanted this rule to do what? You&amp;rsquo;re way off base!).
First off, the ideas that got me going on this game were notions of conflicting loyalties, and the idea of loyalty impairing your ability to act independently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That Will Remain Nameless at this Time</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 03:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-01-that-will-remain-nameless-at-this-time/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s here! Well, actually it&amp;rsquo;s right here, but I mean it&amp;rsquo;s done. And by done, I mean ready to start the process of becoming a real game.
Why the vague &amp;ldquo;its&amp;rdquo; all over the place? Because I still don&amp;rsquo;t have a good name! I&amp;rsquo;m totally stumped. I keep trying to think of one, trying to put it out of my head hoping an answer will pop up unexpected, trying to steal other people&amp;rsquo;s good names, but none are working so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tale that Grows in the Telling</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 12:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-04-26-a-tale-that-grows-in-telling/</guid>
      <description>So, that first draft of the game rules I promised? It&amp;rsquo;s progressing nicely. A little too nicely. What I intended to be a barebones mechanics document is quickly turning into the first draft of the complete rules. I just can&amp;rsquo;t stop writing! So, new ETA for the first draft is May 1st (T minus 5 days).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Excitement!</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2010 11:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-04-22-excitement/</guid>
      <description>Exciting News!
That last game project that I mentioned, with the reading list? I&amp;rsquo;ve been scribbling away notes on the rules, and I&amp;rsquo;m ready to begin typing up the very rough, totally beta, untested at all draft. I would prefer to do some personal playtesting before releasing it into the wilds of the internet, but I&amp;rsquo;m not going to be in a position to do that for awhile, so I will post it for review and solicit recommendations once it&amp;rsquo;s typed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Direction for Now</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2010 03:05:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-04-17-a-new-direction-for-now/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m going to be taking a bit of a break from my starter RPG project for two main reasons. First off, I&amp;rsquo;ve found a wealth of games I&amp;rsquo;d really enjoy to run, some of which I think would make good introductions to what roleplaying is for adult, non-gamer type people. But secondly, I still take the starter RPG notion seriously, but I realized that paradoxically, an RPG designed for beginning players should not be my first full-fledged RPG design.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>