<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HWN on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/hwn/</link>
    <description>Recent content in HWN on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 08:18:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/tags/hwn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Weapon Characteristics, Ammo, and Bleeding Out for Heresies Without Number</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-05-12-weapon-characteristics-ammo-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 08:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-05-12-weapon-characteristics-ammo-and/</guid>
      <description>In the spirit of posting things as they come up, rather than waiting until something is &amp;ldquo;done&amp;rdquo; and taking forever, here&amp;rsquo;s a few rules that came up at the table last night, plus a few more, for Heresies Without Number.
Weapon Characteristics Flame: Flame weapons have the chance to set targets on fire. Damage is rolled as usual, but if the result is in the upper half of the damage die (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equipment Tables for Stars Without Number, Dark Heresy, and Warband</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-04-03-equipment-tables-for-stars-without/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2015 12:41:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-04-03-equipment-tables-for-stars-without/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-uUw6xchofEE/VR7s4d8VN2I/AAAAAAAAEMM/-kfCZwecAkM/s1600/379px-BloodAngelsWargear.jpg
One of the things I want to develop for Heresies Without Number is a set of equipment packages by career. So, in other words, if you choose &amp;ldquo;Arbitrator&amp;rdquo; for a career, you get a stack of equipment to go with it that makes sense. These will hopefully be coming soon, but as a step in my process of figuring out what gear to include, I realized I wanted to be able to compare and manipulate my source equipment lists - Stars Without Number, Dark Heresy, and Warband!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emperor Forgive Us</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-30-emperor-forgive-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 11:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-30-emperor-forgive-us/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-IQ57k8grq_Q/VReWYLyKuZI/AAAAAAAAEHg/koeIn53rmSM/s1600/The_Emperor_Revenant.png ## Introduction To kick off my Heresies Without Number game with my home group, I was casting about for an adventure I could run with fairly minimal adaptation. I ended up settling on a D&amp;amp;D adventure that I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to run since I got it last year: Forgive Us from Lamentations of the Flame Princess*. *
As I went through, I discovered it took surprisingly little modification to get it ready for 40k, but since I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to mess up my book for future use as-is, I decided to type up my 40k specific notes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factions, Reputation, and Acquisition for Heresies Without Number</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-29-factions-reputation-and-acquisition-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 15:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-29-factions-reputation-and-acquisition-for/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-5asF4jPMBOk/VRdVH1OpIVI/AAAAAAAAEHQ/jGIivokNeHw/s1600/arbites_and_hive_ganger_warhammer_40k_dark_heresy_by_jubjubjedi-d4fuyby.jpg
Introduction Taken together, these rules provide for running NPC factions and for players obtaining what they need from them. The faction rules are largely based on the Factions system in the main Stars Without Number rulebook, with a hearty injection from Gus L’s HMS Apollyon faction rules. The faction characteristics range from negative to positive numbers, with zero as average, to work with the acquisition rules, and the faction action and assets rules have been simplified to suit my own GM style.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quirks and Sanity</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-15-quirks-and-sanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 21:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/gaming/2015-03-15-quirks-and-sanity/</guid>
      <description>http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-nZn8_uP1B5I/VQZHjXTsyoI/AAAAAAAAD7c/Fyv-oqHlPSg/s1600/OrdoHereticus.jpg
Introduction I began down this path working on my Heresies Without Number kitbash of Stars Without Number and Dark Heresy. I wanted a fairly simple but still play-affecting sanity system, as well as a way to inject some 40k flavor into characters from the get go. So I turned to two sources: Darkest Dungeon and Arnold K. The sanity rules are pretty much a reskin of this post by Arnold.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>