<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Business on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/tags/business/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Business on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Connections with Oral Storytelling</title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>Humans have been telling stories face to face since forever, and doing it well gives you a leg up personally and professionally. Compelling business presentations are critical for success, and natural storytelling techniques can take them to the next level. Even outside of business, stories help you build relationships and entertain your friends. You can improve your oral storytelling today by paying attention to structure, shortening your stories, using your voice well, and supporting what you say with your face and hands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/coaching/2018-01-8-groundwork-for-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/coaching/2018-01-8-groundwork-for-strategy/</guid>
      <description>Strategy gets used so much and for so many things that it has become almost meaningless. Playing wargames as a kid kindled my fascination with strategy, joining the Army stoked that fire, and going to business school and into management consulting has worked it into a raging blaze. As much as I love strategy, I am painfully aware of its status as a cringe-inducing buzzword. So today I want to lay out my own definition of strategy, a bit of history where it came from, why it has gotten its sorry reputation, and how you might apply it to your own life.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>