<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fellhold Reboot on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/fellhold-reboot/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fellhold Reboot on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/fellhold-reboot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Sages Say&#34; Monster Generator</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 10:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-08-06-the-sages-say-monster-generator/</guid>
      <description>I made a thing that makes monsters. I&amp;rsquo;m terribly pleased with it right now, but let me know what you think. If the embed below is giving you weird formatting (on a phone or tablet, say), or if you just want to mess with it, check out the sheet here.
I used Brendan&amp;rsquo;s excellent methodology to build it in Google Sheets. Every time you refresh this page, you should get a new result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OSR Classes: The Mastermind and the Rook</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 08:08:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-18-osr-classes-mastermind-and-rook/</guid>
      <description>After my last post on Flexible Reaction Rolls, I found myself thinking about how to build Character Classes that fit with the schemey, urban style of play I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for with Fellhold. The trouble for me until now was that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t think of ways to get that stuff without impinging on the Old School playstyle I enjoy. What cracked it for me was turning the Reaction Roll into a mechanic with more knobs to play with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Reaction Rolls</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 11:17:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-16-flexible-reaction-rolls/</guid>
      <description>Reaction rolls are one of my very favorite set of rules. They&amp;rsquo;re quick, easy, and help me to come up with more interesting stuff than I might on my own. I use them as a general purpose social sub-system, though not nearly to the same extent as Courtney Campbell in his excellent On the Non-Player Character. Instead, I use them more as an oracle when I&amp;rsquo;m unsure of how the NPCs would react.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Money &amp; Equipment in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 12:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-07-10-money-equipment-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but I find coming up with equipment lists a huge pain in the ass. Coming up with starting equipment packages? Even harder. So why don&amp;rsquo;t I just use one of the perfectly serviceable equipment lists already out there? Because I definitely buy into the thought that equipment lists are a great way to convey implicit setting and approaches to the game. So I bit the bullet and cranked the below out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Soul Economy in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 14:07:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2018-06-29-the-soul-economy-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>So, back when I first started rebooting my home campaign setting from a Tentpole Megadungeon generic D&amp;amp;D world that owed a lot to Dwimmermount and into something a little funkier, one of the ideas I hit upon was that the economy would be based on souls. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really know what that meant, but it seemed cool, so I ran with it. Well, after lots of reading and thinking and coming up with other parts of the world, it finally clicked together into something that makes some (warped, D&amp;amp;D, in-game) sense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>By Our Powers Combined: Fellhold has an Artist!</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-09-19-by-our-powers-combined-fellhold-has/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-09-19-by-our-powers-combined-fellhold-has/</guid>
      <description>I am very excited to announce that the Fellhold project now has an official artist! The talented and gracious Eric Koch has signed on as the better half of this DIY monstrosity. You can check out his stuff here at his tumblr. So far he has been a joy to work with, and while I plan on greedily hogging all of his RPG-related art time for the next year or so, if after that you&amp;rsquo;re in need of pictures, I highly recommend him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Fellhold Artist to Conquer the DIY D&amp;D World</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-08-11-call-for-fellhold-artist-to-conquer-diy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 06:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-08-11-call-for-fellhold-artist-to-conquer-diy/</guid>
      <description>https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/564x/00/b6/f9/00b6f94294560fd38fefa36b3d6de0fe.jpg
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncaged: Faces of Sigil Review and Rework Part 1</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-31-uncaged-faces-of-sigil-review-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 15:48:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-31-uncaged-faces-of-sigil-review-and/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restaurant and Coffee House Generators</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-26-restaurant-and-coffee-house-generators/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 08:55:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-26-restaurant-and-coffee-house-generators/</guid>
      <description>https://cdn1.artstation.com/p/assets/images/images/002/316/001/large/tim-lochner-rpg-grp.jpg?1460166029
[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fine Dining Carousing Table</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-11-fine-dining-carousing-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-11-fine-dining-carousing-table/</guid>
      <description>http://i2.cdn.turner.com/cnnnext/dam/assets/151104103018-asia-instagram-chefs-lennardy3-super-169.jpeg
One of the things I enjoy the most about living in a big city, and look forward to the most when visiting another city, is the food. Honestly, I&amp;rsquo;d say most of my enjoyment of a vacation comes down to how good the food I get to eat on it is. What&amp;rsquo;s the point of going somewhere beautiful or culturally important if you&amp;rsquo;re eating bland crap while you&amp;rsquo;re there?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conspiracy Generator for Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-08-conspiracy-generator-for-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 09:36:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-08-conspiracy-generator-for-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2782/5805833979_8c7b781b53_o.jpg
I was pretty skeptical of myself when I set out to write this section. Initially, I just planned on including some guidance that basically said &amp;ldquo;go read the section of Night&amp;rsquo;s Black Agents about conspiracies and make something up for your city. But with all of the other generators I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing, it just seemed to go against the ethos I&amp;rsquo;ve been following of &amp;ldquo;make tools that people can use or ignore as they like&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vendors and Merchants of Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-05-vendors-and-merchants-of-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 13:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-07-05-vendors-and-merchants-of-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>http://img02.deviantart.net/e961/i/2013/326/d/a/the_enchanted_trinkets_shop_by_shutupandwhisper-d6v841n.jpg
Today we have another of the specialist NPC types in Fellhold, like the Sages previously presented. Also like the sages, a big, big inspiration for them was Noism/David McGrogan&amp;rsquo;s treatment of fences here. The goal with merchants is twofold: first off, I want to make the people who sell PCs the stuff they frequently buy potentially interesting, and secondly to be contacts in the world of business, providing their own jobs and intrigue and social connections with a different flavor than sages, patrons, or fences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books and Libraries in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-28-books-and-libraries-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-28-books-and-libraries-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>[UPDATE 2/12/19: I no longer support spending money on products that benefit Zak S, or giving him positive attention and connection. The short version is that I find credible claims that he has engaged in unacceptable behavior and not made up for it. For more detail, see here. Please consider these claims and make your own decision on their validity, and the implications thereof, before supporting Zak in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sages and Their Petty Rivalries in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-27-sages-and-their-petty-rivalries-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-27-sages-and-their-petty-rivalries-in/</guid>
      <description>http://www.alchemydiscussion.com/attachment.php?id=334
Noisms/David McGrogan has done some really fantastic stuff with generating player characters&amp;rsquo; social circles in more urban games - most notably in Yoon-Suin, and in development for his new setting/game &amp;ldquo;There is Therefore a Strange Land&amp;rdquo;, as shown in this post. In that post, he provides a table for generating a fence (not a physical barrier around a yard, but a person who buys dubiously acquired merchandise), and I have found it tremendously inspirational for Fellhold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Do you Do in the City? Default Urbancrawl Actions</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-22-what-do-you-do-in-city-default/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 06:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-22-what-do-you-do-in-city-default/</guid>
      <description>http://digitalcollections.lib.washington.edu/utils/ajaxhelper/?CISOROOT=boydBraas&amp;amp;CISOPTR=83&amp;amp;action=2&amp;amp;DMSCALE=90&amp;amp;DMWIDTH=369&amp;amp;DMHEIGHT=460&amp;amp;DMX=0&amp;amp;DMY=0&amp;amp;DMTEXT=&amp;amp;DMROTATE=0
Ever since I decided that the rebooted Fellhold is a massive dungeon-city/city-dungeon, I have been giving a lot of thought to Urbancrawling rules. This series of posts at the Alexandrian covered the topic in a lot of detail, and helped me to organize my thinking, including the core idea of having a &amp;ldquo;default action&amp;rdquo;. And Paolo&amp;rsquo;s discussion of his game Gangs &amp;amp; Bullshit introduced the idea of structuring how you &amp;ldquo;zoom in&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;zoom out&amp;rdquo;, and when I smashed the two ideas together, I felt a tremendous &amp;ldquo;A-ha!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifestyles of the Poor and Adventurous</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-20-lifestyles-of-poor-and-adventurous/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 11:19:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-20-lifestyles-of-poor-and-adventurous/</guid>
      <description>https://ajcarlisle.files.wordpress.com/2014/02/hobbit-chroniclesdosartdesigng4.jpg
One of the major &amp;ldquo;themes&amp;rdquo; of my Fellhold reboot (if that&amp;rsquo;s not too grand a word) is the idea of place being important. Factions have turf, demons have loci they are tied to, and some powers only work in certain places. A frequent hole in the sense of place in D&amp;amp;D games is a place for the characters to live - hence all the murderhoboery. I contend that one contributing reason for this is that most cost of living or lifestyle rules suck and are boring.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Fellhold Random Encounter Tables</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-16-some-fellhold-random-encounter-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 07:28:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-16-some-fellhold-random-encounter-tables/</guid>
      <description>http://uo-planescape.wdfiles.com/local--files/quartiere-gilde/Bazaar_by_Tony_Diterlizzi-02620_(1996)_TSR_AD&amp;amp;D_2ed_Planescape-The_Planewalker&#39;s_Handbook.jpg
Today we continue with some more Fellhold Reboot content - in this case a couple of random encounter tables. There&amp;rsquo;s reference to some district and faction encounters - those are still under developed. The first here is a list of situations you could find your contacts in when you go to find them or bump into them on the street. It&amp;rsquo;s part of a series of rules I&amp;rsquo;m putting together to try to enhance the role contacts play for players in the game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Places of Interest in Fellhold</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-13-places-of-interest-in-fellhold/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 07:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-06-13-places-of-interest-in-fellhold/</guid>
      <description>https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/236x/2c/ab/5b/2cab5b15d229d430e5a56741489829d0.jpg
As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in a few previous posts, I am in the process of pretty extensively overhauling my homebrew setting Fellhold. As a part of that, I&amp;rsquo;ve been drafting some tables to help with stocking the place, which is an enormous, largely ruined city where the dungeon and the urban run together pretty fluidly. Below are the tables for &amp;ldquo;Places of Interest&amp;rdquo;, which are the handful of places within a district likely worth looking into in more detail, also usable to detail out something that catches the players&amp;rsquo; attention in play.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make Anything Gameable: Ask What Three Times</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-01-31-how-to-make-anything-gameable-ask-what/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 11:41:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2016-01-31-how-to-make-anything-gameable-ask-what/</guid>
      <description>So, I like to get into procedures, techniques, and tactics in a lot of aspects of my life: the nitty gritty, detailed ways to exactly do a particular thing. For some gaming related examples, check out these previous posts: creating d100 tables from media, and various procedures in the megadungeon. What I want to talk about today is how to get the most out of mining a book, comic, picture, or whatever for gameable stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fellhold Reboot in 25 Words</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2015-11-14-fellhold-reboot-in-25-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 15:35:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/gaming/2015-11-14-fellhold-reboot-in-25-words/</guid>
      <description>http://cdn.obsidianportal.com/assets/8680/Seattle_Underground.jpg So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on rebooting my homebrew campaign setting for a while now, just letting thoughts percolate, challenging myself to get creative, and I think something clicked when I went on the Seattle Underground tour.
As a sneak peak, here&amp;rsquo;s the new Fellhold in 25 words or less:
Endless forest, Germanic dwarves, falling lich empire, Pacific Northwest, pioneers, crapsack, city, demons, witches, brick, dynamite, warrior lodges, feuds, ratmen, wendigos, tides, totem poles, gods’ bones.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>