<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Psychology on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/psychology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Psychology on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Connections with Oral Storytelling</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2018-01-29-building-connections-with-oral-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>Humans have been telling stories face to face since forever, and doing it well gives you a leg up personally and professionally. Compelling business presentations are critical for success, and natural storytelling techniques can take them to the next level. Even outside of business, stories help you build relationships and entertain your friends. You can improve your oral storytelling today by paying attention to structure, shortening your stories, using your voice well, and supporting what you say with your face and hands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habits for a Happier Life</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-10-13-habits-for-a-happier-life/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I found myself in a funk for a month or two. I don’t want to go all James Altucher and turn this blog into a parade of failures and fears, but I think it’s important to take a look behind the curtain of the generally positive tone I keep here. So, as you read the tips below, keep in mind that they’re coming from someone who needs them.
As you know, I like to have clear definitions before talking about fuzzy topics, so let’s define happiness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Depth Before Breadth - Why You Should Learn One Thing at a Time</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-09-29-depth-before-breadth-why-you-should-learn-one-thing-at-a-time/</guid>
      <description>Many of us have a hard time limiting our effort to one field at a time - there’s so much interesting stuff out there and it’s more available than ever. All of this stuff can lure us into paying hidden costs when we try to learn everything all at once - costs that prevent us from getting the benefits breadth is supposed to bring. On the other hand, if you pursue depth, while you will only focus on one field at a time before moving onto the next, you will get much more out of each field, with a more robust breadth down the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Dunning-Kruger Effect for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-30-using-the-dunning-kruger-effect-for-fun-and-profit/</guid>
      <description>We all labor under a whole pile of cognitive biases day to day, but let’s talk about an especially pernicious one: the Dunning-Kruger effect. This extremely subtle bias afflicts us all, affecting our very ability to assess whether we are suffering from a bias or not. So it’s super important to be aware of it and take appropriate counter measures.
David Dunning and Justin Kruger have experimentally documented the long recognized tendency of people to suffer from “illusory superiority,” and so have had the effect named after them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Start Guide for Your Brain’s User Interface</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</guid>
      <description>Note: This post might get your hackles up a bit. You might find it especially surprising in a space dedicated to agency and self improvement - but stick with me and you might learn something extremely useful.
We overestimate our control over what we think, how we feel, and even what we do. We assume that every moment of every day we are rationally picking and choosing what to do. It turns out this is an extremely inadequate view of how we operate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximize the Value of Your Creative Inputs - Creativity Part 5</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-09-8-maximize-the-value-of-your-creative-inputs-creativity-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-09-8-maximize-the-value-of-your-creative-inputs-creativity-part-4/</guid>
      <description>In the previous posts on creativity, I’ve mentioned “inputs” pretty frequently, but I haven’t gone into much detail about them. Today, I’ll talk about what I mean by inputs, why they’re important, and share some rules for maximizing their usefulness. I’m very excited to be sharing this with you, because I think it’s an often overlooked aspect of creativity that can have huge effects on your work with very little effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Creativity Frameworks - Creativity Part 4</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-09-1-two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-09-1-two-creativity-frameworks-creativity-part-4/</guid>
      <description>In our last installment in this series, we talked about divergent and convergent thinking. Keep that in mind, as it will be central to everything we discuss below. Today, we’re going to talk about frameworks you can use to structure your creative efforts - one for teams and one for individuals. You can use either framework in the other situation, but I find them better suited to different applications.
When we discussed creativity frameworks previously, I mentioned the Basadur Applied Creativity method.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>