<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mental Models on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/mental-models/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mental Models on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpowellrussell.com/tags/mental-models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Make Decisions Like a Boss</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-10-20-make-decisions-like-a-boss/</guid>
      <description>Making good decisions is an essential life skill, and you can improve it with practice. We have some fundamental handicaps to overcome, but if we make it a habit to practice decisiveness in low-impact environments and avoid worthless decisions when it matters, we can dramatically improve our ability to make high quality decisions. By committing to better decision making, recognizing when to make decisions and when not to, improving our ability to do one thing at a time, and clarifying what we are deciding, we can improve not only the quantity but the quality of the decisions we make.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis is Only the Beginning - An Introduction to Systems Thinking</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-06-23-analysis-is-only-the-beginning-an-introduction-to-systems-thinking/</guid>
      <description>Let’s talk about systems. We’ve touched on them in several posts, and they provide an incredibly valuable tool for understanding a complex world. When we stop thinking about things as independent objects and start thinking about them as elements in a greater whole of interdependent parts, we recognize that they are systems. Today we’re going to talk about a method of inquiry custom designed for such highly complex entities: Systems Thinking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Start Guide for Your Brain’s User Interface</title>
      <link>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpowellrussell.com/coaching/2017-07-7-a-quick-start-guide-for-your-brains-user-interface/</guid>
      <description>Note: This post might get your hackles up a bit. You might find it especially surprising in a space dedicated to agency and self improvement - but stick with me and you might learn something extremely useful.
We overestimate our control over what we think, how we feel, and even what we do. We assume that every moment of every day we are rationally picking and choosing what to do. It turns out this is an extremely inadequate view of how we operate.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>