<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Theory on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>/tags/theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Theory on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 23:38:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rumor Has It</title>
      <link>/gaming/2014-01-23-rumor-has-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 23:38:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2014-01-23-rumor-has-it/</guid>
      <description>http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-B8R0KUesZi4/UuIGWNhj3KI/AAAAAAAAAmI/6wlkdkUislo/s1600/640x640_9423_Meleen_s_Silver_Tongue_2d_fantasy_tavern_legends_of_norrath_picture_image_digital_art.jpg
So, in writing the Middenheim series, I really came to love the use of rumors as a way to convey both setting information as well as adventure hooks. Thanks to +Brendan S and +Pearce Shea , I had some further discussion of rumors and why I like them and what they do, and I wanted to expand those thoughts some here.
The first and perhaps most obvious virtue of rumors is their dubious veracity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Situation Based Adventure Design</title>
      <link>/gaming/2014-01-15-situation-based-adventure-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 01:58:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2014-01-15-situation-based-adventure-design/</guid>
      <description>So, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this Middenheim supplement thing, I&amp;rsquo;ve been skimming some of the &amp;ldquo;Enemy Within&amp;rdquo; adventures, especially &amp;ldquo;Power Behind the Throne&amp;rdquo;. Then I read &amp;ldquo;Small But Vicious Dog&amp;rdquo; and immediately wanted to play it, which got me thinking about the problem I&amp;rsquo;ve had with the Old World setting for RPGs: where do you get started, and what do you do? Fortunately, SBVD has some great advice here, but it&amp;rsquo;s gotten me thinking about the published WFRP adventures I&amp;rsquo;ve read and/or skimmed, and I wanted to talk about that some.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GMing Rules, Part 4</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 22:05:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-11-13-porting-dungeon-world-gming-rules-part-4/</guid>
      <description>So, for this post I&amp;rsquo;m taking a bit of a departure from the campaign and domain play rules that I&amp;rsquo;ve been kitbashing from Dungeon World and An Echo, Resounding. This is mostly because it&amp;rsquo;s been awhile, and I&amp;rsquo;m having to reconstruct all the stuff I had figured out from what are now opaque notes, and instead of figuring all that out tonight, I went instead for a simpler problem and decided to tackle some planning/layout issues, and then to address equipment tags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, Part 3</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 10:18:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-10-15-porting-dungeon-world-gm-rules-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Though the title of this post shortchanges the role An Echo, Resounding is playing in my development of the referee rules in my campaign, I figured it was best to stay consistent.
As an example of the role AER is playing, though I&amp;rsquo;m working my way up to the domain rules, rather than down, I am broadly using the categories and concepts from AER&amp;rsquo;s domain play, so that most of the framework for reconciling Dungeon World style GMing tools with the AER domain play should already be there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Wilderness (Porting Dungeon World&#39;s GM Rules, part 2)</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 11:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-10-09-into-wilderness-porting-dungeon-world/</guid>
      <description>As the party is about to venture forth to Mickleheim, I&amp;rsquo;ve started giving some thought to wilderness/sandbox adventure, which I&amp;rsquo;ve intended from the start to be a facet of the Fellhold campaign. I cheated a little bit up front by asking my players to do me the courtesy of agreeing that their characters had come together with the intent to explore Fellhold, at least initially, and we&amp;rsquo;d go from there. This let me devote my initial focus to having mapped and stocked dungeon locations (as it turns out, far more than I&amp;rsquo;ve needed so far - before play, I overestimated the speed with which the party would explore).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Point of Similarity</title>
      <link>/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 22:37:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2012-09-13-a-point-of-similarity/</guid>
      <description>So, all of my recent posts have been about the Old School Renaissance, and my old school D&amp;amp;D game. If you look to the posts that started this blog, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that I was quite enamored of indie RPGs and forge theory and the like. At first glance this seems like something of a flip-flop, but it was actually from the indie &amp;ldquo;scene&amp;rdquo; that I discovered the OSR and became fired up to run a D&amp;amp;D game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smash it up, Smash it up!</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 03:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-06-01-smash-it-up-smash-it-up/</guid>
      <description>So, a recent trend I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading about at the cool kid forums is a sort of game where you say &amp;ldquo;need book X to play&amp;rdquo;. Basically people put out more or less detailed conversion notes for using one set of rules with material from another game (whether just the fluff or some of the actual rules). Shadowrun is a popular target, as it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty universally loved world, with a pretty poorly regarded system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Otherkind Dice</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-10-otherkind-dice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 11:02:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-10-otherkind-dice/</guid>
      <description>Okay, all my thinking about conflict resolution in the prior post is, as I said, tied into reading about really cool conflict resolution systems that do require addressing the fiction and do push the players into directions they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have taken their character themselves, but in a satisfying way. One dirt simple but totally awesome way of doing that is Otherkind Dice.
The link above is really short, it takes like 2 minutes to read, and if you don&amp;rsquo;t check them out, the rest of this entry will be pretty vague and possibly confusing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Return of Conflict Resolution</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 10:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-05-10-return-of-conflict-resolution/</guid>
      <description>So, in an earlier post I talked about some sticking points with conflict resolution as it currently stands in &amp;ldquo;The Book of Threes&amp;rdquo;. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m having some more fundamental questions about the system than just the number of dice that should be put forward by participants in a round. I&amp;rsquo;m wondering how much the current conflict resolution rules contribute to what I want the game to be and how players will actually, you know, play the game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What has Come Before</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-04-10-what-has-come-before/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 09:33:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-04-10-what-has-come-before/</guid>
      <description>So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bit quiet this past week, but not because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been thinking about game design. Actually rather the opposite. Instead, as I linked in a past post, I&amp;rsquo;ve been checking out the design theory over at The Forge, specifically the articles (still trying to wade into the forum, which is daunting) and at anyway.
Not to put too fine a point on it, but this shit has blown my mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Contract</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-04-04-social-contract/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2010 04:09:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-04-04-social-contract/</guid>
      <description>Today I want to talk about something I touched upon in my review of the rules of &amp;ldquo;In a Wicked Age&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;social contract&amp;rdquo; of roleplaying games. This is an idea that has come up a lot in my recent reading at anyway and the articles at The Forge. This is a topic that is so obvious that it is usually ignored or taken for granted, like the sky or the ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Matter of Taste</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:58:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-a-matter-of-taste/</guid>
      <description>So, before we go into how to encourage a particular genre with the rules, there is the question of what genre to shoot for. If my whole contention is that the real draw of RPGs is the non-mechanical aspects, then a good starter RPG needs to have a genre with wide appeal and plenty of material to fire the imagination. I&amp;rsquo;ll run through a brief list of some popular settings/genres and my thoughts on them, but this is an area where personal taste could cloud my judgement extraordinarily easily, so I would very much appreciate comments on what flavors are good choices for players new to roleplaying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting vs Genre</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:52:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-setting-vs-genre/</guid>
      <description>Right now I want to talk about a distinction I recently came up with between setting and genre. Both get used pretty interchangeably with respect to RPGs, with setting usually having a slightly narrower focus. And either one is usually considered fairly separate from rules issues. But in a discussion of whether it was better to have specific rules for every game setting, or to have a great set of generic rules to use in whatever setting, I realized something about the interaction of the game rules and the game world that I think warrants a distinction in terms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rules and Roleplaying</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:51:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-rules-and-roleplaying/</guid>
      <description>Well, last time I talked about how I want to focus more on roleplay than on game mechanics in my starter RPG. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: I&amp;rsquo;m a huge game mechanics nut. Sometimes I enjoy designing game rules more than I do actually playing them. As a kid, I once stayed up all night designing a wargame for little green army men that we never got to play because we were so excited about coming up with rules for each weapon, each vehicle, and every situation we could imagine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The RP in RPG</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:42:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-the-rp-in-rpg/</guid>
      <description>In my last post I talked about my own introduction to RPGs through D&amp;amp;D and it&amp;rsquo;s possible shortcomings as a game for new players, and then a game I found particularly suited to the task, Teenagers From Outer Space.
So why set out to create a set of rules specifically for the purpose of introducing players to the hobby? Well, for one I have pragmatic reasons. I&amp;rsquo;m living and working in a place where I don&amp;rsquo;t know any other roleplayers, and so I don&amp;rsquo;t have the opportunity to indulge in my hobby of choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dungeons and Teenagers from Outer Space</title>
      <link>/gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 03:36:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gaming/2010-02-05-dungeons-and-teenagers-from-outer-space/</guid>
      <description>I have a few ideas on what elements a good &amp;lsquo;starter&amp;rsquo; RPG needs, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading through a number of games in order to find more ideas to add to that list. But I&amp;rsquo;ll start with some of my actual play experience with starting new players on RPGs.
To start with the start, my own (and I suspect many others&amp;rsquo;) first RPG was the venerable Dungeons and Dragons. I myself started out with Advanced Dungeons and Dragons Second Edition.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>