<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Leaves on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</title>
    <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Leaves on Jeff Russell&#39;s Webstead</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/about/</guid>
      <description>For a long time, I&amp;rsquo;ve had somewhat sundered &amp;ldquo;selves&amp;rdquo; on the web - I had a blog and social media account for gaming, another blog and webstead for coaching and thoughts on business and getting more work done and such, and I&amp;rsquo;ve lurked around reading but not putting out there my interests in things like philosophy, mysticism, and religion. After listening to Naval Ravikant talk about why you want to welcome and make the most out of what you have that no one else does, and to Josh Waitzkin talk about how greatness comes from &amp;ldquo;embracing your funk&amp;rdquo;, I made up my mind to set that right - hence, here we are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back This Blog</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/backing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/backing/</guid>
      <description>Hello, dear reader, and thank you for stopping by this corner of my webstead. This is where I tell you how you can help me make some money from the stuff I put out here, if you feel so minded. I already am overwhelmingly thankful that you take the time to read my stuff, but if you choose to do any of the things below, it will help me to put more time and work into writing and sharing my thoughts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bridge Folks</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/bridges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/bridges/</guid>
      <description>When you are first getting started learning a new field, it can be hard to thresh out the wheat from the chaff. Finding out the groundwork in a field is not too hard these days, what with wikipedia and nearly unending books at your finger tips, but if you can find someone with a way of looking at things that is very much their own, maybe even a bit weird - as long as they&amp;rsquo;re not a full-on crank - that is a great boon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russell House Rules</title>
      <link>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/russell_house_rules_master/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpowellrussell.github.io/leaves/russell_house_rules_master/</guid>
      <description>Russell House Rules Master Table of Contents  Rules Outlook Acknowledgments Making a Character  Roll Attributes Choose Race Choose Class Determine Starting HP Determine Weapon Skill and Bow Skill Determine Unarmored AC Determine Skill Slots and Starting Skills Money and Equipment Pick or Roll a Name   Characters  Attributes Movement Hit Points Death and Dying Weapon Skill Shooting Skill Character Skills Gear Slots Character Weariness Hirelings Experience   Exploration  Turns Exploration Movement Load Light Weariness in Exploration The Exploration Die   Meetings  Surprise Reaction Rolls Rounds Initiative   Fighting  Movement in a Fight Target 20 To Hit Roll Critical Hits and Fumbles Ranged Combat Ranges Fighting Options Fighting Conditions Fisticuffs Shenanigans Guts Rolls Armor and Armor Class Death and Dying   Doing Stuff  Skills Advantage &amp;amp; Disadvantage Usage Dice   Character Growth  Experience Points Standard Level Up Chart Earning Experience Leveling Up   Referee Stuff  Treasure Monsters &amp;amp; NPCs    Rules Outlook I put together these rules to have my preferred mishmash of “base” D&amp;amp;D rules all in one place.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>